<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 18:13:22 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 18:13:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Nibenay</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-nibenay.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Nibenay, in his true half-draconic form, lounging on his throne.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he named his city after himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibenay seems to be a very academically-minded Sorcerer-King, which is evident
in how his transformation seems to be the furthest along among the living ones,
but he’s also kinda lazy. For about two thousand years now, he’s been holed up
in his palace-temple complex of Naggaramakam enjoying a life of luxury and study
while his priesthood took care of all those boring “running the kingdom” tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His priesthood are also his templars, which are all women and all his wives. So
this might explain why Dregoth outpaced him 1700 years ago - Nibenay still has
his vices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibebay’s highest ranking templars are known as the High Consorts. There are
five of them, each in charge of one of the city-state’s temples. The Shadow
King’s inner circle is composed of these five, plus his personal arcane
assistants, his half-monster son Dhojakt, and a group of elite goliath
warriors. Only they can enter Naggaramakam and interact directly with their
king. And only they know what Nibenay’s true draconic form looks like - he
disguises himself as a human in his rare public appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things might have continued this way forever if it wasn’t for Kalak’s
assassination and the liberation of Tyr. This kind of lit a fire under Nibenay,
and he decided to end his isolation and take a more active hand in the ruling of
his domain. This has nearly all Nibenese nobles and a large number of
lower-ranking templars in a panic because they’ve been up to a lot of
self-enriching shenanigans that they were sure their king would never notice or
care about. There’s a lot of unpleasant purges in the city’s immediate future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, Nibenay hasn’t completely abandoned his research. He seems to be
particularly interested in Athas’ distant past, and is rumored to be looking for
a way to “bring about a new Age”. That probably involves some sort of
large-scale environmental engineering, though it’s unlikely to be beneficial to
the inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three different stat blocks here, which we’ll see in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shadow-bride&quot;&gt;Shadow Bride&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of Nibenay’s lower-ranking templars. The city’s nobles tend to look
down on them and use them as pawns in their own schemes - the name “Shadow
Bride” is something of an insult. The brides resent them for this, and do
whatever dirty deeds they need in order to claw some wealth and influence for
themselves and climb the ranks of their organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Shadow Bride is a Level 13 Soldier with 130 HP and Speed 6. She fights with
an &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and with &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; at range that do
light cold+necrotic damage. She can inflict the &lt;strong&gt;Curse of the Shadow King&lt;/strong&gt; an
adjacent enemy with a minor action. This marks the enemy until the end of the
encounter and makes it grant combat advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marked enemies within 6 squares who decide to ignore the mark can be targeted
with &lt;strong&gt;Nibenay’s Retribution&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt - the bride teleports to a square
adjacent to the enemy and makes a very accurate attack vs. their Fortitude,
dealing fire+necrotic damage on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her own turns the bride can also &lt;strong&gt;Demand Penitence&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+),
targetting up to two marked enemies in a Close Burst 5, dealing psychic damage,
pulling them 4 squares, and knocking them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yup, this is a Soldier Warlock. Not a combination you see every day. The
“eldritch blast” equivalent here is distinctly secondary. She wants to bring
enemies into melee range and keep them there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-consort&quot;&gt;High Consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the five highest ranked priestess-wives of Nibenay, part of his inner
circle. Just like the city’s nobles, they jockey for position amongst
themselves, constantly engaging in backstabbing and intrigue, though they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;
loyal to their hubby and will fight at his side against meddling PCs who manage
to get that far. They will also fight to the end to protect their own
temples. In any other situation, they run away when the fight turns against
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High Consorts are Level 27 Artillery with 192 HP, Speed 6 and Low-Light
Vision. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Spears&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and with &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Blasts&lt;/strong&gt;
at range 20. These deal cold+necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special spell is &lt;strong&gt;Cage of Shadows&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10), which deals heavy force
damage and immobilizes (save ends). It recharges when they’re bloodied. They can
also practice &lt;strong&gt;Arcane Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; whenever they miss with this power or with a
Shadow Blast while allies are present within 2 squares of them. This is a free
action that inflicts 10 necrotic damage on each such ally, and lets the consort
reroll the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they get surrounded, consorts can use &lt;strong&gt;Nibenay’s Gift&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) as a
minor action, dealing 15 cold+necrotic damage to each adjacent enemy,
teleporting 6 squares, and gaining concealment for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nibenay-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Nibenay, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibenay in his true form is a Large Natural Humanoid, and a Level 29 Elite
Controller with 532 HP. He has ground and teleport speeds of 6 and Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;strong&gt;Sorcerer King’s Guile&lt;/strong&gt; is going to ruin the day of many a PC fighter, as
it makes him not provoke opportunity attacks from making ranged and area
attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In melee, he fights with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Dragon’s Talons&lt;/strong&gt;, which damage and restrain
(save ends). At range, he uses the classic &lt;strong&gt;Ego Whip&lt;/strong&gt; (range 10), which deals
psychic damage and dazes (save ends). Yes, it’s at-will, and &lt;strong&gt;Ego Storm&lt;/strong&gt; lets
him use it twice in the same action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often, he can use &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which automatically
deals 15 necrotic damage to each adjacent enemy and lets Nibenay attack an Area
Burst 2 within 10 to deal necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text is a bit strange here, as it says Nibenay gains +1 to the burst’s
attack roll for each enemy damaged by it. I guess you roll once, count the hits,
add the bonus, and keep repeating the last two steps until he either runs out of
targets or misses someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can creaze a &lt;strong&gt;Zone of Shadows&lt;/strong&gt; that lasts for a turn and
blocks line of sight for everyone except himself. Enemies inside are
blinded. The power recharges when the zone vanishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His version of &lt;strong&gt;Arcane Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; triggers when he hits and deals damage with
either of his basic attacks. It inflicts 10 necrotic damage on each enemy within
2 squares and weakens the target of the triggering attack for a turn. It’s a
&lt;em&gt;free action&lt;/em&gt;, not a reaction or interrupt, so this happens every single time he
hits with Dragon Talon or Ego Whip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nibenay’s Demand&lt;/strong&gt; is his anti-stunlock power, a reaction that lets him
inflict 10 necrotic damage on an enemy within 5 squares and roll a save whenever
he’s subject to an effect a save can end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibenay being an Elite instead of a Solo is not necessarily a sign that he’s
weak, but that the final fight against him will be a crowded affair. Any
surviving high consorts will surely be here, as will any other epic level
assistants and guards the GM wants to add to make the battle a worthy challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Andropinis, Nibenay doesn’t have powers that boost or benefit from his
allies, but at least he doesn’t get in their way either - his area attack is
selective. The High Consorts, however, &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; likely to step on each others’ toes
because their version of Arcane Defiling targets allies instead of enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/12/wir-dscc-nibenay.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/12/wir-dscc-nibenay.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Mearedes</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-mearedes.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Mearedes in her jungle home.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mearedes is a goliath druid, the self-appointed Sentinel of Shault. Shault, in
turn, is a hidden island paradise in the Sea of Silt, one of the greenest areas
remaining in the Tyr Region, largely thanks to the efforts of Mearedes and her
disciples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those disciples are the giants Shakka and Shola, and the dwarf Hippolexes. They,
their master, and a few volunteers from the local stone and beast giant
communities intercept any strangers making landfall on Shault, and demand they
subject themselves to a ritual that prevents them from ever speaking about the
island to others. Those who refuse are killed. As you might imagine, very few
people ever return from Shault, and those who do aren’t saying anything about
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Mearedes has an age-lined face, she’s still as spry as a young goliath,
and has received the respectful title of “Little Grandmother” from the local
giants. Those who help her and her friends fight off threats to Shault will find
her to be a stalwart ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mearedes, as mentioned, is a Goliath. She’s also a Level 18 Controller with 176
HP, Speed 6, and a lot of Classic Druid Powers, which might look very exotic to
typical Athasian characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She fights in melee with a &lt;strong&gt;Thorny Staff&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and slows for a turn;
and at range with &lt;strong&gt;Flame Seeds&lt;/strong&gt; that deal fire damage, and inflict 5 fire
damage on any enemy that enters one of the squares adjacent to the target or
starts their turn there before the end of her next turn. This means &lt;em&gt;the target&lt;/em&gt;
can take this additional damage if they try to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the expected &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Vines&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), a fireball-sized
area attack that damages and then creates a zone of hazardous difficult terrain
that lasts for the rest of the encounter. It damages and slows those caught
inside. Yes, this is a recharge power, so the battlemap will become rougher and
rougher as time goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, Mearedes can assume the &lt;strong&gt;Form of the Ghost Panther&lt;/strong&gt; for a
turn and shift 3 squares. In this form, she cannot attack but gains +4 Speed,
insubstantial, and phasing. She can end this as a free action or sustain it for
another turn as a minor action. And she also has the Goliath &lt;strong&gt;Stone’s
Endurance&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, which lets her gain Resistance 10 to all damage for
a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mearedes will almost always be accompanied by her three apprentices (whose stats
are left as an exercise for the reader) and by as many stone and beast giants
you need to make the fight interesting. She’s also clearly meant to be more of
an ally than an enemy here, so she or some of her apprentices could also tag
along with the group for a short while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/09/wir-dscc-mearedes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/09/wir-dscc-mearedes.html</guid>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Maetan of House Lubar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-maetan-lubar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Maetan Lubar, posing for the cover of a business magazine.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maetan is the current head of House Lubar, one of Urik’s wealthiest noble
houses. He’s been prepared for leadership since childhood, though his time came
much sooner than expected due to the untimely death of his parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house makes its fortunes through commerce and through the ownership of many
profitable fields outside of Urik’s walls. The work on those is performed by
slaves, and their administration by junior house members. Senior leadership like
Maetan has loftier concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maetan, for example, is busy petitioning Hamanu for the opportunity to lead a
large army against the recently freed city of Tyr, as he has a story of success
against Urik’s smaller enemies and wishes to attain new heights of glory and
favor with the sorcerer-king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably relates to the 2e Prism Pentad adventures, which saw the PCs take
part in a battle against Urik’s forces. If this happens in your 4e campaign,
Maetan will likely be at the head of those forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maetan Lubar is a human, and a Level 16 Elite Controller with 302 HP. He fights
using a combination of the fencing skills and psychic powers taught to him from
a tender age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fencing is distinctly second fiddle here: just a basic &lt;strong&gt;Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; attack
that does level-appropriate damage with no riders. Maetan wants to stay a bit
outside of melee range and use his many psychic abilities instead. He’s a
telepath, so all of his powers target Will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serpent’s Kiss&lt;/strong&gt; is a range 20 basic attack that targets up to 2 creatures,
deals psychic damage and makes the target grant combat advantage for a
turn. &lt;strong&gt;Insidious Worm&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will range 10 attack that can only be used
against targets granting him combat advantage; it deals psychic damage and
forces the target to make a melee basic attack against another target of
Maetan’s choice. His usual routine would involve alternating these two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coils of Lubar&lt;/strong&gt; is an area 1 within 10 attack that deals psychic damage and
restrains (save ends). It deals 10 psychic damage as an aftereffect of the
save. It recharges when he uses &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augment&lt;/strong&gt;, a power that triggers when
Maetan hits with one of his two ranged at-wills and further boosts their
damage. And this, in turn, recharges when he’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His two final powers are &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Intrusion&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action ranged attack
that dominates on a hit (save ends). This recharges when he’s first
bloodied. And the &lt;strong&gt;Mind Fog&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, which triggers when he’s hit by
a melee attack, affects a Close Burst 3, deals psychic damage on a hit, and
forces the targets to treat him as invisible (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess this might be a typical example of an evil noble type. The book says
Maetan will always be accompanied by a sizable honor guard, and in a fight he
will try to use his powers to make things easier for those guards (all of them
are selective, so he has no risk of hitting his allies). It also says that
despite all of his psionic might, Maetan is still very proud and overconfident
of his sword skills, so he might end up letting a PC get too close to him
because of this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/08/wir-dscc-maetan-lubar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/08/wir-dscc-maetan-lubar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Lalali-Puy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-lalali-puy.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Lalali-Puy in full regalia proudly standing in front of a vista of
    her kingdom.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lalali-Puy is the Sorcerer-Queen of Gulg, which is possibly the greenest
city-state in Athas. Out of all the Sorcerer-Kings, she’s also the most
personally beloved by her subjects, who call her Oba or Forest Goddess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She uses her magic to bring rain to Gulg, and to protect it from threats both
external and internal. She also owns everything in Gulg, and is responsible for
seeing to its even distribution among the dagadas (communities) in which its
people live. If you’re a citizen of Gulg, everything you wear and eat, all the
livestock you tend and the land it grazes on, all belongs to Oba, who graciously
allows you to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, being a Sorcerer-Queen, Lalali-Puy has further dark secrets unknown
to common citizens. The description of her capabilities above might read as
“epic druid” to someone familiar with standard D&amp;amp;D, but that’s a lie. The reason
she has so much power over her kingdom is because she keeps its primal spirits
enslaved through arcane magic. And the spirits hate her for it. Given the
smallest opportunity, they’d devastate Gulg’s dagadas in revenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite her villainy, Lalali-Puy is described as the most accomplished ritualist
on Athas. Many of the arcane and primal rituals on her extensive library are
unknown to even the other Sorcerer-Kings. PCs might find themselves having to
ally with her in exchange for a specific ritual… or plotting a heist to steal
it from her vaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll take a look at some of Lalali-Puy’s servants here, and then at the
Sorcerer Queen herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nganga&quot;&gt;Nganga&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of Lalali-Puy’s templars, known as ngangas (witch doctors). When a
citizen is selected for nganga training, they’re completely removed and isolated
from society. From that point on, they only appear in public wearing scary
demonic masks enchanted with fear powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nganga we have here is clearly some sort of human warlock pacted to their
Queen. They’re Level 11 Artillery with 90 HP and Speed 6. They fight in melee by
bonking people with a &lt;strong&gt;spirit rattle&lt;/strong&gt; that also serves as their
implement. Their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Ghost Lance&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20
vs. Fortitude) that deals necrotic damage. They can also use &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Jaws&lt;/strong&gt;
(Range 12 vs. AC) that deal force damage and immobilize (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear enchantment on the &lt;strong&gt;Devil Mask&lt;/strong&gt; serves as a good keep-away power:
Close Blast 3 vs. Will, deals psychic damage and pushes 3 squares. At the start
of the target’s subsequent turns, the nganga can choose to push them 3 squares
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they can curse someone with a minor action with &lt;strong&gt;Curse of the
Oba&lt;/strong&gt;. The curse lasts until the end of the encounter, and they can keep cursing
multiple people. They also really want to do that, because when the nganga deals
damage to someone other than the cursed victim, the victim takes the same amount
of damage. If the PCs aren’t quick to deal with the nganga, they’ll soon find
their whole party being “focus-fired” at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;judaga&quot;&gt;Judaga&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judagas are the most elite warriors in Gulg. Like ngangas, they’re mostly
isolated from society, though instead of masks they wear special enchanted
leopard pelts preserved from the Green Age. Lalali-Puy has a honor guard of
judagas with her at all times, and they can also be seen moving among the
populace when she or the ngangas feel physical threats entering Gulg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example judaga here is a human, and a Level 25 Skirmisher with 231 HP. Their
speed is the usual 6, but they also have Forest Walk and a +2 to saves against
Charm and Fear effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judagas fight with &lt;strong&gt;scimitars&lt;/strong&gt; that do level-appropriate damage, and their
&lt;strong&gt;Leopard’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver lets them shift 6 squares and perform a special
attack at any point along the movement. This does a bit less damage than the
basic strike but also inflicts 15 ongoing damage (save ends) and pushes 2
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, if the judaga happens to be within 6 squares of Lalali-Puy herself
(meaning they’re acting as a bodyguard) they can shift as a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book explicitly calls judagas out as willing to perform a coup-de-grace on a
downed PC in the middle of a fight, which makes them a lot more dangerous than
their short list of abilities indicates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lalali-puy-sorcerer-queen&quot;&gt;Lalali-Puy, Sorcerer-Queen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Oba herself is a human, and a Level 28 Solo Controller with 1032 HP and the
Leader tag. She has a ground speed of 6 and a teleport speed of 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lalali-Puy is surrounded by &lt;strong&gt;Ravenous Ghosts&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 5) that give a damage
boost to the melee attacks of any allies within the aura. Her &lt;strong&gt;Oba’s Ambition&lt;/strong&gt;
makes her regain one of her 2 solo action points whenever an enemy cursed by her
drops to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As that description indicates, Lalali-Puy fights like a warlock. In a way, she’s
a “role model” for an epic-level warlock - someone who has long surpassed
whatever entity taught her magic in the first place, and who now makes pacts
with others to teach &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; magic in exchange for service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s begin with the curse-related powers, because those are the core of her
tactics. She can use &lt;strong&gt;Oba’s Curse&lt;/strong&gt; once per turn as a minor action. This is
exactly the same curse the ngangas can use, the one that mirrors melee or ranged
damage inflicted on other enemies to the cursed victims. However, it’s (save
ends) instead of lasting the whole encounter, because Lalali-Puy’s attacks are
much stronger. Still, a string of bad save rolls could still have her “focusing
down” the whole party a once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oba’s Vengeance&lt;/strong&gt; makes that a scenario a certainty when the PCs manage to
bloody her: this is a Close Burst &lt;em&gt;15&lt;/em&gt; attack that affects enemies, deals
necrotic+psychic damage, and stuns for a turn on a hit. It also curses every
target &lt;em&gt;as an effect&lt;/em&gt; (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oba’s Blessing&lt;/strong&gt; is a free action power that lets Lalali-Puy remove her curse
from a victim to end an effect on her or on an ally within 20 squares, so here’s
her stunlock protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep that damage mirroring effect in mind as we look at her “normal”
attacks. All of them have additional things they do to curse victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repelling Touch&lt;/strong&gt; is the melee basic attack. It deals force damage, pushes the
target 5 squares, and then pushes all other enemies cursed by her 2 squares as
an effect. &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Maw&lt;/strong&gt; is the ranged basic attack. It deals force damage,
slides 4 squares, and slides every other cursed enemy 2 squares as an effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit Gale&lt;/strong&gt; is a fireball-like attack (Area Burst 2 within 15). It targets
Will, deals necrotic+psychic damage, and immobilizes (save ends). This
downgrades to “half damage and slowed for a turn” on a hit, but as an &lt;em&gt;effect&lt;/em&gt;,
it lets her slow one cursed enemy she can see (save ends). The first failed save
from that enemy makes them &lt;em&gt;stunned&lt;/em&gt; (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her one power without any curse bonuses is &lt;strong&gt;Oba’s Punishment&lt;/strong&gt; a reaction that
triggers when she’s hit by an attack from an enemy within 15 squares. It’s a
counterattack that deals psychic damage and teleports the target 10 squares on a
hit. Since this is written as a Close Burst, it doesn’t benefit from damage
mirroring, but it will still trigger pretty often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love Lalali-Puy’s mechanics. If the PCs end up fighting her, she will have an
honor guard of judagas with her to use as distractions, all of which probably
benefit from Ravenous Ghosts. And then she’ll curse as many people as she can
and focus her single-target attacks on the weakest of them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/07/wir-dscc-lalali-puy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/07/wir-dscc-lalali-puy.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Jossi the Juggler</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-jossi.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Jossi the Juggler, juggling
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jossi gets a mention in the description of the city of Tyr in the Campaign
Setting book, and a full writeup here. She’s a member of Tyr’s Eyes, which was
originally a group of beggars, street performers and thieves who banded together
for mutual support. Nowadays they also act as a kind of freelance spy agency,
keeping an eye on what goes on in the city both to improve their own chances of
survival and to sell the juiciest gossip to whoever has the money to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jossi is known as a street performer, doing a pretty impressive routine on the
markets of Tyr. She supplements her income with theft and information
broketing. I think both books’ emphasis on her might mean they intend Jossi to
be the PC’s first point of contact with Tyr’s Eyes during your typical campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jossi is an elf, though her speed is only 6 and they forgot to add her low-light
vision. After so many sorcerer-kings, it’s interesting to find a plain old Level
4 Skirmisher with 55 HP in the Personages of Athas section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She fights with the same &lt;strong&gt;Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; she uses in her juggling act, and her
&lt;strong&gt;Juggling Slash&lt;/strong&gt; technique lets her target Reflex instead of AC, deal the same
damage as a basic attack, slide the target 2 squares, and shift 2 squares. This
is &lt;em&gt;at-will&lt;/em&gt;, making her very annoying to fight. On any turn where Jossi shifts
as a move action, she also gains a bit of bonus damage courtesy of her &lt;strong&gt;Fancy
Footwork&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as she realizes the odds are against her, Jossi will try to
escape. &lt;strong&gt;Distracting Toss&lt;/strong&gt; helps with this: when someone makes a melee attack
against her, the can shift her speed as a reaction to reach any square on the
map that has any amount of cover or concealment, and then make a Stealth test
with a +5 bonus (total +16) to become hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mildly interesting, I guess. Jossi is clearly more on the “possible ally” than
on the “enemy” side of the balance, so unless the PCs go out of their way to be
assholes or to antagonize Tyr’s Eyes, they won’t be fighting her. If that ends
up happening, though, Jossi will not be alone. You should assemble a team of the
many “low-Heroic street scum” stat blocks available here and in other books to
act as the fellow Eyes members who come to her aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be interesting to have Jossi as an active ally in one or more fights,
using these stats. Juggling Slash has hilarious synergy with what PC rogues can
do, and Distracting Toss is a good way to quickly leave the fight in case her HP
starts to run low.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/05/wir-dscc-jossi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/05/wir-dscc-jossi.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Haneth Tsalaxa</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-haneth-tsalaxa.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Haneth Tsalaxa
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re following the RPG.net thread with the Campaign Guide reading, you will
already have seen a description of House Tsalaxa on &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.rpg.net/index.php?threads/wir-4e-dark-sun-campaign-guide.925494/post-25647852&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. They’re one
of the dodgier merchant houses with a presence in Tyr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;House Tsalaxa: Based in Draj and known for blackmail and spycraft, trades in
rope, grain, and previously owned cargo. Emblem: two glaring, bestial eyes.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haneth Tsalaxa is the head of their Tyr branch, and he has a very unpleasant
reputation amongst his neighbors. He apparently has tons of dirt on everyone in
the city. Most of his fortune comes from blackmail and information brokering. If
you see him darkening your doorstep, prepare for an unpleasant conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret of his success, which no one but him knows, is that he has a natural
ability to change his shape. He has no idea &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;: changelings are apparently
unheard-of in Athas, making him possibly the only one. He does exploit this
power as much as he can, disguising himself to better infiltrate private places
and overhear all sorts of interesting gossip. In addition to blackmail, he’s
also willing to do espionage and assassination for hire, though his prices are
ridiculously high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haneth is either a 4e changeling or mechanically indistinguishable from one:
he’s a Medium Natural Humanoid with the Shapechanger and Changeling tags, and a
Level 9 Elite Lurker with 154 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that deals standard physical damage and
inflicts ongoing 5 poison damage (save ends) if he has combat advantage, and can
also throw &lt;strong&gt;Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; that target Reflex and deal decent damage. His &lt;strong&gt;Slick
Swordplay&lt;/strong&gt; lets him make 2 sword attacks and shift 3 squares before, between,
or after them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s improved upon the classic “pocket sand” technique and can throw a &lt;strong&gt;Handful
of Poison&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) in a close blast 3, dealing poison damage and blinding
on a hit (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has a couple of classic changeling minor actions: &lt;strong&gt;Changeling
Disguise&lt;/strong&gt; lets him change chape to appear like any Medium humanoid. His
clothing and equipment remain the same, so it might be a bit hard to use in
combat, but it does help a lot when assembling a disguise. He can copy specific
individuals, but only if he’s seen them before. &lt;strong&gt;Haneth’s Trick&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+)
can make one enemy automatically grant combat advantage to him for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no DC to pierce the Changeling Disguise. Presumably you can use the
default rules and roll a contest of his Bluff of +12 against the Insight of any
investigators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haneth’s ability spread makes him more of a skirmisher with reduced AC and HP
than a proper lurker. The ongoing poison damage from combat advantage is better
than nothing, but be lacks something like a Sneak Attack or a really strong
ambush power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing he always has plenty of bodyguards around whenever he’s not in
disguise. He’s a major employer of unscrupulous Mixed Groups of People. Gotta
spend money to make money.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/04/wir-dscc-haneth-tsalaxa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/04/wir-dscc-haneth-tsalaxa.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Creature Catalog: Hamanu</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-hamanu.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Hamanu posing for the cover of a business magazine.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamanu is the Sorcerer-King of Urik. He looks like a big strong man, and is
known to be deeply invested in the success of his city-state. He spends the days
governing it and training with his soldiers, and the nights deep in arcane study
since he no longer has any need for sleep. For Hamanu is the Sorcerer-King who
most genuinely cares about his state and its people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are some tech billionaires in today’s real world that would read
the above paragraph and think “this guy is goals”. And they would not change
their opinions if they learned that he’s also the most totalitarian of the
Sorcerer-Kings as well. The price for his “love” is constant supervision and
total submission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being a very classically-trained wizard, Hamanu loves physical combat
and is quite good at punching people to death. He’s managing his gradual
draconic transformation so that the signs remain subtle for as long as possible,
so most of the time they consist of golden eyes and slightly long teeth. When
wounded in combat, however, be transforms into a big lion-dragon-thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Urik templars live spartan lives, but do get to enjoy the perks of their
station, chief among which is the right to push the common people around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for Hamanu and for a typical templar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toil-templar&quot;&gt;Toil Templar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the templars we saw in previous entries, this isn’t a high-ranking
officer who spends their days next to their king’s throne. Instead, this one is
drawn from the &lt;em&gt;lowest&lt;/em&gt; ranks of Urik’s templars, the one responsible for
managing its enslaved population. It’s a Level 14 Controller with 133 HP,
meaning the PCs are likely to tussle with them long before they ever come
face-to-face with Hamanu himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toil Templars are armed with a whip and a rod, which is very thematic. The
&lt;strong&gt;whip&lt;/strong&gt; is Reach 2 and its attacks damage and push the target 2 squares on a
hit. The rod is used as an implement for their spells: &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Scourge&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 5) deals force damage and knocks prone; &lt;strong&gt;Dazing Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter,
ranged 10) deals lightning damage and dazes for a turn; and &lt;strong&gt;Sulfurous
Detonation&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter; area 2 within 10) is a fancy name for a fireball that
leaves a stinky zone lasting a turn and dealing 5 poison damage to any enemy who
ends their turn inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hamanu-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Hamanu, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The man himself is a Level 27 Solo Controller with 693 HP, Speed 6, and
Darkvision. He exhudes a &lt;strong&gt;Regal Presence&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 2) which inflicts a -2 attack
penalty on any enemy who starts their turn inside. This lasts until the start of
the enemy’s next turn, so it remains for that long even when they leave the
aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamanu’s basic melee attack is done with his &lt;strong&gt;Mighty Fists&lt;/strong&gt;, whose 6d6+14
damage is the envy of every 2e and 3e monk but is typical for a creature of his
level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has a big selection of “classic”-feeling spells. &lt;strong&gt;Thunderous Command&lt;/strong&gt;
is an at-will close blast 5 that deals thunder damage, pushes 3 squares, and
knocks prone. The next three are all big blasty encounter spells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sulfuric Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5) targets up to 5 enemies, deals fire damage, and
inflicts ongoing 10 fire+acid damage (save ends). Until the target saves,
any of the target’s allies that ends their turn next to it takes 10
acid+poison damage. Stinky!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life Drain&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5, enemies only) deals necrotic damage and
inflicts ongoing 15 necrotic damage. Every time a target takes that damage,
Hamanu gains 15 temp HP.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hamanu’s Whisper&lt;/strong&gt; (area 2 within 10, the fireball template) is an
“acidball” that deals immediate and ongoing acid damage (save ends). It leaves
a zone behind that inflicts a -4 penalty to saves on any enemy inside. This
lasts for a turn but Hamanu can sustain it with minor actions and move it
around with move actions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can use an &lt;strong&gt;Invasive Glare&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5) that deals heavy
psychic damage and stuns (save ends). This recharges whenever Hamanu bloodies an
enemy or reduces an enemy to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an adjacent enemy targets him with a melee attack, Hamanu can interpose a
&lt;strong&gt;Cerulean Shield&lt;/strong&gt; spell as an interrupt, gaining 15 temporary HP just before
the attack is rolled. If someone manages to daze or stun him, he can use
&lt;strong&gt;Mental Fortress&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt to roll an immediate save against the
effect, even if it would not normally allow one. On a success, the triggering
enemy takes 15 psychic damage and the effect never happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Lion of the Desert&lt;/strong&gt; automatically triggers with no action
required. This pushes every enemy in a close burst 2 squares, and attacks their
Fortitude to knock them prone on a hit. And then Hamanu turns into the eponymous
beast, which is going to be a nice surprise to any PCs who thought he had spent
all of his tricks already. The Lion has its own stat block, below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Lion form is reduced to 0 HP, Hamanu returns to his human form with the
same HP he had when he transformed into the Lion. When he reaches 0 HP, he uses
Lion of the Desert &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, one last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lion-of-the-desert&quot;&gt;Lion of the Desert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamanu’s beast-form is a big lion-dragon hybrid, probably created by hiding all
of his ugliest draconic mutations in one metaphysical place. It’s a Level 27
Solo Brute with only 125 HP because it’s a stage in the bigger fight against
Hamanu and not something that can appear independently. On the bright side, it
&lt;em&gt;cannot become bloodied&lt;/em&gt;, even when reduced below half HP. It has a Speed of 8,
and retains Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that deals heavy physical damage, and
&lt;strong&gt;Double Claw&lt;/strong&gt; lets him use it twice against different targets. It can also use
a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Corrosive Bite&lt;/strong&gt; that deals a little less damage but inflicts
ongoing 15 acid damage (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Lion’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that
lets him pull off an old-school claw/claw/bite attack sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy misses the Lion with a melee attack, its &lt;strong&gt;Warding Tail&lt;/strong&gt; slams them
as a reaction, damaging and pushing them 3 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a character, Hamanu seems to be what you get when you leave most of your
settings at default, the very first picture that comes into your mind when you
read the general description of what a Sorcerer-King is. The surprises only
start when it’s time to actually fight him, because “muscle wizard” is probably
not the very first thing that comes to your mind, and neither is “lion-dragon
monster”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight, Hamanu will likely want to alpha strike as soon as possible, using
Hamanu’s Whisper and Sulfuric Bolts as soon as enough targets are in range and
then wading in to catch people in his aura and let them catch his hands. He will
sustain the zone from Hamanu’s Whisper and then use Invasive Glare on the PCs
that are inside it, too. Cerulean Shield and Mental Fortress give him plenty of
extra durability for these tactics. As he approaches his bloodied value, make
him look like he’s on the ropes and out of tricks, and then spring the Lion on
the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book doesn’t specify whether the uses of Hamanu’s many encounter powers
should be tracked across his transformations. I’m guessing that the human form’s
spells &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be, but Lion’s Fury should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, meaning it will be ready for a
second use when he transforms again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/02/wir-dscc-hamanu.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/02/wir-dscc-hamanu.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dregoth</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dregoth.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Dregoth on his throne, looking very stately and about to deliver a
    villainous speech.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our narrative present, everyone in Athas believes the Dragon of Tyr is the
only dragon on the planet. Even the Dragon himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every Sorcerer-King wants to ascend in the same way their buddy Borys did, but
for some of them that feels more like a side project. They all have other things
going on, lands to rule, vices to indulge. Dregoth, on the other hand, made “I
shall become a god!” his whole personality. While they partied, he studied
defiling magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dregoth completed his draconic transformation ahead of everyone else except
Borys (who had help!). He created a whole new species in his image (the dray),
and was in the process of perfecting their design and teaching them to worship
him when Abalach-Re decided to see what he was up to and became terrified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She warned the others, and they banded together to eliminate the threat because
the community of Sorcerer-Kings works exactly like a bucket of crabs. The
ensuing battle was titanic. Dregoth was slain, and his city of Giustenal was
shattered, scattering the survivors and flooding the spirit world with the souls
of the dead (many of whom haunt the ruins).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then Dregoth got better. He returned in secret as an &lt;em&gt;undead&lt;/em&gt; dragon,
setting up in a giant cavern far beneath the surface and calling his surviving
loyalists there. Every inhabitant of this New Giustenal is required to undergo
transformation into a dray, if they weren’t one already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan remains the same: gather enough worshippers to undergo apotheosis and
become a real god. By now, centuries after his death, Dregoth has a sizable army
of dray, undead, and other creatures under his command. Real Soon Now (TM), he’s
going to invade the surface to get revenge on his former “buddies” and gather
all the worship he needs to finally complete his unlife’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dregoth’s undeath works like that of a lich. His soul is hidden in an artifact
somewhere in New Giustenal, and if he’s killed he will reform next to that
artifact within three days. The only other person who knows this is Absalom, his
high priest. Absalom used to be human, and was one of the first of Dregoth’s
subjects to be transformed into a dray after Giustenal’s fall. Dregoth then
killed him and raised him as a unique undead being, which explains why he’s
still around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absalom is a competent high priest, but his true loyalty is to the dragonborn of
New Giustenal. Should he ever have to choose, that’s whom he’ll pick. Canny
epic-tier PCs might be able to discover this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, let’s see them in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;absalom&quot;&gt;Absalom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high priest is a Medium Natural Humanoid with then Shapechanger, Undead, and
Dragonborn tags. He’s a Level 22 Elite Soldier with 414 HP, Speed 8, and
Darkvision. Like many undead, he’s immune to disease and poison, and has 15
Resistance to both fire and necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His main weapon is an ancient &lt;strong&gt;Bastard Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that’s probably made of
metal. Its blows do light damage for his level but inflict ongoing 10 damage
(save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Slicing Maneuvers&lt;/strong&gt; lets him attack twice and make his move
action between these attacks. At range he can use &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Siphon&lt;/strong&gt; (range 20,
recharge 4+) to inflict &lt;em&gt;45&lt;/em&gt; ongoing cold+necrotic damage (save ends both). Each
time an enemy takes damage from the power, Absalom or a nearby ally gain 10
temporary HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of running like a pleb, Absalom can use &lt;strong&gt;Dread Wings&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action
to teleport 8 squares and gain a flight speed equal to his speed for a
turn. This is at-will, so it can be the movement he does between Slicing
Maneuvers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His soldierly skills live in his minor and triggered actions. &lt;strong&gt;Overshadowing
Oath&lt;/strong&gt; marks a visible enemy within 20 squares for a turn, and can be used
multiple times per round. If a marked enemy ends their turn in a square that’s
not adjacent to Absalom, they take 20 damage as a reaction and grant combat
advantage for a turn. This means the high priest wants to stay away from marked
enemies, generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other minor actions include &lt;strong&gt;Swirling Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), which does a
blend of necrotic and fire damage, and slides 3 squares on a hit; and &lt;strong&gt;Change
Shape&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets him shift between his natural undead form, a disguise as a
living dragonborn, or a specific individual he’s seen. Equipment and clothes
don’t change. The DC to pierce the disguises is 41, though I imagine it would be
lower if he turns into a specific individual without changing out of his robes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absalom is a strong melee combatant, but he’s much better as a ranged
nuisance. Mark someone at the limit of his Oath’s range and then stay away from
them while attacking with Soul Siphon. When someone gets close, use Slicing
Maneuvers to stab them, and teleport to a distant squishy to stab &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dregoth-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Dregoth, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of that illustration is a bit misleading: Dregoth is a Huge Natural
Magical Beast with the Undead and Shapechanger tags. Interestingly enough he
doesn’t have the Dragon tag, so maybe he isn’t quite done with his
transformation yet. It could also be an oversight, as he has pretty much
everything he’d need to be a dragon in his stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dregoth is a Level 30 Solo Controller with 1072 HP. His ground speed is 8, his
flight speed is 10, he’s immune to disease and poison and has 20 resistance to
both fire and necrotic damage. His special senses include darkvision and
Blindsight 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He projects a &lt;strong&gt;Soul Defiler&lt;/strong&gt; aura with a radius of 3, which is a lot given
he’s Huge. Whenever an enemy starts their turn inside, they take 10 damage and
Dregoth gets to roll a save if he needs one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has a reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and inflicts ongoing 10 necrotic (save
ends), and a reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same and also slows. He can attack
at range 20 with a &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic damage and dazes (save
ends). &lt;strong&gt;Dread King’s Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; lets him do a bite/claw or claw/claw combo, though
the fact that it has both “ranged” and “melee” icons next to it seems to
indicate he could replace one of those attacks with a Gaze too. I wonder which
version (melee only or melee and ranged) is the right one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, his &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a close blast 5 that deals a blend
of cold and necrotic damage, immobilizes, and inflicts a -4 penalty to AC and
Fortitude (save ends both). &lt;strong&gt;Supreme Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) covers a Close
Burst 3, deals heavy untyped damage, and crits on a 17-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action, he can use &lt;strong&gt;Nightmare Travel&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) to become
insubstantial and phasing, and shift 8 squares. If he passes through a
creature’s space during this movement, the creature takes 15 psychic damage and
is knocked prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many encounter powers, that means he becomes a lot less dangerous once
they’re all used up, right? No, because he can use &lt;strong&gt;Spellmaster&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+)
as a minor action to recover any of them. He can also &lt;strong&gt;Change Shape&lt;/strong&gt; to appear
as a Medium dragonborn, or as a specific individual he’s seen before. The DC for
seeing through such a disguise is 47.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Dregoth is hit by an attacker within 4 squares he can use a &lt;strong&gt;Tail
Riposte&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This does some damage, inflicts 15 fire+necrotic
damage, and slides the target 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in melee with Dregoth is &lt;em&gt;extremely dangerous&lt;/em&gt;, because it puts you within
easy reach of nearly all of his attacks. Plus the more PCs are inside his aura,
the better he is at shrugging off negative conditions. Trying to snipe him from
a distance works better, but he’s very mobile and his gaze attack can make it
hard to maintain that distance. And if he has any idea at all that the PCs are
coming for him, he’ll be smart enough to pick a battlefield that forces them to
stay close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that Absalom is a unique undead being that you can’t easily slot into any
classification. Dregoth is technically one too, though the individual components
of his schtick are more familiar. He is a dragon who is a lich, but he’s not a
dracolich. Savvy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, he feels to me like better villain material than the Dragon of
Tyr. The Dragon and the other Sorcerer-Kings mostly want to maintain the status
quo, while Dregoth has an intrinsinc motivation to shake things up. At least, he
would make much better villainous speeches about how he’s going to Show Them
All than any of the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any campaign with Dregoth as an active antagonist will have the PCs meet his
troops much earlier. They’re mostly dray, both alive and undead, who tend to be
evil assholes and consider themselves superior to those who have ties to the old
Giustenal. They often have the Psionic Adept monster theme (more on Monster
Themes later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absalom is dangerous, but his level is so much lower than Dregoth’s you’re not
likely to meet both of them at once. He’s either the guy you convince to ally
with you against Dregoth, or the guy you defeat on the way to enlisting
Dregoth’s aid to fight the Dragon of Tyr.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/01/wir-dscc-dregoth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/01/wir-dscc-dregoth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Andropinis</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-andropinis.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Andropinis, who looks like a regal old wizard when he&apos;s not trying to kill
    you.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis is the Sorcerer-King who rules the city of Balic. His official title
is Dictator, and his city has a lot of Greek and Roman elements as we saw in the
other thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the book says that Balic is clean, orderly, and mostly run along
democratic lines. Its templars, called praetors here, are elected to their
posts. Andropinis himself has an excellent reputation among his population, and
encourages the region’s tradition of ancestral worship and primal magic,
resulting in a remarkably fertile kingdom by Athasian standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the reasons for all of this are quite selfish. Andropinis has
mystically tied himself to the land and its ancestral spirits, and he teaches
his disciples to do the same. He encourages his people to love the land and tend
to it using primal magic because it increases his own power and makes the area
ripe for defiling. And obviously there’s never going to be elections for
Dictator if he has anything to say about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His magical ties to the land form the basis of Andropinis’ power, and he also
seems to be pursuing a more traditional draconic ascension path as a
defiler. While he normally looks like a strong human in late middle age, when
angry his features take on a reptilian cast, with golden scales appearing here
and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we get stats for the man himself and some of the allies he is likely to
surround himself with. We’ll look at them in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;legionnaire-vestige&quot;&gt;Legionnaire Vestige&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those spirits venerated as Balic’s civic heroes. Andropinis can
summon them and order them around. It’s a Medium Shadow Animate and a Level 21
Minion Soldier with a ground speed of 6, a Flight speed of 5, Darkvision, and
immunity to immobilization. Them being Animates instead of Humanoids makes me
think the average Balic citizen is being misled about their true nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, every vestige has a &lt;strong&gt;Guarded Creature&lt;/strong&gt; chosen when they enter the
fight, usually their summoner or creator. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Shade Spears&lt;/strong&gt; that
deal a bit of damage and mark the target until the vestige is defeated or the
encounter ends, whichever comes first. Yes, they can have multiple marked
targets if they last long enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a marked enemy attacks the vestige’s guarded creature, the vestige teleports
to space adjacent to their guarded creature as an interrupt, and grants the
guarded creature +4 to all defenses against the attack. If the attack misses,
the vestige drops to 0 HP. They’re jumping in front of the attack, essentially,
so they’ll want to mark as many enemies as possible to better defend their
charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-praetor&quot;&gt;High Praetor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of the highest-ranking templars of Balic, those chosen to stand by
their Dictator’s side. It’s a Level 22 Soldier with the Leader tag and 211
HP. Their ground speed is 7, and they have a teleport speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re equipped like cliche Roman legionnaires, and their basic attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; that deals increased damage on opportunity attacks. They can use
it in a &lt;strong&gt;Face Cut&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which deals standard damage and dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They attack at range with &lt;strong&gt;eldritch javelins&lt;/strong&gt; that deal force damage and slow
(save ends). Once per encounter they can upgrade this to an &lt;strong&gt;Entrapping
Javelin&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals extra force damage and immobilizes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;High Praetor Assault&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver lets them throw an Eldritch Javelin and
then charge. This also summons a legionnaire vestige, and lets the praetor
determine its guarded creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The praetor’s soldierly skill is &lt;strong&gt;Prateor’s Mark&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets them mark an
enemy within 20 squares for a turn with a minor action. Marked enemies grant
combat advantage when not adjacent to the praeto, and take 15 psychic damage if
they make an attack that doesn’t target the praetor. So unlike most soldier
monsters, high prateors want to be far away from enemies they mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;andropinis-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Andropinis, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dictator of Balic is a Level 25 Elite Controller (Leader) with 468 HP, a
ground speed of 8, a flight speed of 5, darkvision, and blindsight 2. The fact
that he’s an Elite instead of a Solo means he will have a &lt;em&gt;sizable&lt;/em&gt; honor guard
made up of high praetors and epic-level mages when you fight him. The more
allies he has, the more dangerous he is, even beyond the usual encounter maths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis’ ties to his city and the surrounding region manifest in several
ways. One of them is the &lt;strong&gt;Dictator’s Concord&lt;/strong&gt;, an aura (10) that gives a +2
bonus to saves for all allies inside, and allows them to save against charm,
fear, and stunning effects even if they would not normally allow saves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;strong&gt;Wound Pact&lt;/strong&gt; lets him automatically deal psychic damage to anyone who
damages him while he is already bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His basic melee attack is with a &lt;strong&gt;Pact Dagger&lt;/strong&gt;, which damages and knocks prone
on a hit. The first time Andropinis takes damage before the end of his next
turn, the target takes 10 damage and is slowed (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range, he can use psychic powers to inflict &lt;strong&gt;Overwhelming Memories&lt;/strong&gt; on a
target, dealing psychic damage and sliding them 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aggression Pact&lt;/strong&gt; lets him use one of the two basic attacks above &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; let
one ally he can see make a free basic attack. &lt;strong&gt;Land Pact&lt;/strong&gt; attacks enemies in a
Close Burst 3, deals untyped damage, and slows (save ends). While any target is
slowed by the power, Andropinis has Regeneration 15. Land Pact also causes 4
Legionnaire Vestiges to appear in the area, with Andropinis as their guarded
creature. It recharges when he is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis can also use &lt;strong&gt;Transposition&lt;/strong&gt; (move) to switch places with an
ally within 10 squares, and &lt;strong&gt;Dictator’s Authority&lt;/strong&gt; (minor) to let an ally take
a whole standard action right then and there. This, fortunately, only recharges
when he’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if Andropinis ever starts his turn without any allies within 10
squares, a legionnaire vestige automatically appears within 10 squares, with him
as the guarded creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis might outwardly seem to be one of the least bad sorcerer-kings, and a
good propspect for an alliance against his peers. Of course, Balic being
inspired by Greece and Rome means that it’s an enthusiastic practitioner of
slavery. Those nifty civil rights are for citizens, and then only if Andropinis
isn’t angry at them. And when the chips are down Andropinis would not hesitate
to drain his whole kingdom of life in order to protect himself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/30/wir-dscc-andropinis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/30/wir-dscc-andropinis.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Abalach-Re</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-abalach-re.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Abalach-Re, who seems beautiful from a distance, but whose body-horror
    mutations become obvious when you get closer.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re is a Sorcerer-Queen who rules the city of Raam as its Grand Vizier, a
title she chose because she claims to rule on behalf of a (fictional) deity
named Badna. Outwardly, she seems like a lazy, decadent and debauched ruler, who
lets her nobles make war on each other while her police forces oppress a
starving population and numerous rebellions grow right under her nose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, she’s a lot more aware of what goes on in her domain. It’s just that
she enjoys the cruelty on display, and likes to see those nascent rebellions
crushed. She &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; decadent and debauched, but even that is a fruit of her
explorations on the limits of her own physical form. This research has granted
her prodigious body manipulation abilities, which she teaches to her closest
agents and favored children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re keeps a close eye on her peers and was the one who alerted them when
Dregoth got a bit too uppity. She makes sure to keep her own self-modification
experiments a secret from the other sorcerer-kings, as these are her chosen path
to ascension as a god-like being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raam’s day-to-day administration is in the hands of several noble houses, each
of which controls a different district. They’re more like organized crime
syndicates than anything else, constantly at each other’s throats and united
only in their desire to exploit the people under their charge. They’re aided in
this by the city’s police force. Its officers, the Mansabdars, theoretically
answer directly to the Queen, but in practice are all in the pockets of whatever
noble house oversees their beat, and are no more than brutal thugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re lets them all do it because, as stated above, she likes the
cruelty. Instead of reining it in, she created an elite secret police force, the
High Kuotaghas, who actually enforce her will in the city and act to smack down
any noble who gets a little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; confident. Kuotaghas often receive their
queen’s “gifts” and as such have access to some body horror powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Queen’s children are part of her court or members of the Kuotaghas,
but some have turned against her. She lets them, because all of ther children
have unknowingly been implanted with magical locator beacons. Even the
rebellious ones are useful tools to detect other rebels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three entries here and as usual I’m going to talk about them in order of
ascending level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;street-mansabdar&quot;&gt;Street Mansabdar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical member of the force that should be enforcing the city’s laws but is
instead enforcing the will of some local warlord in exchange for fat
bribes. It’s a Level 7 Soldier with 76 HP and a speed of 6. Clad in hide armor,
it’s armed with a mace and a scourge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Mace&lt;/strong&gt; is our basic attack, which damages and marks on a hit. If a marked
target ignores the mark, the mansabdar can use its &lt;strong&gt;scourge&lt;/strong&gt; against them as
an interrupt. It does the same damage as the mace, and knocks prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the mansabdar can use &lt;strong&gt;Beat Down&lt;/strong&gt; against the prone target, which deals
the same damage as a basic mace strike and slows for a turn. If the target
stands up before the end of its next turn, it also takes ongoing 5 damage (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-kuotagha&quot;&gt;High Kuotagha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trusted agent of Abalach-Re, member of the group actually responsible for
enforcing her will in the city. While still tagged as a human in its stat block,
this kuotagha was &lt;em&gt;extensively&lt;/em&gt; mutated by his boss, which I’m sure will be a
nice surprise to the PCs. It’s a level 21 Lurker with 150 HP, a ground speed of
7, and a Spider Climb speed of 6. It also has low-light vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kuotagha fights with &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which target Reflex instead of AC, meaning
they’re the “shreds armor like paper” kind. It can also extrude a &lt;strong&gt;Flesh
Garrote&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage and grabs on a hit. This grab inflicts a -4
penalty to escape attempts, and there is no limit to the number of victims the
kuotagha can grab in this way. I’ll let you imagine how that works. All grabs
can be sustained at once with a single standard action, which also does some
automatic damage to the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All other traits here depend on the kuotagha having one or more grabbed
victims. The &lt;del&gt;creature&lt;/del&gt; agent of the law can inflict criticals on its grabbed
victims on a 18-20 (which is very generous in 4e), has a +4 to all defenses
while it has a grabbed victim, and when someone attacks it while it’s grabbing
someone it can shift 1 square and slide any grabbed victims 1 square to a square
adjacent to it as in interrupt. This will only happen once per round, but it’s
gonna be &lt;em&gt;so annyoing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is a regular monster, meaning you could potentiall fight a whole team
of them at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abalach-re-sorcerer-queen&quot;&gt;Abalach-Re, Sorcerer-Queen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re is a Level 23 Solo Controller with the Leader tag and 856 HP. Like
her henchthing above, she’s technically human, but “technically” is doing even
more heavy lifting in her case. As mentioned above, she’s seeking a custom path
to immorality that involves lot of self-bioengineering, and the fruits of this
are evident in this stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re has low-light vision, a ground speed of 8, and a flight speed of 5
with hover and an altitude limit of 2. The &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Flight&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives her
insubstantial and phasing while she moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of her three basic attacks can be either melee 1 or ranged 10: &lt;strong&gt;Telekinetic
Thrust&lt;/strong&gt; targets Fortitude, deals physical damage, slides 5 squares and
immobilizes (save ends); &lt;strong&gt;Instinct Overload&lt;/strong&gt; targets Will, deals psychic
damage and lets Abalach-Re dictate the next move or standard action the target
will take on their turn, though she cannot force a victim to use a power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third basic attack is &lt;strong&gt;Disrupting Touch&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex and can be
either Melee 3 or Ranged 10. On a hit it deals physical damage and ongoing 10
force damage (save ends). Unlike the others, which are obviously psychic powers,
I think this one might be a touch spell where she stretches her arms really far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, &lt;strong&gt;Morphing Power Splice&lt;/strong&gt; lets Abalach-Re make three attacks with one
action without provoking opportunity attacks, so she could use any combination
of the above on the same turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She can also lay down a &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Field&lt;/strong&gt;, creating a zone in a Close Burst 3
that lasts until the end of the encounter. Any enemy that takes damage within
the zone also takes ongoing 15 necrotic damage (save ends). Thankfully this is
an encounter power, but it recharges when she’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her movement power is &lt;strong&gt;Allocation&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets her teleport 10 squares and
then slide any enemy adjacent to her at the arrival point 5 squares. This also
recharges when she’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to all of the above, when Abalach-Re is hit with any attack she can
use &lt;strong&gt;Vengeance of Adaptive Flesh&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This is a Ranged 10 attack
that targets Will, and deals 15 ongoing damage of the same type she just took
(save ends). Like all of her other ranged attacks, this doesn’t provoke
opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks to me like she wants to stay mostly away from the PCs, using her powers
to slide them into the defiling field so she can further damage them with more
attacks and ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty strong opening for this section, and a brief look tells me
Abalach-Re is likely the weakest of the Sorcerer Kings. She doesn’t seem to have
any particular resistance against being stunlocked by PC powers, so even though
she’s a solo you might want to add some high kuotagha bodyguards to her fight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/27/wir-dscc-abalach-re.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/27/wir-dscc-abalach-re.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
