<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 19:41:53 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 19:41:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Coiled Spring</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/coiled-spring.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Image source: &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://www.deviantart.com/eveyd/art/Antique-Vintage-Pocket-Watch-png-268108244&quot;&gt;EveyD
  on DeviantArt&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coiled Spring is an amulet made of brass. It’s disc shaped and about an inch
thick. On its front, there is a relief of a snake eating its own tail, the
classic Ouroboros. The inside of the ring formed by the snake is a clear crystal
panel, through which can be seen a spring like that of a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That spring can store up to ten Fatigue Points which can be used to enable
bursts of extra effort - most often &lt;em&gt;Extra Effort in Combat&lt;/em&gt; (p. B357), but also
other athletic feats. The stored FP can only be used for those purposes, and is
not affected by negative effects that would sap the user’s own FP. In other
words, it works just like the Heroic Reserves advantage from &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Dungeon
Fantasy 20: Slayers&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; like a power item for martial characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference between the Coiled Spring and a normal Power Item is that it
hijacks the natural recovery processes of the wearer’s body in order to “wind”
itself, and cannot be recharged by the usual methods for power items. While the
Spring is not at full capacity, its wearer is unable to recover their own
Fatigue Points, and the amulet gains 1 FP every 10 minutes. This is a constant
rate - traits which speed up FP recovery for the wearer have no effect on the
amulet. The wearer regains their usual ability to rest when the amulet is fully
charged, or when it’s removed (which stops the charging process).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this does mean recharging the Coiled Spring in town is effectively free,
it can make dungeon delving more complicated for martial characters,
particularly if the GM enforces rules like fatigue costs for fighting a battle
(p. B426 or DF Exploits p. 60). Characters who normally can’t use Fatigue Points
can wear the Coiled Spring and use it to benefit from the Extra Effort rules in
and out of combat, though they can’t recharge it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholars who know of the Spring speculate that it was originally meant  to allow
golems and other constructs to surpass their limits. In an adventure, it will
most likely be found worn by such a construct, or by an elite warrior who
figured out it works just as well for organics. If found in a chest or hoard,
though, it will always start out empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the delvers try to sell the Coiled Spring, or if you decide it’s available in
shops, its monetary value is twice that of a Power Item of the same
capacity. That’s $3400 for the 10 FP version described here, though you could
have versions with greater or smaller capacity. Note that you &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; double-dip
and use the Coiled Spring as a Power Item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variant Springs are possible. Maybe the Flywheel of Faith can power divine
magic, the Arcane Array wizardly spells, and the Goddess Gyre druidic ones. The
recharging mechanics and all other restrictions are the same. They could allow a
construct who can’t normally cast spells or use casting magical items due to a
lack of FP to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/10/coiled-spring.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/10/coiled-spring.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>artifact</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hacking Without a Hacker</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/lancer-horus.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    NPC hackers waiting for the PCs to arrive at the jackpoint.
    Illustration by Tom Parkinson Morgan.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether called a hacker, a decker, or a netrunner, the person who invades
computer systems and makes them do things features prominently in the stories
most cyberpunk RPGs take inspiration from, and so often ends up being a vitally
important archetype in those games. However, they tend to have a very mixed
track record when it comes to actually presenting you with a hacking system
that’s fun and bug-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means there are many possible reasons for why you might find yourself
planning a cyberpunk game but have no cause or wish to use its hacking
rules. Maybe none of the players wants to be a hacker, or maybe the group just
doesn’t like the rules of the game in question. In those cases, a popular
suggestion is to include a NPC hacker, and in this post we’ll discuss a way to
do so that keeps the rest of the group reasonably involved in the hacking. Rules
are for GURPS, but the concepts can be easily translated to other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-from-home&quot;&gt;Work From Home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current best practice in games that include hacker PCs is to devise ways to
keep the hacker together with the rest of the party, so that they can fully
participate in the game even when it’s not hacking time. When your group’s
hacker is an NPC, however, the best thing to do is the opposite. Hacker NPCs
should always do their thing remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing NPCs who constantly accompany the party is a tricky affair. A character
who’s much weaker than the party runs the risk of turning the adventure into a
video-game-style escort quest, one of the most reviled types of mission in
existence. One who is strong enough to protect themselves can end up becoming a
GMPC, a label reserved for annoying characters who overshadow the players and
make them feel like the support cast of someone else’s story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is subjective, which makes it even trickier. Your group’s fun will
be hurt if they &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; either of those scenarios is happening, even if the math
is well-balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remote hacker removes most of the risk. They’re in communication with the
group, and they can do the jobs covered by their niche, but any other challenge
that can be handled by the PC’s own skills &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be, even if it’s
technological in nature. And there are things the hacker can only do with
on-site support from the PCs, which keeps them involved in the actual hack even
if you’re not engaging with those rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact nature of these support tasks depends on how your specific setting
handles computers and hacking. Most games either go the same Retro way of early
Shadowrun and CP2020, or a more “Modern” way that uses more recent tropes such
as the ones employed by Shadowrun 4th Edition or CP2077. We’ll look at how you
can accommodate a remote NPC hacker in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future-of-another-timeline&quot;&gt;The Future of Another Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not immediately obvious to us here in 2023, but the earliest iterations of
Shadowrun’s Matrix and CP2020’s NET were based on a pre-Internet model of
networked computing. Strip all the futuristic terms from their description and
you’ll find out you’re dealing with 80s mainframes. This lies at the root of a
lot of things there that can look a bit weird or silly to modern
readers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Here’s a short and approximately correct explanation for how that
works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainframes are huge (and hugely expensive) computers that are usually
responsible for handling all data processing for an entire company or
organization. They were the dominant form of institutional computing from around
the 1950s to at least the early 1990s, and never really went away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mainframe is operated through remote terminals, which can be in the same
building or even off-site. Therefore, it must be ready to receive connections
and requests from these terminals. And the way you do that in the 80s is through
phone lines and modems. They do have &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; security measures to
authenticate users and prevent one user from seeing or changing other users’
data, but there is no such thing as a firewall because permanent Internet
connections are not yet a thing for mainframes. The most security you can add to
the connection step is to keep the numbers for your mainframe’s phone lines
unlisted&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is why both Shadowrun’s and CP2020’s descriptions of their “global
nets” are so concerned about splitting them into geographical regions and
assigning codes to them and the servers within them. That net is not the
&lt;em&gt;Internet&lt;/em&gt;, but a world-spanning phone circuit. The first step to hacking
into that corporate mainframe is to dial the unlisted number of its modem&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-school-remote-hacking&quot;&gt;Old-School Remote Hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have a PC hacker in these more “retro” games, the number of the
target’s modem line might be included with the mission briefing, letting them
hack removely. It’s more likely that no number is included, then the hacker has
to go in with the group and find an terminal in the target facility through
which they could connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a hacker NPC and they have the number, the reason the adventure is
happening at all is because the mission objectives have a physical component
that must happen at the same time. The typical setup is that you need to steal
the physical prototype while the hacker grabs the research files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don’t have the number, then &lt;em&gt;discovering&lt;/em&gt; the number becomes one of the
physical mission objectives! The place the PCs are infiltrating might not even
have any direct relation to the real, final objective, but it could be a place
that also uses the same mainframe remotely. The number is going to be written
down somewhere in there, either in an official manual, some employee’s personal
notes or even a scrap of paper that was carelessly thrown away&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Some
non-VR-dungeon hacking of a physical terminal to peek at its configuration might
be necessary, which might be resolved by a couple of rolls since dumb terminals
are less secure than the mainframe they talk to. Or you might need to find a way
to scam the info out of an someone who works there (“social engineering”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fact-finding expedition could be a whole adventure in itself, or it might
just be an intermediate step in a more complex operation where the group must
also infiltrate the final target facility at the same time as the hacker does
their thing, as outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twenty-minutes-from-now&quot;&gt;Twenty Minutes From Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent cyberpunk games tend to base their networks on the real-world
Internet and the technologies that support it. This means that every individual
device attached to a network is effectively a full-feature computer, be it an
employee’s workstation, a security camera, or a guard’s smartphone. Different
departments have their own private servers and their own internal network that
doesn’t necessarily connect to the others or to the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less sensitive facilities might allow employees to work remotely from their
homes or from other buildings by letting them connect via &lt;em&gt;virtual private
networks&lt;/em&gt;. These connections to happen over the Internet, but they’re encrypted
and protected from general snooping. Realistically, our dastardly hacker would
need to steal valid credentials to be able to access a VPN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other extreme, a top-secret secure facility might be &lt;em&gt;air-gapped&lt;/em&gt;, which
means it’s isolated and sealed in such a way that no signal can enter or leave
the building. None of its internal networks are connected to the outside world,
and they are not connected to each other either unless this is absolutely
necessary. The servers controlling the security system are isolated from the
servers housing sensitive data. Each has its own independent set of protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is both realistic according to our contemporary understanding of network
security, and an excellent way to make sure PC hackers stick with the group and
have plenty to do once inside. Individual hacking attempts tend to be shorter
but more numerous, and made against devices that are within the hacker’s
immediate reach&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Shadowrun 4th Edition goes deep into this (5th and onwards
go back to the retro model), and it’s also more or less how things work in
Cyberpunk 2077.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-school-remote-hacking&quot;&gt;New-School Remote Hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an environment so full of incentives for the hacker to stick with the party,
how can you accommodate a remote NPC hacker?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the target facility has a VPN that contains the data you want, then many of
the same “classic” techniques for acquiring those old-school mainframe phone
numbers might also work to acquire valid VPN credentials, allowing the NPC to
hack the place remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it doesn’t have a VPN or is completely isolated, then we need to resort to
quantum bullshit. Below we’ll see GURPS stats for the bullshit in question,
imported directly from Warframe. It’s easily usable in other systems, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/CorpusDatamass.webp&quot; width=200/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A datamass.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;datamass&lt;/strong&gt; is a device similar in concept to the causality communicator in
Ultra-Tech page 45, but &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; cheaper. It consists of an armored,
briefcase-sized device that incorporates several kinds of data cable plus laser
and IR micro-communicators and a small radio (GURPS Ultratech pages 43-44). All
of these are connected to a sizable amount of quantum-entangled matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Datamasses are made in entangled pairs that allow high-bandwidth communication
and data transfer between elements of the pair through any amount of barriers or
interference. They have DR 10, HP 8, cost $5000 for the pair, weight 5kg (10 lb)
each, and are LC1 (AKA &lt;em&gt;super illegal&lt;/em&gt;). They also include an emergency
self-destruct switch that melts the internals of both elements of the pair and
can be triggered from either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your typical cyberpunk setting, datamasses were first invented as
super-secret espionage tools by a major government or computer-focused megacorp,
and initially gave them a major leg up in one of the many ongoing cold wars
between such entities. The secret of their existence soon leaked, however, and
an enterprising independent engineer figured out they were quite easy to make
with a properly modified home 3d printer. Yes, even the entangled matter. The
plans for a home-baked datamasses were soon made widely available on the Net,
and they keep popping up no matter how much effort the corps spend to squash
them. That’s why they’re relatively cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Datamass technology is going to be really revolutionary when FTL travel is
invented in the distant future, but for now it’s mostly used for its original
purpose, and allows teams of plucky street mercs like the PCs to operate at the
same level as crack corporate commandos when it comes to high-level
espionage. If the PCs are hired to do a hacking mission, they will usually be
provided a datamass pair. PCs can also buy their own through the usual illegal
channels available to PCs in these games. It should be difficult, but not
impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a setting that has datamasses, hacking missions look a lot like the Warframe
“mobile defense” missions these devices come from. The PCs need to sneak into
the target facility carrying a datamass, and find a place where to connect it. A
direct cable connection to a machine in the target network is best. A wi-fi
connection will do in a pinch, but will make everything that follows take
longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the hacker is an NPC, you don’t need to roll anything for the actual
hack - you just need to give the PCs a time frame for when it will be done. And
then they must stay near the datamass and guard it until that much time has
elapsed. If they snuck in, they need to find a way to maintain stealth and
divert security attention from their access point. If they’re found out, it
turns into a fight, but they still must stay until the hack is done or it will
fail. For added Fun(TM), a difficult mission might require the party to do this
several times from different access points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-destruct switch is useful for when the hack is done, as it allows the
party to leave without having to lug the datamass back out. It can also prevent
the hacker from being traced if the device is captured. Or it can be used in a
double-cross that leaves the team stranded in enemy territory without network
support. Use that last one sparingly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Alas, it’s not related to the whole VR Dungeon thing. That’s weird and
silly for other reasons. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The real-world practice of &lt;em&gt;wardialing&lt;/em&gt; consisted of dialing every number
in a big list or an entire area code looking for accessible modems. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And you can absolutely go wardialiing there. The Genesis version of
Shadowrun even implements it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The real world hacking practice of &lt;em&gt;dumpster diving&lt;/em&gt; consists in searching
a company’s trash for discarded papers with valid passwords and credentials
written down on them. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anywhere from “directly plugged in” to “in the same local wi-fi network”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Mount Hotenow</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mount Hotenow is a huge barely-dormant volcano on the southeast end of the
Crags, in Neverwinter Wood. The heat it produces is the reason the region’s
rivers never freeze, and therefore it’s at the root of Neverwinter’s
prosperity. It was also the cause of its downfall 27 years ago, when a Thayan
ritual caused it to erupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before the cataclysm Mount Hotenow was already the subject of many rumors
and legends. It’s an opening to Hell; it’s an opening to the Elemental Chaos;
demons live here; giants live here; dragons live here; and so on. The most
recent tale is that anyone who enters one of Hotenow’s many caves is fated to
die within a year, even if they make it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fire-cultists&quot;&gt;Fire Cultists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the original mountain in the middle world is back to its pre-cataclysm
state, its reflection on the Shadowfell has been spewing a slow and steady
stream of lava since the cataclysm. Some people believe that this shadow
eruption could cause one in the middle world if the barriers between planes wear
thin enough. Such a state of constant eruption would spell doom for Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief among these believers are the many elemental fire creatures that do indeed
make Mount Hotenow their home. They’re led by the hunchbacked fire giant
Gommoth, who has lived here since he was banished from his clan. The eruption 27
years ago was a major ecstatic experience to him and to every other fire
creature who lived here, and since then Gommoth started a cult dedicated to
making it happen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecstatic experience happened because it was Maegera’s near-awakening that
caused the eruption, and her power tugged at the elementals’ primordial
nature. Gommoth doesn’t know this, but the cult’s latest rising star probably
does. This is Qualthus, the shadovar outcast. Remember him? He was banished from
Xinlenal after being blamed for the accidental sabotage of their mythallar. True
to the general disposition of his former buddies, Qualthus has decided that the
best way to remedy this injustice is to cause Mount Hotenow to erupt again and
bury Xinlenal in lava.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s confident he can do it. After all he’s an arcanist of the Netherese
tradition (read: a megalomaniacal asshole). His actual chances are incredibly
small, after all it took the full might of the Dread Ring to make it happen the
first time. But he could get lucky, since Maegera’s bonds are weakened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To represent Gommoth, the book suggests using an ogre mercenary stat block with
added fire resistance, increased Charisma, and with attacks doing fire
damage. You could also level down a standard fire giant stat block to make him
fit with the campaign’s level range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-river-of-flame&quot;&gt;The River Of Flame&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep underground, beneath the territory of the fire cultists, there is a river
of liquid flame. This isn’t poetic language or a metaphor for magma, but a
literal description. The river follows a winding subterranean path, and the
important thing for player characters is that it passes by a tunnel that leads
directly to Gauntlgrym.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs who know where to disembark could take some sort of fireproof boat or
submersible through this river, and arrive at the lost city. Their main
challenge here besides the hostile environment is Karrundax, the very
territorial young red dragon who lairs in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seekers-of-the-way&quot;&gt;Seekers of the Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that happens repeatedly in this book is that a theme description in
Chapter 2 will give us the impression that the PC in question is the only one
doing something, and then a faction or location description further down the
line will give us a whole group of NPCs with the same goal, and that’s going to
be the first time we hear of these NPCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be a disconnect between different authors, or it might be a sort of
soft “Player’s Guide/Campaign Setting” separation within the same book, since
presumably you want PCs to choose a theme without seeing any spoilers about what
they’ll encounter during the campaign. Whatever the case, we now run into the
group that ties to the Heir of Delzoun, and it’s a genuine Dwarf Fortress
expedition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Heir’s description actively lied to the player: they’re not one of the last
dwarves who are still looking for the lost city. In reality there are so many
that after their disparate teams and groups joined together to coordinate their
efforts they had to elect a government to keep them organized. Their newly
elected leader decided that Mount Hotenow was their best bet, since there were
many stories connecting it to Gauntlgrym and a few confirmed Delzoun outposts on
its slopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extremely large expedition set out from Neverwinter before the Heir got
here, and the litany of setbacks and tragedies they experienced along the way is
what gives me that Fun (TM) Dwarf Fortress vibe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First they bought a letter of safe passage from Neverember in order to pass
through Many-Arrows territory unharmed, but the dwarves and orcs just couldn’t
resist provoking each other until hostilities broke out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they arrived at the Wood and lost yet more dwarves to eladrin arrows and
miscellaneous monsters. Either Shandarar’s guardians were particularly
trigger-happy or it was those old rivalries flaring up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they got to the volcano and lost a bunch more dwarves to Gommoth’s cult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now they’re stuck at the river of flame. Can’t forge ahead because no one
packed a fireproof submersible, can’t retreat because the survivors aren’t sure
they can make it back to Neverwinter alive. To say that morale is low is a
massive understatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morale would be even lower if the expedition’s leader, Vandra Hillborn, revealed
the terrible secret she’s keeping. Many of the dwarves “lost” to the elementals
actually &lt;em&gt;defected&lt;/em&gt; to them, and now work together to bring about the volcano’s
next eruption. Hillborn believes they cracked under the strain of the trip and
went insane, but the truth is even worse: they were intentionally driven insane
by the Gauntlgrym mind-flayers through remote telepathy. The flayers believe
that a volcanic eruption is just the thing to permanently block access to
Gauntlgrym and prevent any meddlers from finding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know, the mind flayers are themselves being controlled by the
aboleths, so we have a true conspiracy onion here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to discover Gauntlgrym’s precise location elsewhere, but
the River of Flame under Mount Hotenow appears to be the most viable path to
actually go there. The fate of the dwarven expedition is a good blueprint of
what an overland journey from Neverwinter to here would involve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible to have an entire party of PCs who would be more interested in
pursuing this journey than dealing with the other hooks in the setting: not just
one or more Heirs of Delzoun but also perhaps one of Oghma’s Faithful who’s
really into archaeology, a Dead Rat Deserter who’s after the score of the
century, and even a Neverwinter Noble in a campaign where finding Gauntlgrym
will give them the popular acclaim they need to take the throne. If there’s an
extended detour to deal with the eladrin, then perhaps the Iliyanbruen Guardian
can get into the mix too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/06/neverwinter-hotenow.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/06/neverwinter-hotenow.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Xinlenal and Related Locations</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post covers the city itself and several nearby locations related to the
Gray Wolf Uthgardt, who serve the Netherese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-warning-brutal-savages-nonsense&quot;&gt;Content Warning: “Brutal Savages” nonsense&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of Gray Wolf material in this section, and this is where the
mounting inconsistencies in their portrayal start to get in the way. The stuff
about them that I read so far gave me the impression of a people who were mostly
minding their own business before the Netherese turned their leaders into
fascist assholes. Most of the actual tribe members were not happy with the
situation: a significant number of them had defected, and those who hadn’t were
open to persuasion by a PC like the Pack Outcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section drops most of that and goes all in on the “brutal savages who
disdain civilization” cliches, painting the Gray Wolf as being bad guys even
before the Netherese got to them. After being co-opted, they got even worse.
Anyone who’s still a member of the tribe at this point is either on board with
the cruelty or too cowardly to ever stand against it. Even their guardian
spirits are disgusted with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to report what the book says below, but I personally would completely
change it were I to run a Neverwinter campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;xinlenal-from-the-outside-in&quot;&gt;Xinlenal From the Outside In&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw before, Xinlenal wasn’t just a Netherese flying city, it was the first
ever built. It fell here in the Wood when Netheril’s magic stopped
working. Today, when viewed from the outside, it looks like an out-of-place
60-foot tall plateau jutting up from the ground in an otherwise flat area of the
Wood. The structures atop it are hidden from view by the Wood’s vegetation,
which grew over it in the two millennia since the city crashed. The Shadovar led
by Prince Clariburnus use Xinlenal as their main base of operations in the
region, and are hard at work trying to make it fly again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-forest-of-hides&quot;&gt;The Forest of Hides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gray Wolf recognize this is the center of Netherese power even though they
don’t know what goes on in here. So when they declared war on the Forsworn, they
started hanging up the skins of their “traitorous kinfolk” in a clearing outside
the plateau. This acts as both a warning to enemies and as a show of support for
their new masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the sheer brutality of this practice has led many rank-and-file Gray
Wolf to question their leadership, and the horrible smell of dead werewolf
lingering about the place acts as a cover for Forsworn spies and makes it easier
for them to scout the plateau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act of building the Forest of Hides outraged and horrified many of the
primal spirits who used to be friends of the Grey Wolf. If the Pack Outcast,
Uthgardt Barbarian, or any other PC who uses primal powers dismantle the Forest
of Hides, those spirits will reward them with a daily power named &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the
Fallen&lt;/strong&gt;, which can be activated after an attack hits and makes the target
vulnerable 5 to all damage (save ends), including that of the triggering
attack. Once the target saves, they take another 10 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you see the first instance of what I talked about in the intro paragraphs
above. There’s more below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-city-and-the-web-of-stone&quot;&gt;The City and the Web of Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The walls of the plateau are a sheer climb, but they look natural after two
millennia of weathering. Some flying monsters even made lairs there. The city at
the top looks completely ruined when viewed from the plateau’s edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those moving towards the center will soon spot a massive suspended “web” made of
stone looming over the skyline. This acts as a gigantic crane and construction
tool used in the Shadovar’s renovation efforts. It can lift whole city blocks
for relocation, or remove an equivalent quantity of soil and vegetation to
reveal the structures buried beneath. Workers both organic and artificial are
constantly swarming all over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This web was built by the shadar-kai witch Korvina, who realized she could use
residual energy from the city’s old protection rituals to power it. Later she
would find out she was actually drawing power from the city’s broken mythallar
and delaying its repairs. When her bosses found out about the oopsie, she
managed to pin the blame for it on her colleague Qualthus, whose fate we’ll
learn in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-womb-of-stone&quot;&gt;The Womb of Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gee, these Netherese sure have a knack for naming things, don’t they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This building is an ancient construct factory reactivated by the Shadovar. This
is where they build all the thaalud constructs they’re using as a workforce. The
ones they build today aren’t as powerful as the ones from ancient Netheril
(using the thaalud constructor stat block from earlier in this book), but they
can do their job just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Womb of Stone is run and operated by a shade named Ulrukan (stats as a human
slaver with shade traits). His left arm and leg are animated prosthetic
constructs, which I think is awesome. Ulrukan discovered the problem with the
Web of Stone before anyone else, decided to keep it to himself until he could
gain something by revealing it, and lost the chance to do so when other people
found the issue and reported it immediately. Now that it’s public he’s trying to
figure out how to extract some advantage from the fact that he knew it before
anyone else did. I don’t think he knows it’s Korvina’s fault, or he’d already be
blackmailing her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cathedral-of-night&quot;&gt;Cathedral of Night&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a ancient building repurposed as a temple to the goddess Shar. The
exterior is still ruined and worn, but the interior is very fancy and all done
up in onyx and jet. It’s also protected by enchanted hungry shadows, a very
interesting hazard that can temporarily remove PCs from play and cause ongoing
psychic and necrotic damage to them while they’re gone. This security protects
the usual temple treasures and also a portal to the Shadowfell, which is used by
the Shadovar to access their supply routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthinos Eln is the priest in charge of both the temple and the restoration
project. He can be found here either meditating or communing with his boss
Prince Clariburnus, who leads the faction as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xinlenals-heart&quot;&gt;Xinlenal’s Heart&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt; is located at its very center. The tower that houses it
was the first building to be completely restored, and a small army of Shadovar
artificers is now busy restoring the artifact itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restoration process is simple to describe but very hard to execute. It
consists of mixing melted glass with large quantities of residuum, carefully
pouring the resulting substance over the &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt;, and molding it so that it
slowly recovers its original spherical shape. Right now it looks like a partial
sphere, already over 100 feet (30 meters!) in diameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the Netherese are scouring the region’s many ruins and dungeons for
magic items and other ancient enchanted relics, and also why they’re poised to
begin raiding Neverwinter. All of that loot is going to get destroyed for its
residuum. The Shadovar are burning the legacies of others to rebuild their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central tower is also where their main war room is located, as well as
Clariburnus’ quarters and throne room. He can either be found here coordinating
the faction’s overall strategy, or somewhere out in the world leading another
raid for magic items. He also sometimes brings members of the Gray Wolf
leadership here for briefings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vellosk&quot;&gt;Vellosk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the main “settlement” of the Gray Wolf tribe, located in the Wood away
from Xinlenal. The quotes are there because they are mostly nomadic, and this is
just where a few more permanent structures are built - pack leader’s homes, a
feast hall, and some other communal buildings. You can also find a number of
tents and lean-tos scattered around the area, belonging to other tribe members
who are currently staying there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book says the Grey Wolf have the technology to make weapons and tools as
sophisticated as that of Neverwinter, but that they have no real culture to
speak of beyond an obsession with behaving like D&amp;amp;D’s idea of a wolf pack. It
could be that this is what the current leadership thinks, but the way the book
phrases it kinda makes me think this is what they were like even before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vellosk’s central feature is a sloped pit whose bottom is coated in dry bones,
and also contains a totem pole decorated with animal skulls. This is their
center of worship, dedicated to Uthgar and the tribe’s guardian spirits. It’s
also where ritual combats and duels happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the permanent structures here is the home of Ormshas, a dark creeper
necromancer who is here officially as a Netherese ambassador and in reality as a
spy placed to make sure the Grey World remain under control. She has a large
group of wraiths under her control, which she uses to uncover secrets and
silence dissenters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gray-wolf-and-the-pcs&quot;&gt;The Gray Wolf and the PCs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the rank-and-file Grey Wolf are very unhappy with the direction the
tribe is taking, but they also believe their leaders’ commands are absolute and
those leaders have been completely bought the Netherese party line. Many tribe
members would rather leave than try to challenge their leaders, but these days
those who express a desire to leave are executed on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs such as the Pack Outcast or the Uthgardt Barbarian would have an easier time
convincing the Grey Wolf to reject their leadership, but they would still need
to challenge those leaders to ritual combat and win (or convince/help a friendly
Gray Wolf to do so). Ritual combat is, of course, to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a legitimate challenge would also require convincing a majority of the
tribe that their leaders are being bamboozled by the Netherese. Just going for
the leaders at once is a sure way to get the whole tribe to declare war on you
no matter what they think about those leaders, so it’s not a good option for
most groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conyberry&quot;&gt;Conyberry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conyberry is a small village at the edge of the Wood that became quite scenic
during the Spellplague when a populated slice of Abeir was isekaied there. It
gained a new lake, a bunch of floating earthmotes, and a mixed population that
learned to live well together after some initial friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately you don’t get to see that version of it, because the Grey Wolf
killed everyone long before the Netherese even got to them. According to the
book they believed the people from Abeir to be hostile invaders and the people
of Conyberry to be their co-conspirators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gray Wolf used the now empty village as a storage area for a time. No one
else went there because everyone (rightly) assumed it had been destroyed after
news stopped coming, and when someone did stumble into the place they were
killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Netherese recruited them they started using the village to, in the
words of the book, “practice civilized behavior” so that they would blend into
the communities they were ordered to infiltrate. Now when outsiders end up there
by accident they’re received by a bunch of Gray Wolf in sheep’s clothing eager
to test their acting skills. Only after the actors are satisfied, or when
they’re found out, do the murder attempts start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xinlenal itself seems like a good dungeon location. A final battle against
Caliburnus in the &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt; chamber would look awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But everything about the description of the Gray Wolf kinda ruins it. The text
is filled with the exact set of racist tropes that draw so much criticism to
D&amp;amp;D. I’m left with the distinct impression that the Gray Wolf are described as
being bad &lt;em&gt;because they’re tribal&lt;/em&gt;, in contrast to the “civilized” people they
disdain and victimize. Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s definitely something I’d completely rewrite if I ever ran a campaign in
this setting. It actually kinda tainted the good memories I had of this book,
and made me stop writing new Let’s Read material for it for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/01/neverwinter-xinlenal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/01/neverwinter-xinlenal.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Dread Ring</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the gloomiest and darkest part of the Wood, there’s a perfectly circular
clearing whose ground is ash. None of the Wood’s animals dare enter this
place. This is where the Dread Ring was built. It was both a fortress and a
ritual tool for a grand spell that would have turned Szass Tam into a
god. Though the spell failed, the ruined fortress now serves as the main base
for the Thayans in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire area of the Ring, both indoors and outdoors, is &lt;em&gt;super cursed&lt;/em&gt;. Check
it out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It counts as both defiled and necrotic ground, the rules for which are found
in the DMG 2. Basically, undead are boosted and HP gains from spending healing
surges are halved.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Powers with either the arcane or necrotic keywords crit on 19-20. Powers with
both keywords crit on 18-20. This is one of the only instances of “critical
range” boosting in the entire game, it’s an extremely rare bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creatures take -1 to Will against powers or effects with the fear keyword.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is also Lorragauth’s grave, some smaller areas in here might also
count as acid-based fonts of power or elemental spouts, making them even more
hazardous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ring-from-the-outside-in&quot;&gt;The Ring from the Outside In&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequent clashes between Shadovar and Thayan forces have turned the outer areas
of the clearing into a blood-soaked battlefield littered with corpses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the ruined outer walls is the &lt;strong&gt;Flesh Factory&lt;/strong&gt;, where corpses,
body parts, and sometimes living victims are stored and used as materials for
Thayan necromancy and flesh-shaping projects. The place’s design lets it raise
undead at a much faster pace and a much larger scale than usual, effectively
mass-producing them. This is where most of the Thayan undead are made, and also
the facility in charge of repairing the fortress’ walls. Instead of bothering
with the logistics of procuring and shipping stone, they decided to patch the
walls with slabs of undead flesh. These walls get a stat block as a trap,
because they can sprout grabby hands that deal damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past the Factory are the &lt;strong&gt;halls of the fortress&lt;/strong&gt;, which follow no plan a
living mind would consider sane since their main purpose was to act as a ritual
tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The center is open, and it’s the current site of the &lt;strong&gt;Thayan excavation&lt;/strong&gt;
that’s trying to reach Lorragauth’s resting place. They’ve managed to reach his
bones and partially unearthed them already, but there’s plenty of work to do
before they’re free of the soil. The excavation pit is deep and hazardous, and
the book has rules for navigating it and for operating the many cranes installed
here during combat to either drop rocks on enemies or slam the crane arm into
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The undead workforce here doubles as the Dread Ring’s garrison, so they get
depleted to a, er, skeleton crew when the Netherese attack. They’re overseen by
Praddak, an battle wight (stats in DMG 2). Also here as protection is the sacred
totem of the Thunderbeast tribe, which as we saw before was a fossilized
thunderbeast skeleton. It’s been animated by necromancy, with the stats of a
rotclaw (an undead monster from the Draconomicon). This of course is a horrible
blasphemy, particularly to the Uthgardt Barbarian PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere near the pit is the &lt;strong&gt;Dread Spire&lt;/strong&gt;, the tallest surviving tower of
the Ring. It houses the Thayan war room, the entrance to Valindra’s sanctum, and
a perpetually dark room that contains a portal to the Shadowfell. It also
contains the Chapel of the Dragon, where Kroskas’ cultists research how to raise
Lorragauth as a dracolich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shadowfell portal is what lets the Thayans bring corpses from Neverdeath
Cemetery for reanimation, and to receive caravans that come from Surcross via
the Shadowfell Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valindra’s Sanctum&lt;/strong&gt; houses her library and an arcane observatory that lets
someone scry remote locations and perform astrological divination. It’s operated
by Lurrens, one of her lieutenants, who watches it 24/7. Lurrens is a former
wizard who was turned into an undead Brain in an Armored Jar (from Open Grave).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The observatory’s grinding machinery is hazardous terrain, should a fight break
out here. PCs might find information on Gauntlgrym and other campaign secrets by
either researching Valindra’s library or learning how to operate the
observatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to my earlier expectations the Dread Ring cannot rise as a floating
battlestation or giant undead mech, though the possibility of them raising a
dracolich is a decent substitute. The place is perfectly usable as an endgame
dungeon, though it could also end up being “just” an important stop on the way
to Gauntlgrym depending on the campaign’s focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have to say “Brain in an Armored Jar” is the best monster name ever.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/28/neverwinter-dread-ring.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/28/neverwinter-dread-ring.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Ruins of Shandarar</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-errata&quot;&gt;Historical Errata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I continue, I feel a correction is in order. This one’s on me, not on the
book, since it was a detail from that long and detailed timeline at the start
that I missed. I’m correcting it here because it will be important later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know, Shandarar was the former capital of Iliyanbruen, an
elven/eladrin empire that existed in this region thousands of years ago. It
coexisted with the human empire of Netheril, and witnessed its fall when the
flying city of Xinlenal fell on the Neverwinter Wood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bit I got wrong was this: the fall of Xinlenal did not also cause the end of
Iliyanbruen. The crash site was far from the city, and though the elves explored
it soon after the event they decided to declare it off-limits after the first
few explosions and carried on with their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iliyanbruen would last for a few centuries longer. They’d manage to repel a
massive orc invasion that covered the North, but their kingdom would collapse
from the effort it spent to kick those same orcs out of the human city of Illusk
(located where Luskan is today). From here on out things proceed as previously
detailed, with the empire’s population scattering and some of them deciding to
take refuge in the Feywild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;present-day-shandarar&quot;&gt;Present-Day Shandarar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The middle world ruins of Shandarar cover a sizable area in the Wood but were
mostly hidden by the passage of time and the growth of vegetation. Sometimes a
farmer at the edges of the forest would find shards of pottery as they plowed a
field, or some village builders would end up unearthing a ruined
structure. These rumors helped the Netherese find the core of the ruins and
steal a bunch of ancient relics from it, which has the eladrin in a tizzy as we
already learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the ruins are still, well, ruins. They’re overgrown and weathered enough
to be hazardous. The oldest part of them, however, is being rebuilt and
renovated by the eladrin, since that’s where they crossed over from the Feywild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest news here is that there are still several shielded vaults in the
ruins that haven’t been found out by anyone yet. They contain extensive troves
of ancient Iliyanbruen artifacts and works of art, of immense cultural value
even when they aren’t magical, all protected against the ravages of time by
stasis spells. The eladrin themselves don’t remember their locations, and this
is the first time the book itself mentions them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is also where it goes into a little more detail on the Feywild side of the
crossing. That’s where the military outpost of New Shandarar is. It was also
built on top of ruins, after the eladrin force kicked out the evil fey that had
been living in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Shandarar’s fortifications are living vegetation shaped by magic, and the
portal opens into a courtyard kill zone. Aside from all the military defenses
you expect, built of out living and magically reinforced wood, the fort also has
plenty of facilities for long-term habitation. This includes a temple to
Corellon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hidden-serpent&quot;&gt;The Hidden Serpent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw before, Merrisara Winterwhite, the force’s commanding officer, is part
of their moderate faction. She spends most of her time in the middle world
overseeing the restoration of the city. Her second-in-command is an extremist,
and spends all of his time in the Feywild. Addemios Three-Dawn, the secret
Asmodeus worshiper, also spends all his time in the Feywild. He has a hidden
shrine to his god underneath Corellon’s temple. The evil fey who were
supposedly kicked out of the area have a hidden camp not too far from the fort,
and they cooperate with Three-Dawn because their interests align.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A side box here explains that Asmodeus presents himself in the Feywild as a
trickster god of a “better class” than the usual archetypes found there. Instead
of lying and cheating for the lulz, he encourages and teaches his followers to
do so in order to advance their own power and influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fey-and-the-pcs&quot;&gt;The Fey and the PCs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another box discusses the possible attitudes of the eladrin towards PCs. As we
already known even the moderates are standoffish and aggressive to outsiders by
default. However, they are likely have a more diplomatic stance towards a party
which includes the Iliyanbruen Guardian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the two sub-factions wins out depends largely on the actions of the
PCs. The moderates win and might become valuable allies if the PCs can offer
them evidence that the Shadovar are responsible for the relic thefts, or if they
can prove Addemios Three-Dawn is a traitor who is manipulating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if the PCs steal from the ruins, fight the eladrin or attack
Three-Dawn before proving his guilt, the Fey will adopt the extremist stance and
launch a full-scale invasion of the region, likely starting a major open war
with the other factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How important the fey of New Shandarar are depends entirely on what the group
wants for their campaign. They could be anywhere from isolated and irrelevant to
a potential region-wide threat that needs to be defused as soon as
possible. Even groups who aren’t interested in spending a lot of time dealing
with these elves might still get an adventure or two out of a visit to their
camp, perhaps as they’re traveling the Wood on the way to some other location
therein.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/24/neverwinter-shandarar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/24/neverwinter-shandarar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Neverwinter Woods</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Neverwinter Wood dominates the northern half of our regional map and is much
larger than the city that gives it its name. It’s a classic Creepy Forest, where
the canopies block out all sunlight and even in the safer trails it seems like
someone is always watching you from the shadows. And that’s just the baseline
mood - the Wood is also currently full of ill-intentioned outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters in a Neverwinter campaign might need to trek through this place for
any number of reasons. This section of the chapter covers some of the Wood’s
most notable places, but it’s large enough that you could run a full
hex-crawling campaign on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book actually includes rules for a “Creepy Woods” hazardous terrain type
that can be included in exploration or combat maps. Anyone on this terrain when
a fight starts must roll a save before rolling Initiative - if they fail,
they’re surprised during the first round. They also gain a -2 to Will while on
Creepy spaces and when they fail a Perception check there they always think they
heard something that’s not there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first post covers the “smaller” areas and “standard” geographical features
of the Woods. It also contains several faction strongholds that will each get
their own post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-crags&quot;&gt;The Crags&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a large mountain range that splits the Wood in two, running from NE to
SW. Mount Hotenow is the most notable place in the Crags, as it’s where the
Neverwinter River starts and also the source of the eruption that caused the
cataclysm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more besides the volcano though - this is a typical D&amp;amp;D mountain
range full of monsters, caves, and hidden valleys and is also rumored to contain
paths to lost Gauntlgrym. Whether those exist or not, the range does definitely
contain a lot of old Delzoun outposts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those outposts will give the Heir of Delzoun something to marvel at even if they
don’t find a path to the lost city here. They’re also targets for Netherese
plundering in their unceasing quest for magic items to burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iceless-waterways&quot;&gt;Iceless Waterways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Wood’s rivers are warmed by Hotenow’s heat, so they never freeze even
during winter, and generally act to keep the forest warm and untouched by the
seasons. They teem with non-monstrous aquatic wildlife but never gave rise to
monsters - except for the River Morgur, the northernmost tributary of the
Neverwinter. It’s still iceless, but also has river monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bones-of-thundertree&quot;&gt;Bones of Thundertree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thundertree used to be a logging village that produced a lot of quality
timber. It was completely destroyed by the eruption, and all of its surviving
inhabitants fled to never return. The place is now haunted by possessed plant
monsters (take plant monster stat blocks of your choice and give them undead
traits). Aside from them, only the dwarf Favria, leader of the more violent
faction of the Ashmadai, calls this place home. She lives in an underground wine
cellar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was given to understand her whole Ashmadai sub-faction used this place as a
base, so it looks like there was a miscommunication between different authors
here. I’d probably add them here if I ran a Neverwinter campaign. Maybe say
those plant monsters are possessed by &lt;em&gt;devils&lt;/em&gt; instead of undead. How do you
like evil treants with 20 fire resistance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tower-of-twilight&quot;&gt;The Tower of Twilight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There used to be a wizard’s tower built in the middle of a lake island. It, and
the bridge leading to it, only appeared at night, becoming more solid as the sun
set and fading out again when it rose. During the Spellplague, the tower
vanished entirely and did not return until after the cataclysm. Now, it appears
sporadically with no set schedule, and no one knows what goes on in there
anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One suggestion from the book is that the tower fades out of &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; when it’s not
visible in the physical world, and the people inside only experience the passage
of time when it appears. This mean that the tower’s wizard and their apprentices
and staff might still be there, either absorbed in their studies as if this was
still 3e or struggling with what is to them a very recent bout of “original
strain” Spellplague.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/22/neverwinter-woods.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/22/neverwinter-woods.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Helm's Hold</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re getting outside of the city proper now! Helm’s Hold is a small town
located on the edge of the Neverwinter Wood, built around a monastery and
cathedral dedicated to the god Helm. It’s about a day’s travel northeast of
Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The town’s proximity to the Wood and its traditions of rugged individualism give
it big “American frontier” vibes, tempered a bit by the monastery’s own
culture. Helm used to be the god of guardians, and the monastery’s purpose since
its ancient founding is to give sanctuary to those who have none. The monastery
came first, and the town slowly grew around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year before the Spellplague, when the inhabitants had just laid the
foundation for the cathedral, Helm died. The grieving priests and citizens
finished the huge building as a monument in his honor, and kept its purpose as a
sanctuary, welcoming people of all faiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience of Helm’s Hold from the computer games and reading this book is
that the place’s narrative purpose is to be infiltrated and secretly taken over
by the current campaign’s Big Bads. It happened in the first computer game
(ancient underground civilization), it happened again shortly before the
Spellplague (Netherese), and now it’s happening once more (the aboleths). We’re
headed for a plot pileup here because the Netherese are also trying to
infiltrate the town anew, via their werewolf minions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lurking-threats&quot;&gt;Lurking Threats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those mysterious disappearances and murders are caused not by the spellscarred,
but by the Grey Wolf Uthgardt, who have been ordered by their Netherese masters
to infiltrate the town and cause chaos. They’re proficient at disguising
themselves as locals or pilgrims, which lets them get into position to wolf out
at night and go hunting. The core of their force hides out in the Wood. The
Netherese don’t think the Hold is strategically valuable, they just want to keep
the barbarians occupied until they’re needed in their true function as
expendable muscle to throw against the Thayans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two barbarian-themed PCs are quite likely to end up here, and a peaceful
resolution to the Grey Wolf plot would involve convincing them the Netherese are
both evil and not interested in the tribe’s well-being. This has to be done
subtly, though, as they are likely to attack the Pack Outcast on sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course there’s also the cathedral itself, which is currently being run by
Rohini’s group and thus is a secret aboleth center of power. No one else knows
about this currently, though ironically the AbSov is also interested in solving
the murders because it will reduce the suspicion currently directed at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hold-and-environs&quot;&gt;The Hold and Environs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hold’s mission as a sanctuary turned into the region’s premier treatment
center for Spellplague victims, a duty which only became heavier about a year
ago when Lord Neverember made it his official policy to send any such victims he
finds in Neverwinter to the cathedral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the region tends to see the spellscarred as dangerous freaks, but
the inhabitants of the Hold see them as unfortunate victims affected by a
horrible curse. Still, the overwhelming influx of new patients has been testing
their open stance, as the city had to do a lot of rush construction to
accommodate them all, with limited success. You can find newer buildings
haphazardly constructed between older structures, their quality dubious due to
the Hold’s chronic labor shortage. Most skilled builders are over on
Neverwinter, where the work pays better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hold’s citizens are further stressed out by the recent spate of mysterious
murders and disappearances, which the more conservative among them have started
blaming on the spellscarred. A group of spellscarred activists calling
themselves the Heirs of Azure has sprung up to try to counter the distrust
heaped upon their community. However, the Mintarn detachment sent by Neverember
to help keep the peace isn’t having much success tracking down the real
culprits, tensions keep increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is governed by a council of elected Speakers who meet at a former
tavern named The Dragon’s Gauntlet. They’re also split on the issue of the
spellscarred, though the official stance is still receptive since current Chief
Speaker is in that camp. The council’s collective power is waning, as there are
enough mercs in town that they could declare martial law unopposed. Their
commander, however, is uncharacteristically responsible and dutiful, so the
order won’t come from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heartward&quot;&gt;Heartward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market plaza, so named because there’s a shrine to Sune here. Fights are
frequent because resources are scarce and prices high. Every now and then, at
night, a major haunting happens here and a bunch of ghosts goes through the
motions of market life. Some crew the stalls, some walk around making purchase
and talk to each other. Most of their words are gibberish, but some are
prophetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-dirty-dwarf&quot;&gt;Old Dirty Dwarf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And old, respected, and dirty tavern, with a reputation as the place for new
arrivals to go in order to get the lay of the land and hear the latest news from
the Hold. The owner is friendly to the spellscarred, but some of the staff
aren’t. Agents of the Prophet keep an eye here at all times and report news to
their boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scar-alley&quot;&gt;Scar Alley&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ground under this neighborhood softened during the Spellplague, causing many
of its buildings to sink and crack. Nowadays it’s a barely-standing,
precariously-patrolled slum that is home to the most deformed of the
spellscarred, those even the Hold shuns. It’s also filled with shady characters
and the occasional monster hiding out in an abandoned ruin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;helms-cathedral&quot;&gt;Helm’s Cathedral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aging faithful of Helm’s Cathedral now share it with a contingent of Oghma’s
priests who arrived to set up a sanatorium for spellscarred patients. Brother
Satarin commands the former: he’s a 160 year old dwarf who was an acolyte before
Helm’s death. Rohini the Prophet officially commands the latter, and is the de
facto boss of the whole place. As we learned a few posts ago, she’s a former
succubus turned aberrant creature, and serves the Abolethic Sovereignity, as do
all her subordinates. She holds the loyalty of Helm’s old priests because some
of her (fake) prophecies hint at his return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface levels of the cathedral are airy and well-lit. The underground is
far less pleasant and houses the sanatorium for the most “severe” cases. Rohini
spends a lot of time down there “treating” them (i.e, turning them into
foulspawn). They go out for exercise every day, and the foulspawn among them are
only detectable as such by people specifically looking for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-warrens&quot;&gt;The Warrens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a failed attempt to expand the city’s drainage system, abandoned when
the dig broke into the monastery’s old crypts and was overwhelmed by
monsters. It became a kind of unofficial sanatorium for monstrous humanoids
afflicted by the plague, who find no acceptance even in a tolerant city such as
this. Goblins, kobolds and others venture into the city to steal food for
themselves, and this has given rise to rumors of fey hauntings. I think it still
connects to the rest of the crypts, described below, and would be a good
alternate route for parties who want to sneak in. I’d probably run that as a
negotiation focused adventure rather than a classic murdery crawl, at least
until the PCs get to the crypts where the actual bad guys are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crypts-of-the-vigilant-eye&quot;&gt;Crypts of the Vigilant Eye&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These crypts lie beneath the Cathedral, and predate its construction. Though the
levels closer to the surface were clearly used by priests of Helm from the older
monastery, things get more ancient and mysterious the deeper you go. There’s a
big vertical pit full of side niches that could only be reached by flight or
teleportation, and is now full of gargoyles. There’s a hallway full of gigantic
robed skeleton statues that don’t resemble any sort of Helmite iconography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all that is without counting the twisting of the place by Spellplague
energies and its current occupation by AbSov agents and foulspawn. Or the
trapped Grey Wolf recon force that still hasn’t managed to find a way out
through all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deepest levels turn into caverns that were excavated and mutated by the
Symphony of Madness, turning into a fungal underground swamp. These are
Chartilifax’s hunting grounds, so they probably contain all sorts of creatures
that are tasty to dragons and dangerous to adventurers. From here you can enter
a pulsating tunnel to the brain-like chamber containing the Hex Locus, a bronze
coffer that acts as a repeater for the Symphony of Madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Locus chamber can also be reached via a teleportation circle somewhere in
the crypt levels, and Rohini will use that as soon as she learns someone is
inside. She is linked to the artifact and can feel when someone enters its
room. This is likely where any final confrontation against her and her pet
dragon will occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot-hooks&quot;&gt;Plot Hooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spellscarred Harbinger will most likely be told to go here soon after the
campaign starts. The Pack Outcast and Uthgardt Barbarian’s pursuit of the Grey
Wolf might also bring them here early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s werewolf problem and the creepy happenings at the cathedral should be
obvious enough to get the PCs investigating, and the growing tension between
locals and refugees would make a fine secondary plot line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rohini herself would not appear immediately villainous - she would instead
attempt to coopt the PCs and get them to help with her goals. By default that’s
serving the AbSov, but the book offers a few alternatives. Perhaps she wants to
break free of them and would secretly help them destroy the Hex Locus instead of
protecting it. She is of course still a devil, so she might double-cross the PCs
once she has what she wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent of that, Mordai Vell is working hard to woo her, aware that she’s a
devil in disguise but unaware of all the rest. So &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; might hire the PCs as
go-betweens in his courtship efforts. That’d be a fun way to introduce the AbSov
and Ashmadai to the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to be fair and write a complete summary of the material in the book, but
the truth is that I have a hard time caring about what’s going on in the town of
Helm’s Hold proper. The original Neverwinter Nights computer game colors my
perceptions here - it skipped the “town” bit entirely and placed you directly
inside the monastery, which it treated as a dungeon. I only learned the Hold was
an actual town once I read this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like most campaigns will go a similar route, focusing all of their “urban
intrigue” creative energy on Neverwinter itself and treating the Hold as a
mostly-skipped prelude to the big delve into the cathedral and the crypts
beneath. On the other hand, it would also be possible to do the reverse and
ignore the big city depending on your party composition. There are several
themes that have more reason to start at the Hold than at Neverwinter, like the
Spellscarred Harbinger, the Uthgardt Barbarian, and the Pack Outcast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/18/neverwinter-helms-hold.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/18/neverwinter-helms-hold.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New project page!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been reading this blog for a while you’ll know that I’ve been doing a
Let’s Read of the Neverwinter Campaign Setting for D&amp;amp;D 4e. This has been
generally less organized than the ones I did for the monster manuals, and it
didn’t have a project page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, now it does! If you want to see all the Let’s Read Neverwinter posts
collected and neatly linked in one single place, then you can &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/neverwinter/&quot;&gt;head over
there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/new-project-page.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/new-project-page.html</guid>
        
        <category>meta</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Underground</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We already saw several underground danger spots in the city. Neverdeath
Cemetery, the dungeons of Castle Never, and of course the Chasm. But there are
even more beyond those. The Mintarn mercs usually stay on the surface, so every
one of these places can be considered “dungeon-like”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shattered-sewers&quot;&gt;Shattered Sewers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverwinter had an extensive sewer system that’s still largely ruined. It makes
for a great way to move about the entire city undetected, but it’s hazardous to
navigate and filled with both monsters and other people who don’t want to be
discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kraken-tunnels&quot;&gt;Kraken Tunnels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an underground complex with a floor plan that vaguely resembles an
octopus. It used to be the former headquarters of the Kraken Society, a criminal
syndicate specializing in slavery. Now it’s the headquarters for the Nashers
faction of the Sons of Alagondar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complex is build right above an underground canal that links to the sea, and
this canal is the home of an actual kraken. The Spellplague reduced the monster
to bestial intelligence. The Society used to feed it and keep it as a guardian
beast, and the Nashers have continued the practice. The complex has several
floor openings through which the creature can attack intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kraken was trained by the Society to recognize anyone bearing an amulet with
its symbol as a friend - it attacks all who &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have this amulet on
them. The Nashers know this and carry Kraken Society amulets with them when
inside the complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a tunnel here that links the Kraken Tunnels to the Dead Rats’ HQ through
the sewers, which the Nashers use to talk and trade with them. The Rats don’t
yet know the trick to avoiding the Kraken, but it’s just a matter of time until
they find out and attempt to take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible the Nashers might end up releasing the kraken into the river or
the docks as a sort of weapon of mass destruction if they become desperate
enough. The aboleths could also try to get to it in order to search its mind for
secrets from back when it was sapient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dead-rat-hole&quot;&gt;Dead Rat Hole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a section of the sewers that has been taken over by the Neverwinter
chapter of the Dead Rats. It’s marked with gang signs gouged into the sewer
walls, and packed with both loot and trash collected by the gangers. Their
leader, Rsolk, holds court at a set of caves near the shores of
Blacklake. There’s a trap here that can let the waters of the lake in and
“flush” the whole complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Dead Rats are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; familiar with the Dead Rat Deserter PC, contrary to
what I thought before. Looks like word hasn’t got to them yet. A bold Deserter
might try to infiltrate the gang and perhaps even challenge Rsolk for
leadership. This starts as a one-on-one duel but turns into a standard mass
fight once he’s bloodied. And of course he flushes the lair if it looks like his
side will lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tunnels-and-trenches&quot;&gt;Tunnels and Trenches&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sewers around the Chasm area are partly collapsed, forming trenches where
the street above was destroyed and tunnels where it hasn’t. This and the influx
of non-sapient monsters provides good cover for the AbSov’s smarter agents to
infiltrate the River District or to escape the city and head to Helm’s Hold and
other places.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 10:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/neverwinter-underground.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/neverwinter-underground.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
