<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 01:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 01:03:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Wraith</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-archons-storm.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustration by Steve Argyle. Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like I missed this Monster Manual/Vault article due to a small typo when I
named its draft. With this, the MM/MV reading is truly completed. Click
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wraiths have been in the game since the beginning as a member of the Undead
Power Ladder, where they were the logical progression from wights. Here, they
appear in both the Monster Manual and the Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wraiths are still kind of a logical progression from wights, in origin if not
necessarily in power. As mentioned in the wight entry, living beings in the D&amp;amp;D
implied setting are composed of body, soul, and will (also known as the
animus). When someone dies in a place filled with strong necrotic emanations,
their animus might pop free and roam around on its own. This errant animus is a
wraith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wraiths perceive the world as if through a heavy shroud. Everything feels cold,
colorless, and gauzy. Bereft of a soul and tormented by vague memories of the
lost life and sensations they can never recover, they quickly descend into a
violent, hateful madness that drives them to attack and slay the
living. “Newborn” wraiths at first behave like they did in life, staying near
the ground and using doors, but soon they learn that gravity and solid barriers
mean nothing to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike some other undead we’ve already seen, wraiths don’t originate only from
evil people. All it takes is for the person to die under the “right”
conditions. A wraith who originated from a good and loving husband is just as
violent and dangerous as one that came from a serial killer. In fact, the first
wraith might specifically seek out and kill its former family without even
knowing why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wraiths kill using their life-draining touch. The animus of a recently slain
victim will pop free as a brand-new wraith almost instantly. These new wraiths
are weak at first, but if allowed to exist for long enough will reach full
strength. Even if the victim is brought back to life via magic, its wraith
remains - a new animus forms to hold body and soul together. Predictably, this
does nothing to improve the wraith’s mood, and it will hunt its former self
tenaciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when a lot of people die suddenly and simultaneously, their tormented
animi coalesce into a single entity known as a Dread Wraith, which is orders of
magnitude more dangerous. Individual wraiths who stick around long enough, and
who kill enough, may also reach an equivalent level of power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. A flying, insubstantial killer who makes more of itself
whenever it kills someone, and who never stops doing that as long as someone is
still alive within reach. As RPG.net member Monsieur Meuble pointed out in his
own Let’s Read of the 3.5 Monster Manual, that’s a recipe for total
extinction. Fortunately for all of existence, wraiths tend to hang out in out of
the way places far from population centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Wraiths are Medium Shadow Humanoids with the Undead Keyword. Dread Wraiths
are Large. All have darkvision. They’re immune to disease and poison,
Insubstantial, and have a fly speed of 6 with Hover and Phasing capability. They
also have 10/tier resistance to necrotic damage. The Monster Manual and Monster
Vault versions differ substantially from this point on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monster Manual wraiths compete with needlefang drakes, ghouls, and hobgoblins as
the most annoying and/or deadly monsters a same-level party can fight. They’re
&lt;strong&gt;Insubstantial&lt;/strong&gt; and most of them have attacks with a &lt;strong&gt;weakness&lt;/strong&gt; rider, which
means your PCs will spend much of the fight doing a quarter of their usual
damage against these monsters. They also have &lt;strong&gt;Regeneration&lt;/strong&gt;, which shuts down
for a turn if they take radiant damage but makes them even more durable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if a MM Wraith does manage to kill a PC, their &lt;strong&gt;Spawn Wraith&lt;/strong&gt; ability will
make another wraith rise from the corpse at the start of the original wraith’s
next turn. This new wraith is identical to its creator and starts out at full
strength. If this ever happens you might very well be looking at the start of a
long, grinding TPK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MV wraiths attempt to address all of these issues. Their &lt;strong&gt;Insubstantiality&lt;/strong&gt; is
the new kind that always takes full damage from force attacks, and it turns off
for a turn if the monster takes radiant damage. They have no regeneration, and
&lt;strong&gt;Spawn Wraith&lt;/strong&gt; creates a minion that can’t spawn further wraiths instead of a
full monster. The weakness rider on their attacks has also been replaced by
other effects that retain the same “life-draining” flavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The differences between “basic” wraiths are big enough that I’m going to give
each book’s version its own sub-section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wraith-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Wraith (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said all of that about wraiths in general, I have little left to say
about the basic MM wraith. It’s a Level 5 Lurker with 37 HP, Regeneration 5,
Necrotic Resistance 10, and Radiant Vulnerability 5. Radiant damage also shuts
down the regeneration for a turn, as I said above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Touch&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex) does necrotic damage and weakens (save
ends). It does extra necrotic damage if the wraith has &lt;strong&gt;Combat
Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;. Once per encounter the monster can use &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Glide&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 6
squares, and any humanoid killed by it produces another full-strength wraith in
the next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wraith-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Wraith (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, the basic MV wraith is mostly composed of the general traits I
discuss above. It’s a Level 5 Lurker with 53 HP and Resist 10 Necrotic. It lacks
a numeric radiant vulnerability, but radiant damage &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; make it substantial
for a turn, and it always takes full damage from force attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Spawn Wraith&lt;/strong&gt;
produces wraith figments instead of full-strength monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Necrotic damage from the &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Touch&lt;/strong&gt; has been substantially increased, and
it further doubles if the wraith was invisible when it started the attack. No
weakness rider, though. &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Glide&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will free action now,
triggered whenever the wraith is damaged by an attack that does neither force or
radiant damage. It causes the wraith to become invisible until it attacks or
until the end of the encounter, allows it to teleport 6 squares, and &lt;em&gt;forbids&lt;/em&gt;
it from attacking until the end of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a evil lurker mechanic. I like it! An unwary party might think they just
popped a minion the first time this triggers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mad-wraith-both&quot;&gt;Mad Wraith (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wraith is different enough from the standard one that it got me wondering
that the explanation for it might be. Then it dawned on me that this is a
renamed Allip, a monster introduced in 3e that was pretty much a wraith with a
stronger insanity theme to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a level 6 Controller with 54 HP in the MM, and 73 in the MV. Both
versions have all common traits for their books, with Necrotic
Resistance 10. Let’s start with the MV Mad Wraith, which is the better one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a &lt;strong&gt;Mad Whispers&lt;/strong&gt; aura (3), which does 5 psychic damage to enemies
caught inside and slides then 2 squares. It also has the standard
&lt;strong&gt;Insubstantial&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Spawn Wraith&lt;/strong&gt; traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mad wraith’s basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Touch of Madness&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Will), which does
psychic damage and inflicts a -2 penalty to all defenses (save ends). There’s
also the &lt;strong&gt;Touch of Chaos&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Will; Recharge 5-6) which does the same psychic
damage, slides the target 5 squares, and forces it make a basic attack against
its nearest ally. A miss does half damage and slides the target 2 squares
(without the forced attack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM version has the same attacks, the Monster Manual standard traits (and
problems), and Radiant Vulnerability 5. Its Mad Whispers aura shuts down for a
turn if it takes radiant damage, but otherwise works the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wraith-figment-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Wraith Figment (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these Level 6 Minion Skirmishers gets created whenever a Monster Vault
wrait kills a humanoid. They have a standard wraith’s senses, resistances and
movement speed, but they lack the Spawn Wraith ability. Their attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;Shadow Caress&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex) that does minion-level necrotic damage and slows
for a turn. They can &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Glide&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter, shifting 6 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having one of these pop up in a fight is bad news, but not as bad as if they
were full strength wraiths. And story-wise they’re still a potential extinction
event, as they would eventually grow into “proper” wraiths given enough time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sovereign-wraith-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Sovereign Wraith (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strongest MV wraith, it likely belonged to a king or a fighting noble, as it
packs an echo of the sword it wielded in life. It’s a Level 8 Soldier with 89 HP
and all standard wraith traits with 10 necrotic resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack uses the &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Sword&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fortitude), which does
both immediate and ongoing necrotic damage, and also makes the target grant
combat advantage (save ends both). Hit or miss, the target is also marked for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sovereign wraith can also inflict a curse of &lt;strong&gt;Lonely Death&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
4-6), which allows it to make a Spectral Sword attack with an additional rider:
on a hit, all creatures except the wraith become invisible to the target. Which
is kinda terrifying when you think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sword-wraith-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Sword Wraith (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to have the same concept as the Sovereign Wraith at is root, but it’s
a lot higher-level and possesses the same issues as all the other MM wraiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sword Wraiths are Level 17 Lurkers with 90 HP and all MM wraith traits with a
Necrotic resistance of 20 and Vulnerable 10 Radiant. Their speed
is 8. They attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Sword&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex) that does necrotic damage
and weakens (save ends). They deal extra damage when they have CA, and when they
hit 0 HP they can shift 4 squares and make one last basic attack as a &lt;strong&gt;Death
Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, doing extra damage if they hit. This seems like it stacks with the
bonus damage from CA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have the usual &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Glide&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Spawn Wraith&lt;/strong&gt; powers. The
printed tactics for them are “fight until bloodied, then run away to
regenerate”. You might have noticed they have almost the same HP as the MV
Sovereign Wraith, and they also do almost the same damage due to the math
bug. The only issue preventing them from being dropped in late-heroic encounters
is their high defense and to-hit bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dread-wraith-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Dread Wraith (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is either an incredibly ancient wraith or one that was formed when hundreds
of people died at once and their animi all fused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dread Wraiths are Level 25 Lurkers with 124 HP and all MM wraith traits, with
Resist Necrotic 30, Vulnerable Radiant 15, and Regeneration 20. Their speed is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They’re surrounded by a &lt;strong&gt;Shroud of Night&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 5) which weakens all light
inside by one step: bright light becomes dim, dim light becomes darkness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Dread Blade&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex), which does necrotic damage
and weakens (save ends). They do even more extra damage when they have CA, and
when they die they release a &lt;strong&gt;Death Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3 vs. Will) which
does psychic damage and dazes (save ends). A miss still does half damage. Shadow
Glide and Spawn Wraith complete their arsenal. Yes, if a dread wraith kills a
PC, they spawn &lt;em&gt;another dread wraith&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a series of increasingly powerful encounters here, pairing dark
creepers, evistros, an immolith and a death titan with increasingly powerful
varieties of wraith. This section also mentions that wraiths pollute the
surrounding area with necrotic energy by their very presence, so now you know
how those “necrotic-infused” places that keep giving rise to undead get that
way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “angry mindless ghost” archetype is useful when designing adventures, but
D&amp;amp;D has always been remarkably redundant in this area. 4e went a ways towards
reducing this redundancy, but it didn’t go all the way since it still gives us
ghosts, specters and wraiths. I did like seeing that the Allip was rolled into
the wraith entry, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, you should absolutely use the MV versions instead of the ones in
the Monster Manual. Level up the sovereign wraith and the figments if you need
dread wraiths for the higher levels.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/22/wraith.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/22/wraith.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Archons, Storm</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-archons-storm.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing our look at the MM2 Archons entry we arrive at Storm Archons. All of
the lore we saw on the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/02/03/wir-mm-4e-archons.html&quot;&gt;original Archon&lt;/a&gt; entry and the extra bits from the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;Earth Archon&lt;/a&gt; post remain valid here, and there’s a bit more that’s specific
to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These beings are more or less the opposite of the earth archons, temperament and
tactics-wise. They’re the Raiders on the Storm, so to speak. They live in
floating cities made out of storms in the Elemental Chaos, which are always on
the move carried by that plane’s winds. Storm archons don’t much care about
whatever is under their storms, except when they grow bored and stage massive
raids for the fun of it. Their gear is made of silvery or grey metal with a
jagged, spiky look. Lightning shaped blades and such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Storm archons tend to associate with storm giants, since both like to hang out
at the same places. The most notable meeting point for the two are the howling
black tempests spat forth by the Abyss, which swirl through the Elemental Chaos
and beyond. Archons and giants love to ride these storms, whose evil energies
make them even more violent and more prone to raiding than usual. Sometimes they
also attract demons who follow and fight alongside them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In less apocalyptic situations, you might also find the archons working as
retainers for storm giants, patrolling their domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Storm archons are Medium Elemental Humanoids with the Air and Water
keywords. They’re immune to disease and poison and have 15 resistance to both
thunder and lightning. This makes them immune to a storm giant’s damaging aura,
so they do synergize well. They move by flying with a speed of 8 (hover).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;storm-archon-squallshield&quot;&gt;Storm Archon Squallshield&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wearing plate and wielding a longsword and shield, these are Level 17 Soldiers
with 168 HP. They can surround themselves with a &lt;strong&gt;Rain Wall&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 1) which
forces enemies caught inside to make DC 22 Athletics or Acrobatics checks or
fall prone. This &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; knock fliers out of the air. The test itself isn’t
terribly difficult for a PC of equivalent level, but the party’s couch potato
wizard might have a bit of trouble with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The squallshield’s &lt;strong&gt;longsword&lt;/strong&gt; does physical damage and marks for a turn. It
attacks at range with &lt;strong&gt;Snarling Lightning&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex; recharge
5-6), which obviously does lightning damage and also marks (save ends). If the
attack hits, enemies adjacent to the target take half damage and are also markec
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After marking one or more PCs, the squallshield can use &lt;strong&gt;Pursuing Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (move
action; recharge 5-6) to teleport to a space adjacent to a marked enemy, which
grants combat advantage to them for a turn. &lt;strong&gt;Mark of the Tempest&lt;/strong&gt; means that
any marked creature hit by the squallshield is also slowed (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite not being Skirmishers, Squallshields can use a combo of Snarling
Lightning and Pursuing Storm to bypass the party’s front line entirely and stick
to a squishy, which will have a hard time running away because they’ll be
slowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;storm-archon-lightning-walker&quot;&gt;Storm Archon Lightning Walker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the soldier was that mobile, imagine what this Level 18 Skirmisher can do. It
has 171 HP and all standard traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walkers fight with &lt;strong&gt;spears&lt;/strong&gt;, which do physical damage and teleport the target
2 squares on a hit. Hit or miss, the archon itself can teleport 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy enters an adjacent square, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Booming Retort&lt;/strong&gt; as a
reaction (recharge 4-6). This hits automatically, causes the enemy to take
ongoing lightning and thunder damage (save ends), and allows the archon to shift
2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Pulse&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2
vs. Reflex), which does lightning damage and allows the archon to teleport 10
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning Walkers never stand still, and keep rearranging the party’s
formation. Trying to surround them leads to mixed results as they can end up
teleporting away anyway, and doing appreciable damage with their Pulse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;storm-archon-tempest-weaver&quot;&gt;Storm Archon Tempest Weaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spellcasters of this lot, Tempest Weavers are Level 21 Artillery with 155 HP
and lots of storm control powers. Like all artillery they prefer to fight at
range. It helps that their &lt;strong&gt;Defensive Squall&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them a +2 to AC and
Reflex against ranged attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tempest weaver is likely to open up with its &lt;strong&gt;Heart of the Tempest&lt;/strong&gt; spell
(area burst 3 within 20 vs. Reflex; targets enemies; encounter), which slides
everyone it hits 3 squares, restrains them, and inflicts both 10 ongoing
lightning damage and 10 ongoing thunder damage (save ends all). The range on
this is so long it can be used as literal artillery, before the archon team
makes contact with the PCs. Its selective targeting also makes it a good option
for &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the archon front-liners have engaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its most common ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Resounding Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Fortitude)
which does thunder damage and ongoing lightning damage (save ends). If the PCs
begin closing in, the tempest weaver can try to clear some space with
&lt;strong&gt;Lightning Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs. Reflex), which does lightning damage and
blinds targets for a round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If pressed into melee the archon will be reduced to using its &lt;strong&gt;Storm Touch&lt;/strong&gt;
(melee 1 vs. Fortitude) to do lightning damage… which is actually kind of a
decent basic melee attack! Still, its ranged powers are much better in terms of
riders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have three sample encounters: one which is all storm archons (level 18), one
which has a mix of fire, ice and storm (level 18) and one with 2 tempest
weavers, a storm giant, and a thunderhawk (level 22).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the contrast between storm and earth archons. Though their damage is
still a bit buggy, storm archons also follow a clear theme in their mechanical
design. Clearly the WotC staff was following a finalized set of design rules for
this book, which wasn’t necessarily true for all the monsters in the first MM.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/20/archons-storm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/20/archons-storm.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Archons, Earth</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-archons-earth.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustration by Jim Nelson. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archons in the 4e sense were introduced in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/02/03/wir-mm-4e-archons.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt; as soldiers
created by the primordials to face the angelic legions of the gods in
battle. Though some still serve the primordials, others sell their services as
mercenaries to other elemental clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first MM had stats for fire and ice archons, and this one brings us three
new types: earth, storm, and water. Earth and water archons already made an
appearance in our Let’s Read because they’re in the Monster Vault, but
chronologically this is their first appearance in the edition. There are enough
stat blocks in here that I feel I can give each type its own post. We start with
Earth Archons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic lore for archons remains the same, as outlined in my post about their
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/02/03/wir-mm-4e-archons.html&quot;&gt;first Monster Manual entry&lt;/a&gt;. Earth archons have some extra bits specific to
them in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth archons look like faceless stone humanoids, following the general archon
theme. Their armor and weapons are made of copper-colored metal with crystal and
obsidian accents. Their military strategy follows the “patient earth” theme:
they attack with slow and inexorable advances, and take the time to occupy and
fortify any positions they take as they do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest earth archon fortress is Thrak-Harda in the Elemental Chaos, which
is ruled by the stone titan King Brakkamul and was built to guard the Diamond of
Despair. Legend has it that the fortress is meant to protect the outside world
from the Diamond, and not the other way around. No one seems to know why it’s so
dangerous, but the Dao (cousins of the djinns and efreets) have been obsessed
with it for a very long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth archons are Medium Elemental Humanoids with the Earth keyword. They have
Tremorsense 20 and are immune to disease, poison, and petrification. Their
ground speed is 6 with Earth Walk, which means they ignore “geological”
difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;earth-archon-ground-rager&quot;&gt;Earth Archon Ground Rager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This archon is a Level 14 Controller with 143 HP and a bunch of earth-bending
powers. These start with &lt;strong&gt;Ground Liquefaction&lt;/strong&gt;, an aura (5) that slows any
creature without the Earth keyword that starts its turn inside and doesn’t move
during it. I guess this is meant to simulate then slowly sinking into shallow
quicksand, but as written it also affects fliers. Maybe tendrils of mud reach
out to grasp them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In melee, ragers use &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;shoves&lt;/strong&gt; to fight. The former are basic
attacks, and the later are a bit weaker but push the target 4 squares and knock
them prone. Two words: stone sumotori.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range they can attack with a spell called &lt;strong&gt;Raging Earth&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20
vs. Reflex) which counts as a basic attack, does a little damage and immobilizes
(save ends). Less often they can cause &lt;strong&gt;Ground Eruptions&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within
10 vs. Reflex; recharge 5-6) which do a bit more damage and knock prone. On a
miss, they do half damage and still knock prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book says ground ragers are drawn to geologically active areas, so you can
expect additional earth-based hazards when fighting them. Good luck staying on
your feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;earth-archon-seismic-striker&quot;&gt;Earth Archon Seismic Striker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rank and file of earth archon armies is made up of Level 16 Soldiers with
160 HP. They wear plate and wield heavy shields and war picks. They also carry
javelins for throwing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those &lt;strong&gt;picks&lt;/strong&gt; are high-crit weapons that do a mix of physical and thunder
damage. The &lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt; have range 10/20 and mark the target for a turn on a
hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Seismic Stomp&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Fortitude) to deal area
damage. A miss does half damage. In either case, the targets are knocked
prone. This is a good thing for seismic strikers because the &lt;strong&gt;Ground Striker&lt;/strong&gt;
trait makes their attacks stronger against prone targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seismic Strikers have a version of the fighter’s &lt;strong&gt;Combat Superiority&lt;/strong&gt;
trait, gaining a +5 bonus to opportunity attack rolls and stopping the movement
of any target they hit with such an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As written, the Stomp is not a “friendly” attack, but I’d definitely make at
least other earth archons immune to it. This would allow strikers to stay closer
together while still keeping enough distance from each other to lure foolish
enemies into the “gaps” in their formation, where they’ll be stopped cold by
opportunity attacks and knocked prone by overlapping stomps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;earth-archon-rumbler&quot;&gt;Earth Archon Rumbler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rumblers are shock troops at the spearhead of any attack, which I imagine makes
them look like a living avalanche from afar. They are Level 17 Brutes with 204
HP, wearing plate and wielding warhammers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can use the &lt;strong&gt;warhammers&lt;/strong&gt; either for basic attacks or for &lt;strong&gt;Avalanche
Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex), which do less damage but knock prone on a hit. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Thundering Might&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them bonus damage when adjacent to more than
one enemy, so they really like to be where the fighting is fiercest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a couple of sample encounters here. A level 14 one with a mix of earth,
fire and ice archons; and a level 18 one with a troop of assorted earth archons
in the employ of a cambion hellfire magus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth archons seem to have a stronger theme than the MM archons, and better
supported by their mechanics. Their damage is still low due to the math bug, but
other than that they’re generally well-built and should be OK to use after a
damage update.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/08/archon-earth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/08/archon-earth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Ant, Giant</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-ant-giant.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ant, Giant” is the actual title for the entry. Now that’s some old-school
naming! Giant ants have been part of the game since the beginning, so this style
feels appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t a lot of mystery to giant ants. They’re red ants the size of an
adult human. Their colonies can have hundreds of individuals, and though that’s
far less than the teeming millions of a mundane anthill, they end up doing a lot
more damage due to their larger size. Once a giant ant colony gets going, it
will swiftly strip the landscape bare for miles around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most ants are classified as “workers”, and as the name implies they handle the
actual work of building the colony and keeping it fed. You also have some larger
variants that are more specialized for combat, and protect the workers. And each
colony has a single Queen who is responsible for laying eggs and perpetuating
the hive. Though the queen is unlikely to leave her chambers once the hive is
established, she’s quite dangerous and remains active throughout her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being of animal intelligence, giant ants possess the same instinct for
teamwork as their mundane counterparts, which means their colonies are more
efficiently organized than many sapient societies. They communicate by emitting
pheromone clouds, and at this scale the chemicals that make up these clouds can
actually be harmful to non-ants. Giant warrior ants are notorious for using them
as weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That bit about “stripping the landscape bare” makes me think giant ants combine
the traits of both army and leafcutter ants. So they’d both hunt other animals
directly and cut up the vegetation to serve as bedding for their vast
underground fungus farms. If that’s the case you do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; want a giant anthill
anywhere near your territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most giant ants are Medium Natural Beasts, with queens being Large. They have
low-light vision and tremorsense 10, but none of them are trained in
Perception. They all have a climb speed equal to their ground speed, though they
lack Spider Climb and so can’t cling to ceilings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several types of giant ant and all of them have some sort of
&lt;strong&gt;Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; ability, which triggers when another giant and within 10 squares
drops to 0 HP. The exact effects vary per stat block, but note that if you have
a bunch of tightly packed ants the death of a single one will trigger Frenzy for
&lt;em&gt;all the rest&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Level-wise they’re all early-to-mid Heroic, on par with the mundane guards and
soldiers for most playable peoples. This means fighting the spread of a giant
ant colony might be one of the common problems a sapient settlement has to deal
with, alongside bandits, stirges, or marauding goblins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hive-worker&quot;&gt;Hive Worker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weakest and most numerous ant caste. They exist to fulfill the functional
needs of the colony and aren’t much good in a fight, but there are a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 1 Minion Skirmishers with ground and climb speeds of 6, and a
burrow speed of 2 with Tunneling. They’re the only giant ants with a burrow
speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their only attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;. Their &lt;strong&gt;Hive Worker Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; makes them shift 2
squares, so if you kill one the horde immediately moves to fill the gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hive-warrior&quot;&gt;Hive Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warriors act as scouts and guards for worker expeditions. They’re Level 2
Skirmishers with 36 HP and a speed of 8. They attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Piercing Bite&lt;/strong&gt;
that does physical damage, and also does bonus acid damage if the target was
already taking ongoing acid damage. The warrior itself can’t inflict this, so
you’ll want to pair it with a soldier, described below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Hive Warrior Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; clears any mark or curse on them, and allows them
to shift 2 squares. Yes, this will make the party warlock sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hive-soldier&quot;&gt;Hive Soldier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stronger and scarier than common warriors, soldiers stay inside the hive to
guard it unless the queen directs them to sally forth. They’re level 3 Soldiers
with 46 HP and speeds of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with their &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt; that grab the target on a hit. They
can use their &lt;strong&gt;Acid Sting&lt;/strong&gt; against the grabbed victim, dealing both immediate
and ongoing acid damage (save ends). Note that this would allow any accompanying
warriors to get bonus bite damage against the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a soldier hits 0 HP it’s wracked by a &lt;strong&gt;Death Convulsion&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 1
vs. Reflex) which knocks enemies prone. Its &lt;strong&gt;Hive Soldier Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; gives it +2
to attacks for a turn when an ally dies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winged-drones&quot;&gt;Winged Drones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These flood out of the colony during mating season, ranging far and wide. At the
end of the season I guess the males die, and the females shed their wings and
burrow to become queens and form their colonies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A winged drone is a Level 4 Skirmisher with 55 HP. It has ground, climb, and fly
speeds of 8. Its basic attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Acid Sting&lt;/strong&gt; that does immediate and
ongoing acid damage, and it can perform a classic &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver with
it. As we already know, this allows the drone to fly its speed without drawing
opportunity attacks and sting someone at any point along the movement. Its
&lt;strong&gt;Hive Drone Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to shift 2 squares and use the sting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once bloodied, the drone can choose to violently shed its wings in a maneuver
called &lt;strong&gt;Shredding Wings&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 2 vs. AC), which does high physical
damage and causes it to lose its fly speed until the end of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hive-queen&quot;&gt;Hive Queen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like their subjects, queens are of animal intelligence. However, they have an
instinctive drive for expanding their colony and the capability to direct their
subjects to go forth and conquer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queens are Level 5 Elite Controllers with the Leader keyword. They’re size
Large, and any other ants &lt;strong&gt;In the Presence of the Queen&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 10) gain a +2
bonus to attack and damage. Their greater bulk makes them slower, so they have a
ground speed of 6 and a climb speed of 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Queens have two basic attacks: a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;kick&lt;/strong&gt;. The kick targets
Reflex, does a bit of damage, and pushes the target 3 squares. The queen’s
&lt;strong&gt;Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; allows her to shift 2 squares and use Kick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter the queen can create an &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; on a Close
Burst 4. This creates a zone that moves with the queen. Any enemy caught inside
takes 2 damage for each other giant ant that’s also in the zone. When first
bloodied, the queen issues a chemical &lt;strong&gt;Call to Arms&lt;/strong&gt; that instantly summons
four giant ant workers to the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also spray their pheromones in an &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 3 within
10 vs. Will; recharge 5-6) which does acid damage and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giant ant encounter groups will tend to contain only the various types of giant
ants: every other creature is food to them. The sample group is level 1 and has
1 soldier, 2 warriors and 4 workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before reading this entry I don’t remember ever seeing much that differentiated
giant ants from all the other giant bugs, but their MM2 lore, sparse as it is,
has me unusually inspired. Mundane ant colonies can be a major problem to
farmers, and the giant version seems to pose even more of an existential threat
than a nearby bandit or goblin lair would.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/02/ant-giant.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/04/02/ant-giant.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Ankheg</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-ankheg.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ankhegs appear in AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, and they would go on to achieve minor fame
among players because of their lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ankhegs are giant burrowing insects who dig mazelike tunnel networks and hunt by
bursting through the ground and snatching surface prey with their huge
mandibles. They also have acidic saliva, which they can spray at enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures live in “family units” consisting of a mated pair and a small
brood of young. These broodlings are rarely seen on the surface - their parents
bring prey to them underground. Other things might also be living in ankheg
tunnels, since the creatures don’t use all of it as living space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the extent of the lore we get in the MM2, but it was the bits left out
that made ankhegs low-key famous. These bits say that ankhegs prefer to dig
through soil rich in minerals and organic matter. This means forests, but it
also means &lt;em&gt;good farmland&lt;/em&gt;. Therefore, these creatures are likely to be found
very close to civilized settlements. I think I saw at least one source that said
having ankhegs underground actually improved the quality of the soil. If this
isn’t true in your campaign, it might very well be a common folk superstition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if ankhegs don’t enrich the soil, their presence might still act as an
extra security measure against the many &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; dangers from the wild, assuming
the farmers in question can develop some way of avoiding the beasts
themselves. If you walk without rythm, you won’t attract the
worm. Unfortunately, it looks like they cannot be tamed, so farming in ankheg
country makes for a very interesting life. Fortunately, you won’t find more than
one “family” of ankhegs in a given area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ankhegs are Natural Beasts, with the adults being Large and the broodlings
Small. Both have tremorsense and a burrow speed, and are of animal intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ankheg&quot;&gt;Ankheg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adult specimen is a Level 3 Elite Lurker with 100 HP. It has Resist 5 Acid
to protect itself from its own saliva, a land speed of 8, and a burrowing speed
of 4 with the Tunneling keyword, which means it leaves stable tunnels behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic ankheg tactic is for the beast to use its Stealth training and
burrowing speed to lie in wait underground until it senses prey passing
above. Then it’s going to erupt and hit its victims with an &lt;strong&gt;Acid Spray&lt;/strong&gt;
(close burst 3 vs. Reflex) which deals immediate and ongoing acid damage and
also slows (save ends both). It can do that again it if’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next it’s going to nab the nearest victim using a &lt;strong&gt;Mandible Grab&lt;/strong&gt;, which
damages and grabs (Acrobatics DC 16 or Athletics DC 14 to escape). It can only
grab one victim at once, but &lt;strong&gt;Mandible Carry&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to move normally with
a grabbed victim. If the victim struggles too much the ankheg can also &lt;strong&gt;Gnaw
and Scuttle&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action, which requires an attack roll and does physical
damage and ongoing acid damage (save ends) in addition to allowing the monster
to shift 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ankheg can put a lot of distance between itself and its victim’s buddies in
a single turn by using a double move and spending a minor action on Gnaw and
Scuttle. Still, if someone does manage to reach it while it has a grabbed
victim, it can use &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks to fight in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ankheg-broodling&quot;&gt;Ankheg Broodling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ankheg attacks are fun for the whole family, because you’re going to be jumped
by Mom and Dad, who will then carry you a ways underground so the kids can come
out and eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broodlings are Level 1 Minion Brutes, with the same tremorsense as the adults, a
land speed of 6 and a burrow speed of 2 with Tunneling. They have basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;
attacks along with a less accurate and more damaging &lt;strong&gt;Mandible Rip&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
some “splash” acid damage to enemies adjacent to the target on a
critical. &lt;strong&gt;Brood Swarm&lt;/strong&gt; gives them a +4 bonus when attacking a creature
grabbed by any ankheg. This more than negates the accuracy penalty from Mandible
Rip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 4: a pair of ankhegs and 6 broodlings plus a rage
drake that was likely their original intended victim before the party came
along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial impression of anhkegs was that they were just another big bug
monster, but the possibility of a setting where ankhegs under your farm fields
are just another fact of life makes the more interesting in my eyes. The section
on encounter groups also mentions that sometimes giant ants “take control” of a
group of broodlings after they drive their parents away, and I can almost hear
David Atenborough narrating that nature documentary.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/30/ankheg.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/30/ankheg.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Angel</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-angel.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustration by Eric L. Williams. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual gave us plenty of lore on this edition’s angels, which
you can see by reading &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/01/21/angel.html&quot;&gt;my first post on them&lt;/a&gt;. The Monster Manual 2 brings
us a few stronger angels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/01/21/angel.html&quot;&gt;my post on MM angels&lt;/a&gt; for the basics of angel lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the original post was one of the first ones I wrote on the Let’s Read, I
hadn’t settled on the present structure yet, so I didn’t say much about the
common traits of angels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angels are Immortal Humanoids with the Angel keyword, which means they don’t
need to eat, breathe or sleep. Though they have no legs, they have a land speed
of 8 and a fly speed of 12. They’re also immune to fear and have 5/tier Radiant
resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature trait is &lt;strong&gt;Angelic Presence&lt;/strong&gt;, a passive ability which inflicts
a -2 penalty on any attacks against the angel while it remains un-bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The angels from the Monster Manual 2 start at where the ones from the first book
stopped, in terms of power. This means they’re all epic level and mostly Large
in size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;angel-of-authority&quot;&gt;Angel of Authority&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the heralds and mouthpieces of a deity, and tend to handle some of the
most important tasks related to the protection and well-being of a deity’s
dominion. Your Metatrons, basically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re Level 22 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 203 HP. They fight with
a &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaff&lt;/strong&gt; doing a mix of physical and radiant damage, and shoot
&lt;strong&gt;lightning bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that do lightning damage and daze
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use their powerful voices for a &lt;strong&gt;Majestic Rally&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5
vs. Will). This does a mix of thunder and radiant damage to any enemies caught
in the area and hit by the attack, and also weakens them (save ends). A miss
does half damage with no riders. Any allied angels in the area instead gain +2
to attacks for a turn. This is why the keyword is important!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;angel-of-retrieval&quot;&gt;Angel of Retrieval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expert trackers, these angels lead squads of divine servitors and agents tasked
with recovering stolen relics or kidnapped creatures. In addition to the
abilities described in their combat stat block (below), they’re also trained in
rituals that allow it to find their quarry and quickly take the squad to it,
like Observe Creature and Planar Portal. They’re Level 22 Artillery with 162 HP
and all standard angel traits except Angelic Presence, plus a teleport speed of
5 and blindsight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as a fight starts, the Angel will use &lt;strong&gt;Hunt the Guilty&lt;/strong&gt; on an enemy
within 10 squares, likely the main kidnapper. This will make all the angels
attacks deal extra damage against that enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it’s going to use its flight and teleport speets to move within reach of
the target of the extraction and use &lt;strong&gt;Isolating Displacement&lt;/strong&gt; on it. The power
can be either used on an enemy as an attack (reach 2 vs. Reflex) to deal radiant
damage, or on an ally as a non-damaging support ability. In both cases, it
teleports the target 5 squares, and teleports the angel to a space adjacen to
the target. The idea is to teleport the target into the midst of the angel’s
more melee-capable allies, who will either protect it and help it run away if
friendly, or beat it unconscious and carry it off if hostile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will then largely stay away and fire its &lt;strong&gt;Angelic Bow&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20/40
vs. AC), which does radiant damage to the target and a smaller amount to any
other enemies adjacent to it. Perfect for disrupting tight formations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also perfect for disrupting formations is &lt;strong&gt;Clear the Way&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 3 within
10 vs. Fortitude; recharge 5-6), which deals radiant damage and slides the
targets 3 squares. A miss deals half damage and slides 1 square. This could be
used to clear a corridor for ther angel’s allies to escape, or to delay
pursuers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If forced into melee, the angel of retrieval will defend itself with a &lt;strong&gt;short
sword&lt;/strong&gt; that deals radiant damage, though this is clearly a sub-optimal
situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;angel-of-light&quot;&gt;Angel of Light&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angels of light are a little different from most of their relatives. They’re the
embodiments of a deities subconscious toughts, who form spontaneously in the
Astral Sea in their multitudes. Angels of light are driven to enact the thoughts
that spawned them, but they’ll also readily work for more powerful angels whose
dispositions match theirs. Once formed, an angel of light is an independent
individual. There have cases where they end up acting contrary to their
originating deity’s wishes because the god has changed their mind, or because
the thought was intrusive in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angels of Light are the only Medium angels in this entry. They’re Level 23
Minion Skirmishers with all common traits discussed above. They fight with
&lt;strong&gt;angelic glaives&lt;/strong&gt; that do radiant damage, and when killed explode in a &lt;strong&gt;death
burst&lt;/strong&gt; whose text is a bit confusing. I think the intent is that it’s a close
burst 10 vs. Fortitude that does 10 damage to enemies in the area and heals
non-minion angels for 10 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;angel-of-supremacy&quot;&gt;Angel of Supremacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These described simply as “the strongest angelic fighters”, they’re said to
guard the homes of the gods and form the backbone of divine strike forces in
serious cosmic conflicts. I can’t shake the feeling that Asmodeus was one of
these before he rebelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angels of Supremacy are Level 24 Soldiers with 226 HP and all common angel
traits. They fight with Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;spears&lt;/strong&gt; that do a mix of physical and thunder
damage, so here’s a surprise for PCs who loaded up on radiant resistance. They
also have &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes them pretty good at restricting
enemy movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll likely start a fight by moving into a chokepoint and casting &lt;strong&gt;Astral
Brilliance&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Reflex; encounter). This deals radiant damage
and creates a zone that lasts until the end of the encounter. While inside the
zone, the angel’s attacks all deal extra radiant damage. Then they’ll attack a
particularly troublesome enemy with the &lt;strong&gt;Light of Justice&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10
vs. Fortitude), which deals radiant damage on a hit and marks the target for the
whole encounter as an effect. From that point on they can use &lt;strong&gt;Summons to
Justice&lt;/strong&gt; (minor 1/round) to pull the marked target 1 square closer to
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging by those power names, I think they might have been named Angels of
Justice before an editing pass gave them this more sinister name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;archangel&quot;&gt;Archangel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a monster, but a template along the lines of those that first
appeared in the DMG 1. It’s meant to represent a higher-ranked angel that might
even be the greatest authority in a divine dominion aside from the actual
god. The template can be applied to any angel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how I would apply it: I’d take a “regular” angel, and add the elite save
bonus (+2) and action point. If the angel was already elite, I’d upgrade it to a
solo with the +5 save bonuses and a total of 2 action points. In either case I’d
double its listed HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I’d add the template powers: &lt;strong&gt;Avenging Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when an
allied angel hits 0 HP and allows the angel to shift 2 squares and make a basic
melee attack against the slayer. And &lt;strong&gt;Overwhelming Presence&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5
vs. Will; enemies only; encounter) which does radiant damage and stuns for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would then probably tweak its basic attack so it can be done twice in the same
turn, which is common in elite monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to ammend my speculation, I’m pretty sure Asmodeus used to be an Archangel
of Supremacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the 4e concept of angels, and so having more of them is cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample encounters in the MM2 are organized a little differently, with one after
each stat block instead of all of them being at the end of the entry. The ones
we get here are most all-angel teams, made up of a mix from the MM1 and MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notable exception is again the Angel of Supremacy encounter, which has three
of them along with a Tormenting Ghost (evil!) and a Deva Fallen Star
(super-evil!). This is a reminder that not all angels serve good deities, and
that creatures with “supremacy” in their names are creepy.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/27/angel.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/27/angel.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I write this, I have just finished a &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;Let’s Read of the first D&amp;amp;D 4 Monster
Manual and Monster Vault in parallel&lt;/a&gt;, which took me about one year and four
months to complete and and around 2 years and 2 months to finish posting
here. This means it’s time to start up on the Monster Manual 2!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published in 2009, this book includes both more varieties of monsters that
appeared in its predecessor, and those that are new either to the game or to
this edition of it. There’s not much in the way of preamble in its text: after
explaining the same thing I just did in the previous sentence, it launches into
a description of the stat block format and then goes right to the monster list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I do the same, I’m going to use this post to describe some useful
information for people unfamiliar with either D&amp;amp;D Fourth Edition, or the
conventions I’ve adopted over time while going through the first Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fourth-edition-encounter-basics&quot;&gt;Fourth Edition Encounter Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you don’t need to be intimately familiar with Fourth Edition D&amp;amp;D to
understand my writeups, it helps to know some basic terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4e uses the same level scale for monsters as it does for PCs. Monsters of the
same level are all worth the same amount of XP, and you calculate an encounter’s
level by adding up their XP values and adjusting it a bit for the size of your
PC party. The game’s platonic ideal of a “balanced encounter” is one where the
party faces a group of monsters of the same size and level as themselves. Note
that “balanced” here means a fairly easy fight of the sort the PCs can go
through several times per day. To make it harder increase either the number or
level of monsters, and vice-versa. A “level+1” or “level+2” encounter is
challenging, a “level+3” or “level+4” one are boss battle material. A difference
of +5 or greater is one of those situations where the PCs might be better off
running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levels go from 1 to 30, though some rare monsters meant to be “final bosses” for
epic campaigns go a bit beyond that. It’s perfectly possible to have an entire
campaign where the party never fights a “balanced”, same-level battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some monsters are “Elite”, which means they are more powerful and are worth two
regular creatures in the encounter building formula. Others are “Solos” and are
worth four regulars - but despite the name might not make for a fun encounter
all by themselves. Combat is a team sport! Last and least, a few are “minions”
which do less damage and go down in one hit. Four of these are worth a single
regular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that you should never evaluate a monster in isolation. Always
assume it’s going to fight alongside a team of other opponents with
complimentary roles and abilities. This is true even for a lot of solo monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monster-roles&quot;&gt;Monster Roles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monster’s role describes both the sort of tactic you should employ when using
it, and acts as a “class” of sorts. A monster’s attack bonuses, defenses, and HP
all depend on its level and role, not on what type of creature it is like in
3.x.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skirmishers&lt;/em&gt; have baseline stats across the board and abilities that make
them highly mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brutes&lt;/em&gt; hit hard in melee and take a lot of killin’. They have high HP, high
damage, and reduced AC.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soldiers&lt;/em&gt; are also melee combatants, but have high AC and tend to have
abilities similar to that of a PC fighter, being good at preventing the enemy
from targetting their more fragile buddies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lurkers&lt;/em&gt; have attacks that do a lot of damage but require some setup. A
typical lurker will have some sort of “routine” where it makes a big attack
one turn and spends the following turn setting it up again. This makes them
good for ambush scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Controllers&lt;/em&gt; have stats similar to those of a skirmisher, but their abilities
are a mix of ranged and melee attacks that also inflict negative conditions on
the PCs or shape the battlefield in other ways.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Artillery&lt;/em&gt; monsters are fragile and have lousy melee attacks, but their
ranged attacks are stronger and more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing an encounter, you’re usually supposed to mix and match the roles
so that they complement each other. &lt;em&gt;In general&lt;/em&gt; you want a “front line” made up
of soldiers and brutes, with artillery and controllers hanging back and
providing ranged support, and with lurkers and skirmishers running around the
edges trying to get past the PC’s own front line. The exact composition of your
Team Monster will of course alter this in all sorts of interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of monster roles means we’ll often encounter monsters with several
different stat blocks, which allow you to do something like an “all-bullywug
fight” that’s still tactically interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dreaded-math-bugs&quot;&gt;The Dreaded Math Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the foundation of the encounter design system in 4e was really solid, it
took a bit of time for the writers to fine-tune the math. Monsters from the
first Monster Manual generally did too little damage. Elites and Solos also had
defenses that were too high, and high-level solos in particular had ridiculously
large HP totals. All of this could lead to fights that were both too easy and
too long to be fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Monster Manual 2, some of these problems were fixed: Elites and Solos
lost their defense bonuses, and Solos have about 20% less HP than they would
have under MM1 rules. Brutes and soldiers also had their accuracy fine-tuned
(the former missed too much, the latter were too accurate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this point on you also start seeing minions with roles: where a MM1 monster
might have been described as a “Level 10 Minion”, here you might get a “Level 10
Minion Brute” for example. Role affects a minion’s defenses and damage, but not
their HP, which is always 1 with a “minions can’t be damaged by missed attacks”
condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem still remains: damage is still too low, by an amount that increases
with monster level. So a level 1 or 2 monster doesn’t suffer from this at all,
but a level 25 epic threat will hit like a feather pillow when it should be
hitting like a speeding truck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re preparing a 4e adventure and you need to fix a MM2 stat block
yourself, the famous &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogofholding.com/?p=512&quot;&gt;Monster Manual 3 on a Business Card&lt;/a&gt; post from Blog of
Holding has a wonderful summary of the definitive formulas, which you get in a
longer form in one of the DMG update PDFs that WotC published back in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An even quicker fix is to add half the monster’s level to all of its damage
rolls, as outlined in this &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogofholding.com/?p=782&quot;&gt;other Blog of Holding&lt;/a&gt; post. So, for example, add
+5 to all damage rolls for a level 10 monster. This should get you close enough
to the “correct” figures.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/25/wir-mm2-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/25/wir-mm2-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a GURPS Spaceplane: The Second Iteration</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/mac-rebisz-20150220-esa-spaceplane-001.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fictional ESA spaceplane.
    Illustration by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/3q14v&quot;&gt;Maciej Rebisz.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/03/06/spaceplane.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we used GURPS Spaceships rules to build a “minimum
viable spaceplane” at TL8, with no superscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company, Octopus Aerospace, builds one of those and sells it to the
Kerbal Space Program for close to a billion GURPS dollars&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and after using
it for a few launches Director Kerbman comes back to us with a few change
requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His astronauts have complained that the Mark I Spaceplane handles very poorly
for its size. They’re entering a phase of their program where future missions
will require a lot of precise orbital maneuvers, like docking and such, so they
need a ship that can do better at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to satisfy KSP’s requests because we want a slice of their inifinte
budget, but we’re also committed to making only Single Stage To Orbit craft. How
can we satisfy both of these requirements?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-mark-ii&quot;&gt;Building the Mark II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still using “realistic” TL 8 for our Mark II, and it’s still streamlined
and winged just like its predecessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in our previous post, a TL8 craft capable of reaching orbit can only
spare 10% of its mass to systems that are not fuel tanks or chemical engines. We
achieved that in the Mark I by shrinking our control systems and cargo bay,
filling the freed space with additional fuel tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want a full size control system for the second iteration, but having that
means we’ll be short on delta-V and can’t make an orbital insertion. We have to
shrink something else to compensate. We’re already shrunk the cargo bay, and I
don’t want to shrink the armor because I’m envisioning as the craft’s heat
shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about the engine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our resulting configuration is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x Metallic Laminate Armor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x SM +8 control room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x 15-ton cargo bay&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;17.33 x Fuel Tanks (865 tons rocket fuel)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x SM +7 Chemical Rocket Engine (1G Acceleration)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One lone G of acceleration is useless for leaving Earth… in a traditional
rocket. We have wings! According to GURPS Spaceships p. 37, a winged craft can
take off and reach Earth orbit even if its acceleration doesn’t exceed 1G.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leaves us with the following stat line for our Mark II space plane:
&lt;strong&gt;dST/dHP&lt;/strong&gt; 70; &lt;strong&gt;Air Hnd/SR&lt;/strong&gt; +3/4; &lt;strong&gt;Space Hnd/SR&lt;/strong&gt; -2/4; &lt;strong&gt;Move&lt;/strong&gt; 1G/6.05mps;
&lt;strong&gt;LWt&lt;/strong&gt; 1000; &lt;strong&gt;Load&lt;/strong&gt; 15.3; &lt;strong&gt;SM&lt;/strong&gt; +8; &lt;strong&gt;Occ&lt;/strong&gt; 4; &lt;strong&gt;dDR&lt;/strong&gt; 0/2/0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model’s Air Handling and Stability is pretty awesome when compared to that
of most contemporary airplanes. Its space handling is still not exactly
spectacular, but it’s the best we can do for a ship of this size at TL 8, and
should help with those delicate maneuvers. It takes longer to reach orbit due to
its lower acceleration, but it still has the same Delta-V. Finally, it has space
for one additional crew member, allowing KSP to bring extra scientists or other
mission specialists along with the payload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheaper engine and more expensive control room balance themselves out. The
Mark II costs the same as the Mark I: a nominal $8.8M for the craft and $693,200
for a full load of rocket fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-notessales-pitch&quot;&gt;Bonus Notes/Sales Pitch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I forgot to mention in the previous post: both the Mark I and
Mark II Octopus Carnival Spaceplanes can take off from conventional runways,
dispensing with the need for an expensive launch pad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mark I would probably require a launchpad if you want to use those 3Gs of
acceleration right away, but if I remember correctly liquid fuel engines can be
throttled. So you can take off using a jet-engine-equivalent 1G and throttle up
when you reach a higher altitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you multiply their nominal cost by 100 for the extremely limited
production run, you still end up with a cost-effective system. SpaceX’s
semi-reusable rockets cost between $50M and $150M &lt;em&gt;per launch&lt;/em&gt;. The real-world
Space Shuttle cost between $500M and $1.5B per launch. The Saturn V cost about
$1.6B per launch in modern dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our fictional spaceplane would cost little more than the cost of a load of
fuel. Sure, it’d need to undergo maintenance between flights, but it probably
wouldn’t need to be practically rebuilt like the real-world systems. So perhaps
we’re looking at $2M per launch or so? It practically pays for itself in six
launches or so when compared to the “competition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, that’s a very optimistic assumption. In your games you’re always free
to assume Octopus Aerospace is full of shit and this thing is a lemon in all its
incarnations. It’s what prevented all those real world spaceplane projects from
going forward, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;$880M, or its nominal cost multiplied by 100 because it’s a production
run of one. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/10/spaceplane.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/10/spaceplane.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>spaceships</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a Spaceplane: A GURPS Spaceships Exercise</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/mac-rebisz-20150220-esa-spaceplane-001.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fictional ESA spaceplane.
    Illustration by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/3q14v&quot;&gt;Maciej Rebisz.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading about Kerbal Space Program recently, and it made me want to
try my hand at designing some GURPS spaceships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the terms that often gets thrown about when talking about near-future
space tech is “Single Stage to Orbit”, or SSTO. This would be a vehicle that can
go from ground to orbit all by itself, without needing any detachable
boosters. In the real world, a lot of plans for building one of these have been
conceived and dropped, but we don’t have a real example yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How close does GURPS Spaceships think we are to such a thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll try to design a spaceplane, a popular type of theoretical SSTO
craft. The basic idea is that they take off and fly to the upper atmosphere
using air-breathing engines, and only then activate their rockets to reach
orbit. After completing their mission, they can re-enter atmosphere and land by
gliding. Spaceplanes are an attractive concept because they can use a lot less
fuel to reach orbit, are fully reusable, and easier to maintain. Plus they tend
to look really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mission-statement-and-design-options&quot;&gt;Mission Statement and Design Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this attempt, we’re going to assume a realistic TL8 setting (“present-day
technology”), giving us access to TL7 and 8 items from the book. I’ll
arbitrarily assign it SM +8, making it a 1000 ton craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, our craft is SM +8, TL8, streamlined, and winged. It must take off
from the ground on Earth and reach orbital velocity using without the aid of
external boosters or detachable stages, while carrying a multi-ton payload in
its cargo hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means it must have a total delta-V exceeding 5.6 miles per second after all
the calculations are done&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We get a bonus 0.3 mps if we launch eastwards
from the equator, but having the craft reach the number on its own would allow
it to launch from anywhere in the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fixed-systems&quot;&gt;Fixed Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design options above lock down 3 of the 20 systems we have available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need 1 armor system because we’re streamlined.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a control room (1 system).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a cargo bay (1 system).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our purposes in this post it doesn’t matter what the armor is made of, but
we might as well use Metallic Laminate since we’re designing a “cutting edge”
craft. The remaining 17 systems will be split among engines and fuel tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At our TL, we have two engine options: the Chemical Rocket and the Jet
Engine. They both help, but use different fuel sources. Adding jet engines means
we need to figure out their top airspeed and subtract that from the necessary
delta-V to reach orbit. Rocket delta-V is purely a function of how many tanks we
dedicate to rocket fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempt-1-mixing-rockets-and-jet-engines&quot;&gt;Attempt 1: Mixing Rockets and Jet Engines.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first draft had the following configuration for our 17 “free” systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 Jet Engines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Chemical Rocket Engine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14 Fuel Tanks (13 for rocket fuel, 1 for jet fuel).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jet fuel allowed us to run the jets for half an hour, which was more than
enough to reach maximum speed and altitude. They lowered our target to 4.63 mps,
but that’s not enough. Combining the rules for chemical rockets and fuel tanks,
our rocket had 3.12 mps of delta-V available to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be good for a fancy passenger plane for people with money to burn,
but not for a SSTO vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempt-2-rocket-plane&quot;&gt;Attempt 2: Rocket Plane&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we build an all-rocket engine assembly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Chemical Rocket Engine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16 fuel tanks (all rocket fuel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding up the delta-V for this version is easier, and we do end up with more of
it, but it’s still not enough. We get 4.8 out of 5.6 mps. So close, yet so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this configuration gives us is a reusable &lt;em&gt;launch-assist vehicle&lt;/em&gt; can get
its 50-ton payload &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; to orbital speeds. The payload itself would need to
be another vehicle that could provide the remaining 0.8 mps of delta-V itself,
and perhaps include a bit more for maneuvers once in orbit. The LAV can spend
all of its own fuel and glide down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempt-3-cheating-with-optional-rules&quot;&gt;Attempt 3: Cheating with Optional Rules.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve run up against one of the harsh realities of the Spaceships design
rules. Using only TL7-8 chemical rockets, you simply can’t make an orbit-capable
vehicle with less than 17 fuel tanks. A traditional disposable rocket can be
modeled with 1 chemical rocket system, 17 fuel tanks, and an upper stage with an
SM 2 smaller than the rocket itself. This upper stage has the armor needed by a
streamlined craft, and the discarded lower stage burns up on re-entry. Our
spaceplane faces some trouble because it needs to include that armor system
itself, leaving us 1 fuel tank short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way we can make it work is by pulling in an optional rule from GURPS
Spaceships 7 p. 4: Smaller Systems. By shrinking both our cargo bay and control
room to SM +7, we decrease our cargo capacity to 15 tons, decrease our
Handling/SR in by 1, and add 1.33 fuel tanks to our all-rocket spaceplane. That
gets us 6.05 mps of delta-V, enough to launch from anywhere on the planet and
still leave us some reserves for maneuvers and corrections. It carries less than
the equivalent disposable rocket but is fully reusable, able to land by gliding
even with an empty fuel tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We leave the armor system at the same size because it’s meant to serve as a heat
shield on re-entry, so it’s probably placed in the central hull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img width=&quot;512&quot;
  src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c2/ED97-43938-1mod.jpg/512px-ED97-43938-1mod.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A X-33 and a VentureStar craft. NASA, public domain, via Wikimedia Commons.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing we just designed is remarkably similar to the Lockheed-Martin
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VentureStar&quot;&gt;VentureStar&lt;/a&gt;, at least if the stats in the Wikipedia article are to be
believed. This is a project for a SSTO spaceplane whose most famous product is
the X-33 prototype, a scaled-down version of the final design intended to test
some of its technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VentureStar was supposed to be a lot simpler to maintain than the space shuttle,
and was intended to be available for sale to private companies and not just to
NASA, kick-starting a wave of private space exploration. The project was
cancelled in 2001 because its fuel tanks were too hard to manufacture using the
technology of the time. Ironically, better manufacturing techniques were
discovered a few years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from having to contend with the “harsh truth” of the design rules we
already mentioned, our spaceplane also illustrates what seems to be a constraint
plaguing real-world designers: separate air-breathing and rocket engines are
inefficient. Go rocket-only or get you an engine that can do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its final stats are: dST/dHP 70; Air Hnd/SR +2/3; Space Hnd/SR -3/3; Move
3G/6.05mps; LWt. 1000; Load 15.3; SM+8; Occ 3; dDR 0/2/0. The Space handling is
terrible, but workable when the mission is “get up, release the payload, get
down”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our spaceplane costs $8.8M according to the design rules. Of course, that’s its
price if it was mass-produced and commercially available. The rather more
bespoke space program manufacturing model means it could cost up to 100 times
more. It runs on liquid hydrogen/liquid oxygen rocket fuel, a full load of which
costs $693,200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LAV version has better handling and stability (+3/4 in air and -2/4 in
space) and costs about $40K less to fuel, and can deliver a bigger payload as
long as that payload has some delta-V of its own. But it’s not a spaceplane, so
nyeh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I like using a proper measurement system, but all of the book’s formulas
are in miles, so I’ll have to use that to avoid getting confused during the
design process. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/06/spaceplane.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/06/spaceplane.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>spaceships</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Traits Appendix</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I close the curtain on this Let’s Read, there’s one more thing to
discuss. I had forgotten it was there at all! Back when the Monster Manual had
just been published, though, I remember thinking it was a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been talking about the animal appendix on the Monster Vault, but the
Monster Manual also has an appendix. This one is filled with stats for using
several of the book’s entries as playable characters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them are for characters from that were traditionally considered “monster
races”, others are for races that had been popular in previous editions but
didn’t fit into the Player’s Handbook. The full list is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bugbear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doppelganger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Githyanki&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Githzerai&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gnoll&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gnome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goblin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hobgoblin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kobold&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minotaur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Orc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shadar-kai&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shifter (Longtooth and Razorclaw)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warforged&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each one has more or less the same information as a basic racial stat block from
the PHB: Average height and weight, ability score bonuses, size speed, vision
modes, starting languages, skill bonuses and a racial power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I forgot this appendix even existed is because it slowly became less
relevant as more 4e material was published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even at the start the appendix races were already a little bit behind
mechanically, since the ones from the PHB had a handful of extra racial feats
each and these didn’t. The gap widened as further player option books came out
with yet more feats and stuff like racial paragon paths. And finally, several of
the appendix races would have more complete versions published in future books,
rendering the appendix version obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Doppelgangers, Shifters and Warforged would appear in the Eberron Player’s
Guide.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gnomes would appear in the PHB2. Half-Orcs too, which you could just reskin
into full orcs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Githzerai and Minotaurs would appear in the PHB 3.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Drow would appear in the Forgotten Realms Player’s Guide and then in Heroes of
the Forgotten Kingdoms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s almost all of them, isn’t it? Gnolls and Shadar-kai would get articles in
Dragon or Dungeon, but they still ended up with less support overall. At some
point in the edition the ability score bonuses also went from “+2 to these two
fixed scores” to “+2 to one fixed score and +2 to one of these other two
scores”, and some of the races here never did get that third option. Still, this
appendix was pretty useful before all of this extra material came out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this slightly maudlin post finally finishes our Let’s Read of the first
Monster Manual! I hope you enjoyed it. I plan on doing the other two and the
other Vault, and hopefully I’ll take less time to post those in their entirety.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/01/traits-appendix.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/01/traits-appendix.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
