<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 16:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 16:36:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Review: GURPS Gun Stats</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine the following situation: you want to feature a certain gun in your
campaign, but you want to do it “properly”. You’re not the kind of GM who would
feel good about just tossing some random numbers in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weapon in question is not in any of your books, and it’s different enough
from the ones that are that you can’t just reskin an existing gun. That’d be the
same as using random numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the story above resonated with you, then you’ll love GURPS Gun Stats. It
gives you an official system to write up GURPS 4th Edition stats for guns
starting from their real world data. If the lack of these rules stopped you
before, you’ll love this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, players who were really into statting up guns might already have been
doing this for years by either building them using the rules from GURPS Vehicles
for 3rd edition, or by using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamingballistic.com/2022/04/11/old-ballistics-spreadsheet-a-repost/&quot;&gt;very scary unofficial spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; cooked up
by Douglas Cole for his own use. Gun Stats is still useful for them, as it’s
much simpler than the spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-looks&quot;&gt;How It Looks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a typical Warehouse 23 PDF. All black and white, with the by now
classical GURPS two-column layout combined with the usual excellent table of
contents and index. Its written by David Pulver with additional
material by S.A. Fisher Hans-Christian Vortisch, which is kind of a seal of
quality in itself when it comes to gun-nut material in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interior art is mostly a mix of illustrations clearly based on photos or 3D
models with a weird “acid etching” surface filter applied to them to unify the
look. You also have a few hand-drawn illustrations. The art credits are fairly
long, listing several photo repositories and 3D studios in addition to a couple
of individual artists. I admit the “acid etching” filter made me take a closer
look, but I believe all the art in this book is either drawn or edited by human
hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Totally-Not-From-Assassin’s Creed lady on page 9 has a bit of an awkward
pose, but it’s organic awkwardness. The rest of the pieces are fine, and look
good without getting in the way of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How It Works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I found nifty about the book is that it’s more than a collection of
formulas. It has some instruction on how to actually do the research to get that
real-life gun data, and a little checklist. You’ll need things like the empty
weight, barrel length and overall length of the gun itself; the weight and
dimensions of its projectile and of the whole cartridge; and how much propellant
it uses per shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of those stats (like the weights and costs) can be written straight into
the stat sheet, while others are used in relatively simple equations to derive
stuff like damage, Accuracy, and range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it. While those simple calculations can still be a little intense
they’ll get you the results you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the book you have a printable checklist for your own research, and
three example weapons: a French anti-material rifle, a 19th-century 6-pounder
cannon, and the gun on the M1A2 Abrams tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caveats-and-annoyances&quot;&gt;Caveats and Annoyances&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book works best when dealing with historical or modern guns that have ample
information available to the public, whether in Wikipedia, more specialized
sites, or even sales brochures. The less information is available for a specific
weapon, the more you’ll have to guesstimate when filling your checklist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can already see this with the Abrams tank gun here. Recent data about it and
its ammunition is classified, so they either use Gulf War-era information or
just make educated guesses about some of its measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fictional guns will often be harder, because they very often lack a lot of
measurements entirely, as those weren’t necessary to tell the story. You’ll have
to come up with those yourself, or maybe go looking for the work of other fans
who have already spent a ton of time doing exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all perfectly doable, but presumably you wanted this book because you
didn’t want to guess all the numbers. On the other hand, doing this will give
you a pretty good ideas of the ways in which this or that fictional weapon is
unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final annoyance for me specifically: like all other GURPS books, this one uses
Imperial measurements exclusively for its calculations. Yes, even though modern
gun data is often presented in metric. You gotta convert all of that to feet,
pounds, and inches before doing the work, which is doubly annoying to me because
I’m going to convert a lot of that right back for the final writeups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS Gun Stats gives me the same impression as a classical UNIX or Linux
command line tool. It’s designed to do one job, it does that job pretty well
despite some usability issues, and it has a lot of options that can be difficult
to remember without looking at the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need to do that job, this is the tool for you, and the learning curve is
worth it. If you’re happy to just toss some eyeballed stats onto a table and
call it a day, then you can skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/20/review-gurps-gun-stats.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/20/review-gurps-gun-stats.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>review</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels has a project page!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/lets-play-hells-rebels/&quot;&gt;right here&lt;/a&gt;, and you can also access it via the Projects link on the
site’s header. Turns out I’ve already published a lot of stuff about this
project over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/18/lphr-project-page.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/18/lphr-project-page.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels: A Decision</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in a &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2025/12/22/lphr-background-change.html&quot;&gt;post back in December&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve been actually playing this
solo game in a sporadic fashion for years. And as I said back when I started, I
planned to post it here. So why didn’t I?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it was anxiety over art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I was going to do was to post the stats for my player
characters, and since these were going to be “proper blog posts”, I decided I
wanted to have illustrations for them just like I have for all the other
characters I posted before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My method of procuring them was going to be the same. I’d use search indexes and
trawl some specific art sites for published images I could add to the post, with
proper credit and a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For certain characters, that’s dead easy. But for a couple of others I ended up
never finding an image that &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; matched what I wanted. Or when I did find
one that had the right vibe, it turned out the artist explicitly forbade this
kind of usage, even with proper credit. Also one of my sources was Pinterest and
I had just learned that one site had a serious “proper credit” issue. Whoops!
What to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know exactly what suggestion is already forming in a lot of your brains right
now, and I’m gonna stop y’all right there and say “no”. I’m not using AI for
this, or anything else. Not now, not ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after way too long you’ll get those posts without illustrations at all. I
can’t draw, but I can write, so you’re getting verbal descriptions. And maybe
then I can finally proceed with publishing this.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/11/lets-play-hells-rebels-announcement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/11/lets-play-hells-rebels-announcement.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels: Origin Corrections</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Wait,” you might ask, “are you still doing this?”. Yes, I am! I have been doing
it since shortly after the last time I talked about it, off and on, but I
haven’t posted anything else here in the blog for entirely personal reasons that
I should overcome any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re going to start with a little correction here, because over the course
of my play, I’ve looked at the timelines a bit closer and the details for the
Knight of the Deep &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.htlm&quot;&gt;origin&lt;/a&gt; don’t make sense as written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC arrives at Kintargo at the start of Adventure 01, which is supposed to
last at least eight weeks or so given the pace at which the “strategic”
rebellion turns move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the aquatic elves that origin is concerned with rescuing are only
captured in the final stretch of Adventure 02. Here’s the timeline as written in
the adventure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The elves arrive in town maybe a week or two before the day of their
capture. This would be in the middle of Adventure 02.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They are seeking Shensen’s help with their problems back home. When they fail
to find her, they spend some time exploring the waters around Kintargo before
being captured by the aboleth’s minions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The day of their capture is “fuzzy” - it’s the day before the PCs first enter
the adventure’s final dungeon. Once they do, the GM is supposed to track their
condition over time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The elves might starve before being rescued, and if they’re still alive after
two weeks they’re taken back home to be dominated by the aboleth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take the Knight’s current background as written, it would mean the elves
have been captured &lt;em&gt;before Adventure 01&lt;/em&gt;. If we want the PC to have any chance
at all to rescue the elven scouts, we either have to make the Lucky Bones delve
the &lt;em&gt;very first thing&lt;/em&gt; the PCs do after the riot, or we have to change the
background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing the former is actually no trouble in Dungeon Fantasy. Starting delvers are
already strong enough to tackle the place, you just might need to put some magic
weapons within easy reach in the first level. If that’s what you want, just have
Laria Longroad point them to the place directly instead of the Wasp Nest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have already played through the Wasp Nest storyline on my own and I
don’t want to restart the game all the way from the beginning, though, I’m going
to change the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of being sent to rescue the scouts, the Knight will be sent in to seek
Shensen’s aid. This gives them a stronger reason to stick with the rebellion,
and a better clue of which path to follow in pursuit of their goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scouts still go to Kintargo in Adventure 02, but this time they do so to
find the Knight, who has been taking much longer than anticipated to return with
Shensen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rules-wise, the only thing that changes is that the optional Obsession to find
Aava becomes an Obsession to find Shensen, worth the same number of points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also changed the description of the theme in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.htlm&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pc-origin-knight-of-the-deep&quot;&gt;PC Origin: Knight of the Deep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You come from one of the subaquatic communities off the coast of Ravounel, where
you enjoy an heroic reputation. You recently went to visit your friend Aava in
the coastal village of Acisazi, only to find the village suffering under a
strange malaise. The village’s elder told you this was caused by a curse that
was beyond her power to break, and begged you to seek the aid of Shensen, a
powerful bard and priest of Sarenrae who lived in the city of Kintargo. You
accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You arrive at this land-lubber town to find it embroiled in a lot more trouble
than you thought possible. Shensen is nowhere to be found. You suspect she
vanished into the prisons of the despotic Barzilai Thrune, and your queries have
led you to the Aria Park protest. You suspect you might need to bloody this
human despot’s nose to fulfill your mission, and that’s just fine with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;: You must belong to a species capable of breathing underwater!
Dungeon Fantasy 3: The Next Level contains two possible choices here: the Sea
Elf and the Water-Infused. From this blog, you might also pick the [Argonian][2]
or perhaps a &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.htlm&quot;&gt;Warforged&lt;/a&gt; who has been modified to be hydrodynamic and
Amphibious. And of course we also have a whole article about the [Denizens of
the Sea][5] that also contains a few usable ancestries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theme is open to any profession, but martial types should probably keep in
mind the rules for [underwater combat for fish-people][3].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: The people of Acisazi know and trust you, and Aava is your good
friend (or even a relative if you’re also a sea elf).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add Swimming, Aquabatics and Survival (Undersea) to your template as
optional skills, and should probably put some points in them during character
creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;: Add Obsession (find Shensen) (12) {-5} to your template as an
optional disadvantage. It’s what you already want to do anyway, but like the
Last Archivist’s Obsession it might drive you to unwise actions.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/22/lphr-background-change.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/22/lphr-background-change.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>character</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dungeon Fantasy &quot;Monster&quot;: Recap</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m going to write this in the same format I use for my Monster Manual Let’s
Reads, even though it’s not really a “monster”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These plump mushrooms are a about a foot tall when fully grown, and have purple
caps. They’re very distantly related to shriekers, but their abilities are much
more specialized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone disturbs a recap, the mushroom scans the person’s memories and
loudly summarizes the most important events of the last week or so of their
lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Most important” here is defined by what’s foremost in the target’s minds. Yes,
they do have a tendency to spill closely held secrets that are big sources of
anxiety or regret for the victim. Some believe recaps they were originally
developed by an underground civilization with a strong tradition in psionics to
act as interrogation tools. Nowadays you can find them in the wild inside caves
and other damp and dark places, like many dungeons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least one investigator on the surface is known to carry a potted recap around
in a specially built cage, using it for its original purpose when questioning
suspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the victim manages to resist the mind reading attempt, the recap
will still speak a bunch of unconnected nonsense words for a minute or so. Those
who are mainly concerned about noise should refrain from touching them at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recaps aren’t “monsters” in a literal sense. Despite their radio-announcer
voices, they’re nonsapient and immobile. A good whack with any weapon will
destroy your typical recap. In GURPS, it has SM -5, DR 0, and 1 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wild-recap-cluster&quot;&gt;Wild Recap Cluster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, recaps grow in clusters and work like traps. Clusters are usually
on the ground, but might also grow on walls or ceilings. If one mushroom in the
cluster is disturbed by a touch at least strong enough to jostle it, the whole
cluster “activates” and performs its narration as one big speaker. Actual damage
also counts, of course - if a damaging attack leaves at least one recap
standing, it will activate on the next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recap cluster takes up 1 hex and has the following stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Detect&lt;/em&gt;: Clusters are usually big enough to be plainly visible. Roll
&lt;strong&gt;Naturalist&lt;/strong&gt; at -2 to identify the mushrooms as recaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disarm&lt;/em&gt;: No. Attacks that deal at least 6 damage to the whole hex at once will
completely destroy all the recaps before they can activate. Anything less will
trigger them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avoid&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;DX&lt;/strong&gt; at -5 or &lt;strong&gt;Light Walk&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;Silence&lt;/strong&gt; spell will render the
cluster harmless for as long as it lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Save&lt;/em&gt;: Quick Contest of &lt;strong&gt;Will&lt;/strong&gt; against skill 16 to avoid having your mind
read. &lt;strong&gt;Magic Resistance&lt;/strong&gt; helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Effect&lt;/em&gt;: About a minute of loud noises. If the target won the contest of Will,
this will be a string of nonsense words. If they lost, the recap will summarize
the previous week of their lives as if it was the last episode of a radio
serial, potentially airing some dirty laundry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shots&lt;/em&gt;: Constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rearm&lt;/em&gt;: No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steal&lt;/em&gt;: Roll against &lt;strong&gt;Naturalist&lt;/strong&gt; to harvest one large, healthy recap
specimen per hex. This weights 1 lb. and is worth $1000 if delivered intact to
the right people back in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recap-inquisitor&quot;&gt;Recap Inquisitor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This consists of a large, healthy recap specimen planted on good soil in a clay
pot, surrounded by a small but sturdy iron cage with large gaps between the
bars. It’s used by the “right people” back in town or by unscrupulous villains
in interrogations. They just need to ask (or force) the subject to poke the
mushroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subject must win a quick contest of &lt;strong&gt;Will&lt;/strong&gt; against a skill of 16 to
prevent the ‘shroom from narrating all their dirty laundry from the past seven
days. It will speak a string of nonsense words if the subject resists, and
experienced handlers will know what that means. The cage offers DR 7 against
swinging attacks and other impacts (such as dropping the device), but the large
gaps mean it doesn’t protect against thrusting ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recap Inquisitors cost $2000 and weight 10 lbs. Monthly maintenance requires
$100 in supplies and success in a &lt;strong&gt;Naturalist&lt;/strong&gt; roll to keep the ‘shroom alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;additional-notes&quot;&gt;Additional Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put in the same resistance mechanics for the two entries but I think they’re
mostly relevant for an interrogation scenario. When you step onto a recap patch
in the wild it’s probably funnier if they just succeed and narrate your last
week. It might even be fun to have the PC’s player do the narration if they’re
so inclined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say this because in my experience PCs rarely have something to hide from each
other, so there wouldn’t be really any dirty laundry that they didn’t want
aired. Of course, if you your group &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a party of sneaky gits who do keep
important secrets from each other, then you should probably keep the resistance
test in place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/10/19/recap.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/10/19/recap.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 03: The New Order</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2025/08/04/guns-of-wolfenstein-02.html&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; of this series, we took a look at the guns that appear on
Wolfenstein: The Old Blood, whose timeline I named “Wolfenstein-2” for ease of
reference. The timeline from the 2001 game, whose guns I talked about [here][2],
was Wolfenstein-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we will take a look at the weapons that appear in Wolfenstein: The New
Order, a game that was published &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; The Old Blood (2014) but whose stories
starts right when The Old Blood ends. We’ll also make some mentions to the last
game in the trilogy, The New Colossus (from 2017) but the weapons that make
their debut in that game will be presented in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-order-plot-overview-contains-spoilers&quot;&gt;The New Order Plot Overview (Contains Spoilers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this game was launched a year earlier, its story starts off right after
The Old Blood ends, in 1946. After B. J. Blaskowicz returns to the Allies with
the location of General Deathshead’s secret hideout, they mount a massive attack
on that island fortress. This is a higher-budget version of the final chapters
of the 2001 game, which ended with Deathshead’s defeat, but things don’t that
well here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack is a disaster. Deathshead kills most of B.J.’s unit and leaves the
rest of them to die in a deathtrap. The survivors manage to escape just as the
room they’re in explodes, but the explosion buries a large piece of shrapnel in
Blazko’s brain. He washes ashore somewhere in Poland, catatonic, and since no
one knows who he is, gets sent to an asylum. He spends the next 14 years there
slowly recovering, with nearly no motor function, slipping in and out of comas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Nazi attack on the asylum in 1960 gives him the impulse he needs to complete
his recovery, and the first actual level of the game is escaping that situation
with a nurse named Anna, the other survivor of the place. They reach Anna’s
grandparents, where Blazko learns that the Nazis won the war in 1948, and that
as far as everyone knows the last members of the resistance had been captured
and sent to an “inescapable” prison in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the game is about freeing these prisoners, rebuilding the
resistance, and striking back at Deathshead through a series of daring
heists. These start with the rescue of good-guy super-scientist Seth Roth&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,
and proceed with the the capture of a giant enemy submarine, the recovery of its
nuclear launch codes from a Nazi base on the Moon, and finally an attack on
Deathshead’s fortress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blazko manages to kill Deathshead during the second attack on his fortress,
though the asshole manages to detonate a grenade as he dies. The game ends as
B. J., too wounded to evacuate, gives his allies the all-clear to launch the
nuke that will destroy this fortress for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guns&quot;&gt;The Guns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the guns here are, again, captured Nazi hardware. And
those, in turn, are “new and improved” versions of the guns we saw in The Old
Blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their actual mechanics and list of available weapons changes a bit between this
game and its sequel in ways that can be better explained by changes in artistic
and gameplay direction than by in-setting developments. The weapons presented
here are based partially on a melding of their two versions, and partially on
what I’d think would be more interesting for a GURPS Action game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post focuses on the weapons that make their first appearance in The New
Order. The next one will present the ones that first appear in The New Colossus,
using the same adaptation strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m omitting price information as usual. In a Wolfenstein-inspired game, PCs
will be picking these up from the corpses of their enemies. In other games, the
GM can figure out a price based on the prices of similar real-world weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pistols&quot;&gt;Pistols&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pistol-model-1960&quot;&gt;Pistol Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A direct descendant of the 1946 model, this one has a more futuristic look, a
double-stacked 20-round magazine, and the ability to fire 3-round bursts. It
still takes the same cinematic silencer. As before, it adds -1 to Bulk, makes
the gun cinematically silent, and also makes it only able to fire in semi-auto
mode (RoF 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If using standard GURPS skills, you need Guns (Pistol) to fire in semi-auto
mode, and Guns (SMG) to fire bursts. If using the optional skills from Pyramid
#3/65, you need Guns (Pistol), with the Burst-Fire technique for firing bursts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Pistol 1960&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;160/1800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1.4kg/0.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-arms&quot;&gt;Long Arms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the standard system, use the Guns skill that corresponds to their description
(SMG, Shotgun, Rifle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the alternate skills from Pyramid #3/65, they all use Guns (Long
Arm), of course. The Burst-Fire technique helps fire weapons at a RoF greater
than 3 without penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;american-submachine-gun&quot;&gt;American Submachine Gun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much a historical &lt;strong&gt;Thompson M1A1&lt;/strong&gt;, described in p. HT122. The
Allies mostly didn’t have access to superscience in this timeline and were
limited to historical equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allied soldiers are armed with this during the 1946 assault on Deathshead’s
compound, and the game expects you to use them for the handful of minutes
between the start of gameplay and the moment when you first grab an enemy
weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assault-rifle-model-1960&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evolution of the 1946 model, it’s lighter and uses a double-stacked 45 round
magazine, but still fires the same round. The biggest change here is an
underbarrel accessory rail that can take a mini-rocket launcher, which appears
as an upgrade midway through the game. This is detailed in the Launchers
section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-1960&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This semi-automatic rifle is about the same length as the AR, but fires a
heftier round (likely 7.92x57mm) from a 10-round magazine. It has an integral
scope. It’s a relatively rare find both in the hands of enemies and as
loot. Clearly the Nazis are bigger fans of the spray-and-pray approach to
marksmanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extended 30-round magazine is available: Shots 30+1(3), Weight becomes
6.2kg/1.05kg. The gun can also fire APHC rounds: Dam 6d+2(2) pi-.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shockhammer-model-1960&quot;&gt;Shockhammer Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another descendant of the gun from The Old Blood, this one uses a “snail drum”
magazine and a single barrel to achieve better performance than its
predecessor. The most commonly available shells for the weapon are standard
buckshot, and “shrapnel”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shrapnel shells fire red-hot fragments that ricochet off walls in a very
video-gamey way, allowing the player to hit enemies behind cover or around
corners by bouncing the shrapnel off the wall behind them. The shotgun can only
fire in semi-auto mode while using these shells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the GURPS version below, I’m treating shrapnel as Multi-Flechette shells
(High-Tech p. 174) with an incendiary effect. Damage becomes 1d+1 pi- inc; Range
becomes 100/1200; RoF becomes 3x20. GMs who wish to replicate the ricochet
effect can reduce the penalty for firing at targets behind cover when there are
suitable surfaces nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the GM’s discretion, any special shells listed in High Tech and Ultra-Tech
might also be available for this shotgun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;long-arms-table&quot;&gt;Long Arms Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Thompson M1A1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+1 pi+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;170/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.1kg/0.8kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;30+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;MP-61&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d pi-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;170/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.1kg/0.4kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;45+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/3100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;45+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;850/3750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg/0.35kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shockhammer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1d+1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.1kg/1.05kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6x9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-weapons&quot;&gt;Energy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a surprising amount of energy weapons in both games. All of these use
Beam Weapons (Rifle) unless noted otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laser weapons in this setting draw power from internal batteries that can’t be
removed without disassembling the weapon. The usual method of reloading them is
by using one of the highly dangerous industrial power outlets that seem to be
everywhere in Nazi-dominated cities and facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In The New Order, these use short-ranged wireless power transfer. In The New
Colossus, they use a thick cable with a plug that resembles a gas station
pump. I suggest picking an aesthethic and sticking to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wireless Charging&lt;/strong&gt;: The wielder must stay within 2 meters of the outlet
during the process, which causes lightning to arc between the outlet and the
weapon’s power receptors. Doing anything with the weapon other than holding it
steady will interrupt the recharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wired Charging&lt;/strong&gt;: The wielder must plug the cable into the weapon (1 Ready
Action), and then stay within 1 meter of the outlet. The weapon cannot be used
while charging. Once charging is done, it takes another Ready maneuver to unplug
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recharge time is listed for each weapon, and has more to do with the weapon’s
ability to absorb incoming power than with the outlet’s ability to provide it!
The later seems to be effectively limitless, at least on a personal scale. Yes,
these things are extremely unsafe. What happens if you stab someone with the
wired plug or intercept them with the arc of the wireless charger is left as an
exercise for the GM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some places you can also find portable batteries that can be used to top up a
weapon through a similar process. The GM will say how many shots from a weapon
an individual battery can recharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lunar-laser-rifle&quot;&gt;Lunar Laser Rifle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Moonbase level of The New Order, everyone carries a laser weapon with the
same external appearance as the Marksman Rifle. It lacks a scope, and can fire
in full-auto mode. Its performance seems to be about on par with the assault
rifle, though it is a lot better at dealing with heavily-armored
enemies. Industrial outlets recharge it at 3 shots per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being a laser weapon based on the Marksman Rifle, Nazi soldiers don’t
usually use Aim maneuvers with it, so they are no more accurate than usual when
wielding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t exist in The New Colossus, not even on Venus. Maybe it was a pet
project of Deathshead’s for the moon base, and got phased out when he died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-combined&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle (Combined)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you return to Earth after the Moonbase level, B.J.’s Marksman Rifle becomes
a combination gadget of sorts, with the scope on a hinged mount. With the mount
closed and the scope in place, it fires bullets as before. With the scope folded
away, it behaves like the Moonbase laser rifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This design is probably more of a video game quality of life decision than
something feasible in setting, but if you want to include it in your campaigns
you can treat it as a Combination Gadget per the rules on Ultra-Tech p. 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under those rules, Weight becomes 8kg/0.35kg (or 8.7/1.05 with the extended
mag). Switching modes requires a Ready maneuver, and the weapon uses the Damage,
Acc, Range, RoF, Shots and ST of whatever version is the currently active
one. Keep track of both ammo counts separately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;laserkraftwerk&quot;&gt;Laserkraftwerk&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an experimental laser weapon that B. J. “liberates” from a lab early in
The New Order. It’s about carbine-sized, and fires shots that are more powerful
than those of the lunar laser rifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LKW also has an alternate “laser cutter” module that’s useful for quietly
severing chains and cutting through chain-link fences and thin metal walls. This
does 2d(2) burn and can run continuously for half an hour on a full battery, if
it matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the game, the player can find several upgrades for the LKW,
including a scope, a double-capacity battery, and new internal parts that allow
it to fire more often or to fire a more powerful “charged” shot that’s better at
dealing with large and heavily armored opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Weapon Table below, you get stats both for the baseline version and the
fully-upgraded one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial outlets recharge the weapon at a rate of 1 shot per second with the
standard battery, or 2 shots per second with the expanded one. The final upgrade
in The New Order is an “ancient supertech” portable reactor that recharges the
weapon at a rate of 1 shot per 2 seconds whenever it’s not being fired,
regardless of its battery size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;energy-weapon-table&quot;&gt;Energy Weapon Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Marskman Rifle (Laser)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/1500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;28*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;LKW (baseline)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;LKW (fully upgraded)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12+2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;charged shot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6dx3(3) burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;**&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*: See description for recharge time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**: Drains power equivalent to 5 shots from the battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grenades-and-launchers&quot;&gt;Grenades and Launchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enemy soldiers are enthusiastic about using hand grenades in the The New Order,
and only a little less so in The New Colossus. Launcher weapons are much rarer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In The New Order, enemies use the same &lt;strong&gt;Hand Grenade&lt;/strong&gt; from the previous post
in the 1946 prologue. By 1960 they’ve switched to using Tesla grenades
exclusively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;tesla-grenade&quot;&gt;Tesla Grenade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like a modernized version of the Stick Hand Grenade used back
in 1946. Its explosive power is equivalent, but also releases an electromagnetic
pulse that can “stun” robotic and cybernetic enemies in a 4-meter radius from
the epicenter of the explosion. They must make a HT-8(2) roll or be knocked out
of action for seconds equal to their margin of failure. That (2) means that any
electromagnetic shielding that would provide a bonus to this roll only works at
half effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; applies to battery-powered weapons of any kind, which usually have
HT 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;underbarrel-rocket-launcher&quot;&gt;Underbarrel Rocket Launcher&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An accessory compatible with the 1960 Assault Rifle, this launcher fires 40mm
anti-armor rockets from a removable cylinder with a 4-round capacity. It’s
issued to soldiers that are expected to go against heavily-armored opposition,
and who are usually heavily-armored themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launcher can only be used if it’s attached to another weapon. By default
that’s the assault rifle, which has the rails to receive it, but players might
decide to get creative with their jury-rigging. It adds its weight to the
overall weight of the other weapon and worsens its Bulk by -1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the standard skill system, this uses the Guns (LAW) skill. In the alternate
one, it’s Guns (Long Arm) aided by the Payload Warhead technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hand-grenade-table&quot;&gt;Hand Grenade Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fuse&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tesla Grenade&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7d cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;linked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;HT-8(2) aff&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rocket-launcher-table&quot;&gt;Rocket Launcher Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Underbarrel Rocket Launcher&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5dx2(10) cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;–&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;linked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d cr ex [1d-1]&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heavy-weapons&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;laser-machine-gun&quot;&gt;Laser Machine Gun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old Venom machine gun from the war has been replaced with this energy weapon
in the Sixties. Like its predecessor, the Laser MG is found in fixed mounts, in
the hands of cybernetic supersoldiers, and mounted on the many models of giant
robot stomping around. It can fire for quite a bit before running dry. This can
look like either a sequence of rapid pulses or a continuous beam, but either
version uses the same stats. Enemies don’t like to aim with it either, improving
the players’ chances of survival when facing it. It’s heavy and bulky enough to
be only a “sometimes” gun for the player, used when found and quickly discarded
when empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial outlets reload it at a rate of 20 shots per second. When attached to
a fixed mount, the weapon’s Acc improves to 18, and it’s recharged as if
connected to an outlet when not firing. Attaching or detaching it takes 2 Ready
maneuvers. The weapon uses the Gunner (Beams) skill even when detached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;heavy-weapon-table&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapon Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Laser MG&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;200*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*: See description for recharge time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Seth belongs to the Da’at Yichud, an ancient society of engineers that had
been building superscience devices as a form of worship since before the
rest of humanity had organized religion. Deathshead’s inventions are all
copied from one of their vaults, which he found in the 40s. I’ve seen the
concept described as kinda problematic despite the designers’ best
intentions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/17/guns-of-wolfenstein-03.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/17/guns-of-wolfenstein-03.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 02: The Old Blood</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html&quot;&gt;our previous article&lt;/a&gt;, we took a look at the guns that appear on Return
to Castle Wolfenstein (2001), whose timeline I named “Wolfenstein-1” for ease of
reference. In this one, we’ll take a look at the timeline I called
“Wolfenstein-2”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wolfenstein-2 setting is the chronology used by the trilogy of games made up
of Wolfenstein: The New Order (2014), Wolfenstein: The Old Blood (2015) and
Wolfenstein II: The New Colossus (2017). The Old Blood is a prequel to The New
Order, so it happens first even though it’s the second game. We’ll talk about it
in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot-overview-contains-spoilers&quot;&gt;Plot Overview (Contains Spoilers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Old Blood is a retelling of the “escape from Castle Wolfenstein” story that
made up the first two chapters of the 2001 game. Where the Wolfenstein-1 version
was just a pulpier version of WW2, this one goes all in on the alternate history
approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like World War 2 in the Wolfenstein-2 timeline starts off more or less
like it did in our world, but things go off the rails somewhere along the
way. Deathshead, the same mad scientist from the 2001 game, is wildly more
successful at coming up with absurd weapons and getting them mass-produced. As a
result the war streches for longer than it did in our world. The game happens in
&lt;em&gt;1946&lt;/em&gt;, with the war still raging on and the Allies on the losing side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like in the 2001 game, B.J. Blazkowicz and Agent One infiltrate Castle
Wolfenstein. Their goal here is more well-defined - among the documents stored
in the castle, there’s a folder that details the location of Deathshead’s secret
fortress, where he’s been developing all these superweapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Castle here is much larger than it was in the first game, and has been
upgraded from its medieval roots into a giant concrete fortress full of
superscience security measures, including prototype supersoldiers tethered to
power lines. Its owner is still an occult-obsessed Nazi officer named Helga, who
now works under Deathshead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broad outline of events is the same - the two get captured, Agent One dies
under torture, Blazko escapes the castle. He heads to the nearby village of
Wolfburg, where Helga leads an archaeological dig in search of buried occult
secrets. Whatever she does triggers a sort of zombie apocalypse. Helga releases
a giant zombie and dies failing to control it. B. J. escapes with the secret
document folder after killing said zombie, completing his mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guns&quot;&gt;The Guns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the usable guns in this game are captured Nazi hardware, since you start
the game proper unarmed save for a (surprisingly effective) sharpened metal
pipe. This “early” in the timeline, a lot of the weapons presented here still
have real-world equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pistols&quot;&gt;Pistols&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pistol-model-1946&quot;&gt;Pistol Model 1946&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still mostly a &lt;strong&gt;Luger P08&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT98), with the only difference being
that it has a 10-round magazine instead of an 8-round one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It accepts a suppressor, which is available to you from the start. It weights
0.25kg, adds -1 to Bulk and makes the gun &lt;em&gt;cinematically silent&lt;/em&gt;. This means
enemies won’t notice the gun firing unless a bullet impacts the environment near
them, or if they survive being shot by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Pistol 1946&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;160/1800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1.2kg/0.3kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rifles&quot;&gt;Rifles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assault-rifle-model-46-t&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle Model 46-T&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still pretty much a &lt;strong&gt;StG-44&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT115). It has a folding foregrip not
present in the real weapon, but that doesn’t affect its stats in any way either
in the computer game or in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-bombenschluss&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle (Bombenschluss)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is likely a version of the &lt;strong&gt;Mauser Kar98K&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT111). Unlike the real
weapon, this one’s magazine is inserted from the side, which means the gun can
still be fired from a prone position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two obtainable upgrades. The first is a 10-round extended magazine
that adds -1 to Bulk and weights 0.44kg loaded. The other is a scope on a
tacticool folding mount. It adds 0.5kg to weight and changes Acc to 5+2. It can
be folded in or out of position with a Ready maneuver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;weapon-table&quot;&gt;Weapon Table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle 46-T&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/1300&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.6kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;30(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bombenschluss&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000/4300&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.5kg/0.25kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shotguns&quot;&gt;Shotguns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;double-barreled-shotgun&quot;&gt;Double Barreled Shotgun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 10-gauge classic makes two appearances: at the start of the game with a
full length barrel, and at the end with the barrel sawn off to “whippet”
length. The full-length gun uses the same stats as the &lt;strong&gt;Lefevre Automatic
Hammerless&lt;/strong&gt; from High Tech. The sawn-off one uses the stats below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shockhammer&quot;&gt;Shockhammer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a semi-automatic 12-gauge shotgun with a Rube Goldberg action. The gun
takes shells from a revolving cylinder that alternates between its twin barrels
with every cycle, which is supposed to allow for a higher rate of fire. The
stats below are somewhat inspired by the &lt;strong&gt;Daewoo USAS-12&lt;/strong&gt; from High Tech, but
there are enough differences to warrant its own stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible upgrade here is a 20-round cylinder that changes Shots to 20(5) and
Weight to 8.2/2.1kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Double-Barreled Shotgun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d-1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.15/0.15kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2x13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2(3i)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shockhammer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1d+1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.1/1.05kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3x9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grenades-and-launchers&quot;&gt;Grenades and Launchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hand-grenade&quot;&gt;Hand Grenade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enemy soldiers use a version of the historical &lt;strong&gt;“stick hand grenade 24”&lt;/strong&gt;
filled with TNT, as mentioned in p. HT190: Damage 7d cr ex, weight 0.7kg, Fuse
4-5. They’re not shy about throwing them at you if you stay for more than a few
seconds behind cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kampfpistole-war-pistol&quot;&gt;Kampfpistole (“war pistol”)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a version of a historical flare gun used in WW2 that could also fire
grenades. Its extremely limited ammo is the best choice for taking out the
tankiest enemies in the game, so I think it fires the HEAT round described in
High Tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Kampfpistole&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d(10) cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10/330&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1kg/0.1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;+ 3d cr ex linked&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heavy-weapons&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see another familiar face here: the &lt;strong&gt;Venom Heavy Machine Gun&lt;/strong&gt;, which loses
its edgy name but is basically the same weapon I already covered in my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html&quot;&gt;previous
post on Wolfenstein guns&lt;/a&gt;. It’s found in the hands of early-model
supersoldiers, and has 250 round belts weighting 10kg. Even a beefy guy like
B. J. has trouble carrying it around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incarnation of the Venom is excellent to mow down human soldiers and
zombies, but doesn’t actually do much to the supersoldiers that carry
it. Therefore we can assume it fires regular ammo instead of armor-piercing: Dam
6d+2 pi.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/04/guns-of-wolfenstein-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/04/guns-of-wolfenstein-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quar and Their Guns in GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I became aware of the Quar. Aren’t they neat?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/quar-unit.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  A squad of Quar soldiers, with officers, standard-bearer, and messenger
  squirrel handler. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://rhyfler.com&quot;&gt;https://rhyfler.com&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These funny anteater people are the stars of a couple of miniature wargames, the
28mm-scale &lt;strong&gt;Clash of Rhyfles&lt;/strong&gt; and the 15mm-scale &lt;strong&gt;This Quar’s War&lt;/strong&gt;. Both of
these have their rulebooks freely available &lt;a href=&quot;https://rhyfler.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, which is also where the
image above comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual Quar is a funny little person who just wants to chill with a hot
cup of tea and a plate of moth cakes. Quar &lt;em&gt;societies&lt;/em&gt; however are very, er,
quarrelsome, so most of their history is an endless procession of wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was motivated to write this article both because I think the setting is neat,
and because the technical information about Quar weapons in the Clash of Rhyfles
game made me think I can stat them up in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;very-short-setting-summary&quot;&gt;Very Short Setting Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wargames cover a particularly turbulent period in the history of Aldwyn, the
Quar home world. It’s marked by at least twenty years of worldwide trench
warfare between two large multinational coalitions. The tech level is somewhere
between WW1 and WW2, and this is pretty much the war that introduced industrial
warfare to their world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the idea of these adorable creatures being fed into one of the worst
meat-grinders imaginable is horrifying to you, then you get the setting’s main
idea. I’ve heard it described as “grimsical”. It replaces the “dark” vibe from
“grimdark” with “whimsical”, but it’s still grim. The cuter the miniatures for
their soldiers and tanks get, the stronger the dissonance becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clash or Rhyfles quickstart book centers on the two main factions of the
war. The Crusade is a coalition of former monarchies who successfully toppled
their old regimes and became republics. They’re led by the Republic of Tok, and
made up of many smaller nations that follow the same standards for equipment and
tactics. The rules here could be used for quar from any of those places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, the Kingdom of Coftyr leads an alliance of the world’s
remaining monarchies to stamp out this revolution. Each kingdom here tends to be
visually distinct, as their whole thing is adherence to ancient traditions and
heraldry. Therefore, the book only covers Coftyr itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free add-ons provide details for “sub-factions” allied to either side. These are
Crusader or monarchist nations who do their own thing on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual for wargames, both sides are morally ambiguous. Opposing monarchy is a
good thing in my book, but the Crusade is also the side that introduced
industrial warfare to the world. Coftyr flavor text is all about honor and
chivalry and heroism, but they adopted industrial warfare just as readily and at
the end of the day are still defenders of absolute monarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the impression that the world of Alwyn could settle into a more or less
stable configuration if everyone just stopped and signed a status quo peace
treaty, but they’ve all been fighting for 20 years by now and none of their
leaders show any sign of wanting to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual for wargames, you pick the side you think looks neater, paint them up,
and pit them against other factions in battles that would fit somewhere in those
decades of war. Most of these battles focus on infantry with the occasional
tanks thrown in. There seem to be airships, but I don’t know if they have
airplanes yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quar-in-gurps&quot;&gt;Quar in GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical Quar is about 1.5 meters tall and weights around 60kg. They follow a
largely humanoid body plan. Their skins can take on any of a large number of
hues, from yellows and greens to blues and purples and oranges. Often, they’re a
little mottled. Their diet tends to include lots of bugs, though those are often
prepared as ingredients in dishes that we would otherwise recognize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stat-wise, I’d say they are absolutely identical to humans. If you insist on
being strict, make them about a foot shorter than their ST would indicate, but
do not adjust their stats in any other way. Being a Quar costs 0 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because that’s the thing, you see? Quar are just people. The horrors inflicted
on them are horrible because &lt;em&gt;war&lt;/em&gt; is horrible, not because Quar are adorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quar-guns-in-gurps&quot;&gt;Quar Guns in GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guns in Clash or Rhyfles don’t actually have damage ratings, just range and
optional traits. The results of a ranged attack roll depend entirely on the
degree of success for your skill roll. They might leave a target unaffected,
Gobsmacked (stunned) or Taken Out, which is different from “dead”: they might
still be rescued during or after the battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the skirmish game rules include enough fluff about the infantry weapons
of the Crusade that I kinda want to try statting them up in GURPS. If I ever get
the same information for the Coftyri ones, I’ll stat them up too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book mentiones the muzzle velocity and caliber of a couple of the weapons,
and if I make a guess about the weight of the bullet I can plug those three
things in the simplest possible version of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamingballistic.com/2022/04/11/old-ballistics-spreadsheet-a-repost/&quot;&gt;unofficial official GURPS
ballistics equation&lt;/a&gt; to get a damage figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That link also contains a complete spreadsheet that demands things like chamber
pressure, which I have no chance of figuring out. So stuff like Accuracy and
range will be derived by the older method of eyeballing existing guns, as will
bullet weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers in the original material are just there for color, of course. None
of them affect the rules of the miniature wargame itself. But if we take them as
true, we see that Quar are very fond guns with big bullets and powerful
propellant charges, fired out of guns with short barrels and very light
construction. The recoil on those is gonna be ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-bogen-rifle&quot;&gt;The Bogen Rifle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signature weapon of the Crusade rhyfler, the Bogen semi-automatic rifle is
said to fire a 12mm bullet at 580m/s. It uses a 5 or 10 round magazine and
weights 2.4kg “fully loaded”. Its effective range is 150-250 meters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest real-world bullet to this one in GURPS High-Tech is the
.45-something family of rifle rounds, which are 11.43mm in diameter and weight
31 grams. After some fiddling, I decide to go with a slightly lower 27 grams for
the Quar bullet, which gives us exactly 7d damage. This is pi+ because of the
caliber. Picture them as being broader, shorter and rounder than Earth rifle
cartridges, which is in theme for all things Quar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives us a gun that packs about the same punch as a real-world M1 Garand
rifle while having almost exactly half its weight and about the length of an M16
assault rifle. That’s going to have a significant kick, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bogen&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7d pi+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;900/3500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.4kg/0.36kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-rhyshi-r4-heavy-rifle&quot;&gt;The Rhyshi (R4) Heavy Rifle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only slightly longer than the Bogen, the Rhyshi fires a huge 20mm round with a
720m/s muzzle velocity. Its magazine carries seven of those, and it’s said to
require a solid stance and firm support to shoot with any kind of accuracy. A
squad mate’s shoulder will do for support, according to the book, but I’m going
to give this rifle an integral folding bipod because I’m not a monster. A
properly braced R4 has greater range than the Bogen, and can penetrate up to
“medium” vehicular armor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closest thing to this I can find on High-Tech is the Mauser Tank-Gewehr 18,
the WW1 German anti-tank rifle. Its caliber is “only” 13mm, but it’s the largest
anti-tank rifle in that table that is even removely Quar-portable. Plugging its
bullet mass, caliber and printed velocity in our magic spreadsheet, we get 10d+3
damage, which following High-Tech convention can be rounded and written as
5dx2. Let’s also give it an armor-piercing round, because I see the WW1 tank
examples in the book have DR 45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5dx2 is the same damage as the T-Gew18, but the Rhyshi again weights less than
half of what the real gun does. It’s not that much longer than the Bogen either,
so it’s gonna be a beast to handle unless it’s properly braced. As the book
says, Quar Crusaders frequently attach a bayonet to the Rhyshi because there’s
no way it can be fired in close quarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Rhyshi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5dx2(2) pi+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100/4400&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.5kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;18B†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grifkis-shotgun&quot;&gt;Grifkis Shotgun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a 10-gauge, six-kilo trench gun firing buckshot ammo. The only Crusade
gun to still be largely hand-made, it’s carried by officers as a badge of honor
and a symbol of courage. The illustration shows its barrel is fairly short, but
it still has a shoulder stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No need to fiddle with spreadsheets this time, we have a 10G double-barrel
shotgun in High Tech. Let’s borrow its stats and adjust for the shortened
“whippet” barrels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Grifkis&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d-1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6kg/0.15kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2x13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2(3i)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short barrels give this gun a more pronounced muzzle blast (+1 to Hearing
and Vision to locate when fired in the dark). I’m using the listed weight for it
here, which makes it about 50% heavier than the real world example from
High-Tech. Big caliber, two barrels, extra chonky? This is basically the Doom
Super Shotgun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;h-11a-light-machine-gun&quot;&gt;H-11a Light Machine Gun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the book, this LMG fires the same round as the Bogen rifle, and the
Crusade likes to use it as an offensive squad support weapon. It appears longer
than the rifle, and can also be used in vehicular mounts when the force can’t
find heavier MGs to put in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I’m just going to crib from High-Tech again, and blend some of the
Bogen’s stats with those of the MG34.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;H-11a&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7d pi+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;900/3500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15kg/2.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12B†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives us a gun that’s actually heavier than the Rhyshi rifle, and whose
recoil is manageable enough that it’s worth firing more than one bullet per
turn. It fires rounds from a non-disintegrating cloth belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at those things. Just look at them. Their damage values combined with the
light weight and short barrel means they have &lt;em&gt;powerful&lt;/em&gt; powder charges. Quar
like big booms and they cannot lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recoil on these things means the act of firing them is somewhere between
“comical” and “painful for the shooter”. I’m guessing that a Taken Out result in
the wargame very often means the target got spooked and decided to play dead,
instead of actually being hit. This also explains why a quar can take
&lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; out on a bad skill roll.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/25/quar-guns.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/25/quar-guns.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>quar</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ultra-Tech Dungeon Delving in GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I started writing this post a few years ago when I was GMing the Iron Gods
adventure path for Pathfinder using the Dungeon Fantasy RPG rules. My approach
to that campaign was pretty slap-dash, and after I stopped I began thinking of a
more structured way to do it. Since a recent comment here on the blog asked for
specifics, I though I’d dust the post off and publish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a Dungeon Fantasy game where you want your characters to get
into contact with more advanced technology. How would you go about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ultra-tech-delving-a-survey&quot;&gt;Ultra-Tech Delving: A Survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Jackson games did a little foray into this area in Pyramid #3/60, in an
article entitled “High-Tech Dungeon Crawl”, which focused on bringing modern-day
characters with guns into fantasy dungeons to mow down orcs with autofire and
take their stuff. This raises the inherent level of colonalism in the genre from
“concerning” to “yikes!”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to focus on here is in an older variation on the theme: fantasy
characters exploring “dungeons” filled with elements you might be more used to
seeing in science fiction stories. When I say “older”, I mean it’s &lt;em&gt;older than
D&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt;: Dave Arneson’s Blackmoor campaign featured a whole ultra-tech city-state
descended from the crew of a crashed spaceship, and it was played for several
years before what became the OD&amp;amp;D rules were finalized and officially
published. D&amp;amp;D proper would explore the same territory with its famous
“Expedition to the Barrier Peaks” module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathfinder dedicates a whole kingdom in its setting to the idea: the land of
Numeria is a barbarian kingdom where a giant spaceship crashed millenia ago,
breaking up during atmospheric entry and scattering its many modules all over
the region. And, of course, in Gamma World and other post-apocalyptic games
&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; “dungeons” are ultra-tech because they’re the ruins of the futuristic
civilization that preceded the apocalypse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ultra-tech-delving-in-gurps&quot;&gt;Ultra-Tech Delving in GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS is of course a uniquely well-suited system for this kind of thing. Its
rules already support a wide range of genres and technology levels from the
corebook onwards. We only need a few adjustments depending on the sort of
campaign we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After The End&lt;/em&gt; already deals with the post-apocalyptic angle and offers a set
of detailed rules. What I want, however, is something simpler and more suited to
a Barrier Peaks/Numeria scenario. The ultra-tech stuff is alien, but characters
can gain an understanding of it with some investment, and the gap between their
usual medievalish milieu and the lofty heights of alien tech isn’t completely
impossible to cross. How would I do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-level-or-the-lack-thereof&quot;&gt;Tech Level, or the Lack Thereof.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on one side we have the usual “medievalish” dungeon fantasy setting. In
GURPS, that’s roughtly TL 4, but without gunpowder. On the other side we have a
space-opera intrusion, which corresponds very roughly to a TL9-10 selection with
a few outliers (personal shields are TL11-12, but they fit the flavor). With
these vague numbers in mind, we can ditch the concept of Tech Levels completely
for our treatment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Default GURPS Tech Level rules are only useful for giving us a starting set of
gadgets to work with. In actual play, the only thing that matters is if a given
thing is “low-tech” and thus familiar to everyone, or “high-tech” and thus a
mystery to the uninitiated. How to differentiate both? With the following
advantage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-familiarity-10-points&quot;&gt;Tech Familiarity (10 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a layman’s knowledge of the basic principles behind the advanced
technology scattered through your otherwise medieval fantasy world. You
understand why it isn’t magic. You know about electricity and how it powers
high-tech devices. You grasp enough of the high-tech design aesthetic to easily
spot a device’s charging port or battery, its control surfaces (be they
switches, triggers, or touchpads), its information displays, and its business
end even if you don’t know what the thing actually &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt;. You can identify the
high-tech civilization’s writing even though you can’t read it, and you can
identify its iconography for “danger”. You can also recognize hazards like
exposed live wires, recognize which type of power cell goes into a device, and
plug it in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a form of Unusual Background that makes you immune to the sort of
amusing accident which plagues other low-tech explorers confronted with
high-tech devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, Tech Familiarity is a pre-requisite for learning high-tech
skills, and the language of the high-tech civilization (if any). With this
advantage, you can spend points on those things normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is quite similar to High TL from the core book, but much cheaper. The
reason is that paying 30-35 points in High TL to get the same benefits is way
too expensive for a campaign in this mold. This advantage doesn’t give you any
familiarity with deeper aspects of the high-tech civilization, just what’s in
the first paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-skills&quot;&gt;Tech Skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills that would require a /TL specialization in standard GURPS rules have only
two versions here: standard (no suffix) and “/Tech”. That way, you don’t need to
change anything about how you write down a standard “medievalish” character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two specialties don’t overlap at all: they don’t default to each other, and
can’t be used at all across the “tech divide”. If you only have standard
Lockpicking, you can’t open a high-tech door with a magnetic lock. If you only
have Lockpicking/Tech, you can’t open low-tech mechanical locks with
old-fashioned picks, tough you might be able to operate a machine that does it
for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-tech weapons are usually firearms of beam weapons - the skills to operate
them properly are always “/Tech” skills. High-Tech &lt;em&gt;melee&lt;/em&gt; weapons are a
possible exception to the “no defaults” rule above, though the GM would need to
rule on each case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weapons that use the same skill as their low-tech counterparts can be used
normally by anyone if the only difference is in their construction (such as a
superfine or hyperdense blade). If they have some additional feature that
requires power (such as a vibroblade or shock baton) then the character has a -2
penalty to use that feature unless they have Tech Familiarity. If they require
an exclusive skill to operate (like a force sword or monowire whip) then that
skill has the “/Tech” suffix. You might be able to get away with a default to a
low-tech skill here, but the only way to improve on that is to buy Tech
Familiarity and the high-tech skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ultra-tech-gear&quot;&gt;Ultra-Tech Gear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the character stuff out of the way, we can talk about the goodies! As I
mentioned above, one advantage of GURPS is that it has entire books of high- and
ultra-tech gadgets that can be plugged straight into your fantasy
campaigns. Therefore, we don’t need to talk about how to stat this stuff up at
all! What we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; need is talk about the effects it’s going to have on your
campaign, which in turn will aid you in selecting which items to include.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-much-is-this-stuff-worth&quot;&gt;How much is this stuff worth?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vital question in the dungeon fantasy genre! Going more or less by the book,
high-tech items should be worth roughly 30 times their list price in a dungeon
fantasy setting. That makes even a relatively innocuous gadget into a major
piece of loot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem a bit too much for a dungeon fantasy setting where magic and
magic items are relatively common, but I think it kinda makes sense. Ultra-tech
items are going to be a lot rarer than magic items, particularly in settings
where they come from that single crashed spaceship. They work regardless of the
local mana and sanctitiy levels. And they can be enchanted! These are exactly
the same reasons why a suit of fine plate armor costs more than a standard suit
enchanted with Lighten 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: A superfine broadword would cost $3600 in its native ultra-tech
society. Recovered from a crashed spaceship in a dungeon fantasy setting, it’s
worth $108,000!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sword gives a +2 bonus to damage and a (2) armor divisor. The closest
“low-tech” equivalent would be a very fine sword with a Penetrating Weapon
enchantment, worth $17,000, almost ten times cheaper. Even if all the bonuses
were from magic, it would still cost only $25,600. However, the superfine blade
will lose none of its functionality in a low- or no-mana zone, and it could be
enchanted with the same magic as the low-tech sword to become even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think that this is too much, you could say that the value of
ultra-tech gear is capped by the value of magic items with similar
properties. The sword from the example would be worth $17,000 then. Gear that
has no magical equivalent might still use the “uncapped” price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;timeworn-gear&quot;&gt;Timeworn Gear&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One concept from Pathfinder that’s useful to borrow is that of timeworn
items. In Barrier Peaks-style setups, most of the high-tech stuff the PCs come
across has been sitting around in derelict ruins for a very long time; even if
it was very well-built, it might not have withstood the passage of the ages
intact. To model that, we introduce the following equipment modifier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timeworn&lt;/strong&gt;: This can be applied to any high-tech armor, weapon, or device that
requires power or ammunition to function. These items can’t be recharged. After
whatever reserves they contain when found are used up, they’ll break down and
become useless. They may also have other quirks arising from their almost-broken
state at the GM’s discretion. Divide final price by 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;weapons-and-armor&quot;&gt;Weapons and Armor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weapons and armor deserve special mention because Dungeon Fantasy is a
combat-heavy genre, and this combat has a very specific “feel” to it. Therefore,
high-tech combat gear will have an outsize impact on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baseline Dungeon Fantasy suggests that PCs should have a maximum total DR of
about 15, as anything more than that will make them invulnerable to too many
monster attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC damage also has some upper bounds. Spellcasters with missile spells and a
spellcasting talent of 6 can do a maximum of 18d damage, though that requires
enough setup to only be possible about once per fight, and not on all
fights. The maximum amount of “at-will” melee and ranged damage a PC can do is
equivalent to about 7d per attack&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing ultra-tech armor into the game almost certainly means you’re going
to exceed the DR cap. Even non-combat safety gear at these tech levels has as
much DR as low-tech plate, while being much lighter. Proper combat armor is much
tougher. Most of the published DF enemies will have trouble getting past the DR
of a PC in full ultra-tech armor with their physical attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, high-tech weapons can change the shape of combat in your
campaign. Dungeon Fantasy usually considers melee to be the main event and
ranged combat to be a specialist niche, but if guns and beam weapons are common
these two are going to swap places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultra-tech melee and ranged weapons can also allow PCs to approach or exceed the
upper damage bounds described above much more easily. Both “boundaries” are
roughly equivalent to rolling 7d of damage per attack. A force sword does 8d; a
laser rifle does 6d, and can can fire many more shots per turn than a bow with
no penalty. Both of those have armor divisors too, which make enemy DR become
much less of an obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step when addressing these issues is to carefully consider which items
are available. What do you want your campaign’s new DR cap to be? What is the
highest armor divisor you’re comfortable with? What sort of maximum damage do
you want your PCs to do with a melee or ranged attack they can use every second?
And, to quote Mister Torgue from Borderlands 2: EXPLOSIONS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second step is to consider the same thing from the side of the opposition:
what’s the highest DR and damage you estimate &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; will be able to routunely
bring to the table? The gear available to the PCs should give them a chance to
match those figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can then safely remove anything that exceeds your new planned limits. That
will end up giving you a pretty good set of guidelines for what the ultra-tech
culture and their ruins look like. A civilian medical lab infested with
non-sapient monsters and low-tech looters might have plenty of medkits and
wonder drugs, but no weapon heavier than a couple of timeworn electrolasers and
some scalpels the thief can use as superfine daggers. For a military base filled
with killer robots and with a tank at the end as a boss fight, the sky is the
limit, though those anti-tank weapons might all be timeworn if you don’t want
the PCs using them outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The article itself includes a section titled “The Sociological
Ramifications are Appalling”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A ST 20 Knight with Weapon Master and a halberd can easily attack twice
every turn and do 3d+13 per attack. This is theoretically possible right out
of character creation if your knight is a half-ogre. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A ST 20 Scout with Weapon Master and Strongbow might be able to shoot once
per turn and do about 4d+10 per shot. This particular boundary is hard to
reach, so your highest “at-will” ranged damage will probably be less than
that. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/13/ultra-tech-dungeons.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/13/ultra-tech-dungeons.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read Hell&apos;s Rebels: Adventure 04, Part 3</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell&apos;s_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/hells-rebels&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re firmly in the wrap-up stage now. If you’re here, the PCs have succeeded at
dismantling the powerful magical defenses of the Temple of Asmodeus and
disrupted a dire summoning ritual that was Barzilai Thrune’s last attempt at
squashing the Silver Raven rebellion. They made it out with a literal dragon’s
hoard worth of loot and if they were particularly skilled they might even have
managed to kill Thrune himself during the raid! In this post, we’ll see what all
of that means for the rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategic-and-campaign-implications&quot;&gt;Strategic and Campaign Implications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as the rebellion is concerned, it has achieved its major goal. All of the
Thrune leadership has been neutralized one way or the other, ceding control of
not just Kintargo but the entire province of Ravounel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few days immediately after the PC’s victory at the temple are a flurry
of activity as the former rebel organization sets itself up as the new
government. If Jilia Bailinus has been rescued and revived (a likely outcome),
then she’s immediately reinstated as Lord Mayor. Otherwise the job goes to a
sympatethic noble or priestly NPC - the players should have some input on who
gets the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new mayor will have several difficult issues to solve in the medium term,
but for now it’s time to celebrate!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-silver-span-celebration&quot;&gt;The Silver Span Celebration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the PC’s heroics quickly become common knowledge, now that there is no
more need for secrecy on their part. Soon after they recover from the temple
raid, they and their allies are invited to a huge party in their honor. It takes
place on Bleakbridge - the same spot where the PCs busted a blockade in Part 01
of the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The place is quite crowded now. A wooden stage has been erected right in the
middle of the bridge, where a whole bunch of statues are covered with cloth
awaiting for their unveiling. The PCs, every single member of the Silver Ravens,
and anyone else whom they had positive interactions with will be at the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time after the party gets going, the mayor calls the PCs up to the stage,
makes a speech renaming the bridge from Bleakbridge to the Silver Span, and
unveils the statues. These represent all the PCs, plus any NPCs who were
especially important to the rebellion’s success at the group’s discretion. These
are going to be installed along the Silver Span, as an eternal reminder of their
heroic deeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCs themselves are then presented with silver Keys to the City! The keys are
worth quite a bit of money, but the real prize here is the major reputation
boost that comes with being recognized as an official hero. That’s a hefty bonus
to gather information or perform for money in the city, as well as a permanent
10% discount on all Kintargan shops that don’t have reason to actively hate the
characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we can close the curtains on this adventure, however, there is the small
matter of the retributive strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-hells-heart&quot;&gt;From Hell’s Heart&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… I stab at thee! That’s a particularly appropriate quote here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, right after the PCs receive those keys, the remnants of the Thrune
faction teleport in and try to kill the PCs. I don’t think they can take the
province back at this point - this is simply done out of spite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who the attackers are depend on what exactly happened so far. From the worst
case to the best one, we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barzilai on a Fucking Dragon&lt;/strong&gt;: If both Thrune and the dragon Rivozair are
still alive, they both show up, with Thrune riding the dragon. This happens
even if Rivozair fled the city after being defeated by the PCs in their
previous confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barzilai OR a Fucking Dragon&lt;/strong&gt;: if either one of the pair is dead, the other
still attacks. Rivozair shows up alone; Thrune appears accompanied by four
bone devils.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Dregs&lt;/strong&gt;: If both main baddies are dead, the GM should build a CR 13
encounter with any secondary villains who managed to escape death over the
course of the adventure, focusing on those the players loved to hate the
most. If there are not enough to hit CR 13 on their own, fill the encounter
with appropriate minions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No One!&lt;/strong&gt;: Particularly thorough groups might have not left anyone alive to
attempt revenge! The chance of this happening is quite low, as there are a lot
of named villains here and many of them will make an effort to escape when
first fought. But if this does happen, just skip this battle altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone shows up at all, they fight to the death this time around regardless
of their previous cowardice. This encounter is the “main event”, and it’s
accompanied by a “sideshow” in the form of a bunch of loyalist dottari and minor
devils who arrive more conventionally and try to slaughter the crowd. These keep
the rest of the NPC Silver Ravens occupied, and are handled as series of
Security checks to prevent civilian deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrune remains as hard to kill as ever, but this time the PCs are fully rested
and have no other encounters to worry about. And with all those NPCs present,
someone is bound to have a handy spell to finish him off if the PCs don’t have
one of their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;victory-tally&quot;&gt;Victory Tally&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this fight is over, we finally get to tally the party’s XP award for
liberating Kintargo. This depends entirely on how many inhabitants have survived
the whole ordeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city starts the game with 11900 inhabitants, according to its stat sheet in
the Player’s Guide. The GM is supposed to keep track of this number from the
start of the campaign until now. There are several events in the strategic layer
(Thrune reprisals, mostly) that kill a number of innocents and reduce this
number. Deaths of innocents during the “tactical adventuring” portions also
reduce the number - for example, the Ruby Masquerade trap, or if the PCs fail to
rescue a sacrifice victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the city has at least 9000 surviving inhabitants at the end of this last
party, the game considers the rebellion an Unmitigated Success. 7500 or more
survivors makes for a Grim Success, and less than that is a pyrrhic victory
marked by Tragic Loss. I think it’s quite hard to end up with less than 9000
citizens unless the group completely fails to prevent the Ruby Masquerade
massacre and really slacks off during the “hot war” portion of this adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-chelish-crux&quot;&gt;The Chelish Crux&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This device, apparently a Hellraiser-style puzzle box, is also the plot coupon I
mentioned earlier. It sits inside Barzilai Thrune’s chest cavity - he replaced
his heart with it back during adventure 2. The book mentions that retrieving
this thing from Thrune’s corpse and opening it up are vital steps to proceed
with the remaining two adventures in the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concluding-the-adventure-and-what-happens-next&quot;&gt;Concluding the Adventure, and What Happens Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, nothing &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to happen from this point on. This is an excellent
stopping point for the campaign if the GM doesn’t feel like spending money on
the last two volumes. Just remove the Crux, and say that Barzilai has lost his
chance to become a genius loci by dying. He’s in Hell forever. Campaign
complete, mission accomplished, let’s leave nation-building to the government
and retire as glorious heroes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do want to continue playing Hell’s Rebels, though, then the Crux still
exists and the situation is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kintargo is free for now, and Cheliax is busy fighting the Glorious Reclamation
in its heartland, but that situation won’t last much longer. Cheliax will
eventually send an army to retake the city, which won’t be able to hold against
an all-out military assault. The key to solving that problem happens to be
inside the Chelish Crux, and we’ll deal with that in the next adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barzilai himself isn’t exactly out of the picture either. Even dead, he’s still
on track to become a genius loci, and solving the Cheliax issue will actually
make that process much faster. Dealing with him once and for all is the subject
of the last adventure in the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/11/06/hells-rebels-04-part-03.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/11/06/hells-rebels-04-part-03.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
