<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 13:37:32 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 13:37:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Wilden</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-wilden.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe wilden are new to 4e, first appearing in the Player’s Handbook 3 as an
option for PCs. This is their corresponding Monster Manual entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden are the middle world’s immune response to the Far Realm. They appeared
very recently, emerging from the Feywild’s deepest and most untouched natural
environments. Theoretically, that’s a reaction to an upsurge in Far Realm
activity in the world, and it’s worrying that the signs of that haven’t been
noticed by anyone else yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not even the wilden themselves have a clear idea of what caused them to
emerge. The setting’s youngest sapient people by far, they have an instinctual
drive to protect nature and oppose aberrant creatures, but they have yet to form
a unified culture and traditions of their own. Most individuals turn to other
creatures around them for examples. For many, those come from more established
fey peoples like elves, eladrin, and gnomes. Others turn to the beasts of the
wild, or to more zealous spirits like dryads and treants, and end up much
fiercer and much less sociable. Some even fall in with evil fey like fomorians,
ending up as villainous as them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden are Medium Fey Humanoids with a speed of 6 and low-light vision. As PCs,
their gimmick is that they may assume one of three &lt;em&gt;aspects&lt;/em&gt; after an extended
rest, each of which changes their appearance a bit and gives them a different
racial power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the three stat blocks in this entry belongs to a single aspect and
carries that aspect’s related power, in a version stronger than what’s available
to PCs. They’re Unaligned and may represent allies, neutrals, or hostiles as
your story requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re all in the low-heroic range, which means you can find NPC wilden in the
same areas where you’d find NPC elves and gnomes. They often use wolves, spiders
and drakes as pets, and there are many such creatures that would be
level-appropriate for a wilden encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wilden-destroyer&quot;&gt;Wilden Destroyer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wildens who adopt the aspect of the Destroyer are usually the designated
warriors of their communities. They wield large carved wooden clubs, and every
time they survive a battle they add a new carving to their weapons to celebrate
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Destroyers are Level 2 Soldiers with 39 HP. Their carved &lt;strong&gt;greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt; damage
and mark for a turn on a hit, and they can throw &lt;strong&gt;handaxes&lt;/strong&gt; as basic ranged
attacks. If an enemy marked by the destroyer tries to ignore the mark, the
destroyer gains a +4 bonus to attack and damage that enemy during their next
turn. If a bloodied enemy attacks the destroyer or one of the destroyer’s
adjacent allies, it can use the &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the Destroyer&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power to
attack that enemy as a reaction. If this hits, the enemy becomes stunned for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC Wildens in Destroyer aspect can use that power too, though for them it dazes
instead of stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wilden-hunter&quot;&gt;Wilden Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden who adopt the Hunter aspect fulfill that role in their community, and
also make for excellent scouts. They are Level 2 Lurkers with 33 HP. They fight
with &lt;strong&gt;shortswords&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;longbows&lt;/strong&gt; that just make basic attacks. All their
interesting stuff is in their passive traits and their racial power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passives are familiar to us by now: &lt;strong&gt;Camouflage&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make
Stealth checks with only partial cover and concealment; &lt;strong&gt;Sniper&lt;/strong&gt; lets them
stay hidden when they miss with a ranged attack from hiding; and &lt;strong&gt;Hidden Shot&lt;/strong&gt;
lets them deal extra damage when they attack from hiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their encounter power is &lt;strong&gt;Pursuit of the Hunter&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when an enemy
ends their movement within 2 squares of the hunter. The hunter can react by
shifting 3 squares, and for their next turn they will deal 5 extra damage with
their attacks against that enemy, and will also ignore partial cover and
concealment against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC Wilden in the Hunter aspect get a similar Pursuit power, except it deals 1d6
extra damage instead of the fixed 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wilden-ancient&quot;&gt;Wilden Ancient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden who adopt the aspect of the Ancients are their community’s shamans and
guides. They’re called “Ancients” because their magic lets them cast their minds
to the collective history of the Feywild and the world. When they go into these
trances, their whole community stops to take care of them and await their
awakening, which might bring important insights or prophecies with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ancient depicted here is Level 4 Artillery with 45 HP and the Leader
tag. It’s a primal spellcaster who fights with a &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; and with several
combat spells. Their spear attacks are very weak but allow an ally adjacent to
the target to make a free melee basic attack at +4 to hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their combat spells have varied effects: &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Vine&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic ranged
attack that deals physical damage and pulls 2 squares; &lt;strong&gt;Rumbling Earth&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) is a ranged area attack that damages and immobilizes (save ends);
and &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a ranged area attack that does heavy
lightning damage, half on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per round as a minor action they can impart the &lt;strong&gt;Wisdom of the Ancients&lt;/strong&gt;,
granting them a +2 attack bonus for their next turn. And then they hit an enemy
with an area attack, they can use their &lt;strong&gt;Voyage of the Ancients&lt;/strong&gt; encounter
power to teleport 3 squares and make one of the enemies they just hit grant
combat advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their many controllery effects, it makes sense for Ancients to be
artillery. They want to stay safe behind a wall of bodyguards and bombard their
enemies, not mix it up in melee like a controller might want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gotta say it feels a bit odd to find a low-heroic entry right after the
high-epic Weavers, but that’s just a product of the book being in alphabetic
order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wildens are serviceable enough as low-heroic enemies, about in line with what I
expect from an entry dedicated to a creature that’s also a PC option.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/18/wilden.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/18/wilden.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Weaver</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-weaver.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weavers have apparently been around since the days of AD&amp;amp;D, appearing in a
Monstrous Compendium Annual there under the name “Spell Weavers”. Their 4e debut
was actually in Dungeon #165, in the adventure titled “Secrets of the White
Lotus Academy”. Here in the MM3 they get updated into a major cosmic threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, it was in a weaver ruin that Kyuss found the writings that let him
become the Worm that Walks, back in the 3e adventure path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weaver civilization is incredibly ancient, and what little remains of it seems
to have been somehow shattered and spread across the cosmos. Records recovered
from these few ruins seem to describe a terrible Far Realm incursion that tried
to inject a seed of chaos into our cosmos. The Weavers tried to stop this, and
were only partially successful. This is what shattered them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To hear the Weavers themselves tell it, their civilization predated even the
gods and primordials, and the event that caused its destruction was in fact what
caused the universe to separate into the Elemental Chaos and the Astral
Sea. Contemporary sages don’t believe this to be true, but the surviving Weavers
certainly do. This belief is at the root of their disdain for all things
divine. To them, the gods are just annoying upstarts. Their own bodies and minds
are the product of aeons of transhuman enhancement. They’re much stronger,
faster, and smarter than your average mortal, and possess an unparalleled
multitasking ability that lets them even cast multiple complex spells at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present-day Weavers preserve as much of their ancient lore as they can, and work
on a grand plan to rebuild their civilization by undoing the planar disjunction
that broke it. Yes, they want to smush the planes back together. If they’re
right, it will be a very bad time for everyone else in the universe. If they’re
wrong, it will be a bad time for absolutely everyone, including themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their plan has two parts. The first is to restore and repair as many weaver
ruins as possible. Within each one is a planar portal that links all active
ruins into a single network, and a mystical furnace that burns the life force of
mortals and the enchantments that power magic items. By feeding these furnaces,
weavers gather power for the series of rituals that will finally accomplish
their goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weaver will be most likely be found masterminding some plan to gather powerful
mortal souls and magic items. They drain this power through enchanted chromatic
disks that only work for weavers. Every individual carries one of these, though
they specialize in different “flavors” of soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weavers easily form alliances with other powerful groups that have the same
negative opinion of the gods and a nihilistic bent, like tulgars and the
Forsaken. They also hold great influence over the Nerra, leading some scholars
to say the creation story in that entry is wrong and the Nerra are actually
creations of the Weavers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weavers are Medium Immortal Humanoids. They have Darkvision, a ground speed of
6, and a teleport speed of 6. Their signature trait is &lt;strong&gt;Multitasking Brain&lt;/strong&gt;,
which limits the effect of the dazed condition on them: they only lose their
move action, and can still take immediate actions (like interrupts and
reactions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other signature trait is more of a design directive: most of a weaver’s
attacks are minor actions, and they’re about as effective as a standard action
from another monster would be. They’re also all Elites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each weaver statted below specializes in collecting the souls of characters who
employ a different power source, using that same power source as its main
weapon. There’s one for every power source except divine, whom they consider
beneath them even as fuel for their furnaces. Ironically, this means divine
characters have a bit of an advantage over weavers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spell-weaver&quot;&gt;Spell Weaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic model, concerned with the collection of arcane power. Spell weavers
usually lead raids into secure locations in order to steal magic itens and
particularly desirable souls. They’re planned months in advance with intel from
spies and divinations, and usually involve the opening of a long-distance portal
as close to the target as possible. Once the spell weaver has what it wants, it
teleports back to the portal and escapes. It’s Level 28 Elite Artillery with 400
HP. Yes, according to this entry the typical weaver is equivalent to a demigod
in power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have three basic attacks, all doable as minor actions: &lt;strong&gt;Esoteric Touch&lt;/strong&gt;
deals force damage and pushes 5 squares; &lt;strong&gt;Dimensional Ray&lt;/strong&gt; allows the weaver
to teleport 2 squares before rolling, deals untyped damage, and teleports the
target 2 squares; and &lt;strong&gt;Esoteric Blast&lt;/strong&gt; deals fire damage to its target and an
automatic 10 fire damage to all enemies adjacent to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also as a minor action, it can wield its chromatic disk and cast &lt;strong&gt;Extract
Arcane Soul&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+). This can only target characters with arcane
powers. It deals psychic damage and dazes (save ends). On a miss it deals half
damage. Hit or miss, the weaver regains 20 HP. So this doesn’t extract your
whole soul, just a bit of your life force. It’s still bad news!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a standard action attack: &lt;strong&gt;Chilling Echo&lt;/strong&gt; can be used to
automatically deal 15 cold damage to all creatures the spell weaver has damaged
since the start of its current turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, when the weaver takes damage, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Defensive Jaunt&lt;/strong&gt;
as a reaction, becoming invisible and teleporting 20 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spell weaver’s minor action attacks deal about half the damage you would
expect from the MM3 formula, but the addition of Chilling Echo brings them back
up to their expected potential. Don’t forget to use it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battleweaver&quot;&gt;Battleweaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly some of the best warriors in the universe, battleweavers wield 4
exquisitely-crafted swords in combat, and hold their chromatic disk in their
other two hands. They collect the life force of worthy warriors. Battleweavers
are Level 26 Elite Soldiers with 488 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s imposssible to duel a battleweaver and come out unscathed, because their
&lt;strong&gt;Blade Mastery&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (1) that deals 10 automatic damage to any
enemies inside and marks them for a turn when this happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have a standard &lt;strong&gt;longsword&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack, but they’re usually going to
open with one of their two minor-action maneuvers, which also count as basic
attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Quick Jab&lt;/strong&gt; deals light physical damage and slides the target 3
squares to a space adjacent to the weaver; &lt;strong&gt;sidestep jab&lt;/strong&gt; does the same damage
and allows the weaver to shift 3 squares to a space adjacent to the
target. Combined, they allow the creature to lead its foes on a merry dance
across the field. The basic attack can then act as a “finisher” in the round,
bringing their damage potential to a level a bit above the one expected by the
formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battleweavers can use their chromatic disk to &lt;strong&gt;Extract a Martial Soul&lt;/strong&gt;,
targetting characters with martial powers. This is like the spellweaver’s
version: it deals psychic damage, dazes (save ends), and heals the weaver for
about 5% of its total HP (24 in this case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy marked by the battleweaver within 10 squares makes an attack that
doesn’t include the weaver as a target, the weaver can teleport to the enemy and
make a melee basic attack against it, as an interrupt. This is the other main
use of their standard-action basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battleweavers will use their “jab” strikes to wander around the battlefield and
disrupt PC formations while their aura damages and marks enemies. Like a
swordmage, it will try to stay far away from enemies it has marked, to increase
the chances of their mark triggering. It will use its stronger longsword attacks
to punish mark-ignoring PCs or to pile on more damage on a target it wants to
focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thought-weaver&quot;&gt;Thought Weaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weaver that specializes in the power of the mind. It usually doesn’t go out
hunting like the others - instead it can be found in weaver ruins working to
restore their gates and furnaces. If forced to fight, it will do so entirely
through the use of psionic powers, barely moving unless absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thought weavers are Level 27 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 500
HP. Their basic attacks are minor actions:: &lt;strong&gt;Quick Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is a standard melee
attack, and &lt;strong&gt;Mind Spike&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack that deals psychic damage,
inflicts a -2 penalty to all defenses for a turn, and slides the target 3
squares. They can also &lt;strong&gt;Extract A Psionic Soul&lt;/strong&gt;, targetting a PC with psionic
powers with the same standard Extract Soul effects. As standard actions, it can
use two powerful mind control techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Puppet&lt;/strong&gt; is a non-damaging attack that slides the target 5 squares,
forces them to make a basic attack against a target of the weaver’s choice, and
then dominates it (save ends). It recharges when no one is dominated by the
power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Command the Puppet&lt;/strong&gt; automatically hits someone dominated by Mental Puppet. It
deals psychic damage and has the same rider as the other power (slide 5 squares,
make a basic attack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone leaves a square adjacent to the dominated puppet, the weaver can use
&lt;strong&gt;Guardian Puppet&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt to have the dominated character use a basic
attack against the triggering enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tought weavers can also choose to spend a standard, move, or minor action
directing a &lt;strong&gt;Coordinated Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, which essentially gifts the spent action to
an ally within 5 squares and allows the ally to immediately take that action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hex-weaver&quot;&gt;Hex Weaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the weaver attuned to the Shadow power source. And what is the Shadow
power source? As far as I know it’s basically “Arcane in a Halloween
costume”. It started getting mentions as something distinct around this time,
and would get a supplement all to itself named Heroes of Shadow the next year.
To my knowledge it never got very popular due to this conceptual confusion with
arcane magic and due to most of its associated classes not being very
good. Anyway, it got a weaver here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hex Weavers are too cool to hang out with other weavers, and instead oversee
portals into the Shadowfell from which they launch expeditions to pursue
mysterious goals that may or may not be related to the overall plan of the
weaver civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Hex Weaver is a Level 27 Elite Lurker with 382 HP, and it’s also too cool to
follow the same rules as the other weavers. Its minor action attacks are
&lt;strong&gt;Extract Shadow Soul&lt;/strong&gt;, which has the usual effects but only targets creatures
with shadow powers, and &lt;strong&gt;Shrouded Eye&lt;/strong&gt;, a ranged attack that deals psychic
damage and makes the weaver invisible to the target for a turn. The latter can
only be used once per round, which breaks from the pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the weaver with the highest number of standard action powers:
&lt;strong&gt;Shadow Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; is a stronger, melee version of Shrouded Eye; &lt;strong&gt;Stinging
Shroud&lt;/strong&gt; is a close burst 1 that deals necrotic damage and is much stronger
against creatures granting combat advantage to the weaver. And &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Mask&lt;/strong&gt;
is an encounter power that makes it invisible for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if the weaver is damaged, it can &lt;strong&gt;Step Into Shadow&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) to
become insubstantial for a turn and teleport its speed as a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hex weavers are a bit disappointing. They’d be a lot more dangerous if Shadow
Mask was a recharge or at-will power, or if Shadow Grasp was a minor
action. They also had the problem that there weren’t a lot of shadow-based PCs
around when they were published, because Heroes of Shadow was like six months
away from its release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not familiar with weavers from previous editions but I really like their
lore here. The targetting restrictions on their Extract Soul attack do feel a
little artificial, but are easily removed. I don’t like the shadow power source
very much, so I didn’t like Hex Weavers, but the others are quite flavorful and
powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/17/weaver.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/17/weaver.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Verbeeg</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-verbeeg.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve been able to find out, verbeegs have been in the game since the
days of AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, first appearing in the Monster Manual II. This means
the game had already run out of synonyms for “Giant” even back then, since their
name is just a scrunched up form of “Very Big”. This is their 4e debut, with
somewhat new lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verbeegs are a species of small-g giants who live in the same places of the
middle world and the Feywild where you might find hill giants and ogres. The
typical verbeeg is a lazy and greedy trickster who wants to make others work to
keep them in a life of luxury. Their great size and strength helps with this,
but they prefer to use their smarts and trickery to get what they want. Even
when the con is harder than plain robbery, it’s also often more fun for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example tale here is that of a verbeeg who set up at a river bridge and began
charging a toll. The toll was expensive, but the giant promised to only collect
it when the traveller came back to their side of the river. Travellers would lie
and promise they’d pay, and when they were in the middle of crossing the bridge
the verbeeg would lift the entire thing and tilt it towards himself, causing the
victim to slide back. “You promised, now pay up!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong verbeeg leader might be able to form a gang with several of his
fellows, increasing the scale of their racket. Verbeegs also find it easy to
take control of nearby groups of ogres and even hill giants, since their
intellectual limitations make them easy to fool. A verbeeg band in charge of a
larger ogre or giant band can be a threat to their whole region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verbeegs aren’t very big on fighting, despite being giants. They’ll avoid it for
as long as possible, preferring to throw minions at the problem or to use
trickery to escape and misdirect. If a battle is unavoidable, they favor mobile
and stealthy tactics and combat styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to all expectations, verbeegs do have a code of honor they always
follow. It consists of two rules: 1) never give a sucker an even break and 2)
always keep your word. They can try to twist the wording of a promise quite far
and add all sorts of clauses before committing to it, but once they do they must
keep it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine you can make groups of non-hostile verbeegs with the same ease you
could make groups of other friendly giants. In that case, the description above
would apply to the ones you fight, not to the species as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verbeegs are Large Fey Humanoids with the Giant keyword, even though their
origin has nothing to do with primordials or capital-G Giants. They have a Speed
of 8 and Low-Light Vision. Their signature trait is the hilarious &lt;strong&gt;Verbeeg
Stealth&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to hide and use the Stealth rules as long as even
as single square they occupy counts as providing total cover or concealment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-verbeeg-elephant.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    It's surprisingly effective if you're not expecting it.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;verbeeg-rowdy&quot;&gt;Verbeeg Rowdy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical verbeeg ne’er-do-well, of the kind you can find operating alone or
in command of a gang of ogre patsies. In larger bands they make up the
rank-and-file. It’s a Level 9 Skirmisher with 99 HP. It wears hide, carries a
shield, and wields a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; in battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spear can be used for basic attacks and for a &lt;strong&gt;Skewering Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that
deals more damage and slides the target 5 squares to a position within 2 squares
of the verbeeg. Perfect for getting those pesky defenders out of the way. All of
these deal bonus damage if the rowdy has combat advantage against the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Bounding Maneuver&lt;/strong&gt; as an at-will move action, which
cancels any marks on them and allows them to shift 3 squares and to pass through
enemy spaces while doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Cunning Trick&lt;/strong&gt; minor action (recharge 5+) is a reach 3 attack vs. Will
that does no damage and knocks the target prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a rowdy has to fight, it’s not gonna stay still, and it’s going to focus on
knocking people down and skewering them with its spear before bounding away to
safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;verbeeg-ringleader&quot;&gt;Verbeeg Ringleader&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sort of individual you might fight running a gang of other verbeegs and
dumber lackeys, and the one responsible for coming up with their verbeeg
plans. It’s Level 11 Artillery with the Leader tag and 91 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ringleaders are warlord-types and project an aura of &lt;strong&gt;Cunning Insight&lt;/strong&gt; (5)
that gives bonus damage to an ally that has combat advantage against their
target. They carry &lt;strong&gt;Spears&lt;/strong&gt; but prefer to stay away and use their
&lt;strong&gt;Longbows&lt;/strong&gt;, whose basic attacks make the target grant combat advantage for a
turn. &lt;strong&gt;Distracting Shot&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) and also gives an ally in reach a free
melee attack against the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the very flavorful &lt;strong&gt;Get Them!&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power allows three allies
within 5 squares of the ringleader to make a charge attack for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;verbeeg-trickster&quot;&gt;Verbeeg Trickster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one manage to score a spellbook or two and learn some combat magic. It’s a
Level 11 Controller with 115 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; strikes knock the target prone
on a hit, and they have four spells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staggering Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack that deals force damage and slides the
target 1 square; &lt;strong&gt;Blinding Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fort, recharge 5+) deals
light radiant damage and blinds for a turn; &lt;strong&gt;Bewildering Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter)
deals psychic damage and prevents the target from attacking (save ends); and
&lt;strong&gt;Concealing Mist&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) creates a zone of mist in a close burst 2. The
zone is lightly obscured, and gives any verbeeg that starts their turn inside
combat advantage against every enemy outside the zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tricksters want to set their mist zone up and stay inside while they shoot at
the PCs outside it with their spells. Staggering bolt helps keep them outside,
and Bewildering Bolt is excellent to shut down controllers or ranged strikers
for a while. IF there’s a ringleader in the same encounter they’ll also want to
stay inside the mist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly personable and very big fey rascals. I wouldn’t want to make the
entire species fit the stereotype, but verbeeg bandits are a nice surprise to
spring on players who expect the giants plaguing the land to be dumb brutes
incapable of subtlety. Add 4 levels or so to the stat blocks present here and
you can upgrade their underlings from ogres to hill giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can have lots of fun as a GM if you have your party fight a verbeeg bandit
gang on a series of hilltops crowned by standing stones. It’s both a very
fey-themed arena, and gives them plenty of hiding places. “These guys are ten
feet tall, how could they sneak up on us like that?!”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/11/verbeeg.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/11/verbeeg.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Umber Hulk</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-umber-hulk.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MM3 Umber Hulks are in a similar situation to a lot of other monsters in the
book. The Monster Vault would soon be released with an &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/20/umber-hulk.html&quot;&gt;updated selection of
basic models&lt;/a&gt;, and so this one features a trio of more niche variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, the basic lore remains the same, but this entry adds some interesting
new details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first new bit is that umber hulks are one of the oldest species in the
world! The creatures are already mentioned in certain ancient records from
before the Dawn War, which makes some sages think they emerged from the raw
stuff of the world before the primordials had finished creating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is that their role as the world builders of the Underdark has a dark
side. Their tunnels may end up linking places that were best left isolated, like
two mutually hostile settlements. This is one of the reasons why underdark
civilizations tend to hunt them down. Some dwarves are also fond of chasing
umber hulks as they tunnel through the earth, for they commonly pass near veins
of precious metals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, these creatures are not a middle world exclusive! In ages past, small
populations of them found and walked through subterranean planar portals and
spread to places such as the Astral Sea or even the Abyss, and proceeded to
adapt to these new environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umber Hulks are Magical Beasts and have a ground speed of 5 and a burrow speed
of 2 with Tunneling, which means their digging creates stable tunnels. They have
Darkvision and Tremorsense 5 as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;umber-ravager&quot;&gt;Umber Ravager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a smaller and weaker relative of the basic umber hulk, so named because
it’s Medium and so it’s not technically a “hulk”. They wander closer to the
surface and are likely to be the first variant found by PCs who are not yet
powerful enough to brave the true Underdark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ravager is a Level 7 Brute with 95 HP. It can attack with a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that
does light physical damage, and can be used in a &lt;strong&gt;claw flurry&lt;/strong&gt; that allows it
to make two attack with a single action. Its most basic psionic power is a
&lt;strong&gt;Crushing Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3 vs. Will) that deals light psychic damage and
knocks targets prone. Less often it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Disarming Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 3
vs. Will, recharge 6+) as a minor action that deals no damage but causes stun
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umber Ravagers hunt in packs, so you might see encounter groups featuring
several of them. Each one will target a different PC with its Disarming Gaze as
an opening move, and then focus its attacks on the stunned target. Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abyssal-hulk&quot;&gt;Abyssal Hulk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hulk’s ancestors managed to dig their way to the Abyss, and then suffered
mutations that allowed to survive there. Its bodily secretions became acidic,
and its psionic powers changed to be more madness-themed. It’s also smarter and
more consciously malevolent, with a Chaotic Evil alignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abyssal Hulks are Level 15 Controllers with 152 HP. They fight up close with
Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, and with a &lt;strong&gt;Gaze of Chaos&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3 vs. Will) that
deals light psychic damage and slides the targets 3 squares on a hit. After
sliding, the targets make a melee basic attack against a target of the monster’s
choice. It can also spray forth some &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Spew&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fort) to
inflict 10 ongoing acid damage (save ends) on those it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the abyssal hulk can use a &lt;strong&gt;Gaze of Crushed Will&lt;/strong&gt; (close
blast 5 vs. Will) to slide targets 3 squares and inflict a -5 penalty on any
saves they roll during this movement. You know when you roll a save during
forced movement? When someone uses it to push you off a cliff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, this cruel mutated almost-demon wants to alternate pushing people off
cliffs with making them stab each other while singing “stop hitting
yourselves!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;astral-hulk&quot;&gt;Astral Hulk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite going to the realm of shiny light, Astral Hulks aren’t any less
unpleasant than their abyssal counterparts. There are signs that they may have
been engineered on purpose by some primordial for use as a weapon, because they
just love to dig into astral domains and tear them up until they become
free-floating debris fields. Several such domains were destroyed by astral
hulks, and the people of the Astral Sea are always on watch against astral hulk
infestations. Their gaze causes a pronounced lethargy on victims, and lures them
closer so the creature can use its natural weapons on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astral Hulks are Level 17 Soldiers with 167 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; damage and mark
for a turn on a hit. If a marked enemy shifts, the hulk can use &lt;strong&gt;Entrapping
Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt; on them as an interrupt, grabbing them on a hit. Their &lt;strong&gt;Gaze of
Lassitude&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude) deals untyped damage, pulls 4 squares,
and slows (save ends). Their &lt;strong&gt;Gaze of Annihilation&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5
vs. Fortitude) is an encounter power that does untyped damage, half on a hit,
and marks everyone it hits for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like umber hulks, you’ll find a use for these. I like that they’re all
very focused in their design intent. There’s one to introduce your players to
the monster earlier, and two to make them despair after they thought they had
left these things behind when they moved out of the middle world.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/09/umber-hulk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/09/umber-hulk.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Tulgar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-tulgar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first time I’m seeing this monster. If they appeared in previous
editions, it was with a different lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, during the days of the Dawn War, there was a certain place in
the world that was a major nexus of primal power, connected to a great number of
spirits. This place was annihilated by one of the many cataclysms being thrown
around as weapons during that war. It was not the target - it was collateral
damage. And it was a god who pulled the trigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirits of that sacred site were cast into the world, rootless and
homeless. Spirits of place without a place, their rage against the gods knew no
bounds. In order to survive, they cast part of their spiritual nature aside and
took on material forms made of flesh, becoming the first tulgars. And then they
swore to destroy the gods and their servants in revenge for what was done that
day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tulgars would soon find out that attaining their revenge was much harder
than they thought. After the Dawn War ended, the gods retreated to their domains
and no longer stepped into the world. Their followers very quickly grew in
number and built complex societies that were much harder to destroy than the
scattered fleeting villages of the War. Many of the tulgars gave up on their
oath over the ages, and now live as bitter mercenaries. Some of them, though,
still keep that flame of hate going and try to find ways to accomplish their
original goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metaphysically, a tulgar is more or less the primal equivalent of a daeva or
rakshasa. When they die, they are immediately reincarnated elsewhere in the
world in a new adult body, with intact memories of their previous lives. I don’t
think they can reproduce by natural means, but they have been increasing their
numbers. They can sense when a primal spirit loses its home or becomes hateful
of sapient mortals or their gods, and converge to the spirit’s location to
convince it to join their numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tulgars are Medium Natural Humanoids with a ground Speed of 7 and the Forest
Walk trait. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Unbroken Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when
they hit 0 HP and gives their nearest ally a “parting gift” of 10 temporary HP
and a +2 to attacks, defenses, and damage that lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the stat blocks here present us with early-epic threats, which is
appropriate for a people who swore vengeance on the gods and has a real shot at
achieving this. It’s possible they would make good allies for the Forsaken,
since they have similar goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tulgar-flesh-hunter&quot;&gt;Tulgar Flesh Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hunter of sapient prey, with centuries of accumulated experience. This is a
Level 22 Skirmisher with 209 HP. It fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;Handaxe&lt;/strong&gt; it
uses as a thrown weapon. Its &lt;strong&gt;On the Hunt&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes it not provoke
opportunity attacks when it moves for a turn after hitting an enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flesh hunter can use &lt;strong&gt;Hunter’s Onslaught&lt;/strong&gt; to make both a spear and a
handaxe attack against different targets on its turn. The ranged attack doesn’t
provoke opportunity attacks when used as part of this power, and the power can
be used in place of a basic attack during a charge! In other words, no reason to
use a single basic attack when this is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, flesh hunters can use a &lt;strong&gt;Rotting Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) to deal
light damage and inflict ongoing necrotic damage on the target (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tulgar-savage&quot;&gt;Tulgar Savage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This unfortunately named enemy is a Level 22 Minion Brute. They have a &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt;
and a &lt;strong&gt;handaxe&lt;/strong&gt; like the flesh hunter, though it does minion-scale
damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;Critical Threat&lt;/strong&gt; ability allows them to crit on a 19-20, and
when they do they grant a free melee basic attack to an ally within 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and they have Unbroken Spirit too, so they make a powerful contribution to
their allies by dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tulgar-half-spirit&quot;&gt;Tulgar Half-Spirit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tulgar that keeps more of its spirit side than most others. It’s a Level 23
Lurker with 116 HP, and it’s Insubstantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that deals minor necrotic damage and immobilizes
for a turn. It also turns the tulgar invisible for a turn as an effect. If it
hits someone who can’t see it, the half-spirit also dazes the target for a turn,
so there’s your lurker loop right there. It can also throw &lt;strong&gt;handaxes&lt;/strong&gt; if no
one is at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the half-spirit becomes bloodied for the first time, it &lt;strong&gt;Unleashes the
Inner Spirit&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Fortitude), dealing necrotic damage and
stunning those it hits for a turn. The half-spirit then becomes invisible for a
turn and teleports 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tulgar-warrior&quot;&gt;Tulgar Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This elite combatant doesn’t care about ranged attacks, and is all about
charging to melee and laying waste to armies. It’s a Level 23 Brute with 265
HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;Inveterate Warrior&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes it crit on a 19-20, and deal 3d12
extra damage on a crit. That last bit might just be a codification of its
&lt;strong&gt;greataxe’s&lt;/strong&gt; High Crit trait, since it’s not spelled out in this stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warrior’s basic axe attacks also inflict a -2 AC penalty for a turn. Its
&lt;strong&gt;Whirling Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver is an encounter power that allows it to attack
everyone in a Close Burst 1, shift 3 squares and repeat the burst attack once
more against anyone who wasn’t hit by the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tulgar-spirit-talker&quot;&gt;Tulgar Spirit Talker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some tulgars retain a stronger connection to their former spirit nature and can
use that to cast spells. However, the other side of that connection is still
&lt;em&gt;broken&lt;/em&gt;, and this slowly erodes their mental stability. Over time, a spirit
talker might become unable to live in its community, and the others consider it
a mercy to kill them so that their minds might be mended by the process of
reincarnation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spirit Talkers are Level 24 Controllers with 225 HP. They project a &lt;strong&gt;Primal
Barrier&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that makes all spaces inside difficult terrain for creatures
without phasing or forest walk. It fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt; whose attacks make
the target be marked by one of the tulgar’s allies within 10 squares. Its ranged
basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Incite Savagery&lt;/strong&gt; spell, which deals psychic damage and
has an interesting rider. If the target doesn’t make a melee attack on its next
turn, it grants combat advantage until the end of its following turn. A great
power to use on primarily &lt;em&gt;ranged&lt;/em&gt; attackers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action the spirit talker can cast &lt;strong&gt;Dismissal&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), which
targets a conjuration, summoned creature, or zone within 10 squares. It attacks
the Will of its creator, and on a hit it causes the target effect to end! If
there’s nothing to dispel, the spirit talker can use &lt;strong&gt;Call Spirit Warrior&lt;/strong&gt; to
summon a tulgar minion to its side, acting right after it in initiative order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of Unbroken Spirit, the Spirit Talker has &lt;strong&gt;Death’s Embrace&lt;/strong&gt;, which
works the same but makes its aura stick around as a zone with the same effects
until the end of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the lore of the tulgars here, because you can see how they might have a
reason for being bitter and angry. I’ll note that the stat blocks here are all
Unaligned, which means the book might agree with me. The only thing I dislike
here is the use of the word “savage” in both the minion’s name and the spirit
talker’s ranged attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can play some tulgar groups as being vengeful against the gods and perhaps
leaning more towards Evil, but you can also portray them as people who gave up
on that vengeance but still can never go back to what they were, which is a very
different story. Maybe some of them might be looking for a way to become full
spirits again, and it might be something that brings them into alliance with the
PCs or with sympathetic NPCs.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/07/tulgar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/07/tulgar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Thri-Kreen</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-thri-kreen.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thri-Kreen got famous as one of the playable options for AD&amp;amp;D’s Dark Sun. This
is their 4e debut. They would return as fully-supported playable characters in
the 4e Dark Sun Campaign Setting, about 3 months after the publication of the
MM3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thri-Kreen are mostly-humanoid sapient insects, adapted to live in arid
climes. They’re all over the Dark Sun setting, but even in this more generic
version their preferred habitats are deserts and arid wastelands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thri-Kreen tradition says they were created by the great primal spirit known to
them as Sand Father, and to other species as Old Grandfather. Sand Father looked
at the deserts of the world and found them too empty for his taste. So he
plucked a species of sand beetle from the world and made them into the first
thri-kreen. Realizing that size and strength would not be enough to guarantee
their survival, Sand Father also gave them the wisdom of the lizard and the
cunning of the desert fox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the distant past, the thri-keen managed to form a large empire that spanned
many of the world’s deserts, a nation known as Val-Karri. It lasted for a
hundred years before it was subjugated and assimilated by the dragonborn empire
of Arkhosia. The thri-kreen recovered their freedom when Arkhosia fell, and
returned to a nomadic lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern-day thri-kreen regard people who live outside the desert as weak, for
only those tested by the sands are worthy of respect. Though they draw no maps
or formal borders of their desert territories, they guard those territories
fiercely and are quite harsh to interlopers who try to pass through without
paying homage to them first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as these protocols are observed, thri-kreen are content to leave other
to their business and to go about their own. They’re very well adapted to their
chosen habitat and don’t need to raid neighbors for resources or anything like
that. Thri-kreen communities tend to be small and nomadic, and might go for
years without meeting other sapients. They display good aptitude for primal
magic and psionic powers, and are often good allies to any druids and wardens
that also make the desert their home. Thri-kreen villains are usually in service
to evil primal spirits, demons, or other groups who corrupt and transform the
land to suit their own foul purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thri-kreen are Medium Natural Humanoids with a ground speed of 7 or 8 and
low-light vision. Their signature ability is the &lt;strong&gt;Mantis Jump&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter
power which allows it to jump a number of squares equal to its speed without
provoking opportunity attacks. Most stat blocks here combine martial training
with minor psionic powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thri-kreen-ambusher&quot;&gt;Thri-Kreen Ambusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are young adults who spent their childhoods learning about the land and,
upon coming of age, are cast out of their tribe to survive alone for a
year. They travel widely to hone their skills, and their extended periods of
solitude also allow them to develop their latent psionic powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambushers are Level 6 Lurkers with 58 HP and a Speed of 8. They fight with two
&lt;strong&gt;spears&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and with a &lt;strong&gt;Mind Stab&lt;/strong&gt; power at range. The power deals
light psychic damage and dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Spinning Spears&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver. This deals about half the
damage of a basic attack, but also gives them a +5 bonus to all defenses for a
turn and recharges their &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Boost&lt;/strong&gt; ability. This one allows them to add
extra psychic damage to a Spear or Mind Stab attack after it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, this is a lurker who doesn’t hide. It will alternate boosted Spear/Mind
Stab attacks with Spinning Spear. It’s still pretty good at hiding as well,
which is why it’s called an Ambusher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thri-kreen-scout&quot;&gt;Thri-Kreen Scout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouts keep watch over their territories and can stand still for hours under the
blazing sun while doing so. They warn the rest of the group when they spot an
intruder, and are cautious to engage them, preparing traps in advance. If a
direct fight starts, they’re frenetic combatants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouts are Level 7 Skirmishers with 80 HP and Speed 8. They fight with
&lt;strong&gt;Spears&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Shuriken&lt;/strong&gt;, and can perform &lt;strong&gt;Leaping Attacks&lt;/strong&gt; to move their
speed and make a stronger spear attack at any point during the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If hit by an attack, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Recoil&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 1 square away as a
reaction. If the attack bloodies them, they can shift 4 squares instead. They
also have a &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Boost&lt;/strong&gt; power similar to that of the Ambusher, though this
one recharges automatically on a 5+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouts will alternate boosted basic attacks with Leaping Attacks, and will
probably have traps lying around the battlefield if they were expecting
company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thri-kreen-desert-talker&quot;&gt;Thri-Kreen Desert Talker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a primal spellcaster with powers over the desert sands. They tend to act
as judges in thri-kreen communities, trying those who break their laws and
customs and punishing the guilty. The most severe punishments are execution and
exile to the desert, but I imagine there are smaller ones for lesser offenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sand Talkers fight with their bare &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; and throw &lt;strong&gt;shurikens&lt;/strong&gt;, but they
also have a couple of sand-bending spells for use in combat. &lt;strong&gt;Shifting Dune
Rend&lt;/strong&gt; (area 1 within 10 vs. Reflex) deals no damage, but knocks prone on a hit
and slides 2 squares as an effect. &lt;strong&gt;Desert Tempest&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5) deals
minor physical damage, pushes 2 squares, and blinds (save ends). It recharges
when the thri-kreen is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this pushing around synergizes with &lt;strong&gt;Sand Trap&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action that
allows it to create three of the things within 10 squares. When an enemy starts
their turn in a sand trap square, they are restrained for a turn, and then the
sand trap disappears. The power recharges when there are no sand traps left in
the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desert talkers are good for breaking up PC formations and setting things up for
their allies, which is exactly what they’ll spend the first few rounds
doing. Their special attacks do very little damage, but their basic ones are
okay and a good choice once all the PCs are good and restrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love thri-kreen! Whether they’re from Athas or not, I find their look
extremely interesting, and I also liked that this generic version of their
culture does not make them universally hostile.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/06/thri-kreen.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/06/thri-kreen.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 01</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been playing a lot of Wolfenstein games these past few days. There’s
something cathartic about unapologetically fighting Nazis. I first did it to
de-stress, and then to celebrate the results of our most recent election (go
Lula!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since I do occasionally want to post something here that’s not Let’s Read
the Monster Manual, I decided to talk a bit about the various guns you use to
kill Nazis in all of these games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re dealing with two separate continuities here: one that starts with Return
to Castle Wolfenstein (2001) and another that starts with Wolfenstein: The New
Order (2014). You could, if you’re so inclined, include both of them in the
GURPS Infinite Worlds framework. I’d call then Wolfenstein-1 and Wolfenstein-2
respectively, though I guess Infinity might call the latter Reich-6 at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we’ll cover the stuff that appears in Return to Castle
Wolfenstein (2001), AKA the Wolfenstein-1 setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-overview&quot;&gt;Game Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a flashier remake of Wolfenstein 3D, the game that more or less started
the FPS genre back in 1992. It’s the first game in the franchise to have a more
fleshed out story wrapped around its gameplay, with voiced dialogue and
cutscenes elaborating on the simpler “you must escape the castle and kill Nazis”
plot of the 1992 game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game takes place in a pulpier version of WWII, where the Nazis are working
on a large variety of scary secret projects and the OSA (a joint Allied spy
agency) is sending agents to stop them from hitting the field. The player
character, as always, is William “B. J.” Blazkowicz. He gets sent along with a
British agent to Castle Wolfenstein to find more about these projects, they get
captured, and the game starts with Blazko’s escape attempt and moves on to
thwarting those projects to the Allies can win the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two sinister things going on here: an attempt by the Thule society to
resurrect ancient evil undead knights, and a mad science lab working to build
cyborg supersoldiers. The final boss is, of course, a bunch of cyborg
supersoldiers possessed by the spirits of ancient evil undead knights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-weapons&quot;&gt;Historical Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfenstein-1 is mostly a pulpier version of WWII, so a lot of the weapons we
see are historical and present on GURPS High-Tech. Though sometimes you’ll start
a level with some Allied weapons issued by the OSA, the vast majority of the
time you’ll be using captured German hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSA-issue weapons include the &lt;strong&gt;Colt M1911A1&lt;/strong&gt; pistol (p. HT99), the &lt;strong&gt;Thompson
M1&lt;/strong&gt; submachine gun (p. HT122), and the &lt;strong&gt;Enfield Sten Mk IIS&lt;/strong&gt; submachine gun
(p. HT 125). The integral suppressor of the Sten works according to cinematic
principles here, making it completely silent to enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, one of the “elite guard” units you face in the game also
uses Stens, because they’re meant to be sneaky and the Sten is the only
suppressed SMG in the game. The other OSA weapons are used exclusively by the
player character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;German weapons include the &lt;strong&gt;Luger P08&lt;/strong&gt; pistol, (p. HT98), the &lt;strong&gt;ERMA MP40&lt;/strong&gt;
SMG (p. HT 124), the &lt;strong&gt;Mauser Kar98K&lt;/strong&gt; rifle (p. HT111), the &lt;strong&gt;Rheinmetall
FG42&lt;/strong&gt; battle rifle (p. HT 115) and the &lt;strong&gt;Panzerfaust&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT147). The player
also uses these extensively, since every enemy drops ammo for one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FG42 is the signature weapon of the other “elite guard” unit in the game,
and has the scope described in its High-Tech entry. It’s also possible to find a
suppressor for the Luger and a variable-power scope for the Mauser, which you
can stat up using the generic rules in p. HT 156 and p. HT 158.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can occasionally also find a few &lt;strong&gt;MG42&lt;/strong&gt; machine gun (p. HT 134)
emplacements in the game. There is also a flamethrower similar to the &lt;strong&gt;M2-2&lt;/strong&gt;
(p. HT179), though this is probably the German equivalent rather than the
American version in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grenades also see use, with most of them being the German &lt;strong&gt;Stielhandgranate
24&lt;/strong&gt;, and the rest American &lt;strong&gt;AMC Mk II&lt;/strong&gt; models. Both are on p. HT190-191.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fictional-weapons&quot;&gt;Fictional Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of pulpy arms research going on here on both sides, so we also get
to see some weapons that don’t exist in reality. We’ll cover these in a bit more
detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snooper-rifle&quot;&gt;Snooper Rifle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a prototype sniper rifle issued to Blazkowicz by the OSA early in the
second mission of the game. You also find captured rifles later on while
breaking into one of the games’ many secret lab facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Snooper is the most down-to-earth of the experimental weapons here, being an
exaggerated version of the &lt;strong&gt;M3 Carbine&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT113). Even the fancy infrared
sight is real! The biggest changes are the addition of a cinematic integral
suppressor that makes the gun completely silent, and making the infrared sight
more advanced than it really was. The one in the game has variable magnification
and requires no external batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venom-machine-gun&quot;&gt;Venom Machine Gun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first entirely fictional weapon we encounter in the game, and the
second most unrealistic one. It’s a portable, six-barreled, belt-fed minigun. It
has relatively short barrels, a shoulder stock and rifle-style grips. There’s an
in-game document that describes it as firing 7.92mm saboted armor piercing
rounds, but the ammo for it is labeled as “12.7mm” in game. You first find the
Venom as a prototype in one of the secret labs that make up the game’s levels,
and after that it starts appearing in the hands of some enemy human
soldiers. Most of the cyborg supersoldiers you meet towards the end of the game
also carry one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll need custom stats for this one! Let’s go with the assumption that it fires
7.92mm ammo, to make it minimally plausible for it to be portable. To make it a
little easier on the user, we can further say it fires the 7.92x33mm Kurz round,
instead of the longer 7.92x57mm Mauser round from the Kar98K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The in-game Venom takes up to 500 rounds. These would probably be in a
disintegrating belt inside a metal can that can be worn as a backpack. The whole
thing weights around 16kg, more than the weapon itself. More reasonable 200 and
100 round belts with their smaller containers might weight in at 8 and 4kg
respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll actually base the stats for it on the Minigun from page 138 of GURPS
Ultra-Tech, making the Venom a TL 7+2 weapon. The one on the table fires APDS
ammo, which is also TL 7+2 in this caliber, and has a 500-round belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d+2(2) pi-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000/4000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15kg/16kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25!&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Venom requires Guns (LMG) to operate, or Guns (Longarm) with the Burst-Fire
technique if using the alternate gun skill rules from Pyramid #3/65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tesla-gun&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weapon used by the advanced cyborg supersoldiers you meet at the very end of
the game. Unlike the Venom this doesn’t bear even the tiniest resemblance to any
real gun. Pull the trigger and it fires a stream of lightning until you release
it or until it runs out of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tesla Gun draws power from a superscience backpack battery equivalent to a
TL 9 D cell, but four times heavier. Its damage follows the same rules as the
Lightning spell: metal armor only provides DR 1, and the target must make a HT
roll with a penalty of -1 for every 2 points of injury taken from it. Failure
means they’re stunned, and must attempt an HT roll every turn in order to
recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d+2 burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;600/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;35kg/10kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50 (5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;18M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tesla Gun requires Gunner (Beam) to operate, even when carried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-for-these-fancy-guns&quot;&gt;How much for these fancy guns?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that I ommitted any price information for the Venom and the Tesla
Gun above. That’s because in Wolfenstein-1 they’re secret prototypes with very
limited production runs. You don’t buy them, you pry them from the hands of dead
Nazi assholes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use them on a different setting where they are available for
purchase, use the following costs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom MG&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$12.500&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom Ammo (100-round belt, APDS)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$180&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom Ammo (100-round belt, solid)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$60&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$60.000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Battery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$400&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are for a setting with a tech level of 7+2. If you’re in a “plain” TL9
setting you might want to use the Minigun and Semi-Portable Electrolaser from
Ultra-tech, which have slightly better stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your setting is like Wolfenstein-1, where the overall TL is a plain 7 and
these are secret superscience prototypes, multiply all prices by 4.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Tannarukk</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-tannaruk.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one feels like an AD&amp;amp;D 2nd Edition creation, as that’s when they renamed
demons as “ta’nari”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tannarukk are engineered hybrids of orc and demon DNA, the product of rituals
performed by demon lords or ambitious mortal spellcasters. These rituals are
effectively a mass-production process, as they involve pulsing vats and can
create dozens of the creatures at once. In most cases they’re immediately put to
work as soldiers and weapons of war, though they’re extremely difficult to keep
under control unless they get “enough” opportunity to commit violence. As you
might expect, that’s a tall order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The few free tannarukk bands that exist tend to seek work as mercenaries. Free or
not, they can most often be found in the Astral Sea or Elemental Chaos, usually
fighting something. They do sometimes show up in the middle world, and they love
it because few warriors there can match their skill and resilience in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tannarukks are Medium Elemental Humanoids with the Demon and Orc keywords. They
have Darkvision and Speed 6, along with Resist Fire 5. Their signature trait is
&lt;strong&gt;Indomitable Fury&lt;/strong&gt;, which kicks in when they drop to 0 HP for the first time
in the fight. It makes them stay at 1 HP instead and gives them +2 to attacks
and +4 to damage until the end of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means the PCs should make sure each Tannarukk in the encounter stays down by
hitting it again before it can get a chance to take more actions. If they don’t,
they’re going to take more damage; if they do, that’s one attack that didn’t go
to a healthier monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tannarukk-marauder&quot;&gt;Tannarukk Marauder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most tannarukks conform to this stat block, which is your basic enthusiastic axe
murderer. Marauders wear hide and wield a &lt;strong&gt;greataxe&lt;/strong&gt;, and can also thrown
&lt;strong&gt;handaxes&lt;/strong&gt; at those they can’t quite reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Nimble Reaction&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them +4 AC against opportunity attacks,
which is good because their signature move relies on fishing for them: &lt;strong&gt;Brutal
Rampage&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to move their speed and make a greataxe attack at any
point during the move. This attack gains a +5 damage bonus for each opportunity
attack made against the marauder during the move (but before the attack). The
opportunity attacks don’t need to hit, they just need to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tannarukk-steel-warrior&quot;&gt;Tannarukk Steel Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bigger tannarukk that received better training and had armor riveted to
its hide. It’s a Level 18 Soldier with 177 HP. Its armor counts as plate, and it
wields a shield and a &lt;strong&gt;Longsword&lt;/strong&gt;, plus a &lt;strong&gt;Crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; for ranged attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sword marks for a turn, and the warrior can make free attacks against
enemies that ignore the mark. It can also be used in a special attack named
&lt;strong&gt;Burning Cage&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+). This melee attack targets Reflex and does heavy
fire damage. The target takes a further 5 fire damage every time it enters a
square during its turn (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tannarukk-flame-speaker&quot;&gt;Tannarukk Flame Speaker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a tannarukk spellcaster whose power relies on a connection to the abyssal
flames that go into their production ritual. It’s level 17 Artillery with 129
HP and resist 10 fire, a bit higher than usual for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flame speaker fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Staff&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and with &lt;strong&gt;fire bolts&lt;/strong&gt; at
range. It can also shoot a &lt;strong&gt;fire barrage&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that targets up to
three creatures but does a bit less damage than the basic bolt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, the flame speaker can summon &lt;strong&gt;Winds of Fire&lt;/strong&gt;, an area
burst attack that deals fire damage and creates a zone that lasts for the rest
of the encounter. Anyone starting their turn inside takes 10 fire damage and is
pulled 1 square towards the zone’s origin square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to Indomitable Fury, the flame speaker also has &lt;strong&gt;Avenging Fire&lt;/strong&gt;,
which triggers when it hits 0 HP for the second time. It deals some automatic
fire damage to the triggering enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stat blocks take up a lot of space on the book, but they’re simpler than
they look. Each one has a solid gimmick and appropriate base stats. I guess
tannarukks are meant to be regular enemies for upper paragon PCs - stronger than
minions, but you’ll still meet a lot of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, I’m not sure I like them. They’re more or less D&amp;amp;D’s take on the
Uruk-Hai, I guess, but there are a lot more opponents at this level range that
feel cooler and less potentially problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/03/tannarukk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/03/tannarukk.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Su Monster</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-su-monster.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su Monsters have been around at least since the AD&amp;amp;D Monster Manual. This is
their 4e debut. It’s likely their lore is new to this edition. They didn’t seem
to have any in the AD&amp;amp;D book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su Monsters are an artificial species created by the wizard Halkith to guard his
tower in the legendary Isle of Dread. In Fourth Edition, the Isle is a wandering
island in the Feywild, and as usual it’s full of very dangerous
creatures. Halkith created the first Su Monsters to guard his tower against the
place’s other inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time after that, a mysterious event caused a worldwide surge of psionic
energy. This affected Halkith’s su monsters deeply and caused them to break from
the wizard’s control. Halkith disappears from history after this - his most
likely fate is that he was eaten by his creations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wizard combined traits from both great apes and fey panthers to make these
creatures. In our narrative present they managed to spread beyond the Isle of
Dread. Their preferred habitat are tropical jungles, particularly those that
contain sources of psionic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su Monsters are nonsapient but cunning, and complement their natural weapons
with residual psychic powers received from the Event. Like cats, they hunt as
much for fun as for food, and kill much more prey than they can eat at
once. They bury the excess meat for later consumption, and mark these stashes
with the prey’s inedible bits (such as its carried treasure). If you find
shinies hanging off tree branches in the jungle, take care!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spellcasters and psionicists often use their power to control these creatures,
putting them to work as guard and attack animals. When free, they protect and
hunt in their chosen territories with surprisingly sophisticated tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su Monsters are Medium Fey Beasts with ground and climb speeds of 7, as well as
the Forest Walk special ability. They have darkvision, and one of both of the
following signature abilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychic Boost&lt;/strong&gt; works like the Star Spawn ability we saw: when a su monster
hits with one of its physical attacks, it can deal bonus psychic damage as a
free action. This recharges when the creature takes psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tribal Fury&lt;/strong&gt; has a very unfortunate name and allows the monster to make a
free claw attack when an ally within 3 squares is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;su-sentinel&quot;&gt;Su Sentinel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many members of a su monster group use this stat block. Each one keeps watch
over a portion of the group’s territory, and calls the others if they spot any
prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su Sentinels are Level 10 Skirmishers with 107 HP. They have a &lt;strong&gt;Skirmish&lt;/strong&gt;
trait that allows them to deal 5 extra damage with their attacks if they moved
4 or more spaces this turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to basic &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; strikes, they can make a &lt;strong&gt;Flashing Talons&lt;/strong&gt;
maneuver that deals a bit less damage and, as an effect, allows them to shift 2
squares. If the targeted enemy moves to a space adjacent to the monster during
their next turn, the creature gets to make this attack against them once more
for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Mind-Rending Bite&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), which deals even less
basic damage but inflicts ongoing 10 psychic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentinels have both Su Monster signature abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;su-ambusher&quot;&gt;Su Ambusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su Ambushers are less physicall imposing but they hunt together, hanging out
near places that see frequent creature traffic and jumping out all at once to
carry prey away. They’re Level 11 Minion Soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have a basic &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack that does minion-tier damage, but instead of
using that they’re going to rely on &lt;strong&gt;Seize Prey&lt;/strong&gt;. This lets them move their
speed and make a claw attack at any point along the move. If they hit, they pull
the target alongside them the rest of the move, and do not provoke opportunity
attacks from it. This is excellent for getting defenders out of the way or
briging squishies closer to danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambushers have Fury, but they replace Psychic Boost with &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Claws&lt;/strong&gt;,
which allow them to make one last claw attack when they hit 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;su-alpha&quot;&gt;Su Alpha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Su Alphas are larger and more powerful specimens who gained some status within
their group by repeatedly proving they can beat up their puny relatives. Smaller
groups have only one alpha, but larger ones might have several. They are Level
12 Brutes with 149 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alphas fight with &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Backhand Slams&lt;/strong&gt;, the latter of which do less
damage but target Fortitude and push the target 1 square. They can also emit a
&lt;strong&gt;Su Howl&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Will) which deals psychic damage and renders its
targets vulnerable 5 to all damage (save ends). On a miss, the target takes half
damage and is vulnerable for a turn. This recharges wherever the alpha takes
psychic damage. They possess both signature abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s another carnivorous ape monster in a book that already has too many of
them. The lore and mechanics seem to disagree with each other on whether su
monsters are sapient. The stats say they are Int 2 beasts, but the lore keeps
saying they organize in “tribes”, a term I’ve avoided using here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanics themselves are mildly interesting, but I don’t like them enough to
use them paired with this lore.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/01/su-monster.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/01/su-monster.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Star Spawn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star Spawn made their debut in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/02/03/star-spawn.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual 2&lt;/a&gt; along with a pretty
awesome chunk of lore that’s also tied to star pact warlocks and the Far
Realm. You can see it all on the link. This entry adds a bit more lore, new star
spawn, and a surprise epic boss!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore in this entry confirms some of the most terrible questions we had in
the MM2. Yes, if you travel far enough in space you do end up in the Far
Realm. Yes, there are things watching across this divide, and some of them are
perceived by the people of the middle world as stars. And yes, some of them have
hostile designs upon the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allabar, the Opener of the Way, is one of these, and it travels across the
universe inciting its fellow stars to send their spawn into the world. Its
wanderings are not random, but filled with terrible purpose. Some warlocks claim
Allabar and its allies are at war with the world itself, and they call this the
Forgotten War because it’s much less noticeable than the Dawn War was but no
less significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The star spawn presented here are all mid-to-high epic tier threats, making them
a lot stronger than the paragon-tier spawn from the MM2. All of them have the
aberrant origin and possess darkvision, but the specifics vary a lot between
individual stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spawn-of-ulban&quot;&gt;Spawn of Ulban&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-star-spawn-ulban.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ulban is a blue-white star whose intense glow affects mortal minds, disrupting
their cognition and robbing them of the ability to recognize danger. Ulban’s
influence starts ill-thought rebellions and prevents divinations of any sort
from working. Its spawn fall to the earth as meteors, and their presence makes
mortals unable to distinguish friend from foe. They also break the “no
tentacles” streak for this type of monster, as you can see in the illustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spawn of Ulban are Medium Aberrant Humanoids, and Level 26 Controllers with 241
HP. They have a speed of 8. They’re immune to domination, and every time they’re
iht by a power that would dominate them, they dominate the attacker instead! And
this is a (save ends) condition even if the one from the attack wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spawn’s basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Bluefire Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex), which causes
both cold and fire damage, and dazes for a turn. It can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Touch of
Strife&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Will) instead, dealing psychic damage and forcing the target to
make a melee or ranged basic attack against a creature of the spawn’s
choice. When it hits with either of these attacks, it can apply a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic
Boost&lt;/strong&gt; as a free action, dealing an extra chunk of psychic damage. This
recharges every time the spawn takes psychic damage, so while it’s not
&lt;em&gt;resistant&lt;/em&gt; to this damage type you still don’t want to use it against the
spawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often, the spawn can produce a &lt;strong&gt;Ripple of Betrayal&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 1
vs. Will, recharge 5+) which deals psychic damage and dominates those it hits
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the spawn can use &lt;strong&gt;Far Realm Reflection&lt;/strong&gt; to form an
eldritch bond with a creature it can see. Whenever that creature shifts, the
spawn can immediately shift an equal number of squares. This lasts until the end
of the encounter, or until the spawn switches targets by using the power
again. An excellent power to use on an ally that can shift long distances, or
even on a PC that can do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spawn of Ulban wants to get in close and stay there, since its attacks are
all melee or close bursts. It’s extremely effective against parties with lots of
psionic PCs, or against those that have lots of Essentials martial
characters. The best way to fight it is to keep your distance and hit it with
non-psychic, non-dominating attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emissary-of-caiphon&quot;&gt;Emissary of Caiphon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-star-spawn-caiphon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caiphon is a purple star that can always be found near the horizon, sometimes
even during the day. It presents itself as a helpful guide star, but will
sometimes betray those who rely on it, leading them down tragic paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emissary of Caiphon is often employed in these betrayals. It’s the most
human-looking of all star spawn, and it mimics the tactics of its patrons by
posing as a guide or a prophet. Its “wise and helpful” advice usually leads to a
lot suffering and death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emissary is a Medium Aberrant Humanoid, and a Level 28 Controller with the
Leader tag and 257 HP. It projects an &lt;strong&gt;Aura of Ruin&lt;/strong&gt; (2) that inflicts a -2
penalty to saves, and whenever it’s hit by an attack that would blind it, it
blinds the attacker instead (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all of the Emissary’s powers mess with the saving throw mechanic, but it
lacks the ability to inflict (save ends) conditions by itself. Be sure to pair
it with plenty of monsters who can do that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Touch of Despair&lt;/strong&gt; that deals light physical damage and
inflicts an extra 20 damage the first time the target fails a save before the
start of the emissary next turn. It’s nifty, but it’s for emercencies only. The
creature prefers to stay far away and use its ranged attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blinded By Greed&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Will) deals light psychic damage, slides the
target 2 squares, and forces them to make a melee basic attack against a target
of the emissary’s choice (“Give me that! It’s mine!”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blinded By Need&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Will) deals standard psychic damage, and
allows the emissary to choose one of the target’s allies. For the next turn, the
target is marked by that ally, and everyone except the chosen ally is invisible
to the target. This doesn’t &lt;em&gt;force&lt;/em&gt; the target and the ally to fight each
other, but it makes it hard for either of them to do anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As minor actions, the emissary can use &lt;strong&gt;Deceptive Veil&lt;/strong&gt; to disguise itself as
a Medium or Small humanoid, with a DC 40 for people to see through the
illusion. It can also target someone with an &lt;strong&gt;Invocation of Calamity&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged
5 vs. Will), which on a hit makes the target fail all of their saves during the
next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For triggered actions, it has the same &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Boost&lt;/strong&gt; as the Spawn of Ulban,
this time applying to tis Blinded By Need/Greed powers. And when it dies,
&lt;strong&gt;Foretelling the Doom&lt;/strong&gt; targets an enemy suffering from a (save ends) condition
and inflicts a -5 penalty on all saves against it until one succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;serpent-of-nihal&quot;&gt;Serpent of Nihal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-star-spawn-nihal.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihal, the Serpent Star, is a reddish celestial body that can’t stay still. It
travels a random snaking route around the point it was supposed to occupy in the
sky according to all standard calculations. That’s why it received this
epithet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Serpents of Nihal first came through the world shortly before the fall of
the ancient empire of Az-Kiral, which dedicated itself to the worship of
Zehir. Its leaders grew ever more ambitious and soon they craved more power than
the snake god was willing to offer. So they sought out a new source of Snek
Power, and found it in Nihal. They opened a portal to the star thinking they
would be able to access this power. What happened instead was that countless
Serpents of Nihal poured through, and destroyed the empire in a matter of
days. They still wander the known cosmos today, and I guess sometimes Allabar
opens new rifts to let more through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serpents are Medium Aberrant Beasts, and Level 29 Minion Lurkers with a ground
speed of 7. They’re only partially present in reality, and keep blinking in and
out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that, despite being minions, they have &lt;strong&gt;Resist 20 to all
damage&lt;/strong&gt;. Yes, even untyped. You need to deal 21 or more damage with one strike
to take them out. It’s not that hard for late epic PCs, but it’s also not 100%
guaranteed, so they have more staying power than your typical minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serpents attack with &lt;strong&gt;mindbites&lt;/strong&gt;, which deal psychic damage and can interfere
with concentration and psionic power usage: if 2 or more of the serpent’s allies
are adjacent to the target, the bite deals extra damage and prevents the target
from spending action points or power points (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy misses the serpent, it can &lt;strong&gt;Depart Reality&lt;/strong&gt;, removing itself from
play for a turn an re-appearing in adjacent to an enemy within 20 squares of its
original location. It can also do this exact same thing when it rolls initiative
with the &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Reality Warp&lt;/strong&gt; ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;allabar-opener-of-the-way&quot;&gt;Allabar, Opener of the Way&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-star-spawn-allabar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yup, you read that right. This is not a star spawn, it’s a &lt;em&gt;star&lt;/em&gt;. Allabar is
here to serve as the end boss for a campaign focused on the Forgotten War, which
would likely feature the PCs facing and unraveling the plans of increasingly
powerful aberrant creatures and star spawn until Allabar itself decides to
personally kill them. As the lore implies, Allabar is not the only eldritch star
who wants to mess with the world, but it’s the most consciously malicious one
and it acts as instigator and enabler to the others. Eliminating Allabar would
effectively end the threat posed by its fellows and their respective star spawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting the lore in astronomical terms would make Allabar similar to a rogue
planet, a planet without a star that moves across the universe. The similarity
is only superficial, of course, because pretty much nothing else about the
Opener of the Way is in any way scientific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allabar is presented here as a Gargantuan Aberrant Animate. Those who feel even
Gargantuan is too small for a planetary entity might instead say this is an
avatar of Allabar, the thing it sends through a portal to personally fight the
PCs. When it dies, the star winks out from the sky. Or you can take a page from
Atropus in Elder Evils, and have the actual body of Allabar be the
dungeon/battlefield on which you fight its avatar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Allabar is a Level 30 Solo Soldier with 1100 HP. It has ground and
flight speeds of 6, with Hover. As a planet, it projects a &lt;strong&gt;Gravity Well&lt;/strong&gt; that
acts as a 20-square wide aura. This plus its Gargantuan size pretty much mean it
covers the entire battle map. Anyone who starts their turn inside the field gets
pulled a variable number of squares depending on how much HP Allabar currently
has. It starts at 1 square, and doubles for every 25% of its HP that are missing
(at 25% or less total HP, it’s 8 squares).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being covered with eyes, Allabar has &lt;strong&gt;All-Around Vision&lt;/strong&gt;, and can’t be
flanked. Its &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Fury&lt;/strong&gt; also gives it an extra standard action per turn
while it’s bloodied, even when it’s dazed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat, the Opener of the Way projects Reach 4 &lt;strong&gt;Tentacles&lt;/strong&gt; to attack, which
deal light physical damage and restrain for a turn on a hit. It can use them in
a &lt;strong&gt;Triple Attack&lt;/strong&gt; to strike three times in a standard action, and it can
enhance a tentacle attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Boost&lt;/strong&gt; similar to that of the star
spawn in this entry. Aside from the boost recharging when Allabar takes psychic
damage, it also recharges when the star succeeds with its &lt;strong&gt;Devour Body&lt;/strong&gt;
attack. This Close Burst 1 vs. Fortitude targets creatures who are at 0 HP or
lower. On a hit, it kills the target and pulls it inside Allabar. It &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt;
target dead allies, but it’s also excellent for making PCs exercise those “when
you die” abilities they surely have by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another very interesting attack is &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the Forsaken World&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast
5 vs. Fortitude, recharge 5+), which deals psychic damage and causes each target
to sprout a hostile tentacle (save ends). While the tentacle is there, it deals
an automatic 20 damage to any target that ends their turn within 2 squares of
the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, you know, no big deal, the Opener can use &lt;strong&gt;Unravel Essence&lt;/strong&gt;
(melee 4 vs. Fortitude), which inflicts 20 ongoing damage on a hit (save
ends). On the first failed save, this increases to 25. On the second, the target
also becomes weakened and insubstantial. On the third, the target drops to 0 HP
if its HP was still positive. A successful save at any point halts the process
and clears all related conditions. This recharges whenever there are no
creatures affected by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, when someone hits Allabar with an attack, it can cause &lt;strong&gt;Psychic
Feedback&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction, automatically dazing the attacker (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allabar is very intelligent and will work to maximize its advantages, abusing
its flight and superior reach, and focusing fire make them drop to 0 HP quickly
so they can be devoured. And if your level 30 PCs are cocky because this end
boss is “only” level 30, add a few Emissaries of Caiphon to make it impossible
for them to pass the many saves imposed by the Opener of the Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The awesome continues! This entry does return to the old standby of “tentacles”,
but the monsters are still pretty evocative and their mechanics
interesting. Allabar reminds me of Atropus, from Elder Evils, but it’s has more
of an aberrant/psychic theme instead of Atropus’ undead/necrotic leanings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Opener of the Way is the fourth and last epic boss to be found in this
book. The previous ones were Imix, Lolth, and Ogrémoch.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/10/28/star-spawn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/10/28/star-spawn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
