<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 12:39:52 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 12:39:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Fell Taint</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fell-taint.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; fell taints are new to 4e - at least, this book is where I first heard
of them. If they showed up in previous editions, it was probably in 3e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess the name made me think of something you might find staining an ogre’s
underwear, but that’s not the case. Fell Taints are small predators from the Far
Realm, where they occupy a niche more or less equivalent to that of our
foxes. However, they’re quite a bit more dangerous when they cross into the
world, which they can do rather easily in places where the border between it and
the Far Realm is even a little bit thinner than usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their presence acts as a beacon for more powerful and dangerous Far Realm
denizens, and slowly erodes the barrier between dimensions. So if you have fell
taints in a place, you’ll soon get bigger horrors from beyond popping up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The taints themselves are also dangerous on their own, since they hunt by
destroying the mind of their intended prey with their psychic powers. This is
not exactly something most mortal creatures have a strong defense against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the bizarre things about Fell Taints is that they’re only half real. The
other half is formed by the minds of those who see them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fell Taints are Baby’s First Elder Things, with levels in the early-to-mid
Heroic tier. If you’re starting an aberrant-themed campaign from Level 1,
they’re going to be the first genuine Far Realm denizens your party meets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fell Taints can fly quite well with a speed of 6 and hover capability, or crawl
along the ground at speed 1 if they must. They’re insubstantial due to that
half-real thing, but vulnerable to psychic damage. The touch of their
&lt;strong&gt;tendrils&lt;/strong&gt; causes psychic damage, and they usually have mind-affecting special
attacks as well. They’re all Aberrant Magical Beasts, and most are Small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ability they all share is &lt;strong&gt;Fell Taint Feeding&lt;/strong&gt;: when they manage to get a
victim helpless or unconscious, they can begin to feed. This causes them to lose
their fly speed and become substantial until the end of their next turn, but
allows them to perform a &lt;em&gt;coup de grace&lt;/em&gt; against the victim. If this kills the
victim, the fell taint immediately recovers all of its hit points. Yeah, they’ll
absolutely attempt to kill any PC that drops to 0 HP during the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-lasher&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Lasher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lashers are Level 1 Soldiers with 20 HP and all standard traits outlined
above. Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Tendrils of Stasis&lt;/strong&gt;, which does a bit less
damage than the basic tendril slap and immobilizes the target for a turn. When
making an opportunity attack, they can shift as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-pulsar&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Pulsar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pulsars are Level 1 Artillery with 18 HP and all common traits. Their special
attacks are a Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;tendril pulse&lt;/strong&gt; that does psychic damage, and a Ranged
10 &lt;strong&gt;tendril flurry&lt;/strong&gt; that makes a slightly weaker attack against up to three
targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-tought-eater&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Tought Eater&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 2 Controllers with 26 HP and all standard traits. They have two
special attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit Haze&lt;/strong&gt; is a Range 10 attack that does psychic damage and dazes for a
turn. &lt;strong&gt;Tought Fog&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a Close Burst 5 that only targets enemies,
does no damage, and slows. This worsens to immobilization after the first failed
save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-warp-wender&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Warp Wender&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 4 Controller is Medium, and has 38 HP. Its single special attack is
&lt;strong&gt;Psychic Transposition&lt;/strong&gt;, which does light psychic damage, dazes (save ends)
and makes the taint and the victim teleport to exchange places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are mostly mixed fell taint groups, because they rarely
work with anyone else. Still, they might be coincidentally found alongside
undead or oozes, creatures they find unapettizing. I imagine some cultists and
such might also know how to bind them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a party’s first contact with the Far Realm, I think these creatures are quite
nifty. They look weird enough to unsettle, and each has a single distinctive
mechanical trick.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/13/fell-taint.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/13/fell-taint.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Elemental</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, any creature with the “elemental” origin is an elemental, but as we
saw in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/16/elemental.html&quot;&gt;Elemental&lt;/a&gt; entry from the first monster manual the name is also
used for a particularly wild subset of that plane’s denizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in that earlier post, Elementals proper are some of the “basest”
life forms of the Elemental Chaos, with bodies that share a lot more with their
constituent elements than with any sort of living organism. Unlike demons
they’re not actively malicious, but they’re mercurial and easy to provoke into a
rampage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As magical beasts, they’re technically sapient, but their intellects tend to be
rather limited. These creatures are also often bound by elementally-inclined
ritual casters such as mortal wizards, efreets, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM2 presents us with more elementals ranging from the mid-Heroic to the
early Epic tier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chillfire-destroyer&quot;&gt;Chillfire Destroyer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-chillfire-destroyer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Large humanoid made of ice wrapped around a fiery core, which means it has
zero chill. It’s a Level 14 Brute with 173 HP, lumbering about at Speed 5. It
has 10 resistance to cold and fire, and is immune to disease and poison. Its
&lt;strong&gt;fists&lt;/strong&gt; do a mix of fire and cold damage, and it can also move its speed and
&lt;strong&gt;trample&lt;/strong&gt; anyone it comes into contact with during this movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this elemental gets damaged, its shell begins to crack. Once it’s bloodied,
its &lt;strong&gt;Leaking Firecore&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (radius 2) that deals fire damage to
anyone caught inside. Once it reaches 0 HP, a &lt;strong&gt;Firecore Breach&lt;/strong&gt; causes it to
explode! This explosion is a Close Burst 3 vs. Reflex, dealing heavy fire
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dust-devil&quot;&gt;Dust Devil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-dust-devil.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A being or air and earth, this capricious living whirlwind has a tendency to
sandblast anyone who makes it angry. It’s Small, and a Level 3 Skirmisher with
47 HP and a ground speed of 8. No, they can’t fly. It’s immune to disease and
poison, and it suffers a -2 penalty to all of its defenses if slowed or
immobilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Winds&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex, does some physical
damage and slides the target 3 squares. &lt;strong&gt;Gale Blast&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to shift 5
squares by moving really fast, and try to knock anyone in the way prone (attack
vs. Fortitude).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can do that sandblasting trick with &lt;strong&gt;Stinging Sands&lt;/strong&gt;
(close burst 3 vs. Fortitude), which does heavy damage and blinds for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flamespiker&quot;&gt;Flamespiker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-flamespiker.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a triple combination of air, earth, and fire, taking the form of a
Medium stony humanoid who can use high-pressure air to fire red-hot spikes from
its fiery core. They’re more like people than wildlife, and often end up hired
as front-line muscle by other sapient elementals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flamespikers are level 5 soldiers with 66 HP and a ground speed of 7. Their
immunities include disease, poison, and petrification, and they also have 10
fire resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flamespiker fights with its Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Stonespikes&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and can also
fire them at out to range 10 as &lt;strong&gt;Spikebolts&lt;/strong&gt;. Both attacks do physical damage,
and the melee one also makes the target vulnerable to fire damage until the end
of the spiker’s next turn. So it pairs really well with fire elementals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy within reach shifts, the stonespiker can react with a &lt;strong&gt;Thunderfire
Thrust&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which is a basic melee attack with an extra follow-up
against Fortitude that does 5 thunder damage and stuns (save ends). This makes
slipping past them a difficult proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;geonid&quot;&gt;Geonid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-geonid.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Large creature has more of a metabolism than most elementals, and needs to
hunt. A stony oyster-like creature, the geonid is extremely hard to tell apart
from a boulder when its shell is closed. When it reveals itself, we can see that
it’s yet another tentacular ambush predator that lives in the shallow Underdark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were initially created to guard the secret pathways of the world, and the
secret caches of weapons, dormant war-beasts, and treasure hidden there by the
forces of the primordials. Some of those caches are still out there, as are
their guardians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geonids are Level 6 Lurkers with 56 HP. They’re immune to disease, petrification
and poison, and cal roll around at speed 4. With its shell closed, potential
victims must pass a DC 28 Perception check to realize it’s not a harmless
boulder. At level 6, this is hard even for the party’s “radar”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the geonid strikes, it fights with &lt;strong&gt;tentacle&lt;/strong&gt; slaps that do standard
physical damage. It can also use a &lt;strong&gt;capturing grab&lt;/strong&gt; that consists of two
weaker tentacle attacks. If both hit, it grabs the target (escape DC 17).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it’s grabbed someone, the geonid will close itself with &lt;strong&gt;Shell Slam&lt;/strong&gt;,
which does a lot of things at once. It slides a grabbed victim to the geonid’s
space, and it tries to knock everyone in a close burst 2 prone (vs. Fortitude).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the shell is closed, the geonid has a ground speed of 0 and a +5 to all of
its defenses, and it can’t target anyone other than the grabbed victim it pulled
inside its shell. The victim can also only target the geonid, but on the bright
side it won’t have to contend with the defense bonus. If the victim escapes, it
gets spit out and appears adjacent to the geonid, who can open its shell with a
minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mudlasher&quot;&gt;Mudlasher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-mudlasher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sapient elemental predator, mudlashers are made of well, mud. They slam
and drown their victims, and then sit atop the corpse as a puddle to slowly
digest it. They’re Medium Level 4 Brutes with 63 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; do physical damage, and once per fight they can upgrade
that to a &lt;strong&gt;Drowning Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude and adds an ongoing damage
follow-up (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also fling &lt;strong&gt;mud balls&lt;/strong&gt; at range (vs. Reflex), which do no damage but
slow their targets. If a target is already slowed, it’s immobilized
instead. This is good because the mudlasher gets a +2 to attacks against slowed
or immobilized targets. A save will end either condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rockfist-smasher&quot;&gt;Rockfist Smasher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-rockfist-smasher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name says it all: they’re humanoid rocks that like to smash with their
fists. Smashers don’t need to eat, so they do that for fun. People who build
elemental themed dungeons like to gather a bunch of these and lock them in
chambers and at the bottom of pits as living traps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hooligans are Large, Level 10 Brutes with 125 HP, the standard suite of
earth-creature immunities, and a speed of 5. Their &lt;strong&gt;Granite Punches&lt;/strong&gt; do good
damage and knock bloodied targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a smasher gets bloodied itself, its &lt;strong&gt;Internal Avalanche&lt;/strong&gt; triggers and
begins accumulating kinetic energy. This gives the smasher 20 temporary HP. If
it still has any temp HP at the start of its next turn, it gains an action point
that must be used in that turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shardstorm-vortex&quot;&gt;Shardstorm Vortex&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-rockfist-smasher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are living blizzards made of stone instead of ice. Despite this impressive
description, they’re just Medium in size and are the scavengers of the Elemental
Chaos. Shardstorms follow in the wake of more impressive beings and feed on what
remains of their battles. In battle they work like slightly stronger dust
devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re level 7 skirmishers with 80 HP. Their ground speed is 0, but they fly at
speed 8 with hover capability and project a &lt;strong&gt;Sandblast&lt;/strong&gt; aura (radius 1) that
inflicts a -2 to all defenses of anyone caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Abrasive Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude and does
physical damage. They can also perform &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Blasts&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that
allow them to shift 4 squares and an attack at the end. This does heavy damage
and pushes 1 square on a hit. It does half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also get two variant stat blocks for them as minions at levels 13
and 23. They still have the aura and the basic attack, but instead of the Blast
they get a &lt;strong&gt;Vortex Step&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will 4-square shift with no built-in attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stormstone-fury&quot;&gt;Stormstone Fury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-stormstone-fury.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Medium stone humanoid infused with the power of a storm. It can throw
explosive stones, cause shrapnel to fly outward from its body, and meld into the
ground for a quick escape. When fighting as part of a team they don’t really
care about catching allies in their blasts, so if you find yourself on the same
side as one of these, bring some thunder protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furies are Level 14 Artillery with 113 HP and Speed 6. They have the usual
immunity suite, and 10 thunder resistance. Its &lt;strong&gt;Grinding Stones&lt;/strong&gt; melee basic
attack is terrible, but its &lt;strong&gt;Hurtling Thunderstones&lt;/strong&gt; have Range 20 and do half
damage on a miss. Hit or miss, they also cause a follow-up explosion (burst 2
vs. Fortitude) that does thunder damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shrapnel Burst&lt;/strong&gt; is their “keep away from me” power, sending shrapnel that
pushes 2 squares and does physical and thunder damage in a close burst 2
(vs. AC). If that fails, &lt;strong&gt;Meld to Ground&lt;/strong&gt; removes them from the map for a
turn, after which they reappear up to 10 squares away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tempest-wisp&quot;&gt;Tempest Wisp&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-tempest-wisp.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gaseous creature is a bit smarter than your average elemental, and actively
seeks to either ally with or coerce other creatures to form groups that
cooperate against threats. It uses its wind powers to push enemies around the
battlefield, and hides behind its allies to avoid damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tempest Wisps are Level 13 Controllers with 134 HP. They’re immune to disease
and poison, and are insubstantial while not bloodied (i.e, while at over 50%
HP). They have a flight speed of 7 with hover capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Air Slash&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex) that does physical damage,
and they can attack at range with &lt;strong&gt;Whistling Wind&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex) for
about the same damage and a 1-square slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their limited special attack is hilarious! Named &lt;strong&gt;Tumbling Updraft&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Fortitude; recharge 5+), it does no immediate damage but instead lifts the
target 20 feet up on a hit and restrains them (save ends). Each failed save
causes the victim to be tossed up another 20 feet. On a successful save, the
victim falls! That’s a minimum of 2d10 fall damage, plus another 2d10 for every
failed save. It’s all subject to the standard rules for falls, though, so you
might be able to reduce or avoid this damage in the usual ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;windfiend-fury&quot;&gt;Windfiend Fury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-windfiend-fury.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another Angry Tornado, this one more purely “stormy” than the others. These
Large beings like to hang around elemental storms, and so tend to get swept away
into other planes. Sometimes archons will capture them and bind them to their
flying ships as a power source and as a means to travel to other planes. You can
also say these are the beings trapped at the core of those Eberron flying ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 12 Controllers with 123 HP and a flight speed of 8. Aside from
the usual immunities to disease and poison they have 15 resistance to lightning
and thunder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They attack in melee with &lt;strong&gt;Flying Debris&lt;/strong&gt;, and toss &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; at
range that do lightning damage and daze for a turn. Their “keep away!” power is
a &lt;strong&gt;Storm Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that does thunder damage and teleports them to just outside
the area of effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;windstriker&quot;&gt;Windstriker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-windstriker.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final Angry Tornado is Medium, and a Level 9 Lurker with 56 HP. They have
the usual immunities and full-time insubstantiality, along with a flight speed
of 8. It attacks unpredictably, though apparently not to feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their attacks do “cold and thunder” damage. They’re probably going to
open up with &lt;strong&gt;Searching Wind&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Will), which knocks prone on a
hit and marks the target as the windstriker’s quarry as an effect. Then they’ll
follow that up with &lt;strong&gt;Lethal Windstrike&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. AC), which hits hard but
only works against the quarry. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Windstrike&lt;/strong&gt; is a lot weaker, so
it’s for emergencies only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the windstriker takes damage, it activates &lt;strong&gt;Shifting Wind&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction,
which gives it the ability to ignore opportunity attacks and pass through enemy
spaces during its next turn. So it’s going to be flitting back and forth to
alternate marking someone as a quarry and attempting to assassinate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a whole bunch of sample encounters here, but they’re all easily to
described: assorted elementals of similar level, occasionally with someone who
might be the spellcaster binding them, like a tiefling heretic or a beholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the lore of elementals in 4e on principle, and we have lots of
mechanically varied stat blocks here… but there’s &lt;em&gt;so many&lt;/em&gt; of them that they
all kinda started blurring together by the end. I almost wish we had gotten an
elemental “plug-in” module for the 4e monster design system rather than this
long list full of angry rock giants and angry living tornadoes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/10/elemental.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/10/elemental.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Eladrin</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-eladrin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already discussed the lore of the Eladrin &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/13/eladrin.html&quot;&gt;over here&lt;/a&gt;, along with how they
differ from your standard elves and from the celestials of 3e. I recommend
reading that post again for those basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 contains three more eladrin stat blocks, along with a bit
of additional lore on their society. I find it very funny that two of them
correspond to very popular elfy classes of editions past, debuting in 4e in the
form of monster entries. It would be some time before playable versions of them
were published, which I imagine must have made their fans quite anxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eladrin-arcane-archer&quot;&gt;Eladrin Arcane Archer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arcane Archers are more than just wizards who can shoot a bow. They practice an
art that’s seamless fusion of the two disciplines, and whose secrets are
jealously kept by certain eladrin societies. The Bow Mage minions we saw in the
MM1 are likely to practice the same style. This entry would represent a more
advanced, experienced, or narratively important practitioner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think we ever explicitly got an Arcane Archer class in 4e. The Seeker
tries to implement the concept using primal magic but ends up not being very
effective. I think there’s also a way to build a Bard specializing in magic
ranged attacks with a bow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arcane Archers are Level 5 Artillery with 51 HP. Their speed is 6 and they have
low-light vision, along with the standard Fey Step power all eladrin get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight, they stay at range and repeatedly fire &lt;strong&gt;Scorching Arrows&lt;/strong&gt; from
their bows. This ability is kinda like a better version of the PC Ranger’s Twin
Strike, allowing them to make two attacks that target the lower of AC and
Reflex. The arrows have the same range as mundane ones, and individually deal a
low-ish mix of physical and fire damage. This adds up, though: an arcane archer
that consistently hits with both attacks punches a fair bit above its weight
class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also fire an arrow that explodes into an &lt;strong&gt;Eldricht Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst
1 within 20 vs Fortitude; recharge 4+). This deals force damage and knocks
enemies prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eladrin-bladesingers&quot;&gt;Eladrin Bladesingers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, bladesingers. I first heard of them in 2e and I can’t remember a more
controversial class from that edition, at least here in the Brazilian fan
community. People either really loved them or really hated them. While I was
eventually convinced that their highly cinematic combat style was cool, I never
liked that they were an elf-only option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, 4e bladesingers are eladrin practitioners of an ancient martial art that
joins swordplay and magic. The resulting style resembles something a Jedi knight
or wuxia hero might use, employing lots of empowered sword strikes and
magic-assisted acrobatic maneuvers. Their code of conduct has elegance as an
important principle, so they put real effort into making their combat techniques
both graceful and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same code also compels them to behave honorably, so they tend to treat
opponents with respect and despise those who slaughter the weak and
defenseless. Despite this, there are many possible reasons for even a party of
good-aligned PCs to come into conflict with bladesingers: they might have
offended the eladrin’s liege, or a given group of bladesingers might have fallen
to the Dark Side of the Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get pretty close to a playable bladesinger by playing a Swordmage, and
apparently there was also a “bladesinger” class published late in the
edition. More obliquely, a Blade Pact Fey Warlock could also fit the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM2 bladesinger is a Level 11 Skirmisher with 114 HP. They have a very nice
ground speed of 8, in addition to the low-light vision and Fey Step power all
eladrin get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wear mail and wield a longsword, both of which are probably magical or at
least very high quality. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Brilliant Blade&lt;/strong&gt; strike,
which deals radiant damage and gives the target a -3 penalty to attack the
bladesinger during the target’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dance of Brilliance&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will combination that allows them to make an
attack dealing light radiant damage, shift 3 squares, and make a basic Brilliant
Blade attack against another target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have two encounter powers. &lt;strong&gt;Crippling Strike&lt;/strong&gt; targets Fortitude and deals
no damage, but is guaranteed to slow the target even on a miss. On a hit it also
weakens them. In both cases the conditions are “save ends”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wyvern Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is much better, allowing the bladesinger to fly 8 squares
without provoking opportunity attacks and perform a strike at any poing along
the movement. This targets Fortitude, deals light physical damage, and 10
ongoing poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally there’s &lt;strong&gt;Combat Shift&lt;/strong&gt;. This allows them to shift 1 square as a minor
action, ending up adjacent to an enemy against which they have combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coure-of-mischief-and-strife&quot;&gt;Coure of Mischief and Strife&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time for more surreal fey nobility! Like “bralani” and “ghaele”, “coure” is a
noble title whose meaning can be a little confusing to mortals. One of the
reasons for this is that while most eladrin societies use the same names for the
titles, the actual rank they confer, and the amount of influence attached to
them, varies from culture to culture. So in this city state ghaeles might be the
rulers, but on that kingdom over there they’re just minor provincial nobles and
it’s the coures who call the shots. Attaining a noble title is rarely a matter
of inheritance - there’s a lot of mystery and mystycism involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever their rank, though, these titles always have some natural phenomenon or
abstract concept attached to them, like “autumn winds”, “winter”, or “mischef
and strife” in this entry. The noble in question will always have powers
relating to this area of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, a coure of mischief and strife is a pointy-eared Loki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This coure is a Level 17 Lurker with 129 HP. It has the usual low-light vision
and Fey Step ability, which in this case is completely redundant because the
coure also has a teleport speed of 6 to complement its ground speed of 6. It
wears leathers and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;rapier&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coure can become &lt;strong&gt;invisible&lt;/strong&gt; at will as a standard action, and this lasts
until it takes damage or &lt;em&gt;misses&lt;/em&gt; with an attack. If it attacks and hits, it
stays invisible! If for some reason the eladrin doesn’t already starts the fight
invisible, this is going to be its very first action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the invisible trickster is close to the party, &lt;strong&gt;Winds of Luck’s Mischief&lt;/strong&gt;
is a good fight opener: a Close Burst 3 vs. Will that does no damage, but makes
everyone it affects miss all attacks whose attack rolls were odd. This is a
“save ends” condition, so it might stick around for a while! Good luck trying to
damage an invisible enemy when half of your blows veer off course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While invisible the coure can also use &lt;strong&gt;Spark of Strife&lt;/strong&gt;, a Ranged 10 attack
vs. Will that deals psychic damage and is stronger than the rapier. A hit also
forces the target to charge its nearest ally, or make a melee basic attack if
it’s already close. This compelled attack is a free action, so it doesn’t eat
into the PC’s turn. However, if the compelled attack hits, the coure gets to use
Spark of Strife against the ally that was hit by it as a free action as well! A
series of lucky rolls is going to rapidly turn the party’s well-tuned battle
formation into a Three Stooges skit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter here is level 10: 3 bladesingers, an eladrin twilight
incanter from the first MM, and a will-o’-wisp which I guess might be the
incanter’s familiar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how the different eladrin celestial types from 3e became a bizarre system
of nobility ranks with a lot of that good faerie flavor. As one rises in rank,
one becomes less tied to the mortal world.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/07/eladrin.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/07/eladrin.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Duergar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-duergar.webp&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chronologically, the first appearance of Duergar in 4e is in the Monster Manual
2, but they were also in the Monster Vault so we covered their basic lore
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In this post, we’ll covered the duergar that appeared in the MM2 but
weren’t updated in the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;previously-on-octopus-carnival&quot;&gt;Previously on Octopus Carnival…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For your information, these are the duergar entries we covered &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;:
Scout, Guard, Thug, Raid Leader, Infernal Consort, and Devil-Bred Duergar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This still leaves us with a sizable selection of stat blocks that didn’t make it
into the Monster Vault. They include some elite warrior types, and several
Hell-themed spellcasters that resemble either warlocks or clerics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in that earlier post, all duergar share two signature traits:
resistance to fire and poison that increases with their level, and the ability
to shoot out their Infernal Quills at someone, once per fight as a minor
action. This has a Range of 3, does light physical damage and a tiny bit of
ongoing poison damage. It also inflicts a -2 penalty to attack rolls. A single
save ends both the ongoing damage and the attack penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-theurge&quot;&gt;Duergar Theurge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weakest of the spellcasters we’re going to look at here. Theurges wear robes
and wield warhammers in melee. At range they fight with a number of spells
themed around fire, smoke, and despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the name they feel a bit more wizardly than the others, who are more
clearly priests of some kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theurges are Level 5 Controllers with 63 HP. They wear robes and fight with
&lt;strong&gt;warhammers&lt;/strong&gt; in melee. Their basic ranged attacks are &lt;strong&gt;Hellbolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Reflex) that do fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a few more powerful spells. &lt;strong&gt;Brimstone Hail&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5-6)
does fire damage over a fireball-sized area and knocks targets prone on a
hit. &lt;strong&gt;Vile Fumes&lt;/strong&gt; (recharges when first bloodied) does poison damage over the
same area and blinds for a turn on a hit. And &lt;strong&gt;Wave of Despair&lt;/strong&gt; is a daily
blast 5 vs. Will and does psychic damage, slows, and dazes (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-shock-trooper&quot;&gt;Duergar Shock Trooper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shock troopers are somewhat similar to the guards we saw in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;the first
article&lt;/a&gt;, but stronger and more suited to open warfare. They wield mauls
instead of puny warhammers and have the ability to grow bigger when the fight
grows more intense!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troopers are Level 6 Brutes with 84 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;mauls&lt;/strong&gt; have no special effects
aside from hitting hard, and their &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Quills&lt;/strong&gt; attack works as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When first bloodied, they can &lt;strong&gt;Expand&lt;/strong&gt; as a free action, growing to size
Large. This makes them take up 4 squares and pushes anyone who was adjacent to
make room for their new bulk. It also gives them a +2 attack bonus and a +5
damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-fleshtearer&quot;&gt;Duergar Fleshtearer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a name “Fleshtearer”, you’d expect this duergar to be a mindless berserker,
but it’s actually a sneaky magical assassin that fights with claws made of smoke
and can become invisible to better slice you with them and make your wounds
bleed faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-number&quot;&gt;The Number&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleshtearers are Level 11 Lurkers with 89 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; also do ongoing
damage. If they have combat advantage they can instead attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Quill
Stab&lt;/strong&gt; that has the same effect as the signature Infernal Quills power as a
melee attack. This one recharges whenever the duergar hits with the basic claw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Underdark Sneak&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action) requires them to be in dim light or darkness,
or adjacent to some cover. It makes them invisible for a turn or until right
after they attack. &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Scourge&lt;/strong&gt; is a passive trait that builds on this by
doubling the ongoing damage the duergar causes if it attacks from invisibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-hellcaller&quot;&gt;Duergar Hellcaller&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This caster-type has focused their infernal magic on having the most fabulous
set of quills in the Underdark. They can fire quills all day long, unlike their
less well-endowed compatriots. Rounding out their arsenal is a small set of
diabolic curses and summoning spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellcallers are Level 12 Artillery with 96 HP. They wield &lt;strong&gt;maces&lt;/strong&gt; for
emergency, but as usual for artillery monsters the real interesting bits are the
ranged attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Quills&lt;/strong&gt; are an at-will Ranged 10 attack, and have the same
effects as the encounter version for other duergar. They can momentarily
increase their rate of fire to make this attack as a minor action, and to fire
off a &lt;strong&gt;Quill Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (area 2 within 10 vs. Reflex) that covers an area and
deals more ongoing damage than usual. Both of these special uses are encounter
powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can also conjure &lt;strong&gt;Asmodeus’s Ruby Curse&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast
5 vs. Will; enemies only) that deals psychic damage and slides those hits to the
outside of the affected area. This movement &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; provoke opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone manages to get close enough to make a melee attack against the
hellcaller, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Devilish Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt. This causes the
duergar to shift beyond the attack’s reach, and to summon a legion devil
hellguard into its former position. The attack targets the new minion, and if it
misses the devil gets to act right after the hellcaller in the initiative order
from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-blackguard&quot;&gt;Duergar Blackguard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evil paladin-type uses its martial skills and magic powers to isolate and
pursue individual PCs across the battlefield. It wears plate and wields both a
shield and a warhammer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-3&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 13 Elite Soldier with 260 HP. Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Blighted
Warhammer&lt;/strong&gt; that deals damage as usual and triggers a secondary attack against
Fortitude with similar effects to the standard Infernal Quills power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blackguard’s own quills are a bit stronger than usual, replacing the
standard power with a &lt;strong&gt;Quill Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage in a Close Burst
3 around the duergar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “isolate and pursue” part comes from a pair of abilities: &lt;strong&gt;Darkfire Mark&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor action 1/round) marks an enemy and compels it to approach and attack the
blackguard - if the enemy fails to do both in its next turn, it takes 10 fire
and necrotic damage. &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Footwork&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that allows the
blackguard to shift 2 squares in pursuit of an adjacent enemy who tries to get
away from it. If that enemy is marked, the blackguard also gets to make a hammer
attack against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-blasphemer&quot;&gt;Duergar Blasphemer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strongest priest-type we’ll see here, weaker only than the Infernal Consort
from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;Monster Vault article&lt;/a&gt;. Like the Hellcaller, the Blasphemer also
has Big Quill Energy, though its other magic is more focused on disruptive mind
control effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-4&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blasphemers are Level 14 Controllers (Leaders) with 140 HP who wield
&lt;strong&gt;greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt; in battle. Like Hellcallers, they can fire &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Quills&lt;/strong&gt; at
will and use a Quick Quill Strike once per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the quills, they have three spells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preach Submission&lt;/strong&gt; (Close burst 10 vs. Will; minor action 1/round) does no
damage but marks on a hit (save ends). An already-marked target is instead
knocked prone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eyes of Asmodeus&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) also does no damage, but
weakens and marks for a turn on a hit. On a miss, or as an after-effect on a
hit, the target is slowed (save ends). This combos nicely with Preach
Submission to knock someone prone immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sinner’s Slip&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt that redirects an attack made against the
blasphemer to the attacker’s closest ally. If no allies can be targeted in
this way the attacker is instead knocked prone and takes some psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one sample encounter here. It’s Level 4, consisting of 2 guards, 1
scout, 1 theurge, and 4 orc drudges that are probably their slaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sure is a lot of duergar, and it further increases the variety and level
range of the available opposition if you want your PCs to go up against a whole
fortress full of them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/06/duergar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/06/duergar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Drakkoth</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-drakkoth.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drakkoths, also known as Dracotaurs, have been around since at least 3e. They
also look like something I’d find in some of the more exotic BECMI supplements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a number of other peoples, drakkoths are distant relatives of
dragons. Their humanoid half looks like a crested dragonborn, and their
quadruped half like a small wingless dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drakkoths are nomadic, somewhat insular and territorial, and have enough
technology to make steel weapons. Their preferred terrain are forests and
jungles, and the borders of their claimed territory tend to shift slightly over
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the book some drakkoth communities worship Tiamat, but others
choose to venerate an individual dragon patron instead. This is most often an
elder or ancient green, given their common terrain preference. I imagine you
could have communities of Bahamut-worshipping or good-dragon-venerating
drakkoths as well. Some dragons actively seek to set themselves as the bosses of
a drakkoth community, because as far as potential servants go they’re a lot more
useful than kobolds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drakkoths are very strong and tough, and quite smart as well. They mostly fight
with weapons, to which they apply poison. They tend to wear hide and leather
armor, but you could also say their scaly hides are naturally tough if you’re so
inclined. Their superior movement speed means they favor “cavalry” and
skirmishing tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also breathe poison in a manner similar to a green dragon, and are
prone to flying into a rage that leaves them immune to pain when bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;common-traits&quot;&gt;Common Traits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drakkoths are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Reptile keyword. They have
low-light vision, and their four legs give them a respectable speed of 7. Though
all of them have a breath weapon and a rage ability, the exact effects vary with
each stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drakkoth-ambusher&quot;&gt;Drakkoth Ambusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 13 Skirmisher with 131 HP. It fights with a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;glaive&lt;/strong&gt;
that does a mix of physical and poison damage. It can also employ a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden
Rush&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (move action; recharge 5-6), allowing it to shift its speed and
make attacks vs. the Reflex of every enemy it moves adjacent to. This does no
damage, but knocks prone on a hit. They also do extra “sneak attack” damage
against an enemy granting &lt;strong&gt;combat advantage&lt;/strong&gt; to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their breath weapon is a very dragon-like &lt;strong&gt;Venomous Hiss&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 2
vs. Reflex; recharges when first bloodied). It does poison damage, and ongoing
poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While bloodied the ambusher enters a &lt;strong&gt;Drakkoth Rage&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes it tougher
by granting it 10 temporary HP whenever it hits with an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drakkoth-rager&quot;&gt;Drakkoth Rager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Level 15 Elite Brute with 366 HP, the rager is a lot more direct in its
approach to combat. It wields a &lt;strong&gt;battleaxe&lt;/strong&gt; and can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Raging
Cleave&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage as the basic attack plus a bit of extra
poison damage in a Close Burst 1. It &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; to be surrounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Venomous Hiss&lt;/strong&gt; and its &lt;strong&gt;Drakkoth Rage&lt;/strong&gt; have all the same effects as
those of the ambusher, but the rage also gives it a +2 to attacks and +5 to
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drakkoth-venomshot&quot;&gt;Drakkoth Venomshot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This archer is Level 16 Artillery with 125 HP, and carries a &lt;strong&gt;longsword&lt;/strong&gt; and a
&lt;strong&gt;longbow&lt;/strong&gt; into combat. Its arrows have a rider that gives the target
Vulnerable 10 Poison (save ends), which pairs nicely with the poisoned weapons
of its buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of the standard Venomous Hiss, it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Venomshot Hiss&lt;/strong&gt; that does
less damage but can be used more often, recharging at the end of any turn where
the venomshot is bloodied. Its &lt;strong&gt;Rage&lt;/strong&gt; is the same as the ambusher’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to palling around with dragons, drakkoths also train creatures
native to their territories to fight alongside them, and they can make
short-term alliances with neighbors to take down powerful threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 14: a rager, two venomshots, and a viscera devourer. I bet there’s an
interesting story behind that one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 16: 3 ambushers, 2 venomshots, and a roc!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t even remember drakkoths existed before I got to this entry, but these
look interesting. I’m sure you could also reskin bog-standard centarus into
drakkoths and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/05/drakkoth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/05/drakkoth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Drakes</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-drakes.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drakes make their debut on the first 4e Monster Manual, and this entry brings us
a few more of them. They remain a popular choice of animal for domestication but
the intro text mentions they retain a wild side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloodseeker-drake&quot;&gt;Bloodseeker Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These expert trackers were included in the Monster Vault, so we already looked
at them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/01/drakes.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;horned-drake&quot;&gt;Horned Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, horned drakes are pack predators who spend most of the day sleeping
and basking in the sun, going out to hunt at night. They have an excellent
instinct for teamwork, and a pack of them is able to take down much larger prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that, when domesticated, they make stronger alternatives to the
bog-standard guard drake, treating their handlers as part of the pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horned Drakes are Medium Natural Beasts and Level 5 Skirmishers with 63 HP. They
have low-light vision and a speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This drake’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does standard physical damage and
allows the creature to shift 2 squares on a hit. The &lt;strong&gt;Pack Movement&lt;/strong&gt; reaction
also allows them to shift 2 squares when an enemy adjacent to them is hit by a
melee attack. This makes them great a setting up flanks with their fellow drakes
or with their handlers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Goring Horns&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which does high physical
damage and knocks prone on a hit. It also has a +1 attack bonus over the basic
attack, which indicates to me that it’s meant to be a charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, these drakes are set up charge an enemy, then surround and run circles
around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scytheclaw-drake&quot;&gt;Scytheclaw Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another species of pack predator, scytheclaws inhabit forests and
grasslands. They are known for their cunning and for their devious tactics. If
you see one scytheclaw, odds are there are two or three others approaching you
from behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, they’re Jurassic Park raptors!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scytheclaws are Medium Natural Beasts and Level 10 Skirmishers with 105 HP,
which explains why the Jurassic Park protagonists had such trouble with
them. Their ground speed is an amazing 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is the titular &lt;strong&gt;Scytheclaw&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals physical damage
and knocks the target prone. If used against an already prone target, it hits
harder and inflicts 5 ongoing damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the drake hits with its basic attack, it can immediately use &lt;strong&gt;Springing
Step&lt;/strong&gt; (free action; recharge 4-6), which allows it to jump 8 squares and attack
someone else at the end of the jump. This doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks
from the target of the original attack, making it safe to move away from most
PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a prone enemy within reach tries to get up, its &lt;strong&gt;Overwhelming Attacker&lt;/strong&gt;
trait allows it to make an opportunity attack against that enemy. If this hits,
the target remains prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scytheclaws are therefore set up to bounce between PCs while knocking them
prone, and they will absolutely kick you when you’re down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fang-titan-drake&quot;&gt;Fang Titan Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you include the Raptors, you almost certainly have to include the T-Rex as
well. And sure enough, here it is. The largest species of drake, few creatures
other than dragons can pose much of a treat to them. Mostly solitary, they claim
large territories and chase away all other big predators, so ironically
creatures beneath the fang titan’s notice end up enjoying a measure of
protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most settings, such a creature would be impossible to domesticate, but in
D&amp;amp;D’s implied setting some sapients such as giants can manage it due to not
being that much smaller than them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fang Titans are Huge Natural Animals and Level 18 Elite Controllers with 348
HP. Their ground speed is 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a humongous &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that can target one or two creatures,
dealing physical damage and dazing them (save ends). They can also grab one of
the targets on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs. Reflex; recharge
4-6) that does high physical damage and knocks prone. Their &lt;strong&gt;Furious Roar&lt;/strong&gt;
works exactly like a dragon’s Frightful Presence, and when they’re bloodied they
recharge it and use it immediately as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters And Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two sample drake encounters in this entry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 3: A lizardfolk hunting party with a pair of bloodseeker drakes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: A quartet of fire giants and their pet fang titan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned during my reading of the MM/MV, I love drakes and more of them
are always welcome. For many of them, it’s also easy to “de-skin” them as
dinosaurs if you’re so inclined, but making them a distinct type of creature
also frees the authors (and you!) from having to adhere to best paleontological
practices.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/04/drakes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/04/drakes.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragon, Silver</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-silver.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons have been in the game since the days of AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, as part
of the classic metallic dragon set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons are described by the book as “the knights-errant” of
dragonkind. They like to travel the world looking for “interesting conflicts”,
and then throwing themselves at the center of those. When not doing that, they
chill in their lairs, which are usually in cold mountain-tops or in cloud
castles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons are highly susceptible to flattery, but get angry when the people
talking to them behave in an arrogant or aggressive manner. They breathe ice,
but they prefer to mix it up in melee. They can fly, but their flight is slower
than that of most other dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this kinda make me think of the “Outrageous!” incarnation of Aquaman from
the “Batman: The Brave and The Bold” cartoon. A silver dragon patterned after
him would be a true ally of justice who travels in search of wrongs to make
right, and who is also really loud and boisterous about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can still have ambiguous or evil silver dragons without changing the written
text, though. Note that it doesn’t make any mention of which side in those
interesting conflicts a silver dragon prefers to join. So a villainous one could
be a mercenary who’s interested in chances to inflict violence and who joins
whoever pays him the most (and the villains almost always have more money in
these scenarios).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, a silver dragon will want to be where the fighting is
thickest. They’re all about beating people up in melee, and the more surrounded
they are the better their offense becomes. Their cold breath weapon isn’t their
most damaging attack, but it makes enemies vulnerable to damage from other
sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons are Solo Brutes. They have darkvision, and cold resistance that
starts at 15 and increases by 5 in each subsequent age category. Their ground
speed starts at 6, increases to 8 at Adult, and to 10 at Ancient. Their flight
speed is always equal to the ground speed, making them indeed slower than other
dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their size progression is pretty standard: starts at Large, grows to Huge at
Elder and Gargantuan at Ancient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 8 with 376 HP. They have the usual Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; as basic attacks, doing Brute-level damage. &lt;strong&gt;Dragon Onslaught&lt;/strong&gt;
allows them to make a claw attack against every enemy in range in a single
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude; Recharge 5-6) does light
cold damage and makes targets vulnerable 5 to all damage (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied
Breath&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; work as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s reaction skill is &lt;strong&gt;Wing Slice&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when it’s hit by
an attack from an enemy flanking it. It makes an attack vs. AC dealing light
physical damage to both the attacker and the other enemy flanking the dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults are level 15 with 608 HP. They have all the abilities of youngsters with
some upgrades and additions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dragon Onslaught&lt;/strong&gt; adds an extra bite attack, so it’s a claw against everyone
in reach and a bite against a target of the dragon’s choice. They also gain
&lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing them to make opportunity attacks against anyone
they can reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elders-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Elders Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Level 22 with 840 HP. They’re Huge, but their melee reach remains
at 2. They have bigger numbers and all the abilities of adults, with the
following two additions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tail Slam&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. AC) does high physical damage and dazes (save
ends). It’s also an at-will action!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable&lt;/strong&gt; is a passive trait that allows the dragon to roll extra saves
against ongoing damage at the start of its turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancients are Level 29 with 1072 HP. It has all the abilities of an Elder, with
bigger numbers. It doesn’t gain new abilities, but its bite reach increases to
3, which benefits from Threatening Reach and also improves Dragon Onslaught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters play up the goodly tendencies of a silver dragon, pairing
it up with similarly “righteous” creatures. There’s a Level 8 encounter with a
young’un and 2 eladrin twilight incanters, and a level 17 one with an adult and
2 daeva zealots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other likely companions include dwarves, dragonborn, and angels. Mechanically,
you want monsters that can benefit from being shielded by a big brute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outrageous! I now totally want to include Arthur the Boisterous Heroic Silver
Dragon in my next game.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/02/dragon-silver.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/02/dragon-silver.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Iron Dragon</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-iron.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron Dragons were bit players in 3e, appearing in Dragon Magazine #356 seemingly
as part of an effort to make a dragon for each element in the periodic table. In
4e, they are promoted to the Monster Manual 2 alongside adamantine dragons to
replace the bronze &amp;amp; brass duo that was removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron dragons are kind of the black sheep of the metallic family, since unlike
most of their relatives they’re surly, anti-social, and underhanded. They lair
in isolated places and prefer terrain that contains plenty of hills, forests,
and other features that provide plenty of hiding spots for large predators such
as themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They still gather followers and henchthings with the promise of generous pay
and/or loot, but they see those as expendable dupes. They’ll send those
followers first to intercept any intruders, and will only join the fight
themselves if doing so looks like it will bring victory. If the hench-people are
severely outmatched, the dragon will get away and leave them to their fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have gathered, iron dragons are sneaky and prefer to attack from
ambush. They breathe lightning, and their metallic scales become tougher the
older they get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron dragons are Solo Lurkers, and have Darkvision like all other
dragons. They’re not actually very lurkery aside from a basic level of
sneakiness (Stealth training). Their abilities focus on damage mitigation with a
side order of control, all on top of the standard dragon loadout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young’uns start out Large, growing to Huge at Elder and Gargantuan at
Ancient. They have Resist Lightning 15, increasing by 5 per age category beyond
Young. Their speed starts out at 8 both in the ground and in the air, growing to
9/9 at Elder and 9/10 at Gargantuan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young iron dragons are Level 5 with 268 HP. They have a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does a mix
of lightning and physical damage, and a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does about half that in
physical damage. The usual &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to claw twice, allowing
them to spread some damage around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; does lightning damage, as described earlier, and also
pulls 3 squares on a hit. Maybe it magnetizes the dragon for a moment?
&lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; are here and work as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also &lt;strong&gt;Wing Block&lt;/strong&gt;, an interrupt with triggers when the dragon is hit
by a melee attack. This gives the dragon Resist 5 against that attack, and
allows it to make a melee attack dealing light physical damage against the
attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is Level 11 with 472 HP and all the traits of a youngster with bigger
numbers. No new abilities appear at this level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Elder Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Level 19 and have 740 HP. They have all of the adult’s abilities,
again with bigger numbers all around. Their Double Attack turns into a &lt;strong&gt;Triple
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing for three claw swipes with a single action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also gain &lt;strong&gt;Wing Defense&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action; recharge 5-6), which grants the
dragon a +2 bonus to all defenses for a turn. As long as it keep recharging,
they can keep using it every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancients are Level 26 with 992 HP. They have all of the elder’s abilities and
gain two new ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predator’s Response&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that triggers when the dragon is hit by a
melee or close attack. It allows the dragon to make a claw attack against the
triggering enemy and shift 2 squares. I now notice the dragon’s reach remains 2
even though it’s now Gargantuan. Either their limbs and neck are comparatively
tiny, or you should increase the reach for the Elder to 3 and the Ancient to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iron Wing Shroud&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action; recharge 6) allows them to make a close
burst 3 vs. AC attack dealing physical damage, and gain resist 15 to all damage
until the start of its next turn. While the damage resistance is active, the
dragon can’t make any attacks. I guess this represents the dragon hiding behind
its wings and catching surrounding enemies in the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shroud’s “can’t make attacks” clause is less of a disadvantage than it
seems - an ancient iron dragon can make all of its attacks for the turn and use
the Shroud ability as its last minor action. It will lose access to opportunity
attacks and Predator’s Response, but will be able to act normally when its next
turn rolls around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: A young iron dragon and 3 dwarf hammerers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: 1 adult iron dragon and 2 minotaur warriors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of them would follow the standard pattern I described in the Lore section,
with the lackeys being mercenaries lured by the promise of treasure, only to be
abandoned by their boss when the fight begins to go sideways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron dragons are the ones who least fit the classic metallic dragon stereotype,
which makes sense given their origins as an obscure magazine-only 3.x
dragon. Also I guess it’s hard to make a draconic Lurker who doesn’t sound shady
as fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I like that they’re here. That shadiness is one point in favor of them as
far as their utility in a story goes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/01/dragon-iron.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/01/dragon-iron.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragon, Gold</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-gold.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons are the original metallics and have been around since the beginning
of D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons are among the most powerful children of Io, with the oldest being
among the most dangerous creatures in existence. And yet they’re among the
dragons who most enjoy the company of mortals. I guess a lot of the “scholarly
metallic dragon” stereotype comes from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their preferred terrain are plains or rolling hills, but that’s a secondary
concern. Proximity to a sapient society, or to some great source of magic, are
much more important. Gold dragons like to rule, but it seems they don’t need to
make much of a fuss about it like the other dragons. It just happens! Any
community or society located in gold dragon territory will soon find itself
being heavily influenced or ruled outright by that dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons are usually honest and fortright in their dealings, but the more
selfish ones don’t really care about the concerns of “lesser beings”. These
individuals tend to shape the societies under their influence to suit their own
long-term plans regardless of what the actual people who live there might
want. And of course, you can still find more traditionally “Good” gold dragons
out there as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons breathe fire, and as they age they gain more affinity with radiant
energy as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, we get a stat block for each significant age category of gold
dragon. They’re all Solo Controllers, and have Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young dragons start at size Large, with 15 fire resistance, a ground speed of 8,
and a flight speed of 10 with Hover. They gain another 5 fire resistance with
each subsequent age category, and their flight speed increases to 12 at
Elder. They grow to size Huge at Elder, and Gargantuan at Ancient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young Golds are Level 9 Solo Controllers with 380 HP. Their melee reach is 2,
and their basic attacks are a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does a mix of physical and fire
damage, and a weaker &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to claw twice in a
single action, bringing claw damage almost to parity with the bite. I guess it’s
good if they want to spread damage around rather than concentrate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an adjacent creature hits the dragon, it can hit back with a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Wing
Riposte&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Fortitude), which pushes the impudent mortal 5 squares
and inflicts 5 ongoing fire damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Reflex; recharge 5-6) does fire
damage and weakens (save ends), or half damage on a miss. &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; work as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults are Level 17 with 652 HP. As usual they have all the attacks of a
youngster with bigger numbers. This includes the ongoing damage from the
Riposte, which is now 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also gain a new ability: &lt;strong&gt;Burning Tomb&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within 20
vs. Reflex; recharge 6) is a spell that does the same fire damage as the breath
weapon, immobilizes (save ends), and creates a zone that does 15 fire damage to
anyone who starts their turn inside and can be sustained with minor actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Elder Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Level 24 with a cool 888 HP. They have all the abilities of adults
with bigger numbers. Their Melee Reach increases to 3 due to their Huge size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is at the age where their radiance begins to have a game effect, giving
them a new ability: &lt;strong&gt;Beguiling Glow&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 8 vs. Will; enemies only;
recharge 5-6) is a minor-action attack that does no damage and pulls targets 5
squares on a hit, nicely setting them up for Burning Tomb or the breath weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also project an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Weakening Flames&lt;/strong&gt;, which forces enemies
caught inside to choose between taking 15 fire damage or being weakened for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancient Gold Dragons are Gargantuan Level 30 Solo Controllers with 1088 HP. This
puts them on par with the friggin’ Tarrasque both in size and danger level. The
Tarrasque has more HP, but that’s before you apply the MM2 Solo HP fixes. And
the dragon is much smarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have all the abilities of Elders with bigger numbers, including in reach,
aura size and damage, and ongoing damage from Riposte. Double Attack becomes
&lt;strong&gt;Triple Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing three claw swipes in one action. Their new
“capstone” skill is &lt;strong&gt;Ancient Radiance&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 4 vs. Fortitude; enemies
only; recharge 6) which does radiant damage and dazes for a turn. After the daze
clears, the target gains Vulnerable 10 Radiant (save ends). This is important
because the dragon’s &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; now does “fire and radiant” damage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons surround themselves with allies and subjects that match their
individual dispositions. The evil ones employ beings such as evil minotaurs,
ogres and trolls as dumb disposable muscle. The good ones have a variety of
willing allies acting as guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: a young gold dragon and 2 angels of valor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: an adult gold dragon and 3 savage minotaurs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Level-wise, these are certainly the most powerful of dragons. The Ancient is a
match for the Tarrasque and could put up a decent fight against beings such as
demon lords or other “campaign end bosses”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do have the same problem as the Tarrasque in that they lack strong
condition mitigation powers - that +5 to saves from being a solo might not be
enough to prevent stun-locking by an epic party. They also wouldn’t do so well
on their own against Demogorgon, so if you want to have a kaiju fight you might
want to use the dragon as an ally of the PCs instead of sending it in alone.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/31/dragon-gold.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/31/dragon-gold.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragon, Copper</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-copper.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are part of the classic set and have been in the game at least
since the AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition Monster Manual. Here, they are the only remaining
members of the “sorta orange-ish metal trio”, which used to feature bronze and
brass dragons as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are highly sociable creatures, but they’re also among the
greediest metallic dragons. They’re not likely to resort to outright robbery
like your typical red dragon, but they’re almost always looking for a way to
profit from their interactions with others. PCs can usually walk up to a copper
dragon and ask it for information or instruction. The dragon will be most happy
to give it to them… for a price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are quite protective of their hoards. They like to make their
lairs in rocky terrain like hilly badlands or mountains, which they can easily
patrol from the air but which restrict the mobility of land-bound intruders. If
they see the need to fight, they’ll do so by harassing their enemies with highly
mobile aerial attacks over an extended period of time. They breathe acid, and
prefer to recruit allies that can keep up with their high mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like it that the illustrations for copper dragons give then verdigris
streaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are Unaligned, Natural Magical Beasts with the Dragon Keyword. We
get stat blocks for the usual four age categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their size starts at Large when young, and increases to Huge at Elder. They
never reach Gargantuan size, which I guess means they’re a bit smaller than the
others in general. They have trained Perception, Darkvision, and Acid Resistance
that starts at 15 when Young and increases by 5 per age category. Their speed is
quite high, starting at 8 (fly 12) and reaching 10 (fly 14) at Elder and
older. They also have Overland Flight 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-copper-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Copper Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young copper dragons are Level 6 Solo Skirmishers with 296 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;
allows them to shift 2 squares both before and after the attack, and deals a mix
of physical and acid damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are a simple basic attack, but
&lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to claw twice and then shift 2 squares. Looks like
choosing between a bite and a double attack is a meaningful tactical decision!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s most frequent attack is likely to be a &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, where it
flies its speed and makes a melee basic attack at any point during the
movement. This does not provoke opportunity attacks from the target of the
attack. The bite is the clear best choice here, since it’s stronger and has
built-in shifts which I think would happen even in the midst of the Flyby
Attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Reflex; recharge 5-6) does acid damage
and slows (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; are also
here and work as described in earlier posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, &lt;strong&gt;Cutwing Step&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that triggers when someone moves to
a position that flanks the dragon. It’s an attack vs. AC that does light
physical damage and allows the dragon to shift 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-copper-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Copper Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adult Copper Dragons are Level 13 Solo Skirmishers with 528 HP. They have all
the abilities of a young specimen with correspondingly bigger numbers. All
attacks that allowed shifts other than the bite have the shift amount increased
to 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also add a new passive trait: &lt;strong&gt;Unfettered Wings&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to roll
saves against the Immobilized, Slowrd and Restrained conditions at the start of
their turns in addition to the normal end-of-turn rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-and-ancient-copper-dragons&quot;&gt;Elder and Ancient Copper Dragons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Elder grows to size Huge as previously mentioned, and is a Level 20 Solo
Skirmisher with 760 HP. It has bigger numbers than the Adult due to its higher
level, but its suite of abilities is otherwise identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ancient is a Level 27 Solo Skirmisher with an even 1000 HP. It has all of
the Elder’s abilities, and its &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt; upgrades to a &lt;strong&gt;Double Flyby
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it to attack two different targets during its strafing
run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are against all-skimmisher teams. There’s a Level 8 one
with a young copper dragon and 3 hippogriffs, and a level 14 one with an adult
and 2 dragonborn raiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are really flexible in the dramatic roles they can occupy even
when you stick to their written description. It all depends on which part of the
“sociable but greedy” stereotype you want to emphasize. I also like that most of
their illustrations in this book have their coppery hides shot through with
veins of verdigris.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/30/dragon-copper.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/30/dragon-copper.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
