<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 13:08:23 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 13:08:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Jossi the Juggler</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-jossi.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Jossi the Juggler, juggling
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jossi gets a mention in the description of the city of Tyr in the Campaign
Setting book, and a full writeup here. She’s a member of Tyr’s Eyes, which was
originally a group of beggars, street performers and thieves who banded together
for mutual support. Nowadays they also act as a kind of freelance spy agency,
keeping an eye on what goes on in the city both to improve their own chances of
survival and to sell the juiciest gossip to whoever has the money to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jossi is known as a street performer, doing a pretty impressive routine on the
markets of Tyr. She supplements her income with theft and information
broketing. I think both books’ emphasis on her might mean they intend Jossi to
be the PC’s first point of contact with Tyr’s Eyes during your typical campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jossi is an elf, though her speed is only 6 and they forgot to add her low-light
vision. After so many sorcerer-kings, it’s interesting to find a plain old Level
4 Skirmisher with 55 HP in the Personages of Athas section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She fights with the same &lt;strong&gt;Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; she uses in her juggling act, and her
&lt;strong&gt;Juggling Slash&lt;/strong&gt; technique lets her target Reflex instead of AC, deal the same
damage as a basic attack, slide the target 2 squares, and shift 2 squares. This
is &lt;em&gt;at-will&lt;/em&gt;, making her very annoying to fight. On any turn where Jossi shifts
as a move action, she also gains a bit of bonus damage courtesy of her &lt;strong&gt;Fancy
Footwork&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as she realizes the odds are against her, Jossi will try to
escape. &lt;strong&gt;Distracting Toss&lt;/strong&gt; helps with this: when someone makes a melee attack
against her, the can shift her speed as a reaction to reach any square on the
map that has any amount of cover or concealment, and then make a Stealth test
with a +5 bonus (total +16) to become hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mildly interesting, I guess. Jossi is clearly more on the “possible ally” than
on the “enemy” side of the balance, so unless the PCs go out of their way to be
assholes or to antagonize Tyr’s Eyes, they won’t be fighting her. If that ends
up happening, though, Jossi will not be alone. You should assemble a team of the
many “low-Heroic street scum” stat blocks available here and in other books to
act as the fellow Eyes members who come to her aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be interesting to have Jossi as an active ally in one or more fights,
using these stats. Juggling Slash has hilarious synergy with what PC rogues can
do, and Distracting Toss is a good way to quickly leave the fight in case her HP
starts to run low.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/05/wir-dscc-jossi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/05/wir-dscc-jossi.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Haneth Tsalaxa</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-haneth-tsalaxa.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Haneth Tsalaxa
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re following the RPG.net thread with the Campaign Guide reading, you will
already have seen a description of House Tsalaxa on &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.rpg.net/index.php?threads/wir-4e-dark-sun-campaign-guide.925494/post-25647852&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. They’re one
of the dodgier merchant houses with a presence in Tyr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;House Tsalaxa: Based in Draj and known for blackmail and spycraft, trades in
rope, grain, and previously owned cargo. Emblem: two glaring, bestial eyes.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haneth Tsalaxa is the head of their Tyr branch, and he has a very unpleasant
reputation amongst his neighbors. He apparently has tons of dirt on everyone in
the city. Most of his fortune comes from blackmail and information brokering. If
you see him darkening your doorstep, prepare for an unpleasant conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret of his success, which no one but him knows, is that he has a natural
ability to change his shape. He has no idea &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;: changelings are apparently
unheard-of in Athas, making him possibly the only one. He does exploit this
power as much as he can, disguising himself to better infiltrate private places
and overhear all sorts of interesting gossip. In addition to blackmail, he’s
also willing to do espionage and assassination for hire, though his prices are
ridiculously high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haneth is either a 4e changeling or mechanically indistinguishable from one:
he’s a Medium Natural Humanoid with the Shapechanger and Changeling tags, and a
Level 9 Elite Lurker with 154 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that deals standard physical damage and
inflicts ongoing 5 poison damage (save ends) if he has combat advantage, and can
also throw &lt;strong&gt;Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; that target Reflex and deal decent damage. His &lt;strong&gt;Slick
Swordplay&lt;/strong&gt; lets him make 2 sword attacks and shift 3 squares before, between,
or after them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s improved upon the classic “pocket sand” technique and can throw a &lt;strong&gt;Handful
of Poison&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) in a close blast 3, dealing poison damage and blinding
on a hit (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has a couple of classic changeling minor actions: &lt;strong&gt;Changeling
Disguise&lt;/strong&gt; lets him change chape to appear like any Medium humanoid. His
clothing and equipment remain the same, so it might be a bit hard to use in
combat, but it does help a lot when assembling a disguise. He can copy specific
individuals, but only if he’s seen them before. &lt;strong&gt;Haneth’s Trick&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+)
can make one enemy automatically grant combat advantage to him for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no DC to pierce the Changeling Disguise. Presumably you can use the
default rules and roll a contest of his Bluff of +12 against the Insight of any
investigators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haneth’s ability spread makes him more of a skirmisher with reduced AC and HP
than a proper lurker. The ongoing poison damage from combat advantage is better
than nothing, but be lacks something like a Sneak Attack or a really strong
ambush power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing he always has plenty of bodyguards around whenever he’s not in
disguise. He’s a major employer of unscrupulous Mixed Groups of People. Gotta
spend money to make money.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/04/wir-dscc-haneth-tsalaxa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/04/wir-dscc-haneth-tsalaxa.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Creature Catalog: Hamanu</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-hamanu.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Hamanu posing for the cover of a business magazine.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamanu is the Sorcerer-King of Urik. He looks like a big strong man, and is
known to be deeply invested in the success of his city-state. He spends the days
governing it and training with his soldiers, and the nights deep in arcane study
since he no longer has any need for sleep. For Hamanu is the Sorcerer-King who
most genuinely cares about his state and its people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are some tech billionaires in today’s real world that would read
the above paragraph and think “this guy is goals”. And they would not change
their opinions if they learned that he’s also the most totalitarian of the
Sorcerer-Kings as well. The price for his “love” is constant supervision and
total submission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being a very classically-trained wizard, Hamanu loves physical combat
and is quite good at punching people to death. He’s managing his gradual
draconic transformation so that the signs remain subtle for as long as possible,
so most of the time they consist of golden eyes and slightly long teeth. When
wounded in combat, however, be transforms into a big lion-dragon-thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Urik templars live spartan lives, but do get to enjoy the perks of their
station, chief among which is the right to push the common people around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for Hamanu and for a typical templar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;toil-templar&quot;&gt;Toil Templar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the templars we saw in previous entries, this isn’t a high-ranking
officer who spends their days next to their king’s throne. Instead, this one is
drawn from the &lt;em&gt;lowest&lt;/em&gt; ranks of Urik’s templars, the one responsible for
managing its enslaved population. It’s a Level 14 Controller with 133 HP,
meaning the PCs are likely to tussle with them long before they ever come
face-to-face with Hamanu himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toil Templars are armed with a whip and a rod, which is very thematic. The
&lt;strong&gt;whip&lt;/strong&gt; is Reach 2 and its attacks damage and push the target 2 squares on a
hit. The rod is used as an implement for their spells: &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Scourge&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 5) deals force damage and knocks prone; &lt;strong&gt;Dazing Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter,
ranged 10) deals lightning damage and dazes for a turn; and &lt;strong&gt;Sulfurous
Detonation&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter; area 2 within 10) is a fancy name for a fireball that
leaves a stinky zone lasting a turn and dealing 5 poison damage to any enemy who
ends their turn inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hamanu-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Hamanu, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The man himself is a Level 27 Solo Controller with 693 HP, Speed 6, and
Darkvision. He exhudes a &lt;strong&gt;Regal Presence&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 2) which inflicts a -2 attack
penalty on any enemy who starts their turn inside. This lasts until the start of
the enemy’s next turn, so it remains for that long even when they leave the
aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamanu’s basic melee attack is done with his &lt;strong&gt;Mighty Fists&lt;/strong&gt;, whose 6d6+14
damage is the envy of every 2e and 3e monk but is typical for a creature of his
level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has a big selection of “classic”-feeling spells. &lt;strong&gt;Thunderous Command&lt;/strong&gt;
is an at-will close blast 5 that deals thunder damage, pushes 3 squares, and
knocks prone. The next three are all big blasty encounter spells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sulfuric Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5) targets up to 5 enemies, deals fire damage, and
inflicts ongoing 10 fire+acid damage (save ends). Until the target saves,
any of the target’s allies that ends their turn next to it takes 10
acid+poison damage. Stinky!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life Drain&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5, enemies only) deals necrotic damage and
inflicts ongoing 15 necrotic damage. Every time a target takes that damage,
Hamanu gains 15 temp HP.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hamanu’s Whisper&lt;/strong&gt; (area 2 within 10, the fireball template) is an
“acidball” that deals immediate and ongoing acid damage (save ends). It leaves
a zone behind that inflicts a -4 penalty to saves on any enemy inside. This
lasts for a turn but Hamanu can sustain it with minor actions and move it
around with move actions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can use an &lt;strong&gt;Invasive Glare&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5) that deals heavy
psychic damage and stuns (save ends). This recharges whenever Hamanu bloodies an
enemy or reduces an enemy to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an adjacent enemy targets him with a melee attack, Hamanu can interpose a
&lt;strong&gt;Cerulean Shield&lt;/strong&gt; spell as an interrupt, gaining 15 temporary HP just before
the attack is rolled. If someone manages to daze or stun him, he can use
&lt;strong&gt;Mental Fortress&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt to roll an immediate save against the
effect, even if it would not normally allow one. On a success, the triggering
enemy takes 15 psychic damage and the effect never happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Lion of the Desert&lt;/strong&gt; automatically triggers with no action
required. This pushes every enemy in a close burst 2 squares, and attacks their
Fortitude to knock them prone on a hit. And then Hamanu turns into the eponymous
beast, which is going to be a nice surprise to any PCs who thought he had spent
all of his tricks already. The Lion has its own stat block, below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Lion form is reduced to 0 HP, Hamanu returns to his human form with the
same HP he had when he transformed into the Lion. When he reaches 0 HP, he uses
Lion of the Desert &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, one last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lion-of-the-desert&quot;&gt;Lion of the Desert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamanu’s beast-form is a big lion-dragon hybrid, probably created by hiding all
of his ugliest draconic mutations in one metaphysical place. It’s a Level 27
Solo Brute with only 125 HP because it’s a stage in the bigger fight against
Hamanu and not something that can appear independently. On the bright side, it
&lt;em&gt;cannot become bloodied&lt;/em&gt;, even when reduced below half HP. It has a Speed of 8,
and retains Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that deals heavy physical damage, and
&lt;strong&gt;Double Claw&lt;/strong&gt; lets him use it twice against different targets. It can also use
a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Corrosive Bite&lt;/strong&gt; that deals a little less damage but inflicts
ongoing 15 acid damage (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Lion’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that
lets him pull off an old-school claw/claw/bite attack sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy misses the Lion with a melee attack, its &lt;strong&gt;Warding Tail&lt;/strong&gt; slams them
as a reaction, damaging and pushing them 3 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a character, Hamanu seems to be what you get when you leave most of your
settings at default, the very first picture that comes into your mind when you
read the general description of what a Sorcerer-King is. The surprises only
start when it’s time to actually fight him, because “muscle wizard” is probably
not the very first thing that comes to your mind, and neither is “lion-dragon
monster”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight, Hamanu will likely want to alpha strike as soon as possible, using
Hamanu’s Whisper and Sulfuric Bolts as soon as enough targets are in range and
then wading in to catch people in his aura and let them catch his hands. He will
sustain the zone from Hamanu’s Whisper and then use Invasive Glare on the PCs
that are inside it, too. Cerulean Shield and Mental Fortress give him plenty of
extra durability for these tactics. As he approaches his bloodied value, make
him look like he’s on the ropes and out of tricks, and then spring the Lion on
the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book doesn’t specify whether the uses of Hamanu’s many encounter powers
should be tracked across his transformations. I’m guessing that the human form’s
spells &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be, but Lion’s Fury should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, meaning it will be ready for a
second use when he transforms again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/02/wir-dscc-hamanu.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/02/wir-dscc-hamanu.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dregoth</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dregoth.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Dregoth on his throne, looking very stately and about to deliver a
    villainous speech.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our narrative present, everyone in Athas believes the Dragon of Tyr is the
only dragon on the planet. Even the Dragon himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every Sorcerer-King wants to ascend in the same way their buddy Borys did, but
for some of them that feels more like a side project. They all have other things
going on, lands to rule, vices to indulge. Dregoth, on the other hand, made “I
shall become a god!” his whole personality. While they partied, he studied
defiling magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dregoth completed his draconic transformation ahead of everyone else except
Borys (who had help!). He created a whole new species in his image (the dray),
and was in the process of perfecting their design and teaching them to worship
him when Abalach-Re decided to see what he was up to and became terrified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She warned the others, and they banded together to eliminate the threat because
the community of Sorcerer-Kings works exactly like a bucket of crabs. The
ensuing battle was titanic. Dregoth was slain, and his city of Giustenal was
shattered, scattering the survivors and flooding the spirit world with the souls
of the dead (many of whom haunt the ruins).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then Dregoth got better. He returned in secret as an &lt;em&gt;undead&lt;/em&gt; dragon,
setting up in a giant cavern far beneath the surface and calling his surviving
loyalists there. Every inhabitant of this New Giustenal is required to undergo
transformation into a dray, if they weren’t one already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan remains the same: gather enough worshippers to undergo apotheosis and
become a real god. By now, centuries after his death, Dregoth has a sizable army
of dray, undead, and other creatures under his command. Real Soon Now (TM), he’s
going to invade the surface to get revenge on his former “buddies” and gather
all the worship he needs to finally complete his unlife’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dregoth’s undeath works like that of a lich. His soul is hidden in an artifact
somewhere in New Giustenal, and if he’s killed he will reform next to that
artifact within three days. The only other person who knows this is Absalom, his
high priest. Absalom used to be human, and was one of the first of Dregoth’s
subjects to be transformed into a dray after Giustenal’s fall. Dregoth then
killed him and raised him as a unique undead being, which explains why he’s
still around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absalom is a competent high priest, but his true loyalty is to the dragonborn of
New Giustenal. Should he ever have to choose, that’s whom he’ll pick. Canny
epic-tier PCs might be able to discover this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, let’s see them in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;absalom&quot;&gt;Absalom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high priest is a Medium Natural Humanoid with then Shapechanger, Undead, and
Dragonborn tags. He’s a Level 22 Elite Soldier with 414 HP, Speed 8, and
Darkvision. Like many undead, he’s immune to disease and poison, and has 15
Resistance to both fire and necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His main weapon is an ancient &lt;strong&gt;Bastard Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that’s probably made of
metal. Its blows do light damage for his level but inflict ongoing 10 damage
(save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Slicing Maneuvers&lt;/strong&gt; lets him attack twice and make his move
action between these attacks. At range he can use &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Siphon&lt;/strong&gt; (range 20,
recharge 4+) to inflict &lt;em&gt;45&lt;/em&gt; ongoing cold+necrotic damage (save ends both). Each
time an enemy takes damage from the power, Absalom or a nearby ally gain 10
temporary HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of running like a pleb, Absalom can use &lt;strong&gt;Dread Wings&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action
to teleport 8 squares and gain a flight speed equal to his speed for a
turn. This is at-will, so it can be the movement he does between Slicing
Maneuvers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His soldierly skills live in his minor and triggered actions. &lt;strong&gt;Overshadowing
Oath&lt;/strong&gt; marks a visible enemy within 20 squares for a turn, and can be used
multiple times per round. If a marked enemy ends their turn in a square that’s
not adjacent to Absalom, they take 20 damage as a reaction and grant combat
advantage for a turn. This means the high priest wants to stay away from marked
enemies, generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other minor actions include &lt;strong&gt;Swirling Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), which does a
blend of necrotic and fire damage, and slides 3 squares on a hit; and &lt;strong&gt;Change
Shape&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets him shift between his natural undead form, a disguise as a
living dragonborn, or a specific individual he’s seen. Equipment and clothes
don’t change. The DC to pierce the disguises is 41, though I imagine it would be
lower if he turns into a specific individual without changing out of his robes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absalom is a strong melee combatant, but he’s much better as a ranged
nuisance. Mark someone at the limit of his Oath’s range and then stay away from
them while attacking with Soul Siphon. When someone gets close, use Slicing
Maneuvers to stab them, and teleport to a distant squishy to stab &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dregoth-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Dregoth, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of that illustration is a bit misleading: Dregoth is a Huge Natural
Magical Beast with the Undead and Shapechanger tags. Interestingly enough he
doesn’t have the Dragon tag, so maybe he isn’t quite done with his
transformation yet. It could also be an oversight, as he has pretty much
everything he’d need to be a dragon in his stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dregoth is a Level 30 Solo Controller with 1072 HP. His ground speed is 8, his
flight speed is 10, he’s immune to disease and poison and has 20 resistance to
both fire and necrotic damage. His special senses include darkvision and
Blindsight 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He projects a &lt;strong&gt;Soul Defiler&lt;/strong&gt; aura with a radius of 3, which is a lot given
he’s Huge. Whenever an enemy starts their turn inside, they take 10 damage and
Dregoth gets to roll a save if he needs one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has a reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and inflicts ongoing 10 necrotic (save
ends), and a reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same and also slows. He can attack
at range 20 with a &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic damage and dazes (save
ends). &lt;strong&gt;Dread King’s Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; lets him do a bite/claw or claw/claw combo, though
the fact that it has both “ranged” and “melee” icons next to it seems to
indicate he could replace one of those attacks with a Gaze too. I wonder which
version (melee only or melee and ranged) is the right one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, his &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a close blast 5 that deals a blend
of cold and necrotic damage, immobilizes, and inflicts a -4 penalty to AC and
Fortitude (save ends both). &lt;strong&gt;Supreme Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) covers a Close
Burst 3, deals heavy untyped damage, and crits on a 17-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action, he can use &lt;strong&gt;Nightmare Travel&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) to become
insubstantial and phasing, and shift 8 squares. If he passes through a
creature’s space during this movement, the creature takes 15 psychic damage and
is knocked prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many encounter powers, that means he becomes a lot less dangerous once
they’re all used up, right? No, because he can use &lt;strong&gt;Spellmaster&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+)
as a minor action to recover any of them. He can also &lt;strong&gt;Change Shape&lt;/strong&gt; to appear
as a Medium dragonborn, or as a specific individual he’s seen before. The DC for
seeing through such a disguise is 47.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Dregoth is hit by an attacker within 4 squares he can use a &lt;strong&gt;Tail
Riposte&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This does some damage, inflicts 15 fire+necrotic
damage, and slides the target 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in melee with Dregoth is &lt;em&gt;extremely dangerous&lt;/em&gt;, because it puts you within
easy reach of nearly all of his attacks. Plus the more PCs are inside his aura,
the better he is at shrugging off negative conditions. Trying to snipe him from
a distance works better, but he’s very mobile and his gaze attack can make it
hard to maintain that distance. And if he has any idea at all that the PCs are
coming for him, he’ll be smart enough to pick a battlefield that forces them to
stay close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that Absalom is a unique undead being that you can’t easily slot into any
classification. Dregoth is technically one too, though the individual components
of his schtick are more familiar. He is a dragon who is a lich, but he’s not a
dracolich. Savvy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, he feels to me like better villain material than the Dragon of
Tyr. The Dragon and the other Sorcerer-Kings mostly want to maintain the status
quo, while Dregoth has an intrinsinc motivation to shake things up. At least, he
would make much better villainous speeches about how he’s going to Show Them
All than any of the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any campaign with Dregoth as an active antagonist will have the PCs meet his
troops much earlier. They’re mostly dray, both alive and undead, who tend to be
evil assholes and consider themselves superior to those who have ties to the old
Giustenal. They often have the Psionic Adept monster theme (more on Monster
Themes later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absalom is dangerous, but his level is so much lower than Dregoth’s you’re not
likely to meet both of them at once. He’s either the guy you convince to ally
with you against Dregoth, or the guy you defeat on the way to enlisting
Dregoth’s aid to fight the Dragon of Tyr.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/01/wir-dscc-dregoth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/01/wir-dscc-dregoth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Andropinis</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-andropinis.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Andropinis, who looks like a regal old wizard when he&apos;s not trying to kill
    you.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis is the Sorcerer-King who rules the city of Balic. His official title
is Dictator, and his city has a lot of Greek and Roman elements as we saw in the
other thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the book says that Balic is clean, orderly, and mostly run along
democratic lines. Its templars, called praetors here, are elected to their
posts. Andropinis himself has an excellent reputation among his population, and
encourages the region’s tradition of ancestral worship and primal magic,
resulting in a remarkably fertile kingdom by Athasian standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the reasons for all of this are quite selfish. Andropinis has
mystically tied himself to the land and its ancestral spirits, and he teaches
his disciples to do the same. He encourages his people to love the land and tend
to it using primal magic because it increases his own power and makes the area
ripe for defiling. And obviously there’s never going to be elections for
Dictator if he has anything to say about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His magical ties to the land form the basis of Andropinis’ power, and he also
seems to be pursuing a more traditional draconic ascension path as a
defiler. While he normally looks like a strong human in late middle age, when
angry his features take on a reptilian cast, with golden scales appearing here
and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we get stats for the man himself and some of the allies he is likely to
surround himself with. We’ll look at them in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;legionnaire-vestige&quot;&gt;Legionnaire Vestige&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those spirits venerated as Balic’s civic heroes. Andropinis can
summon them and order them around. It’s a Medium Shadow Animate and a Level 21
Minion Soldier with a ground speed of 6, a Flight speed of 5, Darkvision, and
immunity to immobilization. Them being Animates instead of Humanoids makes me
think the average Balic citizen is being misled about their true nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, every vestige has a &lt;strong&gt;Guarded Creature&lt;/strong&gt; chosen when they enter the
fight, usually their summoner or creator. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Shade Spears&lt;/strong&gt; that
deal a bit of damage and mark the target until the vestige is defeated or the
encounter ends, whichever comes first. Yes, they can have multiple marked
targets if they last long enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a marked enemy attacks the vestige’s guarded creature, the vestige teleports
to space adjacent to their guarded creature as an interrupt, and grants the
guarded creature +4 to all defenses against the attack. If the attack misses,
the vestige drops to 0 HP. They’re jumping in front of the attack, essentially,
so they’ll want to mark as many enemies as possible to better defend their
charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-praetor&quot;&gt;High Praetor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of the highest-ranking templars of Balic, those chosen to stand by
their Dictator’s side. It’s a Level 22 Soldier with the Leader tag and 211
HP. Their ground speed is 7, and they have a teleport speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re equipped like cliche Roman legionnaires, and their basic attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; that deals increased damage on opportunity attacks. They can use
it in a &lt;strong&gt;Face Cut&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which deals standard damage and dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They attack at range with &lt;strong&gt;eldritch javelins&lt;/strong&gt; that deal force damage and slow
(save ends). Once per encounter they can upgrade this to an &lt;strong&gt;Entrapping
Javelin&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals extra force damage and immobilizes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;High Praetor Assault&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver lets them throw an Eldritch Javelin and
then charge. This also summons a legionnaire vestige, and lets the praetor
determine its guarded creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The praetor’s soldierly skill is &lt;strong&gt;Prateor’s Mark&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets them mark an
enemy within 20 squares for a turn with a minor action. Marked enemies grant
combat advantage when not adjacent to the praeto, and take 15 psychic damage if
they make an attack that doesn’t target the praetor. So unlike most soldier
monsters, high prateors want to be far away from enemies they mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;andropinis-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Andropinis, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dictator of Balic is a Level 25 Elite Controller (Leader) with 468 HP, a
ground speed of 8, a flight speed of 5, darkvision, and blindsight 2. The fact
that he’s an Elite instead of a Solo means he will have a &lt;em&gt;sizable&lt;/em&gt; honor guard
made up of high praetors and epic-level mages when you fight him. The more
allies he has, the more dangerous he is, even beyond the usual encounter maths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis’ ties to his city and the surrounding region manifest in several
ways. One of them is the &lt;strong&gt;Dictator’s Concord&lt;/strong&gt;, an aura (10) that gives a +2
bonus to saves for all allies inside, and allows them to save against charm,
fear, and stunning effects even if they would not normally allow saves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;strong&gt;Wound Pact&lt;/strong&gt; lets him automatically deal psychic damage to anyone who
damages him while he is already bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His basic melee attack is with a &lt;strong&gt;Pact Dagger&lt;/strong&gt;, which damages and knocks prone
on a hit. The first time Andropinis takes damage before the end of his next
turn, the target takes 10 damage and is slowed (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range, he can use psychic powers to inflict &lt;strong&gt;Overwhelming Memories&lt;/strong&gt; on a
target, dealing psychic damage and sliding them 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aggression Pact&lt;/strong&gt; lets him use one of the two basic attacks above &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; let
one ally he can see make a free basic attack. &lt;strong&gt;Land Pact&lt;/strong&gt; attacks enemies in a
Close Burst 3, deals untyped damage, and slows (save ends). While any target is
slowed by the power, Andropinis has Regeneration 15. Land Pact also causes 4
Legionnaire Vestiges to appear in the area, with Andropinis as their guarded
creature. It recharges when he is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis can also use &lt;strong&gt;Transposition&lt;/strong&gt; (move) to switch places with an
ally within 10 squares, and &lt;strong&gt;Dictator’s Authority&lt;/strong&gt; (minor) to let an ally take
a whole standard action right then and there. This, fortunately, only recharges
when he’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if Andropinis ever starts his turn without any allies within 10
squares, a legionnaire vestige automatically appears within 10 squares, with him
as the guarded creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andropinis might outwardly seem to be one of the least bad sorcerer-kings, and a
good propspect for an alliance against his peers. Of course, Balic being
inspired by Greece and Rome means that it’s an enthusiastic practitioner of
slavery. Those nifty civil rights are for citizens, and then only if Andropinis
isn’t angry at them. And when the chips are down Andropinis would not hesitate
to drain his whole kingdom of life in order to protect himself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/30/wir-dscc-andropinis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/30/wir-dscc-andropinis.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Abalach-Re</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-abalach-re.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Abalach-Re, who seems beautiful from a distance, but whose body-horror
    mutations become obvious when you get closer.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re is a Sorcerer-Queen who rules the city of Raam as its Grand Vizier, a
title she chose because she claims to rule on behalf of a (fictional) deity
named Badna. Outwardly, she seems like a lazy, decadent and debauched ruler, who
lets her nobles make war on each other while her police forces oppress a
starving population and numerous rebellions grow right under her nose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, she’s a lot more aware of what goes on in her domain. It’s just that
she enjoys the cruelty on display, and likes to see those nascent rebellions
crushed. She &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; decadent and debauched, but even that is a fruit of her
explorations on the limits of her own physical form. This research has granted
her prodigious body manipulation abilities, which she teaches to her closest
agents and favored children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re keeps a close eye on her peers and was the one who alerted them when
Dregoth got a bit too uppity. She makes sure to keep her own self-modification
experiments a secret from the other sorcerer-kings, as these are her chosen path
to ascension as a god-like being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raam’s day-to-day administration is in the hands of several noble houses, each
of which controls a different district. They’re more like organized crime
syndicates than anything else, constantly at each other’s throats and united
only in their desire to exploit the people under their charge. They’re aided in
this by the city’s police force. Its officers, the Mansabdars, theoretically
answer directly to the Queen, but in practice are all in the pockets of whatever
noble house oversees their beat, and are no more than brutal thugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re lets them all do it because, as stated above, she likes the
cruelty. Instead of reining it in, she created an elite secret police force, the
High Kuotaghas, who actually enforce her will in the city and act to smack down
any noble who gets a little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; confident. Kuotaghas often receive their
queen’s “gifts” and as such have access to some body horror powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the Queen’s children are part of her court or members of the Kuotaghas,
but some have turned against her. She lets them, because all of ther children
have unknowingly been implanted with magical locator beacons. Even the
rebellious ones are useful tools to detect other rebels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three entries here and as usual I’m going to talk about them in order of
ascending level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;street-mansabdar&quot;&gt;Street Mansabdar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical member of the force that should be enforcing the city’s laws but is
instead enforcing the will of some local warlord in exchange for fat
bribes. It’s a Level 7 Soldier with 76 HP and a speed of 6. Clad in hide armor,
it’s armed with a mace and a scourge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Mace&lt;/strong&gt; is our basic attack, which damages and marks on a hit. If a marked
target ignores the mark, the mansabdar can use its &lt;strong&gt;scourge&lt;/strong&gt; against them as
an interrupt. It does the same damage as the mace, and knocks prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the mansabdar can use &lt;strong&gt;Beat Down&lt;/strong&gt; against the prone target, which deals
the same damage as a basic mace strike and slows for a turn. If the target
stands up before the end of its next turn, it also takes ongoing 5 damage (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-kuotagha&quot;&gt;High Kuotagha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trusted agent of Abalach-Re, member of the group actually responsible for
enforcing her will in the city. While still tagged as a human in its stat block,
this kuotagha was &lt;em&gt;extensively&lt;/em&gt; mutated by his boss, which I’m sure will be a
nice surprise to the PCs. It’s a level 21 Lurker with 150 HP, a ground speed of
7, and a Spider Climb speed of 6. It also has low-light vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kuotagha fights with &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which target Reflex instead of AC, meaning
they’re the “shreds armor like paper” kind. It can also extrude a &lt;strong&gt;Flesh
Garrote&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage and grabs on a hit. This grab inflicts a -4
penalty to escape attempts, and there is no limit to the number of victims the
kuotagha can grab in this way. I’ll let you imagine how that works. All grabs
can be sustained at once with a single standard action, which also does some
automatic damage to the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All other traits here depend on the kuotagha having one or more grabbed
victims. The &lt;del&gt;creature&lt;/del&gt; agent of the law can inflict criticals on its grabbed
victims on a 18-20 (which is very generous in 4e), has a +4 to all defenses
while it has a grabbed victim, and when someone attacks it while it’s grabbing
someone it can shift 1 square and slide any grabbed victims 1 square to a square
adjacent to it as in interrupt. This will only happen once per round, but it’s
gonna be &lt;em&gt;so annyoing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is a regular monster, meaning you could potentiall fight a whole team
of them at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abalach-re-sorcerer-queen&quot;&gt;Abalach-Re, Sorcerer-Queen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re is a Level 23 Solo Controller with the Leader tag and 856 HP. Like
her henchthing above, she’s technically human, but “technically” is doing even
more heavy lifting in her case. As mentioned above, she’s seeking a custom path
to immorality that involves lot of self-bioengineering, and the fruits of this
are evident in this stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abalach-Re has low-light vision, a ground speed of 8, and a flight speed of 5
with hover and an altitude limit of 2. The &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Flight&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives her
insubstantial and phasing while she moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of her three basic attacks can be either melee 1 or ranged 10: &lt;strong&gt;Telekinetic
Thrust&lt;/strong&gt; targets Fortitude, deals physical damage, slides 5 squares and
immobilizes (save ends); &lt;strong&gt;Instinct Overload&lt;/strong&gt; targets Will, deals psychic
damage and lets Abalach-Re dictate the next move or standard action the target
will take on their turn, though she cannot force a victim to use a power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third basic attack is &lt;strong&gt;Disrupting Touch&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex and can be
either Melee 3 or Ranged 10. On a hit it deals physical damage and ongoing 10
force damage (save ends). Unlike the others, which are obviously psychic powers,
I think this one might be a touch spell where she stretches her arms really far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, &lt;strong&gt;Morphing Power Splice&lt;/strong&gt; lets Abalach-Re make three attacks with one
action without provoking opportunity attacks, so she could use any combination
of the above on the same turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She can also lay down a &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Field&lt;/strong&gt;, creating a zone in a Close Burst 3
that lasts until the end of the encounter. Any enemy that takes damage within
the zone also takes ongoing 15 necrotic damage (save ends). Thankfully this is
an encounter power, but it recharges when she’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her movement power is &lt;strong&gt;Allocation&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets her teleport 10 squares and
then slide any enemy adjacent to her at the arrival point 5 squares. This also
recharges when she’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to all of the above, when Abalach-Re is hit with any attack she can
use &lt;strong&gt;Vengeance of Adaptive Flesh&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This is a Ranged 10 attack
that targets Will, and deals 15 ongoing damage of the same type she just took
(save ends). Like all of her other ranged attacks, this doesn’t provoke
opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks to me like she wants to stay mostly away from the PCs, using her powers
to slide them into the defiling field so she can further damage them with more
attacks and ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty strong opening for this section, and a brief look tells me
Abalach-Re is likely the weakest of the Sorcerer Kings. She doesn’t seem to have
any particular resistance against being stunlocked by PC powers, so even though
she’s a solo you might want to add some high kuotagha bodyguards to her fight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/27/wir-dscc-abalach-re.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/27/wir-dscc-abalach-re.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dragon of Tyr</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dragon-of-tyr.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Dragon of Tyr, making a dapper pose for the camera.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry appeared among the monsters, right where you’d find standard dragons
in another monster book. I thought this was odd, because he’s the only dragon in
Athas and also one of its more important “personages”, so why isn’t he in that
section?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, I suspect, is because to be in the Personages section the character
has to be someone who could be a potential ally to the PCs, and the Dragon of
Tyr is not someone any party of PCs should be allying with. Instead, he’s the
final boss of Dark Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless I’m talking about him here, because he &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an important personage
and knowing his story gives a lot of context for the sorcerer-kings you’ll also
find in this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone in Athas knows and fears the Dragon of Tyr. This great and terrible
monster comes in from somewhere on the other side of the Sea of Silt every once
in a while, and demands a huge tribute of treasure and slaves. Even the
sorcerer-kings fear him, and so they scramble to meet his demands. Once that’s
done, the Dragon flies home with his loot, leaving the region alone until his
next appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is common knowledge. Only the sorcerer-kings themselves know the
full story: the Dragon was once one of them. His original name was Borys the
Butcher, and like his colleagues he was one of the fifteen secret apprentices of
Rajaat the Sorcerer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, arcane magic on Athas is a truly unnatural phenomenon, a flaw that
slipped into the world when the primordials defeated the gods way back when
Athas was still green. Rajaat was the first mortal to discover and master arcane
magic. He was also the first to learn that you could pull more power from the
life around you to cast bigger spells - in other words, the first defiler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajaat taught dozens of pupils, but he only taught the secret of defiling to his
inner circle of fifteen secret apprentices. For Rajaat was a major asshole, and
when he felt his Champions were ready, he ordered them to go out on a worldwide
genocidal rampage to cleanse Athas of all the species he deemed “impure”. So
much defiling magic was flung around in those wars that Athas’ previously green
ecosystem was completely destroyed, starting the world’s transformation into the
desert it is today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In time, even the Champions became convinced that all of this was a bit too
much. Led by Borys, they turned on their master and managed to imprison him in a
pocket dimension outside of time and space. Once Rajaat was out of the picture,
the former Champions quickly conquered or built city-states in one of the last
habitable regions of Athas, setting themselves up as the Sorcerer-Kings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By then, they knew that attaining the pinnacle of power as a defiler would lead
to transformation into a dragon. Borys, who had taken it upon himself to guard
Rajaat’s prison, successfully argued that the other Sorcerer-Kings should help
him speedrun the transformation, since he’d need the power to contain their
former master forever. And so they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ritual for the final transformation required the sacrifice of every citizen
of Ebe, the island city Borys ruled. Borys renamed the resulting hellish
wasteland Ur Draxa, the City of Doom. The Dragon dwells in the ruins of Ur
Draxa’s palace to this day, leaving the city only to collect his tributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city itself is inhabited by a very large number of undead, and by the living
slaves brought in as tribute. The city’s day to day operation is in the hands of
the Dead Lords, a council of liches who serve the Dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dragon keeps their soul vessels (the book uses the p-word here) hidden deep
within his palace to ensure compliance. He is wise to do this, for the Lord
Vizier who leads the council has his own agenda. He’s secretly researching a way
to cross into the Astral Sea and escape Athas altogether, and often sends his
personal minions out on missions to recover any bit of planar lore he hears
about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for the Dragon of Tyr and for the Lord Vizier in this entry. The
two are completely different, of course, so we’ll cover all their traits in
their respective entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dragon-of-tyr&quot;&gt;The Dragon of Tyr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only dragon in Athas is a Gargantuan Natural Magical Beast with the Dragon
tag (obviously). He’s also a Level 33 Solo Controller with 1216 HP, Darkvision,
ground and flight speeds of 10, and a teleport speed of 5. He can hover,
too. His alignment is Chaotic Evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Dragon’s Actions&lt;/strong&gt; trait means old Borys doesn’t roll initiative at
all. He has three whole turns per round at initiative counts 40, 30, and 20. He
cannot delay or ready actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His basic attack is a massive Reach 4 &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and strips all
necrotic and psychic resistance on a hit (save ends). His &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; deals more or
less the same damage and immobilizes (save ends), with a Slow aftereffect (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He can also use wider swipes to perform the &lt;strong&gt;Raking Claws&lt;/strong&gt; attack, attacking
all enemies in a Close Blast 4 for slightly less damage than the single-target
version and also sliding them 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for physical attacks. Now for the spells and psychic powers, because
of course he has both!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Dragon’s Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; is a hazard all on its own, targetting all creatures
in a Close Burst 5 and dealing necrotic damage on a hit. He can use the energy
gathered with this to cast &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Death&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10), dealing heavy
necrotic damage and ongoing 20 necrotic damage to the target (save ends). After
the first failed save, the ongoing damage increases to 30!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dragon of Tyr starts the fight with Defiling Death charged, and once it’s
cast he must hit with Dragon’s Defiling to recharge the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Dragon is bloodied, he can use his &lt;strong&gt;Breath of Shredding Sand&lt;/strong&gt;,
attacking all creatures in a &lt;em&gt;Close Blast 20&lt;/em&gt; and dealing the same amount of
damage as the bite on a hit, half on a miss. Fortunately this is an encounter
power and doesn’t recharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if the PCs manage to surround Borys, he can use a &lt;strong&gt;Telekinetic Pulse&lt;/strong&gt;
(encounter), a Close Burst 5 that deals the same damage as the bite, pushes its
targets 5 squares, and knocks them prone. On a miss, it deals half damage and
pushes 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dragon can use his move action on a &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Uplift&lt;/strong&gt;, automatically
pushing every adjacent enemy 2 squares and flying his Speed + 2 (i.e, 12
squares). If an enemy ends its movement within 4 squares of the Dragon, he can
hit them with his &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Tail&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction, dealing the same damage as the
claw and knocking them prone. And when the dragon is first bloodied, Telekinetic
Pulse recharges and he can use it immediately as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physical attacks all target AC, the necrotic and tekekinetic ones all target
Fortitude, and the sand breath targets Reflex. As the most powerful arcane
caster in the whole world, you can say he knows pretty much every ritual in the
game for use outside of combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-lord-vizier&quot;&gt;The Lord Vizier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the oldest and most powerful lich among the council of Dead Lords, which
makes him their leader. Ostensibly, he un-lives to serve his master the Dragon,
but as we saw he’s also privately looking for a way off this dying rock. He is a
Medium Natural Humanoid with the Undead tag, and Level 26 Elite Artillery. He
has Speed 6, and Darkvision. He’s immune to diseases like all undead, and has
Resist 15 Necrotic and Resist 10 Poison. His alignment is Evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lord Vizier has a &lt;strong&gt;Necrotic Aura&lt;/strong&gt; (5) that deals 10 necrotic damage to
anyone who enters it or starts their turn inside. Like all liches, he’s
&lt;strong&gt;Indestructible&lt;/strong&gt; while his soul vessel remains intact: when reduced to 0 HP,
his body and possessions become dust and reform within 1d10 days near the
vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wields the &lt;strong&gt;Dead Lord’s Scepter&lt;/strong&gt;, and his basic attack is to bonk someone
with it, dealing lightning-and-necrotic damage. His basic ranged attack is the
&lt;strong&gt;Grasp of the Dead&lt;/strong&gt; spell (range 20 vs. Fortitude), which deals necrotic
damage and lets one undead creature adjacent to the target make a free melee
basic attack. If the attack hits, the creature marks the target for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He can also cast a &lt;strong&gt;Plume of Death&lt;/strong&gt; (area 2 within 10 vs. Fortitude, recharge
5+), a fireball-sized spell that deals acid-and-necrotic damage and summons a
Vizier’s Skeleton on a square within the burst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action, the Lord can draw on his secret knowledge and perform a brief
&lt;strong&gt;Planar Displacement&lt;/strong&gt;, teleporting 15 squares and leaving a brand-new Vizier’s
Skeleton in the origin square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;viziers-skeleton&quot;&gt;Vizier’s Skeleton&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sophisticated undead minions are constantly produced by the Lord Vizier’s
special attacks, and he will probably have a whole bunch of them on hand when
the fight starts in addition to some powerful non-minion undead. They’re Medium
Natural Animates (undead) and Level 26 Minion Brutes who fight with &lt;strong&gt;Deadflame
Swords&lt;/strong&gt; that do fire-and-necrotic damage, and can shoot &lt;strong&gt;Chill Shards&lt;/strong&gt;
(Ranged 10) to do cold-and-necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When met outside his city, the Dragon is always alone and on a specific
mission. He will usually completely ignore most people who have nothing to do
with his goal, believing they are beneath his notice. Of course, if those people
are stupid enough to pick a fight with him, he is only too glad to oblige,
completely confident of his victory and with good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If he is attacked &lt;em&gt;in Ur Draxa&lt;/em&gt;, I imagine the Dead Lords would join the fight
too. Better bring an army or ten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lord Vizier generally obeys the Dragon’s every order and kills whoever he
wants dead. I wonder if he can be met in friendlier terms when following his own
agenda. Epic PCs would make perfect agents for recovering that lost lore without
the Dragon noticing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/25/wir-dscc-dragon-of-tyr.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/25/wir-dscc-dragon-of-tyr.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Personages of Athas</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’d normally expect a monster book to end right after the “Zombie” entry, but
we’re only at the two-third mark on this one. We’re now entering the section on
the “Personages of Athas”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book has a really short intro for it, explaining that it takes a lot of
skill and luck to survive for long in this world, and that this is a sample of
people who managed to do exactly that and are therefore remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between the entries in this section and the ones in the monster
section are not mechanical. As far as I can understand, every entry in this
section concerns one or more specific individuals. And while I haven’t read
every entry yet, I also suspect the book doesn’t expect them to automatically be
your enemies. They could be entirely neutral to your goals, or they might even
be potential allies. While one of these things is also often true about the
monster entries, both should be true for everyone in this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is why the Dragon of Tyr was in the monster section. He is a
specific individual, but he’s also the “final boss” of Dark Sun. By default,
he’s not particularly interested in making new alliances and no PC party who
isn’t completely rotten to the core would think of allying with him for real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sorcerer-Kings, however, &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; in the Personages section, because I imagine
PCs might want to form temporary alliances with some of them against the
others. We’ll also see a bunch of much lower level randos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I stated in an earlier post, I decided to move the Dragon’s description to
this section as I consider him to be more of a Personage than a monster. So
we’ll start with him on the next post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/24/wir-dscc-personages.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/24/wir-dscc-personages.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Creature Catalog: Zombie</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-zombie.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    This is similar to a zombie, but it seems to be a repurposed
    picture of another creature.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zombies in Athas have the same origin as zombies in every other D&amp;amp;D world:
they’re created either intentionally by necromancy, or accidentally from dead
bodies left for long enough in areas exposed to strong necrotic energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Athas that means areas touched by the Gray, the Darker and Sunnier version of
the Shadowfell. Any bodies left in these places have a high chance of rising as
zombies. As the natural environment in these areas tends to be particularly
harsh as well, they can do interesting things to these bodies before they rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common of those is that by the time the body rises its flesh is long
gone due to the actions of predators and scouring winds, so you get a skeleton
instead. But some places like the ones named below can preserve the flesh of a
corpse, giving enough time to rise as a Darker and Sunnier Zombie with extra
powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The zombies described in this entry are Natural Humanoids, which I think
is an error because every other zombie is a Natural Animate. In any case, they
have the Undead tag and the usual immunity to poison and disease and resistance
to necrotic damage. They also tend to be faster than standard zombie varieties
(which still exist in Athas!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;salt-zombie&quot;&gt;Salt Zombie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are created from the big necrotic zone in the Salt Meres. They tend to lie
beneath the salt flats, erupting out of the ground when they sense living beings
walking the surface. They probably look dried out and mummified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salt Zombies are Level 1 Soldiers with 28 HP and a ground speed of 6. Their
necrotic resistance is 5 and they have Vulnerable 5 to Radiant damage. Their
basic &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; damage and grab on a hit, but their &lt;strong&gt;Salt Feast&lt;/strong&gt; attack is
usually more effective: it does the same damage and also grabs, but the target
has a -4 penalty to escape the grab and takes another 5 damage every time they
fail. And of course, the zombie can also keep attacking the grabbed target
either way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also suffer from the &lt;strong&gt;Zombie Weakness&lt;/strong&gt; that afflicts a lot of standard
zombies, and so are instantly destroyed when someone scores a critical hit on
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;black-reaver-zombies&quot;&gt;Black Reaver Zombies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There originate from the Black Sands region. Legend has it that an ancient act
of defiling magic summoned these sands into the region, and that they drained
the souls of everyone they touched. There’s a creepy deserted city at its
center, which was presumably the target of this magical WMD. Modern Athasians
tend to give it a wide berth, and anyone who dies here will probably rise as one
of these zombies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black Reavers are Level 5 Lurkers with 51 HP and a zippy ground speed
of 7. They’re blind, and so have the corresponding tag and are immune to
blinding and gaze attacks, perceiving the world through their
Blindsight 10. Their necrotic resistant is 10, and while they don’t take extra
damage from radiant damage it does prevent them from using their Shadow Burst
power for a turn, basically defanging them for that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, their basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; does a relatively weak mix of physical and
necrotic damage, so they really need the extra necrotic damage from attacking a
target that couldn’t see them at the start of their turn in order to be a threat
to equivalent-level PCs. And the most likely way for them to get that bonus is
&lt;strong&gt;Shadow Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), a move action that lets them teleport 5 squares
and create a Burst 1 zone that blinds everyone inside around their arrival
point. This zone lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using these in an encounter, you might want to add plenty of
vision-blocking terrain to the battle map, like ruined buildings or big rocks. A
zombie without Shadow Burst could still get that damage bonus if it was behind
such terrain before charging out and attacking, something its high Speed would
help with. Darkness also helps, but not as much since PCs are likely to have
many options for lighting up the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feasting-zombie&quot;&gt;Feasting Zombie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one appears in the Forest Ridge where halflings live. Halflings who catch
terminal diseases are not eaten when they die, for obvious reasons. Instead,
they’re buried, which is believed to return them to nature’s embrace. This
alternate funerary practice is less effective at preventing them from rising as
zombies when conditions are right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feasting zombies are Small, since they originate from halflings, and they’re
Level 6 Minion Brutes with Speed 5. They &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, and when they die they
perform a &lt;strong&gt;Clamping Bite Death Chomp&lt;/strong&gt;, which does the same damage as the bite
attack and also slows (save ends) because the dead zombie doesn’t let go until
you pry it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cinder-zombies&quot;&gt;Cinder Zombies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were killed and preserved by fire. This could be because they lived in
some of the volcanic islands in the Sea of Silt, of because their village was
torched by raiders. They’re charred instead of rotten, and therefore smell of
burned meat. They’re also quite strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinder Zombies are Level 12 Soldiers with 121 HP and Speed 5. They have Resist
Necrotic 15, Resist Fire 10, and Vulnerable Radiant 5. They project an aura of
&lt;strong&gt;Burning Embers&lt;/strong&gt; that deal 10 fire damage to any enemy who leaves the aura,
giving them an incentive to remain close. They pummel enemies with their &lt;strong&gt;Fists
of Cinder&lt;/strong&gt; that do a mix of physical and fire damage. If an enemy within their
aura makes an attack that doesn’t target them, the zombie uses &lt;strong&gt;Punishing
Sparks&lt;/strong&gt; on them to deal a bit of fire damage on a hit. When the creature is
first bloodied, it releases a &lt;strong&gt;Choking Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks the Fortitude of
enemies in a Close Burst 3. On a hit it deals poison damage and prevents them
from spending healing surges (save ends). On a miss it deals half damage and
prevents surge expenditure for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the four zombie types presented here are new, they’re still zombies. You
use them in the same way you use standard zombies which, again, exist on
Athas. I think I like the cinder zombies the most, as they have an interesting
Defender Aura-like setup and fire zombies make sense in non-Athas settings too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While three of the four zombies presented here are strongly associated with
their specific home regions, there’s nothing preventing an enterprising villain
from importing them to wherever their lair is, or from somehow replicating the
process of their creation in a lab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/23/wir-dscc-zombie.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/23/wir-dscc-zombie.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Wight</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-wight.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A wight posing in a threatening manner.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athasian wights are, at their root, pretty much the same as standard ones:
undead whose soulless bodies are animated by a scrap of animus (or will) the
dead person left behind. However, their description here goes on to say that
wights were driven to complete some kind of mission or achieve an important goal
when they died, and the “will” that animates them is an obsession with
fulfilling that task. It also gives them an eternal hunger for life force, and
robs them of the capacity to feel anything but hatred, grief, and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can technically exorcize a wight by fulfilling its task. This is extremely
difficult &lt;em&gt;at best&lt;/em&gt;, and it’s often impossible. Wights are not exactly willing
to give detailed interviews about the circumstances of their death. Even if the
PCs can discover those many of the creatures have been dead for so long that all
people and places involved are simply gone. This will probably force the PCs to
resort to the second most effective anti-wight strategy: extreme violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a wight to be truly destroyed, its body must be obliterated. A popular
tactic is to dismember and then burn their corpses. Not doing this means the
creature will restore itself and return eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wights presented here are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Undead keyword,
and a bunch of traditional undead traits: Darkvision, immunity to disease and
poison, 10 resistance to necrotic damage, and and 5 or 10 vulnerability to
Radiant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These wights tend to lack the default ability to eat your healing surges, but
they gain other individualized tricks in its place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wight-thrall&quot;&gt;Wight Thrall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the exception to the wight lore I described above because they’re
&lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; living their best unlife. Their obsession was to serve their beloved
master for all eternity, and that’s exactly what they’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wight thralls have about as much initiative as your typical zombie, but they’re
&lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better at following their master’s commands. If you find these, their
master is likely nearby, either as a more powerful wight or as some other
monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are Level 12 Minion Brutes with a speed of 7 and the standard
traits mentioned above (except radiant vulnerability). Their &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; damage
and have a life drain effect that’s modeled slightly differently: targets hit by
the attack cannot gain temporary HP at all and recover 5 less HP from healing
effects (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When destroyed by non-radiant damage, their &lt;strong&gt;Dark Passing&lt;/strong&gt; ability restores 5
HP to a nearby undead ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-runner-wight&quot;&gt;Dune Runner Wight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an elf who died trying to deliver an important message or warning to
their community. Every night they arise and try to complete the impossible run,
only to appear back at the starting point when the sun rises. During the day,
they terrorize nearby creatures to vent their frustration and slake their
thirst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune Runner Wights are level 12 Minion Skirmishers with 124 HP and the common
traits mentioned above. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; have no effect beyond their decent
damage, but they deal extra damage if the runner moved at least 4 squares before
attacking, and can be used as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Mobile Melee Attack&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that
lets the runner move its speed without and attack at any point during the move
without provoking an opportunity attack from the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a 1/round minor action, they can try to afflict someone with a &lt;strong&gt;Running
Curse&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Will), which forces at target to move at least 4 squares
on their turn or take a bit of psychic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oath-wight&quot;&gt;Oath Wight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These used to be inhabitants of one of Athas’ many ancient ruins, who were on
the verge of completing an important task when their entire city was leveled by
a sorcerous WMD of some kind. Maybe they were scholars nearing a research
breakthrough, maybe they were thieves about to pull that big score… or maybe
they were mothers undergoing childbirth. So there’s some nightmare fuel for
ya. They’re Level 14 Elite Controllers with 140 HP and a speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their frustration with the futility of their task is so potent it leaks out, and
can be used as a weapon. This aura of &lt;strong&gt;Inevitable Failure&lt;/strong&gt; inflicts a -2
penalty to attacks, skill checks, and defenses to any non-dominated enemies
inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wight can dominate enemies with its &lt;strong&gt;Accursed Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action, ranged
5 vs. Will), which dominates for a turn on a hit. It can also use the
&lt;strong&gt;Frustration’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, which attacks the Will of 2 nearby
targets. On a hit, it reals psychic damage and forces the target to make a free
melee basic attack (or a charge!)  against another target of the wight’s
choice. If this secondary attack &lt;em&gt;misses&lt;/em&gt;, the target is dominated (save
ends). A miss with the power deals half damage and dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Frustration’s Fury is unavailable, the wight uses its basic &lt;strong&gt;Rotting
Touch&lt;/strong&gt;, which does necrotic damage and prevents HP recovery for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were wondering why the wight has so little HP for an elite, it’s because
reaching 0 HP triggers its &lt;strong&gt;Promised Return&lt;/strong&gt; power, causing it to reappear
with full HP near its last position at the start of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The description of wights as the products of obsession that lingers beyond death
is so cool that I’m tempted to make this the default description of wights in
any game I run. The mechanics of the ones presented here are interesting and
help bring them into the paragon tier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wights might very rarely work with the living if they can convince the creature
they have similar goals, but they mostly hang out with other undead or with
predatory beasts who don’t see them as food.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/19/wir-dscc-wight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/11/19/wir-dscc-wight.html</guid>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
