<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 12:07:16 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 12:07:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Devils, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing our slog through the Devils entry, let’s look at the next batch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;infernal-armor-animus&quot;&gt;Infernal Armor Animus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-devil-animus.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve talked a lot about devils always trying to acquire souls by hook or by
crook, but what do they use them &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;? Here we have a concrete example of one
of the many products in Hell’s catalogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These monsters are made by binding the soul of a mortal within a suit of
infernal armor, which is animated by the process. The animated armor has its own
mind - the soul is just the power source. The animus understands Common and
Supernal, and at Int 8 it’s smart enough to understand the orders of its
infernal masters. When it’s destroyed in combat, it releases the trapped soul,
which will usually be consumed by a nearby devil for a quick performance boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animi are Medium Elemental Animates with the Devil and Undead keywords - the
only non-humanoid devils in the MM2. They’re also Level 3 Minion Soldiers, which
means they appear in the “bargain bin” section of the catalog and will be found
fairly early in a zero-to-hero campaign with devils as the main
antagonists. They have darkvision, Resist Fire 5, and a ground speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things project a &lt;strong&gt;Bloodlust&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that gives nonminion devils within
a +1 to damage rolls. Multiple auras are cumulative, so I imagine animi keep a
tight formation around their boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wield shields and shortswords in combat, and the &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; attack is
nothing special. When they’re destroyed, &lt;strong&gt;Essence Transference&lt;/strong&gt; triggers and
heals the nearest non-minion devil within 15 squares for 15 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 5: 8 animi, 2 spined devils, 1 tiefling heretic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at that healing value for Essence Transference! This tells me infernal
animi aren’t used as dumb muscle - that’s the job of legion devils. Instead
they’re ambulatory &lt;em&gt;snacks&lt;/em&gt; just waiting for the PCs to unwrap them and feed
them to their master. They might be able to get a hit or two in before that
happens, but that’s just a bonus. Kill them before damaging their masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;misfortune-devil&quot;&gt;Misfortune Devil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-devil-misfortune.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valued members of the acquisitions department, misfortune devils collect souls
by tempting mortals into taking ever-larger risks, which ultimately culminate in
the mortal dying and the devil owning their soul. It helps that they know a lot
of probability-warping magic to speed the process along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that there are many strategically-placed tomes out in the world that
teach a ritual to summon one of these and describe it as a “wise advisor” who
will always have the summoner’s best interest at heart. Satisfaction guaranteed
(and never mind the fine print)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misfortune devils can also choose prospective victims on their own inititive. If
the victim in question is someone who knows better than to listen to a devil,
they can use innocuous-looking underlings to make contact, or disguise
themselves with magic rituals. And finally, they can also be attached as support
spellcasters to a unit of devils out on some mission of a more military nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Medium devils are Level 15 Artillery with 115 HP. They have darkvision and
truesight 10, ground and fly speeds of 6, and interestingly enough no elemental
resistances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They attack at range with a &lt;strong&gt;Ray of Distortion&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20 vs. Reflex), which
does high physical damage - unusual for an at-will attack. The catch is that the
target of this attack can choose to take only 5 damage instead, and have the
original damage re-rolled and applied to their ally with the most HP. How
close-knit is your party, really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy manages to get close, they can fight back with a &lt;strong&gt;Lucky Maneuver&lt;/strong&gt;
(melee 1 vs. Will; basic) that does light psychic damage and allows the
misfortune devil to teleport 4 squares. If someone does manage to hit them with
a melee or ranged attack, they ran react with &lt;strong&gt;Roll the Bones&lt;/strong&gt; (interrupt;
encounter) to have the attack target another creature of their choice that’s
within 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-impressions-1&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is one of those “attached to a unit” situations: Level 13,
2 erinyes, 5 legion devils, and 2 misfortune devils. Almost identical to the one
listed for erinyes, only it’s misfortune instead of chain devils following
along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are surprisingly fun, and might cause some intra-party friction
among the PCs. With the interrupt ability it’s clear that it’s the misfortune
devil causing a friendly fire incident, but the Ray of Distortion requires a
conscious decision by the first target to work its special magic. Do you want to
betray your beefy friend in order to avoid pain? C’mon, do it! What’s the worst
thing that could happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shocktroop-devil&quot;&gt;Shocktroop Devil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-devil-shocktroop.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For when a phalanx of bearded devils just isn’t shock-troop enough for the
job. These Large winged devils perform a function a lot like that of mortal
cavalry: units of them charge into enemy lines to break up tough formations,
cause havoc, and slay as many as they can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shocktroop devils fly really fast and can’t be dismounted since they don’t
&lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; mounts, but much like mortal cavalry they can end up losing momentum if
they stay mired in the melee for too long. If that happens they’ll attempt to
retreat, and will be back to fight once they’ve recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 16 Soldiers with 155 HP. They have darkvision, a ground speed of
6, and a fly speed of 8. They lack any elemental resistances, which I think must
be an error of some sort. I’d expect them to have 15 or 20 fire resistance. They
wear plate and wield a sword and shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, they’re protected by &lt;strong&gt;Asmodeus’s Shield&lt;/strong&gt;, a passive trait that
gives them +2 to all defenses against divine powers while they’re unbloodied,
and a -2 penalty to the same while bloodied. “Divine powers” means anything
that’s not a basic weapon attack from any of the classes with the divine power
source: clerics, paladins, avengers, invokers… I’d say it also covers any
attacks by angels and the like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;sword and shield&lt;/strong&gt; combination which, as a basic
attack, can be used in a charge. It deals physical damage and triggers a
secondary attack vs. Fortitude. A hit on that one pushes the target 2 squares
and dazes them for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in the fray, they can increase their rythm and perform a &lt;strong&gt;Shocktroop
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to make three Sword and Shield attacks in a single
action, each against a different target. This encounter power recharges whenever
the shocktroop devil has full HP, which means they can use this every turn until
they’re damaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-impressions-2&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 16: 1 bone devil, 1 misfortune devil, and 3
shocktroop devils. A command squad of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit, the basic concept behind shocktroop devils seemed so bland when I
first read through this book that I never took a good look at its stat block
until now. It turns out they can be a lot of fun, and the designers managed to
really capture that “cavalry” feeling with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recharge condition on Shocktroop Attack means these monsters are more
dangerous when deployed in groups as part of an encounter. The natural instinct
of 4e players to focus-fire on a single monster at a time will work against them
here, because it might keep the shocktroops they ignore at full HP for longer,
allowing them to attack lots and lots and lots of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For extra Fun(TM), add a unit of leveled-up Infernal Armor Animi to your
shock-troop devil vanguard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;withering-devil&quot;&gt;Withering Devil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-devil-withering.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Misfortune Devils, Withering Devils are soul collectors and members of the
acquisitions department. However, they use a different strategy: their powers
bend mortal minds towards apathy and depression, eroding their ability to care
for their fellow sapients or for much of anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat this translates into spells that slow enemies down and make them less
effective, but these fiends are much more dangerous on a narrative scale. They
can cause entire societies to succumb to plague, famine, and strife by
targetting the people whose job was to prevent this and turning them into
lazy shadows of their former selves. “Just open the economy up already, fighting
this plague is too hard, I’m sure everything will work out”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though their natural appearance is horrible, they are adept at disguising
themselves as mortals, either with magic or with heavy cloaks in dark rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-3&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Medium devils are Level 14 Controllers with 138 HP. They have Darkvision,
Resist Fire 15, and a ground speed of 6. The illustration gives them wings but
they don’t fly, presumably because it’s too much of a bother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Withering devils project an &lt;strong&gt;Aura of Weariness&lt;/strong&gt; (3) that weakens all enemies
inside. Their basic melee attack is with the &lt;strong&gt;Staff of Weariness&lt;/strong&gt;, which has
no funky riders despite the awesome name. At range they shoot &lt;strong&gt;Draining Rays&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 20 vs. Reflex) that do psychic damage and immobilize for a turn. As a
minor action they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Gaze of Apathy&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Will; recharge
5-6) which does no damage but slows (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, I bet these things are really annoying to fight if positioned just behind a
line of beefy front-liners so that their weakness aura affects the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters do just that, either using bearded and legion devils as
the front-line, or attaching the devil to a mixed-party of yuan-ti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for the devils in this book, but we’re not out of the D’s yet.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/11/devils-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/11/devils-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Devils, Part 01</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book includes a whole bunch of demons, and it was inevitable that it was
also going to include a whole bunch of devils. Their base lore remains unchanged
from what it was in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2019/11/21/devils.html&quot;&gt;original introduction&lt;/a&gt; in the Monster Manual Let’s
Read, so I recommend re-reading that article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry includes a whole bunch of devils that are new to 4th edition, though
some of them also appeared in earlier editions. As I mention in the original
intro, devils tend to be more “humanoid” in appearance and use weapons to
fight. I’m also really fond of making jokes about devils being corporate
employees and/or fascists, so get ready for those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, all devils have the Immortal origin, and the Devil keyword. Nearly
all of the ones we’ll look at in this book are Humanoids, with one exception who
is an Animate. All of the devils in the first MM had really high fire
resistance, and some of the ones here do as well, but a surprising number of
them lacks resistances entirely. They all still have darkvision, but their
remaining traits vary a lot per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I’ll cover enough individual monsters to hit the size limit I’ve set
on each post, and will have as many parts as it takes to cover the entire
“Devil” entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;assassin-devil&quot;&gt;Assassin Devil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-devil-assassin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As every servant of Asmodeus knows, you can’t make it in this economy without a
little murder. Assassin devils are specialized service providers that cater to
that particular need of successful businessmen everywhere. Their magic allows
them to manipulate shadows to hide themselves and to kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That “service provider” crack isn’t just a joke: assassin devils are always
found assisting the plots of some other infernal muckety-muck, never
masterminding their own. The hidden truth is that many of them report directly
to Asmodeus, snitching on those same plots to keep the CEO abreast of what his
scheming underlings are up to. If the underlings in question discover this, they
rarely make public accusations or reprisals, and instead try to feed the
assassin misinformation to make themselves look good in the eyes of the boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assassin Devils are Medium Level 24 Lurkers with 167 HP. They have darkvision
and Resist 25 Fire, as well as an amazing ground speed of 12. They wear light
armor and fight with shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can use magic to form a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Sword&lt;/strong&gt; which does necrotic damage and
ongoing 5 physical damage (save ends). It also deals a lot of extra necrotic
damage against targets granting combat advantage to the assassin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assassin devils can wrap themselves in a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Cloak&lt;/strong&gt; that makes them
invisible until they make an attack, or they can cast those same shadows as a
&lt;strong&gt;Shadow Net&lt;/strong&gt; (Area Burst 2 Within 10 vs. Reflex) that restrains all it hits
and inflicts 10 ongoing necrotic damage. These abilities can’t be used at the
same time. The Cloak recharges when the devil uses the Net, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like the type of devil PCs from the world would rarely see because
they’re almost always employed in the internecine struggles of Hell itself. The
book notes they like to work alone, but if circumstances mandate a team they
prefer to partner up with strong soldier-types like war devils who are good at
keeping the enemy distracted and setting up flanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 22 and has 2 assassins, a high-level human
diabolist, and 2 war devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;erinyes&quot;&gt;Erinyes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-devil-erinyes.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erinyes are inspired by the Furies of Greek myth, and have been in the game
since at least 1st Edition. I think it was 3.x that tried to present them as
devilish counterparts to succubi (who were demons in that edition), but 4e leans
more into the “Fury” aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fourth Edition, Erinyes act as arbiters and enforcers of infernal law, which
of course also implies they’re pretty good in a fight because this is Hell we’re
talking about. Their skills with sword and shield are so renowned that certain
mortal warriors have been known to sell their souls in order to train under
them. This implies there’s an official erinyes school of arms with their own
signature style, and maybe its own trademark enforcement arm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In battle, Erinyes are elite infantry of the sort that gets deployed to untangle
tricky situations and inspire the rank and file around them to fight
harder. They’re more or less equivalent to fighty warlords. They can also be
found leading hunting parties whose purpose is to find those who skipped out on
infernal contracts and drag them to Hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erinyes are Medium Level 13 Soldiers with the Leader keyword and 131 HP. They’re
clad in high-quality infernal plate (which is a lot more than they wore in other
editions), and wield a shield and a bastard sword. Their speed is 5, and they
mostly fight using showy but lethal martial techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re very good at holding the line due to the &lt;strong&gt;Devastating Opportunist&lt;/strong&gt;
trait, which gives them a +3 bonus to opportunity attacks and allows them to
shift 1 square if they hit with such an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Compelling Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that does standard physical damage
and allows one ally within 5 squares to gain 8 temporary HP. They can also use
the &lt;strong&gt;Flitting Blade&lt;/strong&gt; technique to make attacks dealing light physical damage
against up to three different targets, at-will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When first bloodied, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Bloody Spiral&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 1 vs. Reflex)
as a reaction. This does a tiny bit of physical damage and knocks prone on a
hit, and if two or more enemies are knocked down it bestows 10 temporary HP to
every ally within 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-impressions-1&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 12 and has 3 erinyes, 2 chain devils and 5 legion
devil hellguards. It’s likely one of those hunting parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I like these new erinyes a lot more than I did the “naked winged woman,
but a devil” that I remember them being in 3e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gorechain-devil&quot;&gt;Gorechain Devil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-devil-gorechain.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a chain devil, but bigger. Where standard chain devils are jailers,
gorechain devils are more like bounty hunters. They’re named like this because
their chains are often encrusted in gore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their fighting style is a lot less acrobatic than that of their smaller
counterparts, but they turn out to have a lot more mental control over their
chains. So much, in fact, that they can use those chains to manipulate ensnared
victims and make them into puppets. They’re also a lot smarter than they look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Large devils are Level 12 Elite Brutes with 298 HP. They have resist 10
fire but seem to lack darkvision. Their speed is 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Chains&lt;/strong&gt; of a gorechain devil act as an aura (3) that forces
enemies to make a DC 21 Athletics or Acrobatics check if they attempt to leave
its bounds. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Gorechain Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is reach 3, and the &lt;strong&gt;Gorechain
Flail&lt;/strong&gt; ability (recharge 6) allows them to make one of these attacks against
every target in range with a single action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gorechain Takeover&lt;/strong&gt; (reach 3 vs. Fortitude; recharge 5-6) does about the same
damage as the basic strike, and also dominates (save ends). The domination also
ends if the target is more than 3 squares away from the devil when the target’s
turn starts. A lucky enough series of recharge rolls could see multiple PCs
dominated in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tactics here are clear: bring all the PCs in for a group hug, and never let
them get away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-impressions-2&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 12 and has two of these, a skeletal tomb guardian,
and a skull lord. I imagine they might also take part in those erinyes-led
debtor-hunting parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that the look of gorechain devils is a bit deceptive at first. A PC who
sees one of these things might expect a big dumb brute, but they can fight smart
and the Takeover power will come as a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not quite enough to make me like them as enemies, since I’m not really that
fond of kytons either, but that’s on me and not on this stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/11/devils-01.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/11/devils-01.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Deva</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-deva.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word “Deva” used to refer to Lawful Good angels in earlier editions, but now
it means something different. Deva as presented here are new to Fourth Edition,
and first appeared as a playable option in the Player’s Handbook 2. They occupy
the same dramatic role as aasimar did in earlier editions, but in my opinion are
much cooler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ancient times, a group of good angels decided they liked the world so much
that they would become a part of it. So they assumed mortal form, and the
resulting creatures became known as devas. They have lived countless lives since
then, and still carry some memories of the deep past with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deva begins life by materializing from thin air, fully grown and capable of
both speech and motion on the level of any other adult sapient humanoid. More,
actually, since they also appear with the skills necessary to defend themselves
and others. Few newborns can claim that! Newly-incarnated Deva have vague
memories of their past lives and retain their basic personality, but their slate
is otherwise clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s no wonder then that a very high percentage of devas end up following
adventuring careers, or otherwise dedicate themselves to fighting evil. They’re
not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; members of divine classes, but those are quite common given their
usual temperament. In the end, though, they’re folk like everyone else. It’s
quite possible for some deva to settle for a peaceful life instead, or to go
down less-righteous paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a deva dies, be it from natural or violent causes, they disappear and
immediately reincarnate at a random place in the world, clean slates once more,
ready to begin life anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deva who turns to evil will reincarnate as a rakshasa on their next
life. Rakshasa have perfect recall when they reincarnate, so this might seem
like a good deal to a deva who has grown too attached to its present
identity. However, even they revile this fate, so they would rather avoid death
altogether than to undergo the transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given their perfect recall, it’s possible every rakshasa remembers being a
deva. I’d say that should a rakshasa redeem itself and become good (or at least
non-evil) once more, it will return to being a deva in its next life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deva fashion for all genders tends towards flowing robes, sometimes with
revealing chest “windows”. Their armor tends to be designed to go over those
robes. Armored or not, their outfits usually include back or shoulder
decorations resembling wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deva are Medium Immortal Humanoids, have tier-dependent resistance to both
radiant and necrotic damage, and a +1 to all defenses against bloodied
creatures. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Memory of a Thousand Lifetimes&lt;/strong&gt;, a
free-action encounter power that allows them to add +1d6 to an attack roll,
skill test or ability test they just made. This represents memories and flashes
of insight from the deva’s previous lives, and could end up turning a failure
into a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC Devas have the same abilities, though their resistances are a bit more
granular and they also have the customary attribute and skill bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deva-knight-errant&quot;&gt;Deva Knight-Errant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This deva travels the world acting as a champion of holy causes. It’s the first
monster I find in this book who is explicitly Good in alignment, and described
as most likely to serve the role of an ally to the PCs. Still, a party entirely
composed of shady fucks might find themselves at the wrong end of the
knight-errant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knight is a Level 11 Soldier with 111 HP and all standard Deva traits. Their
resistances are set to 10. Being paladin-types, they wear full plate and wield a
sword, a shield, and a holy symbol. Their speed is 5 due to the heavy armor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knights fight with a mixture swordplay and divine magic. The &lt;strong&gt;Inner Radiance&lt;/strong&gt;
trait allows them to switch the damage type of any of their attacks to Radiant,
and to accept a -2 attack penalty to make the attack deal an extra 4 radiant
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knight’s &lt;strong&gt;broadsword&lt;/strong&gt; marks for a turn on a hit, and they can perform a
&lt;strong&gt;Rejuvenating Strike&lt;/strong&gt; with it that heals the knight for half the damage
dealt. It recharges whenever the knight hits with a normal sword attack. This
will become substantially more powerful once you fix their damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a couple of pure-magic abilities as well: &lt;strong&gt;Martyr’s Cry&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst
3 vs. Will; recharge 6) deals psychic damage and marks all targets hit (save
ends). &lt;strong&gt;Health Transfer&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action; encounter) transfers up to 25 damage
&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a condition from an ally within 10 squares to the knight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knight-Errants are well set-up to be allied NPCs, with those support and marking
abilities. The self-healing strike is important to give them some longer-term
staying power when riding with the party, as most healing abilities that depend
on healing surges are less effective on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deva-zealot&quot;&gt;Deva Zealot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The zealot opposes evil, well, zealously. They’re a lot less nice in their
judgment and methods than the knight, and thus Unaligned. They wear leather or
other light armor, and wield falchions. Their resistances are set to 10. Their
speed is 6. If they were PCs, they’d be Avengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;falchion&lt;/strong&gt; his a high-crit weapon and deals some bonus radiant
damage. It’s their main attack, and all their other abilities support
it. &lt;strong&gt;Skirmish&lt;/strong&gt; works as usual, adding more bonus damage when they move at
least 4 squares in that turn. &lt;strong&gt;Dazzling Soul&lt;/strong&gt; (minor; recharge 4-6) makes the
zealot shine so brightly it gains concealment and emits bright light in a
6-square radius and dim light out to 12 squares. &lt;strong&gt;Path of Virtue&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter)
allows them to shift their speed and make one falchion attack against each enemy
in reach during the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, &lt;strong&gt;Radiant Retribution&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;at-will free action&lt;/em&gt; that
triggers when the zealot takes damage from an attack, and deals half that amount
as radiant damage to the attacker. I think this means it will trigger against
every attack made on the deva - if it was a reaction or interrupt, it would only
happen once per round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deva-fallen-star&quot;&gt;Deva Fallen Star&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deva who went bad and is all set to become a rakshasa on their next
incarnation, though ideally they don’t want to die at all. They’re Level 26
Artillery with 188 HP. Their resistances are set to 15. Using a rod as an
implement, if they were PCs they’d likely be a warlock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fallen star will likely open the fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Soul Scourge&lt;/strong&gt; spell (area
burst 2 within 15 vs. Will), a fireball-sized blast that deals immediate radiant
damage and ongoing 15 necrotic damage (save ends). This recharges when it’s
first bloodied. Until then it will use a &lt;strong&gt;Forgetting Ray&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20
vs. Reflex) which does psychic damage and restricts the target to using only
at-will attacks (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hit by an attack, the fallen star can use &lt;strong&gt;Fateful Transposition&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged
10 vs. Will) as an interrupt, targeting an enemy. A hit allows it to switch
places with that enemy, making it take half the triggering attack’s damage. The
deva still takes the other half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fallen start’s basic melee attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Rebuking Rod&lt;/strong&gt;, which does
psychic and radiant damage and triggers a secondary attack vs. Fortitude: if
that one hits, the fallen star gains total concealment against the target (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fallen star’s research into evil magic has allowed it to trade the usual
Memory of a Thousand Lifetimes power for &lt;strong&gt;Fate Manipulation&lt;/strong&gt;. This can add 1d8
to their rolls &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; remove 1d8 from an enemy’s roll, and it recharges once the
fallen star is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, we have the ability that confirms this deva “fell” because it
wanted out of the circle of reincarnation: &lt;strong&gt;Vile Rebirth&lt;/strong&gt;. When the deva is
reduced to 0 HP by non-necrotic damage, it doesn’t die. Instead, it remains at 0
HP until its next turn, when regains 25 HP and acquires the undead keyword. In
other words, it becomes something close to a newly-minted lich! This power
recharges, but the “non-necrotic” bit becomes “non-radiant”. In other words, you
have to either kill it with necrotic damage the first time around, or with
radiant damage after it becomes undead. If you don’t, it keeps coming back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d say that if Vile Rebirth triggers and the falen star escapes, you can use it
as a lich in subsequent encounters. And if it dies “for real”, it’s rakshasa
time, though in that case it would take longer to return to the campaign if it
makes an appearance at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book admits most PC parties are unlikely to find themselves facing a
knight-errant or even a zealot, so the sample encounter is Level 27 and features
a pair of fallen stars along with 2 efreet karadjins and 2 efreet
pyresingers. So it looks like the deva have joined the ranks of nobility at the
City of Brass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like Deva! Aasimar from previous editions just had a celestial
somewhere in the family tree, Deva have a cool backstory on par with the one
that was given to tieflings. One thing I find particularly cool about the stat
blocks from this entry is that they could represent the trajectory (and tragic
fall) of a single individual over three lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/27/deva.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/27/deva.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Vault 2: Demons, Part 04</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-yochlol.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the last post covering the “Demons” entry in the Monster Manual 2, and
it features a lone demon: the Yochlol, who has been in the game since at least
AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yochlols are the handmaidens of Lolth, being some of her most favored
servants. This a fact which those not initiated in Her mysteries will find
baffling because yochlols don’t resemble spiders in any way. In their natural
form these demons look like pillars of snot with a baleful red eye embedded near
the top. They can also take the shape of beautiful drow women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yochlols might be assigned by their mistress to assist mortal priests that have
also earned her favor, but they mainly works as spies. They’re so good at
passing for mortal drow that they can remain undetected for years at a time and
attain positions of great power in their society. I’ll write more about the
implications of this in the Impressions section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of yochlols is one more point in favor of my pet theory that Lolth
is actually a demon lord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a single stat block here, named Yochlol Tempter, which I guess is
representative of most of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yochlols are Medium Elemental Humanoids with the Demon and Shapechanger
keywords. They’re Level 17 Controllers with 158 HP. Despite being demons, they
lack Variable Resistance and have Resist 10 Poison instead. They have
darkvision, a ground speed of 6, and a climb speed of 8 with Spider Climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yochlols have two sets of attack powers, one for when they’re in demon form, the
other for when they’re in drow form. They can &lt;strong&gt;switch forms&lt;/strong&gt; with a minor
action, but I guess an infiltrated yochlol will stick to drow form to avoid
blowing its cover. Once that happens, though, it will change shape as often as
it needs to assemble the best combos it can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In demon form, the Tempter fights with its Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Tentacles&lt;/strong&gt;. A basic
tentacle attack is quite weak, but the demon can make four of them with its
&lt;strong&gt;Amorphous Flurry&lt;/strong&gt;. If two or more flurry attacks hit the same target, that
target takes a -4 penalty to Will (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range, it can project a &lt;strong&gt;Maddening Web&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 2 within 10
vs. Reflex). It does no immediate damage, but immobilizes and deals 5 ongoing
damage (save ends). It recharges on a 4-6, but only while the yochlol is
bloodied. So it’s less of a web and more of flung ball of runny snot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In drow form, this demon’s attacks are all what you would expect out of a
priestess of Lolth: a &lt;strong&gt;spider touch&lt;/strong&gt; in melee that also deals ongoing 10
poison damage (save ends); a &lt;strong&gt;venom bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex) that deals
physical and ongoing 5 poison damage (save ends); and a minor-action &lt;strong&gt;Seductive
Glare&lt;/strong&gt; which despite the horrible name is a slow-acting mind control spell
(ranged 10 vs. Will). On a hit the target is dazed (save ends); the first failed
save worsens that to Stunned, and the second to Dominated. In all cases a
successful save ends the effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 16 and as you would expect involves a lot of drow:
2 arachnomancers, 1 blademaster and a priest, accompanied by 2 yochlol
tempters. Your call as to whether the drow know about the demons or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, I find yochlols quite interesting with their two forms that have
complimentary powers. A lone yochlol can set up some interesting combos by
itself, by using Amorphous Flurry to weaken someone’s Will and then the mind
control attack in the next round. If you have two of them, they can do that a
lot faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember seeing complains in Let’s Reads for older editions about how these
demons don’t seem to have much to do with Lolth thematically speaking. After
all, spiders are officially Her Thing and yochlols are not spiders. And despite
them being described as the ultimate shape-shifting spies, they can only turn
into drow, so they can’t be used to spy on the drow’s enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bits of lore here help make sense of all that. Lolth is also the goddess of
lies, and treachery is among her commandments. How much do you think such a
deity would trust their followers? No, Yochlols aren’t made to spy on the
enemies of the drow. They’re made to spy &lt;em&gt;on the drow&lt;/em&gt;. Their un-spider-like
nature gives Lolth some plausible deniability. It is, perhaps, a hint that these
demons are the product of another side of Lolth’s personality, one rarely known
to her worshippers. Because despite all the dedication the drow people lavishes
on her, Lolth doesn’t trust them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s kinda tragic, for both the Drow and for Lolth.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-04.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-04.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Demons, Part 3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continue looking at the many monsters in the Demons entry of the Monster
Manual 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nycademon&quot;&gt;Nycademon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-nycademon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure these winged, four-armed creatures used to be classified as
Yugoloths in previous editions, where their name was written as
“Nycadaemon”. Yugoloths, or daemons, were the Neutral Evil Fiends, created
because the writers of AD&amp;amp;D decided every alignment needed its own
representative outsider. Fourth Edition uses a different cosmology and a
different alignment system, so its authors elected to turn daemons into demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nycademons spend their days flying over the open expanses of the Abyss in search
of creatures to snatch and drop from a great height, which they think is hella
funny. This has given them the nickname of “sky demons”. They place great value
in physical strength, and so have a tendency to underestimate beings whose power
is less obvious (“Do you even lift, bro?”). They’re also hesitant to attack
someone who seems big and strong, for the same reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many former daemons, nycademons have a mercenary temperament and will work
for anyone who pays them. These contracts tend to be short-lived though, as
their superiority complex tends to infuriate most allies. All that flexing can
get annoying really fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nycademons are Large Elemental Humanoids (demons) and Level 22 Skirmishers with
210 HP. They have Variable Resistance 20 (2/encounter), as well as ground and
fly speeds of 6. The one in this book fights with a pair of greataxes it wields
one-handed, leaving it with two free hands to snatch victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Wicked Axe&lt;/strong&gt; attacks are Reach 2 and High-Crit, and also cause ongoing 5
damage (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Wicked Edges&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make two such attacks in one
action, putting its damage near where it should be even without the math fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of axing someone, the nycademon can &lt;strong&gt;Snatch&lt;/strong&gt; them (Reach 2
vs. Fortitude). It can fly 6 squares before or after making the attack, which
does no damage but grabs the target. The &lt;strong&gt;Strong Flyer&lt;/strong&gt; trait exempts it from
the usual obstacles to moving a grabbed target, so it can travel its full speed
with the grabbed victim without needing to make additional tests to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these traits lend themselves well to the “snatch and drop” tactics
described in the lore. Grab someone, fly up for a few rounds while attacking
them with the axes, drop them for a bunch of d10s of fall damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter has three nycademons, a goristro and a rot harbinger. It’s
Level 21, and likely affiliated with Orcus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While mechanically simple, I kinda like the whole “snatch and drop” thing. It’s
also fun to imagine these creatures as condescending gym bros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pod-demons&quot;&gt;Pod Demons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-pod.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly disgusting examples of demonkind, these slimy creatures can spawn
miniatures of themselves from their blistered bodies, using them to corner and
terrorize their victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spawn have no mind of their own, being extensions of the demon’s main
body. In fact, the pod demon can transfer its conscience to a podling, causing
it to grow to full size while the original body shrinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures have some connection to the mysterious Chained God (AKA
Tharizdun, but no one in-setting rememebers that name). Some of them wrap
themselves in chains to show their allegiance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pod Demons are Large Elemental Humanoids (demons), and Level 15 Elite Artillery
with 176 HP. They have darkvision and Variable Resistance 15
(2/encounter). Their ground speed is 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight by using their half-formed spawn as ammo. They can either throw a
spawn so it explodes on impact using &lt;strong&gt;Fling Podspawn&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within 10
vs. Reflex), or squeeze it to spray nearby enemies with &lt;strong&gt;Spew Podspawn&lt;/strong&gt; (close
blast 3 vs. Reflex). In either case, targets take acid damage on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fully formed podspawn constantly pop free of the parent body: one appears within
2 squares of the original at the start of its turn as long as there are fewer
than 4 podspawn in play. The parent can also force them out with &lt;strong&gt;Generate
Podspawn&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs. Reflex), which does poison damage and fills
unoccupied squares with enough podspawn to reach the limit of 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action the pod demon can &lt;strong&gt;Transfer Essence&lt;/strong&gt;, effectively swapping
positions with a podspawn within 10 squares. As a minor action it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Detonate Minion&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10), causing a podspawn in range to explode and deal
a bit of automatic poison damage to adjacent creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If forced into melee, they attack with a weak &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that also does ongoing
poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m guessing that if you have multiple pod demons in play, each of them will be
able to have its own set of four minions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The podspawn themselves also have a little stat block. They’re Level 15 Minion
Skirmishers whose resistances always match the parent’s, and who attack with a
&lt;strong&gt;corroding slime&lt;/strong&gt; that’s slightly stronger than the parent’s claw. Their
&lt;strong&gt;dangerous proximity&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them combat advantage against any adjacent
enemy, no flanking required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 16: 1 immolith, 1 pod demon, 4 podspawn and 2 red
slaads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;runespiral-demon&quot;&gt;Runespiral Demon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These turtle-beetle things have complex patterns of arcane runes etched into
their shells, which channel arcane energies from deeper within the Abyss. The
specimens depicted here turn this energy into lightning, but there are others
with variant runic patterns that use other elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Runespiral demons are sapient, but they don’t have hands and are nowhere near
smart enough to be good at arcane magic. The runes are either natural or etched
by some unseen patron. In combat, they rely on the magic of these runes to
attack at range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-runespiral.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We actually get two varieties here: common Runespiral Demons are Small Elemental
Magical Beasts, and Level 5 Artillery with 51 HP. Arctide Runespiral Demons are
Large, and Level 12 Artillery with 97 HP. They have Variable Resistances of 10
and 15 respectively, and a ground speed of 7. Their attacks are almost
identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can attack distant opponents with either a &lt;strong&gt;Focused Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Reflex) that does standard lightning damage, or a &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (Area
Burst 2 Within 10 vs. Reflex), which does bit less lightning damage as a
baseline, but has that damage increase by 1 for each creature caught in the
blast. That’s &lt;em&gt;creature&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;enemy&lt;/em&gt;: allies caught in the blast will increase
its damage, but will also be damaged by it since it’s not a selective burst. The
Arctide Demon’s burst is also &lt;strong&gt;Charged&lt;/strong&gt;: it does all of the above and
additionally gives allies damaged by it a +1 bonus to their next recharge rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy moves adjacent to one of these demons they release an &lt;strong&gt;Arcane
Arc&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Reflex) as an interrupt, dealing lightning damage. In melee
they’ll &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; for very little physical damage, and when bloodied they release
a &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Shock&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 1 vs. Reflex) that deals lightning damage and
dazes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter has 2 basic runespiral remons, 2 evistros, and the human
hexer who summoned them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions-1&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More demon artillery support. They have some mechanical weaknesses: all of their
good attacks deal the same type of damage and target the same defense. Some GMs
might want to pull a Gygax and say that runespiral demons with other elements
look identical save for their different runes and that it takes an Arcana test
to distinguish them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rupture-demon&quot;&gt;Rupture Demon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These demonic amoeboids are the least spawn of Juiblex, and they act as abyssal
scavengers, following more powerful demons around and eating the remains of
their kills. When they die their own remains can infest those more powerful
demons and make them even stronger. Does that serve some plan of Juiblex? No one
knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-3&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rupture Demons are Level 5 Minion Soldiers, with low-light vision, a ground
speed of 6 and a climb speed of 3 with Spider Climb. They lack any elemental
resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can attack directly with a &lt;strong&gt;Slimy Extrusion&lt;/strong&gt; for minor physical damage,
or they can use an &lt;strong&gt;Enveloping Embrace&lt;/strong&gt;. This hits automatically, does no
damage and restrains the target (save ends). It also kills the demon, presumably
because it has to rupture to envelop someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a rupture demon dies, either due to an attack or from using the Embrace, it
explodes into a mass of ichor and pseudopods that latches onto another demon
within 5 squares. This infestation heals 5 HP and gives it a +2 damage
bonus. Multiple infestations stack, up to a maximum of +10 damage. For this to
work the infested demon must be level 10 or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter has 1 Black Pudding, 1 Evistro, and 6 rupture demons. An
interesting contrast, because the pudding is going to split into smaller enemies
and the rupture demons will join with the Evistro as the fight goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions-2&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like their concept! The level limitation is a bit strange. Presumably you
could have higher level minions that could affect more powerful demons. In that
case you should make sure they’re still a few levels behind the “real”
opposition, since you want them to die fast and provide that damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-3&quot;&gt;End of Part 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one more to go, with the last remaining demon.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-03.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-03.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Demons, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing with the “Demon” entry of the Monster Manual 2, let’s look at a few
more abyssal greeblies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gnaw-demon&quot;&gt;Gnaw Demon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-gnaw.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These round boys live to eat. Their hunger is insatiable and they’re always
gnawing on and eating everything around them. That sentence is quite literal
too: they can eat &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;, so they eat &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;, all the time. Being
demons, of course, they prefer living flesh above all else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, gnaw demons are also quite cowardly and will run away if they see
they’ve bitten off more than they can chew. Tracking them down isn’t too
difficult, though, since they’ll soon become distracted by some other
weak-looking target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gnaw demons can teleport, but it’s apparently a reflex not under their conscious
control. Though they’ll likely avoid the thick of the fight at first, the smell
of blood drives them into a frenzy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gnaw Demons are Small Elemental Humanoids, and Level 5 Skirmishers with 66
HP. They have Darkvision and are slow and blobby with a ground speed of 3 and a
flight speed of 5 (clumsy). They have Variable Resistance 10 (1/encounter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat they’re all about biting, since they’re pretty much trying to eat
you. Their &lt;strong&gt;Ankle Biter&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) inflicts a -2 penalty to the speed of any
enemy caught inside. Their basic attack is the obvious &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals
extra damage to bloodied enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That reflexive teleport is modeled with two different abilities: &lt;strong&gt;Hungry
Teleport&lt;/strong&gt; (move action) allows the demon to teleport 10 squares into a square
adjacent to a bloodied enemy. &lt;strong&gt;Pain-Induced Teleport&lt;/strong&gt; (free action when first
bloodied) is an unrestricted 10-square teleport, which it will likely use to
flee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda like these critters. They’re more flavorful than evistros (which
smoulder with generic rage), though they also pair really well with them or
other front-liners that can get the enemy bloodied so they can teleport in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 6 and has three of these spherical terrors
accompanying a pair of gnolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kazrith&quot;&gt;Kazrith&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-kazrith.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazriths are barracuda-like aquatic demons that prowl the watery bodies of the
abyss and might be summoned to do so elsewhere. Despite their preference for
water they’re also perfectly capable of operating on land, so you don’t have to
build an underwater dungeon in order to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though sapient, kazriths prefer to act as ambush predators, burying themselves
in the ground and jumping out to attack anything that looks like it would be fun
to kill. Their pores secrete strong acid, which helps both with the burrowing
and with the killing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They burrow as fast as they can run and leave stable tunnels behind, which means
all bodies of water in kazrith territory are linked by networks of flooded
tunnels. So if you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want to make an underwater dungeon, you have the perfect
excuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazriths are Medium Elemental Magical Beasts with the Demon and Water
keywords. Note that they &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have Aquatic, so they don’t gain that +2 attack
bonus when fighting underwater. They’re Level 20 Lurkers with 146 HP, an
immunity to acid, and Variable Resistance 20 (2/encounter). They have a ground
speed of 6, a burrow speed of 6 with Tunneling, and a swim speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that also deals 5 ongoing acid damage (save
ends). They can also burrow back into the ground while spraying acid behind
them: this &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Retreat&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5-6) is a close burst 2 vs. Refles,
deals light physical damage, and 10 ongoing acid damage (save ends). It also
allow the demon to burrow its speed as an effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bloodied, its &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Seepage&lt;/strong&gt; increases, causing it to gain +4 burrow
speed and deal 10 acid damage to enemies that start their turn adjacent to the
kazrith. Its &lt;strong&gt;Slippery&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows it to make extra saves against the
immobilized, slowed and restrained conditions at the start of its turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fighting a kazrith is like playing a corrosive game of whack-a-mole, as it will
keep burrowing back and popping up to bite you, and it’s hard to pin down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 18 and features an Evil Party of aboleths, their
minion servitors, and a pair of kazriths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazriths sound like something that should logically exist, but by themselves
they don’t really stoke my imagination. They do make decent additions to
adventures featuring varied demons as opposition, and they work well with
Aboleths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;needle-demon&quot;&gt;Needle Demon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-needle.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These prickly assholes love seeing former friends and allies turn on each other
with murderous intent, particularly when they were the ones who instigated
it. They’re much smarter than they look and often end up as advisors to more
powerful villains, sometimes even as the power behind the throne. However, their
lust for infighting often gets the better of them, so these deceptions never
last long and cause terrible damage when they collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needle demons are Medium Elemental Humanoids (demons), and Level 12 Controllers
with 123 HP. They have darkvision and Variable Resistance 15 (2/encounter). They
run with speed 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with their pincers and spiked tail. The &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack is pretty
standard, and &lt;strong&gt;Claws of Betrayal&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to attack twice with them. If
both attacks hit the same target, that target takes 10 ongoing damage (save
ends). The &lt;strong&gt;Tail&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction attack that does light physical damage and is
triggered by an enemy moving to a square adjacent to the demon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their most thematic power is &lt;strong&gt;Rage of the Betrayed&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Will;
enemies only; recharge 6), which does no damage but dominates (save ends). Yes,
it’s a mass dominate. It works by convincing the affected target that their
allies have betrayed them, so I guess the demon is going to use it to make the
PCs focus on fighting each other instead of itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters have them working alongside gnolls and drow, but repeat
that it never takes long for them to turn on their own allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions-1&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple, but quite effective due to that mass dominate. I’m guessing you could
use a recurring needle demon NPC as a source of lots of drama, having it appear
somewhere in every villainous group the PCs oppose only to always run away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;neldrazu&quot;&gt;Neldrazu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-neldrazu.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These demons are into kidnapping, for which they use their four hooked
claws. During a battle they like to hide around the edges and jump out to snatch
an enemy and drag it either to an isolated spot or into the midst of the
neldrazu’s allies. They’re often summoned by slavers who don’t mind if the goods
are slightly damaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-3&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neldrazu are Large Elemental Humanoids (demons) and Level 8 Lurkers with 71
HP. They have darkvision and Variable Resistance 10 (1/encounter). They have a
ground speed of 8 and a climb speed of 6 with Spider Climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a standard &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt;, but when only one enemy is within 5
squares of the neldrazu they can really stretch and use &lt;strong&gt;Flaying Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which
do double damage plus ongoing 5 damage (save ends). This means they’ll lurk
until they can catch a PC alone, and then move in with this attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After using Flaying Claws, a neldrazu will likely follow it up with &lt;strong&gt;Abduct&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5-6), a move action attack that targets Reflex and can only be used
against enemies. It does no damage, but teleports the target 10 squares to a
place of the demon’s choice on a hit. The demon teleports 10 squares right after
this, either adjacent to the target on a hit, or to anywhere it chooses on a
miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the best way to use this is to drop an enemy right in the middle of the
neldrazu’s allies. If a lurker isolates itself with a PC, things tend to go
poorly for the lurker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions-2&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 3 and later on the Monster Vault would include the Babau, a
level 13 Skirmisher demon that’s quite similar, and which we covered
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/07/babau.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. At the time I remember poo-pooing the babau’s abduction tactics
because I assumed it would always take the victim to an isolated place, but now
I see it can also take them to its allies instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the babau, the neldrazu is a better team player, since it can abduct
more often in a fight. Its special attack is quite situational, but it can be
used &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the abduction, which means it doesn’t have to choose between
isolating a victim and bringing it to its allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-2&quot;&gt;End of Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s at least one more post’s worth of demons to cover.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Demons, part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go [here][1] to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You thought getting out of the Abyss was going to be easy? Right after finishing
all nine pages of Demogorgon’s entry, it’s time to proceed to eleven more pages
of assorted demons. Each individual demon entry comes with a bit of lore and a
sample encounter group, so it’s better for me to do “Lore” and “Numbers”
subsections for each of them instead of the other way around. Since each
individual entry seems fairly simple, I’ll keep adding them to this post until I
hit my “usual” post size, and split it into subsequent parts as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, though, we get a small paragraph of extra Abyss lore. It says demons are
among the oldest creatures in the universe, which places the creation of the
Abyss waaaaay back at the literal dawn of time. At first there were only a few
of them: the book implies these were the original demon lords (or “demon
princes”, as written), who initially served the Chained God and had orders to
bring the universe under his heel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess they were either the primordials caught in the “blast” that created the
Abyss, or the first ones to enter the place. Plus Dagon, who was already
there. Anyway, as the corruption of the Abyss spread, it infected other
elemental creatures and turned them into the types of “lesser” demon we know
today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abyssal-eviscerator&quot;&gt;Abyssal Eviscerator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures made it to the Monster Vault, and I covered them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/05/abyssal-eviscerator.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. My
impression of them hasn’t changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abyssal-rotfiend&quot;&gt;Abyssal Rotfiend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-abyssal-rotfiend.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An abyssal rotfiend is what you get when you take the undead spirit of an evil
creature and stuff it inside a meat puppet made of stitched-together bits of
demons and devils. The spirit is usually a demon soul, but any evil creature
will do in a pinch. With that description you’d think they’re mindless, but
they’re actually quite intelligent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As undead demons, rotfiends are an Orcus specialty. Many inhabit the halls of
his fortress of Everlost, put there as a defense against teleporting
enemies. Despite their hulking appearance they rely more on damaging mind magic
than on brute force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rotfiends are Large Elemental Humanoids (demons) and Level 26 Controllers with
245 HP. They have Truesight, ground and fly speeds of 6, and a whole bunch of
resistances! They’re immune to fear, have Resist Fire 20, Resist Necrotic 10,
and Variable Resistance 20 (3/encounter). They are surrounded by &lt;strong&gt;Abyssal
Fields&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 5) that prevent anyone inside from teleporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re attacks are all related to madness and body horror. The basic attack is
&lt;strong&gt;Skullsplitter&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. Reflex), which does psychic damage and is
stronger against &lt;em&gt;unbloodied&lt;/em&gt; targets. &lt;strong&gt;Conjure Abscess&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Fortitude) also does psychic damage, and does a bit of delayed damage if the
target moves more than 2 squares in its next turn. If the rotfiend is bloodied,
that delayed damage happens when the target moves 1 or more squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Floating Despair&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 2 within 10; encounter) creates a zone
of miasma that last for a turn but can be sustained and moved with a minor
action. Anyone caught inside takes 10 psychic damage and grants combat advantage
to the rotfiend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 24 and has a rotfiend, a glabrezu, and a
marilith. Due to the math bug its damage is low enough that I think a lot of PCs
will just take the extra hit from the abscess instead of limiting their
movement. If you fix that, though, the rotfiend becomes a better controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ghosts clothed in dead demon flesh” is a nice, creepy concept, though I think
they lack a bit of mechanical oomph. After increasing their damage, I’d probably
tag them with the Leader keyword and make the Floating Despair zone make victims
grant combat advantage to any enemy, not just that single rotfiend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bebilith&quot;&gt;Bebilith&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-bebilith.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, let’s face the truth here: Lolth is a demon lord. She’s Chaotic Evil,
lives in the Abyss, and has lineages of demons aspected to her. It’s likely the
only reason she’s classified as a “Goddess” is that she was one before in the
same way Graz’zt was a devil. And maybe due to Drow publicity campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bebiliths are one of those Lolth-aspected demon lineages. They’re huge
spiderlike monsters, whose forms diverge from a spider’s only in ways that make
them scarier. Sapient but not very smart, they prowl the Demonweb Pits and other
planes eternally hunting and killing for the joy of it. Drow often use them as
heavy summoned muscle, which is the largest role their limited intellect allows
them to play in drow intrigue. They’re what your typical drow queen is going to
call up when she’s ready to start an open war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bebiliths are super-fast, have wicked claws, venomous bites, and shoot webs that
are on fire. They’re near the top of the spider-monster hierarchy, of which
Lolth is the undisputed leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Huge Elemental Magical Beasts (demons) and Level 18 Solo Brutes with
696 HP. They have darkvision and Tremorsense 20, and are surrounded by a
&lt;strong&gt;Spectral Death Web&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 3). Enemies caught inside that lose all their
resistances for a turn when they’re hit by an attack. It doesn’t have to be an
attack by the bebilith!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have ridiculous ground and climb speeds of 12, obviously with Spider
Climb. They also don’t roll initiative: their &lt;strong&gt;Dangersense&lt;/strong&gt; makes them act at
initiatives 20 and 10, with a full set of actions in each of these
turns. Additionally, their &lt;strong&gt;Hunter’s Reflexes&lt;/strong&gt; (reaction; recharge 5-6) allow
them to shift 4 squares when someone moves adjacent to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Reaving Claw&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 3 vs. AC) which does damage and
inflicts a cumulative -1 AC penalty on the target, which clears at the end of
the encounter. &lt;strong&gt;Flashing Claws&lt;/strong&gt; allows bebiliths to make this attack twice in
the same action, against different targets. There’s also a &lt;strong&gt;Venomous Bite&lt;/strong&gt;
(melee 1 vs. AC; recharge 6) which does more or less the same damage as a claw
plus ongoing poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Flaming Web&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Reflex; recharge 5-6) does fire damage,
slows, and does ongoing fire damage (save ends both). The first failed save
causes the ongoing damage to increase and worsens the “slowed” condition to
“restrained” (save still ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 20, and has a Bebilith, 3 drider shadowspinners,
and 1 drow priest. The demon is this team’s heavy, but the others can be
dangerous too, particularly against a level 15-16 party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions-1&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have “fond” memories of bebiliths because one of them featured prominently in
Hordes of the Underdark (the epic-level campaign in Neverwinter Nights). Though
they’re mostly “even giant-er” spiders, I like the mechanical “feel” on this
version. It has plenty of options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloodseep-demon&quot;&gt;Bloodseep Demon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demon-bloodseep.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things are covered in thin, translucid skin that constantly cracks and
weeps poisonous blood. They coat their claws in this foulness and spray it at
their victims. They’re also clever enough to use it in subtler ways, tainting
the food supplies of their intended targets in order to weaken them for the
final attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bloodseep demons are Medium Elemental Humanoids (demons) and Level 7 Skirmishers
with the Leader keyword and 79 HP. They have darkvision, a ground speed of 7 and
a teleport speed of 3. Their Variable Resistance is 10 (1/encounter), and they
project a &lt;strong&gt;Weeping Poison&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that deals 5 poison damage to enemies
caught inside. If the demon is bloodied the aura also heals any demons inside
for 5 HP at the start of their turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; also do ongoing poison damage (save ends), and once per
encounter they can squeeze out a &lt;strong&gt;Poison Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude)
which does light poison damage. Demons caught in the blast instead heal the
rolled amount of HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their final trick is the &lt;strong&gt;Poison Portal Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4-6), which allows
them to teleport 5 squares, attack someone with a claw, and teleport another 5
squares. If used well this can cause some havoc in the party’s back line and
force some defenders to turn away from the front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 7 and has one of these, 2 barlguras and 2
evistros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impressions-2&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bloodseep demon” is a horrible name, but the actual monster seems a bit more
interesting than I thought at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dretch&quot;&gt;Dretch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lowest of the low, dretches were covered in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/12/dretch.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; of the Monster
Manual/Vault Let’s Read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-part-1&quot;&gt;End of Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s about it for this post. I estimate it will take two more of about the
same size to go through all this book’s demons.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-01.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-01.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>De-monk-ifying Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/marching-fire.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Is this guy a Martial Artist? A Swashbuckler? A Knight? Yes.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy has the Swashbuckler template. Swashbucklers are physical
combatants who prioritize mobility and precision over heavy armor and brute
strength. They use a specialized set of weapons, are obsessed with improving
their skill, and strive to learn secret techniques of legendary reputation and
effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy also has the Martial Artist template. Martial artists are
physical combatants who prioritize mobility and precision over heavy armor and
brute strength. They use a specialized set of weapons, are obsessed with
improving their skill, and strive to learn secret techniques of legendary
reputation and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, those descriptions use most of the same words. When you look at these two
professional templates from a large enough distance, they really are two takes
on the same concept. They could, in theory, be represented by the same
template. The reason Martial Artist is a separate archetype in Dungeon Fantasy
is because Monk is a separate class in D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the reason Monk is a separate class in D&amp;amp;D, as far as I can tell, is because
of a particular set of media cliches that have surrounded the words “martial
arts” in a lot of media contemporary with earlier editions of D&amp;amp;D. I guess you
could call it a form of orientalism&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some of these media sources, “martial arts” are this mysterious and exotic
secret from the mysterious and exotic East, much more sophisticated than the
crude flailings of Western barbarians. Knowing it makes you more “enlightened”
and gives you superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In others, they’re this fancy dance for pansies that’s totally ineffective in a
“true” fight, because a Real Man knows he just has to punch the other guy. The
Real Man in this scenario is of course always a man, and always Western too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D monks were originally based on this character named Remo Williams, the
protagonist of the Destroyer series of novels. These novels came out in the 70s,
and they were very much in the “exotic secret that gives you superpowers”
camp. Williams learned a fictional martial art from an exotic foreign master and
proceeded to use it to defeat a string of (usually Asian) bad guys. D&amp;amp;D writers
applied a “shaolin” veneer to the class in later editions but many monk
abilities are still based on stuff Williams did in the novels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS replicated this in Dungeon Fantasy because it tries to replicate D&amp;amp;D, but
its “default” approach to martial arts turns out to be a lot better in my
opinion. It has a supplement named GURPS Martial Arts that treats historical
styles from all over the world with the same level of respect. The message
contained in its rules seems to be that these styles are all different
expressions of the same thing&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. How good an individual combatant is matters a
lot more than where his techniques come from. I really liked that when I first
read it, and I’ve only grown to like it more over the years. It kinda bothers me
to see a game that still treats the subject in that older “Destroyer” way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every character who practices a fighting style and trains to improve their skill
at it is a martial artist by definition, no matter &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; that fighting style
comes from. Whether that training gives you superpowers has always been more of
a genre or campaign “setting” than something that should be assigned to
individual character types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the dungeon fantasy genre, that particular setting is obviously
stuck on “yes”. Every PC can perform impossible feats of badassery, that has
been a given since the very beginning&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Someone who comes from a culture that
talks about things in terms of Chi will likely describe any such character as
possessing “strong chi”. Someone who doesn’t will just describe them as being
really good at fighting. This in no way changes the fundamentals of how their
abilities work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s what I’m going to do in my campaigns from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demonkified-dungeon-fantasy&quot;&gt;Demonkified Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chi Mastery no longer exists as a specific power. There is no Chi Talent, and
all its component abilities lose the power modifier along with the associated
discounts and drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only have access to the DFRPG, do this instead: if a former Chi ability
is described as “working like” another trait, you can buy that trait
instead. For example, Tough Skin instead of Dragon Skin, and Striking ST instead
of Mantis Strike. For abilities that have no parallel… keep the same cost,
it’s simpler. In all cases you no longer get a bonus for Chi Talent, but you
also no longer need Disciplines of Faith: Chi Rituals to keep them either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swashbuckler and Martial Artist become related templates. A Swashbuckler
gains access to the Martial Artist’s abilities and power-ups, and
vice-versa. Characters of each template might still look and behave very
differently on a role-playing level, but there isn’t any fundamental difference
in their mechanics any more. The 30 points that would go to Chi Talent in the
Martial Artist template are instead avaialble to be spent on any template
advantages or skills. And there you go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re also using &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html&quot;&gt;Streamlined Mastery&lt;/a&gt;, this means that a PC built using
the Martial Artist template could start off with True Master and Iron Limbs for
the same cost as the official Trained By a Master and Chi Talent 2 advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-knights&quot;&gt;What about Knights?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything I said about monks and swashbucklers in my introduction applies
equally well to Knights and the other “fighty” templates. However, I still want
to keep it as a separate template because it’s good to still have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt;
guidance when building characters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Combatant who prefers strength and heavy gear” is different enough from
“combatant who prefers precision and speed” to remain a useful distinction. I’d
still allow some judicious cross-aisle shopping for traits that make sense for a
specific PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, combining this with some form of &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/08/30/agnostic-dungeon-fantasy.html&quot;&gt;Agnostic Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; (where
either no spellcaster is a priest or they all are) would leave us very close to
ditching templates entirely, or at least having a collection of “classes” that’s
much closer to that of the oldest of old D&amp;amp;Ds: “warrior” and “magic user”. Maybe
I’ll try that some day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-the-path&quot;&gt;What About the Path?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the side-boxes in the Dungeon Fantasy Companion 2 introduces the notion
of The Path, an alternate progression scheme that a Martial Artist PC can opt
into at character creation. Basically, it makes your Chi Talent levels limit how
many levels you can have in certain traits. As a result those limits are lower
to start with, but with enough time and points they can end up much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think The Path is more appropriate for a campaign that does the reverse of
what I’m trying to do here, where &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; uses chi mechanics. I’ll leave it
out of my games for now and maybe write about it at a future date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though of course I’m not an expert on the subject and will gladly defer to
people who are. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, Bruce Lee said this, and yes, the book does talk about him with great
admiration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Don’t even try to bring the Guy at the Gym fallacy into this. The guy at
the gym will never have 200 HP or be able to fight 50 goblins without
breaking a sweat. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/20/demonkification.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/20/demonkification.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Demogorgon (Part 3)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the third and final post covering the huge Demogorgon entry in the
Monster Manual 2. As you might have guessed from what was said back in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/06/11/demogorgon.html&quot;&gt;part
1&lt;/a&gt;, it covers not one but &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; multiversal big shots: the titular Demogorgon
and his buddy Dagon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demogorgon&quot;&gt;Demogorgon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demogorgon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Jesper Ejsing. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demogorgon has existed in D&amp;amp;D since at least the days of AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition. As I
might have mentioned his &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt; got really popular due to the Stranger Things TV
show, though I understand the monster there is a different creature from the
two-headed mandrill found in the actual game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demogorgon claims the title of Prince of Demons, which is quite the bold claim
even among demon lords. His personality and motivations make him the demon
lord’s demon lord. He’s not obsessed with a specific aspect of evil, like Orcus
is with undeath. He’s not overly committed to a single modus operandi like
Graz’zt is with his sexy manipulations. He doesn’t limit his influence to a
single people like Yeenoghu does with gnolls or Baphomet with minotaurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, Demogorgon’s goals are to become the most powerful thing in the multiverse
and destroy anyone who causes him anger or jealousy (i.e, almost everyone). His
wordly cults, as we saw, are focused on wanton destruction and have this theme
of outward madness that hides powerful mysteries. He and his agents are also
quite capable of deception and will use that to achieve their goals just as
readily. You can find servants of Demogorgon anywhere in the universe, and they
can belong to any people. His domain in the Abyss is covered in tropical jungle
but also includes seas and vast brine flats, and he is at home in all of these
environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demogorgon’s main enemies are Orcus and Graz’zt, but though these other two are
very powerful, Demogorgon is more. The books emphasize that he has never lost a
fight - that duel with the god Amoth that nearly split him in two? He won that
one, killed Amoth, killed Storralk right after it, and then got better. Though
to Amoth’s credit, he was the only entity to ever &lt;em&gt;scar&lt;/em&gt; the demon lord: he used
to only have one head before the duel, and that remained split afterwards,
healing into the current two heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of Demogorgon’s heads has its own name, mind and personality: Aameul is the
one that prefers deception, and Hethradiah is the one that prefers
destruction. They detest each other and their plans are frequently at odds,
which is probably the main obstacle preventing the demon lord from conquering
the universe. Still, sometimes those competing plans end up synergizing into
something that advances his goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This split nature is reflected all the way down his cult hierarchies. The layout
of his temples is split down the middle with each half dedicated to one of the
heads. The most powerful cults are led by pairs of twins, each dedicated to a
head. And as we already say even individual cultists have a “dual nature” thing
going on, starting fights as cold and calculating combatants and devolving into
frothing berserkers when they’re wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most powerful among his cultists might know the ritual to summon an Aspect
of Demogorgon, a living echo of his power. Like the Aspects of Orcus, they share
the personality and a fraction of the power of their originator, but their
existence is independent. An aspect doesn’t know what the original is thinking,
and vice-versa. They’re a bit like avatars from previous editions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demogorgon himself is a Garguantuan Elemental Humanoid and a Level 34 Solo
Controller with the Aquatic and Demon keywords. This is literally
the highest-level monster we saw so far in the entire Let’s Read - Orcus, the
former holder of the title, was level 33. His HP total is 1260.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has trained Perception and Darkvision, Variable Resistance 30 switchable
3x/encounter, ground and swim speeds of 8, and a teleport speed of 10. Remember,
a teleport speed means he can teleport at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has the two traits previously seen on ettins. &lt;strong&gt;Double Actions&lt;/strong&gt; means
he rolls initiative twice at the start of combat, once for each head, and takes
two full turns each round. His immediate actions refresh before each action. You
have to specify which turn belongs to which head, though - that head can’t use
the other’s special power. &lt;strong&gt;Dual Brain&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to automatically save
against the Dazed and Stunned conditions and against any charm effects at the
end of one of his turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat, Demogorgon fights with his copious tentacles and with psychic powers:
the basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach 5 vs. AC), but he has many more
interesting options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Blast 5 vs. Fortitude) does almost the same damage and
deals ongoing 15 damage (save ends). If it hits a target that was already taking
ongoing damage, that damage is increased by 5. &lt;strong&gt;Forked Tail&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 5
vs. Reflex) deals necrotic damage and weakens (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are the physical attacks; now for the magic ones!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any enemy who starts their turn within 10 squares of Demogorgon is subject to
the &lt;strong&gt;Gaze of Abyssal Might&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Will; free action), which dazes until the end
of the target’s turn. He can let his enemies take a peek inside his minds with
&lt;strong&gt;Dual Aspects of Demogorgon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 10 vs. Will; recharge 6) which deals
heavy psychic damage and knocks the targets unconscious (save ends) on a
hit. That’s a potential TPK right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, each head has a special power that can be used in its
assigned turn. These are minor actions, so they’ll happen alongside one of the
other attacks. They’re both Close Blast 5 vs. Will. &lt;strong&gt;Aameul’s Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; does
psychic damage and dazes (save ends). If the target was already dazed, for
example by the Gaze of Abyssal Might, they are dominated instead (save
ends). &lt;strong&gt;Hethradiah’s Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; does a bit less psychic damage but forces the
target to use an &lt;em&gt;at-will attack power&lt;/em&gt; against a target of Demogorgon’s choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running away from all this is also quite hard: &lt;strong&gt;Inescapable Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; is a Ranged
&lt;em&gt;50&lt;/em&gt; power that targets Will and teleports the target to a square within
tentacle reach of Demogorgon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also get a stat block for the Aspect of Demogorgon, which is very similar but
smaller in all ways. It’s “only” Huge, and a Level 25 Elite Controller with 476
HP. It uses Forked Tail as its basic attack and replaces the named gazes with a
&lt;strong&gt;Dominating Glare&lt;/strong&gt; that deals psychic damage and dominates. It has all the
other attacks, including the Double Actions and Dual Brain traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dagon&quot;&gt;Dagon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demogorgon-dagon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagon is inspired by the Lovecraftian entity of the same name, but is not quite
the same creature. He’s been in the game since the days of AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-lore-1&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first primordials who entered the Abyss shortly after it had formed found
Dagon already lurking in its depths. He is the first and most ancient Demon
Lord. His presence poses a disturbing question: did Tharizdun create the Abyss,
or merely open a passage to it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I think this gets answered in the Demonomicon, but it’s still cool even if left
as a mystery).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagon is remarkably secretive for a demon lord, and he sits on an endless trove
of blasphemous knowledge and terrible cosmic secrets. He allied himself with
Demogorgon shortly after the latter became a demon lord, and the two have
cooperated ever since. Their cults often work together, and though Dagon’s
cultists are a minority in these joint efforts, access to their master’s
knowledge makes them very effective leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagon shares some of his knowledge with Demogorgon to further both of their
goals, but ever since the the “split” he has taken to whispering different bits
of lore to each head, which ends up making Aameul and Hethradiah antagonize each
other even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagon is a Gargantuan Elemental Magical Beast with the Aquatic and Demon
keywords, and a Level 32 Solo Soldier with 1184 HP. He has the usual Darkvision
and Variable Resistance (10, 3x/encounter). His ground speed is only 4, which
doesn’t matter because you’re definitely fighting him underwater. He also has
swim and teleport speeds of 8. Dagon also has an &lt;strong&gt;Eye of the Abyss&lt;/strong&gt; aura (10)
that pulls any enemies who start their turns inside 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagon might begin the fight at range, using his control over &lt;strong&gt;Abyssal Tides&lt;/strong&gt;
to attack the PCs. This is an Area Burst 3 within 20 vs. Reflex, doing force
damage and immobilizing the targets on a hit (save ends). As an effect, Dagon
can also teleport 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the PCs are in reach, it’s Tentacle Town. Dagon can uses his tentacles
either for a basic &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach 5 vs. AC) or a &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Blast&lt;/strong&gt;
(Close Blast 5 vs. AC), both of which damage and slide the targets 2 squares on
a hit. They also act on their own with &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Tentacles&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach 5 vs. AC),
an interrupt that triggers when an enemy in reach attacks Dagon. This does a
little less damage than the basic attack and grabs the target. The escape DC is
something like 44 or 46 depending on the skill you use, which will be tricky for
a non-specialist even if they’re level 30. And of course these Reach 5 tentacles
have &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not all tentacles either! Dagon’s repertoire includes a hefty dose of pure
madness. &lt;strong&gt;Doom Drone&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 10 vs. Will; minor action; recharge 5-6)
targets enemies and does psychic damage. It also pulls them 5 squares and stuns
them on a hit (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Form of Madness&lt;/strong&gt; is similar but slides and dazes
instead of pulling and stunning. If several enemies manage to get in close
Dagon can use &lt;strong&gt;Claws of the Abyss&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 1 vs. Reflex) to deal heavy
physical damage with his non-tentacle appendages. Note he can use the claws
&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; both mental attacks in a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tactics paragraph makes a reference to a power named &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the Deep&lt;/strong&gt;,
though that’s not in the stat block. One of them is wrong. In either case
Dagon’s goal should be to keep all the PCs, particularly the squishies, well
inside the tentacled killing zone surrounding him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the big bosses, only Demogorgon features in a sample encounter here: Level
35, him and two balors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two make nice final bosses for an epic campaign, though probably not at
the same time. Demogorgon’s Dual Brain gives him a decent amount of control
resistance. Dagon is a bit less strong in that area, but both of them can output
an incredible amount of control themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that a campaign that ends with the defeat of Demogorgon is one where
Dagon never shows up in person at all - he’d be too clever to stick around in
that case. The reverse is harder to predict. Demogorgon values the alliance but
is probably too selfish to try and help Dagon if a party of epic demigods knocks
at his briny door. He might however, try to exact revenge on them later, so he
could end up being the “final final” boss in a Dagon-focused campaign. Or
perhaps he does things on a long enough timescale that he ends up being the boss
of the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/15/demogorgon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/15/demogorgon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Demogorgon (Part 2)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/06/11/demogorgon.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, this time we’ll be looking at Demogorgon’s
Exarchs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Exarch” is the term D&amp;amp;D 4 uses for the “lieutenants” of a god or equivalent
entity. They might preside over a narrower slice of their master’s portfolio, or
simply help run their operations in the world and other planes. Though
subordinate to someone else, exarchs are in no way weak: in the god-ranking
system used in previous editions, all of them would have ranked as anything from
demigods to intermediate deities themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orcus, which we looked at in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/26/ettin.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual let’s Read&lt;/a&gt;, had one exarch:
Dorensain, the King of Ghouls. Demogorgon has two, described below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kazuul&quot;&gt;Kazuul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazuul used to be a human champion of Erathis a long time ago, and in her
service he carved many a swath of order through savage lands. I guess that in
the end something convinced him that this “carving a swath” business didn’t make
him any different from the “savages” he claimed to oppose, and so he decided to
embrace that and pledge himself to Demogorgon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demon lord gave him a gift of size and strength, making him double in size
and become deformed by his over-developed demonic musculature. Kazuul now fights
in the name of Hethradiah, the “brutal but cunning” head, driving a horde of
demons before him to raid places in the Abyss and elsewhere in the multiverse. I
guess Kazuul is a big inspiration to those shrieking cultists we saw in the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/06/11/demogorgon.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a former human, Kazuul fights with weapons. Being a former &lt;em&gt;adventurer&lt;/em&gt;,
he’s always on the lookout for better weapons. If he notices one of his
opponents is wielding something particularly sweet (say, a level 28+ magical
weapon), he will engage that opponent and ignore everyone else until he’s taken
the weapon for himself. Otherwise, he will just focus on killing whoever is
closest and repeating that until there is no one else to kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obsession with magic weapons stems in part from the fact that Kazuul used
to own a legendary sword named Gorgorin the Shatterer. He lost it in a battle
against Hainard, one of Pelor’s exarchs. He’s still sore about that, and looking
for a way to either get his sword back or to find a suitably awesome
replacement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazuul’s current weapons are quite awesome already: there’s The Tooth of Grom, a
sword forged from the tooth of a fire titan lord, and The World Splitter, an axe
taken from Clangeddin Silverbeard, one of Moradin’s Exarchs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an ancient prophecy which proclaims that when Kazuul recovers Gorgorin,
he will use it to slay Demogorgon and then displace Yeenoghu as the lord of
gnolls. This prophecy has caused lots of infighting amongst demons, and there
have been several failed attempts by all factions involved to find the blade’s
current hiding place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazuul is a Large Elemental Humanoid with the Demon tag, making him an official
demon. He’s a Level 28 Elite Soldier with 528 HP. He has Darkvision and demonic
Variable Resistance 10, switchable 3x/encounter. He has ground and fly speeds of
5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has two basic attacks with his sweet magic weapons: the &lt;strong&gt;Tooth of Grom&lt;/strong&gt;
(Reach 2 vs. AC) does physical damage and forces the target to make a melee
basic attack against a target of Kazuul’s choice on a hit; the &lt;strong&gt;World
Splitter&lt;/strong&gt; (reach 2 vs. AC) also does physical damage and inflicts a -4 AC
penalty (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of Kazuul&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to attack with both weapons
in a single standard action. Oh, and &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to make
opportunity attacks against any enemy he can reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If his enemies are beyond the reach of his blades, Kazuul can attack with
&lt;strong&gt;Abyssal Flames&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 3 within 20 vs. Reflex) at will, doing fire
damage on a hit. He also has a couple of handy spells for use when he gets
closer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Word of Doom&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Will; encounter) does heavy physical damage
and allows Kazuul to crit against the targets on a natural roll of 15-20 (save
ends). This is scarier than it might sound for someone used to 3.x! In Fourth
Edition, criticals happen only on a natural 20. Only a handful of powers in the
entire game increase that range. Word of Doom is the only one I can think of
that widens it this much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vortex of Blades&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Reflex; enemies only; encounter) does
double the damage of a basic attack and stuns (save ends). Simple, but still
scary: stun (save ends) is a pretty serious condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thrarak&quot;&gt;Thrarak&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demogorgon-thrarak.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Chippy. Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrarak’s origins are closely tied to the mythological origns for &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/26/ettin.html&quot;&gt;ettins&lt;/a&gt;
that I wrote about during the first Monster Manual/Vault Let’s Read. It starts
with Demogorgon fighting the god Amoth, who split his head in two. Before that
wound had even healed, the earth primordial Storralk ambushed him and tried to
take him down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the linked post says, Demogorgon defeated the would-be usurper handily, and
bound his broken but still-living form under his throne. It was Dagon who gave
him the idea for a bit of extra cruel punishment: using a ritual provided by
Dagon, Demogorgon caused the first Ettins to be born from Storralk’s spilled
blood, and to scatter through the world. Each one contains a small fraction of
Storralk’s essence, so whenever an ettin feels pain, Storralk’s body feels it as
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those first ettins chose to stay at Demogorgon’s side, and to seek his
favor by alternatively healing and cutting Storralk’s flesh. This eventually got
his attention and Demogorgon made her one of his exarchs: Thrarak, the Flayed
Maiden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrarak is specifically the Exarch of Ameul, the cunning head. She acts as
Demogorgon’s emissary of vengeance, going after mortals and other entities that
have angered the Prince of Demons or those who have the potential to become
threats in the future. An expert torturer, she fights using twin lashes and
yelling streams of maddening lore that’s dangerous to hear. She prefers to focus
on one opponent at a time, which will either be the target of her master’s ire
or the closest available enemy. Once she chooses a target she will ignore any
other enemies to focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legend has it that if Thrarak is slain and her heart burned upon Demogorgon’s
throne, Storralk will finally break free of his prison. Freeing him could be an
important step in defeating Demogorgon himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrarak is a Large Elemental Humanoid (giant) and a Level 26 Elite Brute with
596 HP. She has all the traits common to all Ettins: trained Perception,
darkvision, ground speed 8, and the Dual Brain and Double Actions traits
described in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/26/ettin.html&quot;&gt;original ettin post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her basic melee attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Lash of Ruin&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach 3 vs. AC) which does
physical damage, knocks prone, and dazes for a turn on a hit. She can sometimes
increase her rythm and perform a &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (close burst 3
vs. AC; recharge 5-6), dealing physical damage and dazing (save ends) all she
hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter she can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Howl of Madness&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Blast 5
vs. Will), which does psychic damage, slides the targets 3 squares, and forces
them to make a melee basic attack against a target of Thrarak’s choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those ettin traits I linked to are quite important to all of this: Thrarak has
two full turns per round and some resistance to restrictive conditions. She can
do a lot, which makes her dangerous to those enemies she’s focusing on. She
should be put in charge of a monster team who can keep the remaining PCs off her
back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have one encounter for each Exarch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 25: Thrarak, 1 abyssal rotfiend, and 2 nycademons.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 27: Kazuul, 1 marilith, and 1 balor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels appropriate to add a whole bunch of minions to either encounter, if you
think they’re not dangerous enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I like these two as villains more than I like Dorensain, Orcus’
exarch. Mechanically, Thrarak is just an epic ettin, but she has an interesting
backstory tied to her people’s mythological origins. Kazuul’s magic weapon
obsession is also interesting, and the Gorgorin lore has a lot of potential as
an adventure hook.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/14/demogorgon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/14/demogorgon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
