<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:26:55 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:26:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Psionic Adept</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As we all know by now, psychic powers are very common in Athas. Anyone might
have some, even if that’s not their main specialty. For PCs, this is implemented
as a couple of character themes (Noble Adept and Wilder).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For NPCs and monsters, we have the Psionic Adept theme presented here. You can
add this to a non-psionic monster to make it more controller-ish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psionic Adepts gain a +2 to either either Diplomacy and Intimidate (force of
personality!) or to Insight and Perception (sixth sense!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the usual design strategy of adding new abilities that work “around”
established attacks, we get a collection of powers that hinder and debuff
enemies. All of the ones that require attack rolls target Will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bling the Mind’s Eye&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a ranged attack that makes the
creature invisible to the target (save ends). This ends when the creature
attacks the target. Lurkers can use this to enable their big attacks, while
others can use it as a way to ease pressure on themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empathic Wall&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) creates a 12-square wall that lasts a turn. It
blocks line of sight. People can cross it, but its squares are difficult
terrain, and anyone inside them is lightly obscured.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mantle of the Mind&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a close burst 4 that attacks will and
prevents affected targets from targeting the creature with their attacks (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Marionette&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a sustainable domination power. It
dominates for a turn on a hit, but can be sustained with standard actions to
let the creature repeat the attack against the same target, potentially
prolonging the domination. On a miss, it dazes for a turn. It’s a little
weaker than a fire-and-forget (save ends) power, because it eats up standard
actions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three variants of &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augmentation&lt;/strong&gt; that add a little extra something
when the creature hits with a melee basic attack. One deals extra psychic
damage, the other dazes for a turn, and the third one inflicts ongoing psychic
damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a lot more clearly “utilities” than the ones for elemental
creatures. They’re all encounter powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Bastion&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt that gives a +4 to Will, potentially
turning a hit into a miss.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open the Mind’s Eye&lt;/strong&gt; gives blindsight 5 and all-around vision for a
turn. The latter means the creature cannot be flanked.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oracular Empathy&lt;/strong&gt; is a weird one. When an nearby ally of the creature is
hit by an attack, the creature can use a reaction to switch its initiative
order to be just after the attacker’s.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psionic Flight&lt;/strong&gt; automatically pushes each adjacent enemy 1 square and lets
the creature fly its speed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty cool! It seems more thematically tight to me than Elementally
Infused. Adding these powers to someone like an ogre would be a nice/nasty
surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/22/wir-dscc-theme-psionic-adept.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/22/wir-dscc-theme-psionic-adept.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Elementally-Infused Monster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Athas is a world particularly close to the Elemental Chaos, and so there are
lots of places in it that are soaked in elemental energies of some kind. The
creatures that inhabit these areas often end up elementally-infused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book suggests changing the creature’s origin to elemental if its mutations
end up being inheritable, though that just affects the lore and so it’s just
necessary if it will affect the game’s stories in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main mechanical thing you must decided about an elementally-infused creature
is its element. All of its powers that deal damage have it written as “[damage
type]” in the book, and you’re meant to replace that lacuna with a type
corresponding to the creature’s associated elements: one of fire, acid, cold,
thunder, or lightning (very very frightening!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of its attacks need to do the same type of damage. Multi-element
elementals are a thing now, after all. And you might decide to make one or more
of these attacks untyped, which would be common for an earth elemental whose
rock-based attacks deal physical damage for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementally-infused creatures get +2 to Intimidate and Athletics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these powers deal damage of the type you chose above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Auras&lt;/strong&gt;, one that triggers when the monster is
bloodied and damages enemies inside, and one that is always active and makes
enemies vulnerable to your chosen element.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Eruption&lt;/strong&gt; causes an explosion when the monster is first bloodied,
a close burst 2 that targets Reflex and deals elemental damage equal to the
monster’s best basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Manifestation&lt;/strong&gt; converts the damage of all of the monster’s
attacks to your chosen element.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Persistence&lt;/strong&gt; is recharge 5+ and inflicts 5/tier ongoing damage of
the chosen type when the monster hits with a melee attack. It’s said to
increase “damage output and entertainment value”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious here is &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Damage Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;, which should be high
enough for the monster to resist its own attacks (or I guess 5/tier if you don’t
want to do math). If a monster’s attacks are untyped, you could give it
variable resistance instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all of the others deal damage, proving that the “attack”/”utility” split
is more of a guideline here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Dissipation&lt;/strong&gt; lets the monster vanish from play for a turn and
reform next to an enemy, dealing a bit of damage and making them grant combat
advantage for another turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Ground&lt;/strong&gt; is a third aura variant, this time meant to keep enemies
close. The aura’s radius becomes difficult terrain and enemies take damage
when they leave it, instead of when they enter it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Step&lt;/strong&gt; deals elemental damage to anyone who hits the monster with
an opportunity attack while it moves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Transport&lt;/strong&gt; lets the monster teleport between patches of hazardous
terrain that deal damage of the chosen type. Clever!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mutable Body&lt;/strong&gt; is appropriate for water-based or otherwise gooey monsters,
and lets the creature count as one size smaller when squeezing through narrow
openings.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want elemental damage? We got elemental damage! I like the design strategy
of additional attack powers that modify and work around the monster’s usual
attacks, and it works particularly well here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/20/wir-dscc-themes-elemental.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/20/wir-dscc-themes-elemental.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Customizing Monsters</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re past the monster lists, but there’s still a fair amount of book to
cover. Its final third is dedicated to Encounter Options, and the first
subsection of that is a small lesson on Customizing Monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of it is that when you want to bring a “generic” D&amp;amp;D monster to Athas,
you should change them a little to make them fit the more brutal and desperate
tone of the setting. In other words, you should make them Darker and Sunnier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next page has a few tips on how to do that. First, you should keep the
monster recognizable, since it both keeps things a little familiar and makes
the differences stand out that much more. And then you can apply one or more of
the customization guidelines they suggest, each with an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No change&lt;/strong&gt;: Some monsters already fit the aesthetic and could just be
dropped in where you need them. Gnolls and bullettes, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altered Appearance&lt;/strong&gt;: Some monsters need a little extra make-up to fit the
visual style of Athas. You’ll rarely find traditional mammals here for
example, but you could have equivalent creatures that have carapaces, scales,
and bony plates instead of soft fur. Hill giants might look more rocky, with
skin matching the colors of the surrounding terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altered Environment&lt;/strong&gt;: Creatures that live in frozen or aquatic biomes in
their original forms could be changed to live in the desert wastelands of
Athas instead. Sure, the aquatic ones could live in oases, but turning them
into sand-burrowers can be a “nice” surprise for the players.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternative Lore&lt;/strong&gt;: This most important for creatures whose lore has
extensive ties to the Astral Sea and divine magic, both of which are mostly
inaccessible in Athas. Eidolons are one example, and they’d need to be changed
to be tied to arcane or primal magic instead unless they’re relics from when
the gods were still around. Angels and the like should also be reskinned
unless your entire game revolves around the mystery of why they appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Powers&lt;/strong&gt;: New mechanical abilities might be just the thing to make a
given creature Darker and Sunnier. This should mostly be handled through
Monster Themes, which are discussed in the next page.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-converted-monsters&quot;&gt;Sample Converted Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two are given as examples, and in some cases are also stealth updates to
the originals, using the new Monster Manual 3 math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silt-shark&quot;&gt;Silt Shark&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the Fleshtearer Shark from the Monster Manual 2, this creature occupies
a similar niche to the bullette, with slightly different abilities. Its
water-based traits were replaced with sand-themed equivalents, and it’s been
given training in Athletics to make higher jumps. It “swims” through sand and
loose soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silt Shark is a Large Natural Beast and a Level 10 Brute with 128 HP. It has
a ground speed of 5, and a burrow speed of 8, with low-light vision and
Tremorsense 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original shark’s Aquatic trait has been replaced with &lt;strong&gt;Silt Swimmer&lt;/strong&gt;,
which lets the shark shift and charge while burrowing, and gives it a +2 damage
bonus while burrowing against any creature without a burrow speed. It cannot
burrow through solid stone, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shark has a basic &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt;, and a &lt;strong&gt;Lockjaw Charge&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that deals the
same damage and grabs on a hit. While the shark has a grabbed victim, it can
automatically deal damage to them with &lt;strong&gt;Shredding Teeth&lt;/strong&gt;. And once the grab
ends, the victim takes ongoing 5 damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the shark starts its turn within 5 squares of a bloodied creature, it enters
a &lt;strong&gt;Feeding Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt;, and makes a free attack against a creature adjacent to
it. If it was grabbing someone, it releases them first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ssurran-dune-mystic&quot;&gt;Ssurran Dune Mystic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Greenscale Marsh Mystic from the Monster Manual, modified into a
Ssurran version. The swamp theme of the original’s abilities has been switched
to a sand and desert theme, its Constitution was increased a little, and its
basic attack has been given a push rider to match the Ssurran Shaman from that
entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We end up with a Level 6 Controller (Leader) with 72 HP and a ground speed of 6
with Earth Walk. It has a &lt;strong&gt;Sun Blessing&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that heals 3 HP to any ally
that stats their turn inside, and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and
pushes 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystic also has a couple of fireball-style combat spells: &lt;strong&gt;Salt Cloud&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) deals poison damage and dazes for a turn; &lt;strong&gt;Sand’s Grasp&lt;/strong&gt;
(encounter) is non-damaging, but it immobilizes (save ends) and creates a zone
of difficult terrain that lasts for the rest of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite likely that anyone who still actively plays D&amp;amp;D 4th Edition is
experienced enough at reskinning monsters that they don’t really need this
advice. Nevertheless, it’s still good to see it printed, and with worked
examples to boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up: Monster Themes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/11/wir-dscc-customizing-monsters.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/11/wir-dscc-customizing-monsters.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Creature Catalog: Zeburon, the Iron Rider</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-zeburon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Zeburon
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeburon is the leader of the Black Sands Raiders, a brutal and feared bandit
gang that hides out in the Black Sands. According to rumor they always number a
hundred, and ride war-trained kanks to assault caravans and settlements around
the Black Sands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iron Rider got this title because of his signature metal helmet, which has a
pair of prominent horns and completely conceals his face. Not even most of the
Raiders have ever seen it - only his most trusted lieutenants (such as the
defiler Fevik) know what he looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is because Zeburon’s big secret is that he’s a tiefling. The book lists
reasons why no one has figured it out yet, and they’re actually a little
funny. He lacks a tail because he cut it off himself years ago. People tend to
mistake the reddish tone of his skin for sunburns instead of natural
pigmentation. And they think the horns are part of the helmet, when in fact
they’re poking through a pair of holes in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeburon hides his true nature from the rank and file of his gang because he’s
afraid of how they’d react if they found out. Given bigotry is never in short
supply around Athas, I’m guessing the answer is “not well”. And being a fearsome
individual warrior is not very helpful if about ninety guys on war kanks decide
they want you dead and charge you all at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeburon is a Level 12 Elite Soldier with 246 HP. He has a ground speed of 6,
low-light vision, and Resist Fire 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of his attacks deal bonus damage against bloodied targets due to his
&lt;strong&gt;Bloody Violence&lt;/strong&gt; trait. He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Bastard Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that can make
standard basic attacks and be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Wild Bloodletting&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver,
attacking a Close Burst 1. A hit deals damage, slows the target, and inflicts
ongoing 10 damage (save ends both). This recharges when he’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can use his &lt;strong&gt;Iron Fist&lt;/strong&gt; (metal gauntlet!) to make another
attack, which does the same damage as the sword, and immobilizes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, he has the tiefling &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; power which, when used, gives
him a bonus to attacks and damage against any enemy that hit him since the end
of his last turn. This lasts for a turn or until he hits an enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fight against Zeburon will also include a sizable contingent of Black Sands
Raiders, as well as his best buddy and top lieutenant Fevik the Defiler. Plus
any amount of kank mounts you deem necessary. It will likely come after the PCs
have fought multiple encounters against the raiders, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure I’ve seen someone a lot like Zeburon in one of the many Brom
illustrations for DS: muscles, leather straps, face-concealing horned helmet,
menacing pose.  I haven’t read any older DS material to know whether he’s
someone from the old days, or if he’s new and just likes following local
fashions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/24/wir-dscc-zeburon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/24/wir-dscc-zeburon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels: Origin Corrections</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Wait,” you might ask, “are you still doing this?”. Yes, I am! I have been doing
it since shortly after the last time I talked about it, off and on, but I
haven’t posted anything else here in the blog for entirely personal reasons that
I should overcome any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re going to start with a little correction here, because over the course
of my play, I’ve looked at the timelines a bit closer and the details for the
Knight of the Deep &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.htlm&quot;&gt;origin&lt;/a&gt; don’t make sense as written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC arrives at Kintargo at the start of Adventure 01, which is supposed to
last at least eight weeks or so given the pace at which the “strategic”
rebellion turns move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the aquatic elves that origin is concerned with rescuing are only
captured in the final stretch of Adventure 02. Here’s the timeline as written in
the adventure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The elves arrive in town maybe a week or two before the day of their
capture. This would be in the middle of Adventure 02.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They are seeking Shensen’s help with their problems back home. When they fail
to find her, they spend some time exploring the waters around Kintargo before
being captured by the aboleth’s minions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The day of their capture is “fuzzy” - it’s the day before the PCs first enter
the adventure’s final dungeon. Once they do, the GM is supposed to track their
condition over time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The elves might starve before being rescued, and if they’re still alive after
two weeks they’re taken back home to be dominated by the aboleth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we take the Knight’s current background as written, it would mean the elves
have been captured &lt;em&gt;before Adventure 01&lt;/em&gt;. If we want the PC to have any chance
at all to rescue the elven scouts, we either have to make the Lucky Bones delve
the &lt;em&gt;very first thing&lt;/em&gt; the PCs do after the riot, or we have to change the
background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing the former is actually no trouble in Dungeon Fantasy. Starting delvers are
already strong enough to tackle the place, you just might need to put some magic
weapons within easy reach in the first level. If that’s what you want, just have
Laria Longroad point them to the place directly instead of the Wasp Nest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have already played through the Wasp Nest storyline on my own and I
don’t want to restart the game all the way from the beginning, though, I’m going
to change the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of being sent to rescue the scouts, the Knight will be sent in to seek
Shensen’s aid. This gives them a stronger reason to stick with the rebellion,
and a better clue of which path to follow in pursuit of their goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scouts still go to Kintargo in Adventure 02, but this time they do so to
find the Knight, who has been taking much longer than anticipated to return with
Shensen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rules-wise, the only thing that changes is that the optional Obsession to find
Aava becomes an Obsession to find Shensen, worth the same number of points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also changed the description of the theme in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.htlm&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pc-origin-knight-of-the-deep&quot;&gt;PC Origin: Knight of the Deep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You come from one of the subaquatic communities off the coast of Ravounel, where
you enjoy an heroic reputation. You recently went to visit your friend Aava in
the coastal village of Acisazi, only to find the village suffering under a
strange malaise. The village’s elder told you this was caused by a curse that
was beyond her power to break, and begged you to seek the aid of Shensen, a
powerful bard and priest of Sarenrae who lived in the city of Kintargo. You
accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You arrive at this land-lubber town to find it embroiled in a lot more trouble
than you thought possible. Shensen is nowhere to be found. You suspect she
vanished into the prisons of the despotic Barzilai Thrune, and your queries have
led you to the Aria Park protest. You suspect you might need to bloody this
human despot’s nose to fulfill your mission, and that’s just fine with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;: You must belong to a species capable of breathing underwater!
Dungeon Fantasy 3: The Next Level contains two possible choices here: the Sea
Elf and the Water-Infused. From this blog, you might also pick the [Argonian][2]
or perhaps a &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.htlm&quot;&gt;Warforged&lt;/a&gt; who has been modified to be hydrodynamic and
Amphibious. And of course we also have a whole article about the [Denizens of
the Sea][5] that also contains a few usable ancestries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theme is open to any profession, but martial types should probably keep in
mind the rules for [underwater combat for fish-people][3].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: The people of Acisazi know and trust you, and Aava is your good
friend (or even a relative if you’re also a sea elf).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add Swimming, Aquabatics and Survival (Undersea) to your template as
optional skills, and should probably put some points in them during character
creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;: Add Obsession (find Shensen) (12) {-5} to your template as an
optional disadvantage. It’s what you already want to do anyway, but like the
Last Archivist’s Obsession it might drive you to unwise actions.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/22/lphr-background-change.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/22/lphr-background-change.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>character</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Ulruun The Repugnant</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-ulruun.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Ulruun, a bald and beardless dwarf in a fancy tunic. He&apos;s smiling
    repugnantly.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re fresh out of Sorcerer-Kings, but there are still a couple of randos to
read through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ulruun used to be a skilled gladiator who managed to survive the arenas of
Nibenay for many years, a rarity. He eventually won his freedom, not for his
victories, but as a reward for murdering someone for his patron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dwarf then proceeded to become a living example of the cycle of abuse as he
went on to become a slave auctioneer for House Shom, and to run his own slave
trading operation on the side. The money he earned from both activities made him
wealthy, and finally allowed to achieve the luxurious life of debauchery he so
envied in the people who had forced him to risk his life for entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His epithet, “the Repugnant”, is not someone people call him to his face, but it
still describes his demeanor very well. He always travels with plenty of
bodyguards in case a competitor or the “merchandise” decides to take a swipe at
him, and has been known to take shelter behind lines of chained prisoners and
other innocents when attacked. If pressed, he can still rely on his arena
skills - that walking stick is mostly for show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ulruun is a Level 8 Soldier with 89 HP. As a dwarf, he has a ground speed of 5,
+5 to saves against poison, low-light vision, and the same &lt;strong&gt;Stand the Ground&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Steady-Footed&lt;/strong&gt; traits PCs get. These reduced forced movement inflicted on
him by 1 and allow him to roll a save to avoid falling prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ulruun’s main weapon is a &lt;strong&gt;Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; whose basic attacks damage and mark for a
turn, and which can be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Hamstring&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that deals the same
damage and causes the target to fall prone if they move more than half their
speed before the end of their next turn. If a marked enemy tries to shift away
from him, he can use Hamstring on them as an interrupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If his pursuers are too insistent he can surprise them with a &lt;strong&gt;Hurled Cane&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor, ranged 5), which targets Reflex and on a hit knocks prone and
immobilizes for a turn. This is an encounter power, as he only has one cane on
him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ulruun prefers his obvious bodyguards to be very large and intimidating, so he
tends to recruit goliaths and muls to the role. He also has more discreet humans
and halfling guards hidden in nearby crowds when walking through the city. And
if there are any innocents on the map when a fight breaks out, he’ll use them as
cover as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ulruun is, well, repugnant, though other than being a dwarf there’s probably not
much that’s unique about him. I think he’s meant to be a typical example of a
sleazy slave trader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/17/wir-dscc-ulruun.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/17/wir-dscc-ulruun.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4e</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Tectuktitlay</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-tectuktitlay.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Tectuktitlay, dressed in extravagant regalia and holding a human heart.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tectuktitlay is the king of Draj, and while he is not the only sorcerer-king to
claim to be a god, he’s apparently the one most willing to enforce that claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His priests tell the story of how he’s the son of the moons Ral and Guthay, who
descended into the mortal realm already a god. This divine family gave Draj the
gifts of bountiful harvests and prowess in battle, and can easily revoke them
if they’re not properly worshiped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disagreeing with Tectuktitlay about any of this is a particularly painful form
of suicide. He constantly appears to his people at the top of his
stepped-pyramid palace (the “Temple of the Father and Master”), and his vigilant
gaze is etched on structures all through Draj. It’s hard to tell whether his
subjects believe he’s really a god - they have gotten extremely good at going
through the motions of worshiping him in the name of self-preservation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly couldn’t tell from the book’s description if Tectuktitlay really
believes in his own divinity. Whether he does or not, he also knows he’s the
weakest of the Sorcerer Kings, and probably has something of an inferiority
complex about it. He tries to compensate for his personal weakness by making his
realm military strong instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three stat blocks here. Draj is the Aztec-themed domain, so everyone here
just loves to rip out people’s hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moon-priest&quot;&gt;Moon Priest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a typical templar of Draj, equal parts bureaucrat and enforcer of his
god’s creed. They’re always on the lookout for heresy, and ready to violently
punish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moon Priests are Level 11 Controllers with the Leader tag and 110 HP. Their
leaderly qualities come from their aura of &lt;strong&gt;Enforced Zeal&lt;/strong&gt; (1) which gives
allies inside a +2 damage bonus; and from &lt;strong&gt;Blood Demands Blood&lt;/strong&gt; an encounter
power that gives allies within 5 squares a +2 attack bonus as a reaction when
the priest is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Scourge&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and inflicts a -2 attack penalty for
a turn. They also have a dagger in hand that has a scarier purpose: the &lt;strong&gt;Worthy
Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (melee 1 vs. Reflex), which knocks a target prone on a hit
and lets them make a secondary attack against the same target. If &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; hits,
it deals heavy physical damage, dazes (save ends), and gives 10 temporary HP to
each nonminion ally the priest can see. They try to rip your heart out! And this
is at-will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can use a minor action to charm an enemy with a &lt;strong&gt;Sacrificial
Summons&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 15 vs. Will) which pulls 5 squares and makes the target grant
combat advantage for a turn. If this ends up with the target in melee reach,
it’s that much easier to hit them with the big sacrifice attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jasuan-temple-guard&quot;&gt;Jasuan Temple Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are elite bodyguards hand-picked from Draj’s knightly orders for their
unquestioning devotion to their god. They protect the Father and Master Temple,
and Tectuktitlay himself. They’re Level 21 Soldiers with 200 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Broadswords&lt;/strong&gt; that deal immediate and ongoing
physical damage, and also mark (save ends both). And they can throw &lt;strong&gt;Bone
Harpoons&lt;/strong&gt; that deal physical damage and immobilize (save ends). Once a target
has been immobilized, they can be targeted by &lt;strong&gt;Reel In&lt;/strong&gt; (minor, ranged 10
vs. Fort), which pulls them 5 squares or knocks them prone on a hit. If they end
up adjacent to the guard, the guard can hit them with his sword again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, their &lt;strong&gt;Wicked Cruelty&lt;/strong&gt; gives them 10 temporary HP whenever they
bloody an enemy for the first time, and it’s the first time that enemy has been
bloodied in the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tectuktitlay-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Tectuktitlay, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tectuktitlay is Level 22 Elite Artillery (Leader), lower level than any other of
the sorcerer-kings we saw so far in this book. He has 316 HP and a speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tectuktitlay projects a large aura of &lt;strong&gt;Imposed Zealotry&lt;/strong&gt; (4) that gives a +2
attack bonus to allies inside, and another one of &lt;strong&gt;Bloody Vigor&lt;/strong&gt; over the same
area that heals 10 HP to any bloodied ally that starts their turn inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has a &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; for melee, but the real star of the show here are his
spells, all of which have a maximum range of 20. &lt;strong&gt;Arrows of the Two Moons&lt;/strong&gt;
deals necrotic + radiant damage, the most unexpected combination I’ve ever
seen. &lt;strong&gt;Spear of the Sky&lt;/strong&gt; is a selective area attack that deals fire +
lightning damage, and &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; lets him use both spells in the same
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kiss of the Two Moons&lt;/strong&gt; is his limited-use special, firing off two separate
bolts at different targets. The first does necrotic damage and weakens (save
ends); the second does radiant damage and blinds (save ends). A miss on either
attack deals half damage and inflicts the associated condition for a turn. This
recharges when he’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least there’s &lt;strong&gt;Thief of Hearts&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fort, recharge 5+), in which
he attempts to teleport someone’s heart to his hand. A hit deals damage equal to
the target’s healing surge value, and hit or miss the target is dazed (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Tectuktitlay is hit with a melee or ranged attack, he can order an
&lt;strong&gt;Involuntary Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt, choosing an ally within 4
squares. That ally shifts to be adjacent to his master, and is hit by the attack
instead of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tectuktitlay wants to stay 20 squares away from the PCs and bombard them with
spells. His at-wills are annoying enough, but what will really light a fire
under the PCs to end him as soon as possible is when Thief of Hearts lands for
the first time. I initially read it as dealing damage equal to the target’s
&lt;em&gt;bloodied&lt;/em&gt; value, but even if the actual damage is just half that, the
psychological impact is still high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party will want to get into melee with him as soon as possible, as he has no
protection against opportunity attacks, but that will be made harder by the
small army of jasuan guards and maybe up-leveled priests that will also be
there. They’ll get in the way, and their king can pull them in to take hits in
his stead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next best thing is to inflict dazes or stuns on him, since he lacks
protection against those aside from the usual elite save bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/15/wir-dscc-tectuktitlay.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/15/wir-dscc-tectuktitlay.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Nibenay</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-nibenay.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Nibenay, in his true half-draconic form, lounging on his throne.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he named his city after himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibenay seems to be a very academically-minded Sorcerer-King, which is evident
in how his transformation seems to be the furthest along among the living ones,
but he’s also kinda lazy. For about two thousand years now, he’s been holed up
in his palace-temple complex of Naggaramakam enjoying a life of luxury and study
while his priesthood took care of all those boring “running the kingdom” tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His priesthood are also his templars, which are all women and all his wives. So
this might explain why Dregoth outpaced him 1700 years ago - Nibenay still has
his vices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibebay’s highest ranking templars are known as the High Consorts. There are
five of them, each in charge of one of the city-state’s temples. The Shadow
King’s inner circle is composed of these five, plus his personal arcane
assistants, his half-monster son Dhojakt, and a group of elite goliath
warriors. Only they can enter Naggaramakam and interact directly with their
king. And only they know what Nibenay’s true draconic form looks like - he
disguises himself as a human in his rare public appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things might have continued this way forever if it wasn’t for Kalak’s
assassination and the liberation of Tyr. This kind of lit a fire under Nibenay,
and he decided to end his isolation and take a more active hand in the ruling of
his domain. This has nearly all Nibenese nobles and a large number of
lower-ranking templars in a panic because they’ve been up to a lot of
self-enriching shenanigans that they were sure their king would never notice or
care about. There’s a lot of unpleasant purges in the city’s immediate future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, Nibenay hasn’t completely abandoned his research. He seems to be
particularly interested in Athas’ distant past, and is rumored to be looking for
a way to “bring about a new Age”. That probably involves some sort of
large-scale environmental engineering, though it’s unlikely to be beneficial to
the inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three different stat blocks here, which we’ll see in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shadow-bride&quot;&gt;Shadow Bride&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of Nibenay’s lower-ranking templars. The city’s nobles tend to look
down on them and use them as pawns in their own schemes - the name “Shadow
Bride” is something of an insult. The brides resent them for this, and do
whatever dirty deeds they need in order to claw some wealth and influence for
themselves and climb the ranks of their organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Shadow Bride is a Level 13 Soldier with 130 HP and Speed 6. She fights with
an &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and with &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; at range that do
light cold+necrotic damage. She can inflict the &lt;strong&gt;Curse of the Shadow King&lt;/strong&gt; an
adjacent enemy with a minor action. This marks the enemy until the end of the
encounter and makes it grant combat advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marked enemies within 6 squares who decide to ignore the mark can be targeted
with &lt;strong&gt;Nibenay’s Retribution&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt - the bride teleports to a square
adjacent to the enemy and makes a very accurate attack vs. their Fortitude,
dealing fire+necrotic damage on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her own turns the bride can also &lt;strong&gt;Demand Penitence&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+),
targetting up to two marked enemies in a Close Burst 5, dealing psychic damage,
pulling them 4 squares, and knocking them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yup, this is a Soldier Warlock. Not a combination you see every day. The
“eldritch blast” equivalent here is distinctly secondary. She wants to bring
enemies into melee range and keep them there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-consort&quot;&gt;High Consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the five highest ranked priestess-wives of Nibenay, part of his inner
circle. Just like the city’s nobles, they jockey for position amongst
themselves, constantly engaging in backstabbing and intrigue, though they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;
loyal to their hubby and will fight at his side against meddling PCs who manage
to get that far. They will also fight to the end to protect their own
temples. In any other situation, they run away when the fight turns against
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High Consorts are Level 27 Artillery with 192 HP, Speed 6 and Low-Light
Vision. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Spears&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and with &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Blasts&lt;/strong&gt;
at range 20. These deal cold+necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special spell is &lt;strong&gt;Cage of Shadows&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10), which deals heavy force
damage and immobilizes (save ends). It recharges when they’re bloodied. They can
also practice &lt;strong&gt;Arcane Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; whenever they miss with this power or with a
Shadow Blast while allies are present within 2 squares of them. This is a free
action that inflicts 10 necrotic damage on each such ally, and lets the consort
reroll the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they get surrounded, consorts can use &lt;strong&gt;Nibenay’s Gift&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) as a
minor action, dealing 15 cold+necrotic damage to each adjacent enemy,
teleporting 6 squares, and gaining concealment for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nibenay-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;Nibenay, Sorcerer-King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibenay in his true form is a Large Natural Humanoid, and a Level 29 Elite
Controller with 532 HP. He has ground and teleport speeds of 6 and Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;strong&gt;Sorcerer King’s Guile&lt;/strong&gt; is going to ruin the day of many a PC fighter, as
it makes him not provoke opportunity attacks from making ranged and area
attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In melee, he fights with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Dragon’s Talons&lt;/strong&gt;, which damage and restrain
(save ends). At range, he uses the classic &lt;strong&gt;Ego Whip&lt;/strong&gt; (range 10), which deals
psychic damage and dazes (save ends). Yes, it’s at-will, and &lt;strong&gt;Ego Storm&lt;/strong&gt; lets
him use it twice in the same action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often, he can use &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which automatically
deals 15 necrotic damage to each adjacent enemy and lets Nibenay attack an Area
Burst 2 within 10 to deal necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text is a bit strange here, as it says Nibenay gains +1 to the burst’s
attack roll for each enemy damaged by it. I guess you roll once, count the hits,
add the bonus, and keep repeating the last two steps until he either runs out of
targets or misses someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can creaze a &lt;strong&gt;Zone of Shadows&lt;/strong&gt; that lasts for a turn and
blocks line of sight for everyone except himself. Enemies inside are
blinded. The power recharges when the zone vanishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His version of &lt;strong&gt;Arcane Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; triggers when he hits and deals damage with
either of his basic attacks. It inflicts 10 necrotic damage on each enemy within
2 squares and weakens the target of the triggering attack for a turn. It’s a
&lt;em&gt;free action&lt;/em&gt;, not a reaction or interrupt, so this happens every single time he
hits with Dragon Talon or Ego Whip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nibenay’s Demand&lt;/strong&gt; is his anti-stunlock power, a reaction that lets him
inflict 10 necrotic damage on an enemy within 5 squares and roll a save whenever
he’s subject to an effect a save can end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nibenay being an Elite instead of a Solo is not necessarily a sign that he’s
weak, but that the final fight against him will be a crowded affair. Any
surviving high consorts will surely be here, as will any other epic level
assistants and guards the GM wants to add to make the battle a worthy challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Andropinis, Nibenay doesn’t have powers that boost or benefit from his
allies, but at least he doesn’t get in their way either - his area attack is
selective. The High Consorts, however, &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; likely to step on each others’ toes
because their version of Arcane Defiling targets allies instead of enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/12/wir-dscc-nibenay.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/12/wir-dscc-nibenay.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Mearedes</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-mearedes.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Mearedes in her jungle home.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mearedes is a goliath druid, the self-appointed Sentinel of Shault. Shault, in
turn, is a hidden island paradise in the Sea of Silt, one of the greenest areas
remaining in the Tyr Region, largely thanks to the efforts of Mearedes and her
disciples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those disciples are the giants Shakka and Shola, and the dwarf Hippolexes. They,
their master, and a few volunteers from the local stone and beast giant
communities intercept any strangers making landfall on Shault, and demand they
subject themselves to a ritual that prevents them from ever speaking about the
island to others. Those who refuse are killed. As you might imagine, very few
people ever return from Shault, and those who do aren’t saying anything about
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Mearedes has an age-lined face, she’s still as spry as a young goliath,
and has received the respectful title of “Little Grandmother” from the local
giants. Those who help her and her friends fight off threats to Shault will find
her to be a stalwart ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mearedes, as mentioned, is a Goliath. She’s also a Level 18 Controller with 176
HP, Speed 6, and a lot of Classic Druid Powers, which might look very exotic to
typical Athasian characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She fights in melee with a &lt;strong&gt;Thorny Staff&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and slows for a turn;
and at range with &lt;strong&gt;Flame Seeds&lt;/strong&gt; that deal fire damage, and inflict 5 fire
damage on any enemy that enters one of the squares adjacent to the target or
starts their turn there before the end of her next turn. This means &lt;em&gt;the target&lt;/em&gt;
can take this additional damage if they try to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s the expected &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Vines&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), a fireball-sized
area attack that damages and then creates a zone of hazardous difficult terrain
that lasts for the rest of the encounter. It damages and slows those caught
inside. Yes, this is a recharge power, so the battlemap will become rougher and
rougher as time goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, Mearedes can assume the &lt;strong&gt;Form of the Ghost Panther&lt;/strong&gt; for a
turn and shift 3 squares. In this form, she cannot attack but gains +4 Speed,
insubstantial, and phasing. She can end this as a free action or sustain it for
another turn as a minor action. And she also has the Goliath &lt;strong&gt;Stone’s
Endurance&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, which lets her gain Resistance 10 to all damage for
a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mearedes will almost always be accompanied by her three apprentices (whose stats
are left as an exercise for the reader) and by as many stone and beast giants
you need to make the fight interesting. She’s also clearly meant to be more of
an ally than an enemy here, so she or some of her apprentices could also tag
along with the group for a short while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/09/wir-dscc-mearedes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/09/wir-dscc-mearedes.html</guid>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Maetan of House Lubar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-maetan-lubar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Maetan Lubar, posing for the cover of a business magazine.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maetan is the current head of House Lubar, one of Urik’s wealthiest noble
houses. He’s been prepared for leadership since childhood, though his time came
much sooner than expected due to the untimely death of his parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The house makes its fortunes through commerce and through the ownership of many
profitable fields outside of Urik’s walls. The work on those is performed by
slaves, and their administration by junior house members. Senior leadership like
Maetan has loftier concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maetan, for example, is busy petitioning Hamanu for the opportunity to lead a
large army against the recently freed city of Tyr, as he has a story of success
against Urik’s smaller enemies and wishes to attain new heights of glory and
favor with the sorcerer-king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably relates to the 2e Prism Pentad adventures, which saw the PCs take
part in a battle against Urik’s forces. If this happens in your 4e campaign,
Maetan will likely be at the head of those forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maetan Lubar is a human, and a Level 16 Elite Controller with 302 HP. He fights
using a combination of the fencing skills and psychic powers taught to him from
a tender age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fencing is distinctly second fiddle here: just a basic &lt;strong&gt;Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; attack
that does level-appropriate damage with no riders. Maetan wants to stay a bit
outside of melee range and use his many psychic abilities instead. He’s a
telepath, so all of his powers target Will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serpent’s Kiss&lt;/strong&gt; is a range 20 basic attack that targets up to 2 creatures,
deals psychic damage and makes the target grant combat advantage for a
turn. &lt;strong&gt;Insidious Worm&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will range 10 attack that can only be used
against targets granting him combat advantage; it deals psychic damage and
forces the target to make a melee basic attack against another target of
Maetan’s choice. His usual routine would involve alternating these two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coils of Lubar&lt;/strong&gt; is an area 1 within 10 attack that deals psychic damage and
restrains (save ends). It deals 10 psychic damage as an aftereffect of the
save. It recharges when he uses &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augment&lt;/strong&gt;, a power that triggers when
Maetan hits with one of his two ranged at-wills and further boosts their
damage. And this, in turn, recharges when he’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His two final powers are &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Intrusion&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action ranged attack
that dominates on a hit (save ends). This recharges when he’s first
bloodied. And the &lt;strong&gt;Mind Fog&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, which triggers when he’s hit by
a melee attack, affects a Close Burst 3, deals psychic damage on a hit, and
forces the targets to treat him as invisible (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess this might be a typical example of an evil noble type. The book says
Maetan will always be accompanied by a sizable honor guard, and in a fight he
will try to use his powers to make things easier for those guards (all of them
are selective, so he has no risk of hitting his allies). It also says that
despite all of his psionic might, Maetan is still very proud and overconfident
of his sword skills, so he might end up letting a PC get too close to him
because of this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/08/wir-dscc-maetan-lubar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/08/wir-dscc-maetan-lubar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
