<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:01:52 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:01:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dragon, Volcanic</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-dragon-volcanic.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volcanic dragons were created by Vezzuvu, the Living Mountain. The petitioners
who approached this primordial were &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt;. You see, dragons were made in Io’s
image, but Io’s demise proved he was weak. Therefore, these dragons thought,
&lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; were weak, and this realization felt like an insult to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vezzuvu promised that if the dragons bathed in the boiling magma of his domain,
their weak flesh would be burned away and replaced with a truly strong body. His
petitioners obeyed and dove in. The survivors became volcanic dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All was well with the volcanics for a time, but then their old pride and sense
of entitlement began to gnaw at them again. Where their new bodies truly
stronger? Had they been given all the power they were promised, all the power
they surely deserved? When they concluded they hadn’t, they turned on their
former master and went their own way. Their history from this point on is filled
with instances of volcanic dragons allying with servants of either the gods or
the primordials for a time, only to betray them a short time later. In our
narrative present, everyone knows an alliance with these beasts is likely to end
in sudden but inevitable betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical volcanic dragon’s temperament is like that of a red, but worse. They
make a show of craving treasure and rulership over a territory, but what they
truly crave is destruction. In other words, volcanic dragons love burning stuff,
especially flesh. It makes them feel good. They like the company of other
fire-elemental beings with similar dispositions, but any alliance they make is
temporary at best. They live inside volcanoes and on other similar burning
landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Volcanic Dragons follow the same general format of the other catastrophics
you could argue they are right about getting a bad deal from Vezzuvus. They’re
Elemental Magical Beasts with the Dragon and Fire keywords, Darkvision, and a
Clumsy Flight speed equal to their ground speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;volcanic-dragon-wyrmling&quot;&gt;Volcanic Dragon Wyrmling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyrmlings are Medium Level 5 Brutes with 77 HP and Speed 6. They’re surrounded
by an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Noxious Fumes&lt;/strong&gt; that deals 3 poison damage to enemies who
end their turns inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; are weaker than those of most brutes,
but the bite inflicts ongoing fire damage and the claws strip the target of all
fire resistance until the start of the dragon’s next turn. As usual &lt;strong&gt;wyrmling
fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to use both attacks in the same action while bloodied. Use the
claw first!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hit by a fire attack, the wyrmling uses a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Flare&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction,
causing each enemy inside the dragon’s aura to take 5 fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;young-volcanic-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Volcanic Dragon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young’uns are Large Level 10 Elite Brutes with 264 HP and speed 8. They have all
the same attacks as the wyrmling, but their Wyrmling Fury upgrades to a full
&lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. Their numbers are also bigger, of course, and they gain two
new attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Growing Heat&lt;/strong&gt; is their “disaster” ability. When activated with a minor
action, it makes their Noxious Fumes aura grow to size 3, then to size 5 on the
next turn, and then explode in the turn after that. This explosion targets
Reflex and deals both immediate and ongoing fire damage. After it resolves the
dragon’s aura shrinks to its original size and the power recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon can also create a &lt;strong&gt;Lava Vent&lt;/strong&gt;, an Area Burst 1 zone that lasts
until the end of the encounter and deals 5 fire damage to anyone who enters or
starts their turn there. This recharges once the dragon is first bloodied, so
each dragon in the fight can create 2 vents total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-age-categories&quot;&gt;Other Age Categories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adults&lt;/strong&gt; are Level 15 Elite Brutes with 363 HP, and have all the same
abilities of a young dragon with bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elders&lt;/strong&gt; are Huge Level 20 Elite Brutes with 468 HP, and likewise have all the
same abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancients&lt;/strong&gt; are Huge Level 25 Elite Brutes with 574 HP. They have all the same
abilities as elders and are also able to create a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Fissure&lt;/strong&gt; in addition
to the lava vents. This works like a temporary wall of fire (and it’s a wall 6
pattern) that deals 20 fire damage to anyone who tries to touch or cross it. It
only lasts for a turn but it’s a minor action and a recharge 5+ attack instead
of an encounter power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volcanic dragons might be weaker than traditional ones, but they’re much better
at subverting expectations. Typical PCs might see that it’s a fire monster and
load up on fire resistance effects, only to realize the dragon’s aura deals
&lt;em&gt;poison&lt;/em&gt; damage and it can remove fire resistance with its claws. Also, the bulk
of the damage from its basic attacks is untyped, further limiting the usefulness
of fire resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, paranoia and entitlement seem to be their strongest personality
traits. They’re hard to deal with because they always feel they’re not getting
their due. Even when a deal is fair and happens as promised, they’ll probably
feel the other party got one over on them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/17/dragon-volcanic.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/17/dragon-volcanic.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dragon, Earthquake</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-dragon-earthquake.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earthquake dragons were created by Balcoth, the Groaning King. The petitioners
who approached this Earth primordial were terrified by the death of Io, and were
willing to swear loyalty to anyone who could protect them. Balcoth agreed, and
fulfilled his promise by swallowing the dragons up and keeping them inside his
furnace-like belly, where they “cooked” and were changed by his essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balcoth would vomit up a few earthquake dragons when he needed their
service. When the primordial was beheaded and slain during the Dawn War, the
rest of his dragons escaped through the wound and into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, Earthquake dragons are extremely into the whole “living
disaster” thing. When they settle down somewhere, the surrounding region is soon
wracked by tremors of increasing intensity and duration. The dragon feeds on the
people killed by these tremors, and will sometimes destroy a city on purpose
just because they can. They lair in the ruins for months, digesting their prey
and enjoying the view of the ruins until they grow tired of them and fly away to
look for another place to devastate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike their blizzard cousins, earthquakes are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; team players. They’ll form
temporary alliances with inedible creatures (mostly earth-themed), and can
sometimes be bribed into service by mortals, but these arrangements never last
long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dragons aren’t great fliers, but they can swim through earth and rock as
if it was water. They hunt by suppressing their earthquake aura and stalking
their prey from underground. When they attack, they make a spectacular entry and
fight with all of their powers, though they usually retreat back underground
rather than fighting to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earthquake Dragons follow the same general plan as Blizzards. They’re Elemental
Magical Beasts with the Dragon and Earth keywords. They have Darkvision,
Tremorsense, and both burrow and clumsy flight speeds that are about half of
their ground speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;earthquake-dragon-wyrmling&quot;&gt;Earthquake Dragon Wyrmling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Medium Level 4 Soldier with 58 HP, representing the youngest dragon
that can be a threat in combat. Their speed is 6 (burrow 2, clumsy flight
2). They project a Quaking Earth aura (1) with a very “soldierly” effect: if an
enemy inside the aura makes an attack that doesn’t include the dragon as a
target, the enemy falls prone and takes 5 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wyrmling’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; basic attacks do physical damage without
riders, and &lt;strong&gt;Wyrmling Fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make both attacks in the same action
while it’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they have a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Quake&lt;/strong&gt; ability that triggers when they’re knocked
prone or subjected to forced movement. It knocks all enemies inside the dragon’s
aura prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-earthquake-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Earthquake Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young dragons are Large Level 9 Elite Soldiers with 206 HP. Their ground speed
increases to 8, their burrow and flight speeds to 4. They have all the same
abilities as a wyrmling, with bigger numbers. They replace Wyrmling Fury with a
proper &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; and add two new powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earthen Maw&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) is a melee attack that does more damage than a
basic bite and restains the target (save ends). After the first save the target
is instead petrified! A save still ends this, but the target is entirely unable
to act until they make that save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their “disaster” power is &lt;strong&gt;Rising Tremors&lt;/strong&gt;, which follows the same pattern
seen for blizzard dragons. When it’s activated with a minor action, it increases
the dragon’s aura size to 3. At the end of the next turn, the aura increases
again to 5. And at the end of the turn after that, the dragon makes a Close
Burst 5 attack vs. Reflex. This one deals physical damage, knocks targets prone,
and prevents them from standing back up (save ends). After the attack, the aura
resets and this power recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-age-categories&quot;&gt;Other Age Categories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adults&lt;/strong&gt; are Level 14 Elite Soldiers with 288 HP, and have all the same
abilities with bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elders&lt;/strong&gt; are Huge Level 19 Elite Soldiers with 374 HP, and again have all the
same abilities with bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancients&lt;/strong&gt; are Level 24 Elite Soldiers with 456 HP, and gain Threatening
Reach 3. They once again have all the same abilities as younger dragons with
bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m surprised the dragons in this entry are still marked as Unaligned despite
being a lot more actively destructive and cruel than blizzard dragons. I’d have
thought “I exist to satisfy my twin urges to destroy and devour” would rate a
Chaotic Evil alignment. Of course, you can go the other way and give them more
flexible personalities and more varied motivations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, earthquake dragons are very good at knocking people down and
&lt;em&gt;keeping&lt;/em&gt; them down, so they pair really well with melee lurkers and skirmishers
whose attacks are more powerful when they have combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/16/dragon-earthquake.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/16/dragon-earthquake.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dragon, Blizzard</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-dragon-blizzard.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blizzard Dragons were created by Umboras, Lord of the Rimefire. The dragon
petitioners who approached this primordial were the coldest-hearted among their
number. Umboras took them to the coldest reaches of the Elemental Chaos and
entombed them there for a year and a day while he worked his magic on them. When
they emerged, they were blizzard dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umboras had a specific goal in mind when he did this. He had been an ally of the
winter goddess Khala, who shared with him the goal of freezing the world
solid. However, the Raven Queen had just usurped Khala and claimed the domain of
winter from her, so Umboras was out for revenge. He created blizzard dragons to
help transport his troops to the Raven Queen’s new home of Letherna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Queen, however, was smarter than him. She retreated to the labyrinthine
astral domain of Pandemonium, and used its twisty little passages (all alike) to
separate Umboras from his main forces and lock him in one of the domain’s empty
vaults. He’s still there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blizzard dragons scattered after their master was imprisoned. Some stayed in
Pandemonium, some returned to the Elemental Chaos, some even went to the coldest
places of the world. For obvious reasons, though, you’ll rarely find one of them
in the Shadowfell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blizzard dragons don’t usually have grand plans of their own, and are usually
content to freeze and sculpt their territories. However, they’re surprisingly
good team players and can often be found allied to other creatures of compatible
disposition, helping them achieve their goals. This varies from the usual frost
giants and ice archons to liches or winter fey, depending on the individual. And
they’re always down for breaking a primordial out of prison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blizzard dragons are Elemental Magical Beasts with the Cold and Dragon
keywords. They have Darkvision, Ice Walk, and a clumsy flight speed. All of
their attacks do cold damage, even the bites and claws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blizzard-dragon-wyrmling&quot;&gt;Blizzard Dragon Wyrmling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyrmlings are Medium, making them the smallest dragons I’ve seen in my Let’s
Read so far. They’re Level 2 Controllers with 38 HP. They have ground and air
speeds of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that’s right, wyrmlings are &lt;em&gt;regulars&lt;/em&gt;. This means they’ll almost always
be found cooperating with a sizable group of other monsters. The most obvious
candidates are their clutch-siblings, but they’re smart enough to strike an
alliance with lots of other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are surrounded by an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Freezing Wind&lt;/strong&gt;. Enemies that end their
turn inside are slid 1 square. When hit by a cold attack, the wyrmling reacts
with &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Flurry&lt;/strong&gt;, immediately sliding all enemies inside its aura 1
square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; immobilizes, and their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; slide the target 1 square on a
hit. While they’re bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Wyrmling Fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to spend an action to
attack with both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-blizzard-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Blizzard Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young’uns grow to size Large, and become Level 7 Elite Controllers with 166
HP. Their speed increases to 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have all of the wyrmling’s abilities with a few differences and
additions. The simplest one is that Wyrmling Flurry is replaced by a standard
Double Attack ability, and their claws slide 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other dragons, blizzards don’t have a breath weapon. Instead, when
they’re hit by a melee attack, a high-pressure blast of frozen liquid bursts
forth from the wound. This is written as a reaction named &lt;strong&gt;Chill Rebuke&lt;/strong&gt;, a
Close Blast 5 vs. Fortitude. It deals cold damage and slows on a hit (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also where the “living disaster” mechanic kicks in. Here it’s an ability
named &lt;strong&gt;Rising Winds&lt;/strong&gt;. Once this is activated as a minor action, it causes the
size of the dragon’s Freezing Wind aura to grow to 3. At the start of the
dragon’s next turn, it automatically expands again, to 5. And at the start of
the following turn, the dragon makes a Close Burst 5 attack vs. Fortitude, with
a hit dealing cold damage, slowing, and blinding the targets. Once the attack is
resolved, the aura returns to is initial size of 1 and Rising Winds recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adultelder-blizzard-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult/Elder Blizzard Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults and elders are identical to young’uns, with bigger numbers. Adults are
Level 12 Elite Controllers with 252 HP, and Elders are Level 17 with 338
HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Huge and can move at speed 10. They can slide enemies 3 squares with
their claws and 2 squares with their auras. Their Rising Winds attack restrains
instead of immobilizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-blizzard-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Blizzard Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancients are Huge in size, and are Level 22 Elite Controllers with 422
HP. They’re almost idendical to elders, with bigger numbers. They also have a
new encounter power named &lt;strong&gt;Deep Freeze&lt;/strong&gt; that works kinda like a breath weapon,
though I guess it’s more of a high-pressure blood ejection, since the dragon
must be bloodied to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ability attacks enemies in a Close Burst 5, targetting Fortitude. A hit
deals cold damage, immobilizes, and imposes a -5 penalty to Fortitude (save ends
both). A miss deals half damage and imposes the same penalty for a single
turn. All of the dragon’s non-basic attacks target Fortitude, so this penalty
makes it a lot more dangerous while it lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blizzard dragons feel like they slide into the exact same niche as white
dragons, with a similar cold theme and a similarly unpleasant
personality. Blizzards are smarter and not technically evil, but they still make
for terrible neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like dragons and like cold themed creatures without
actually using any of the signature mechanics for either! This is a dragon that
does not have a breath attack or a fear aura, and a cold creature that is not
immune to cold. It’s fascinating!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/13/dragon-blizzard.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/13/dragon-blizzard.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dragon, Catastrophic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve talked a lot about dragons, and why I like their 4e implementation, over
the course of these book readings. Sometimes it feels like no big D&amp;amp;D bestiary
is complete without introducing a new dragon subtype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual talked about the classic chromatics, which were then updated
on the Monster Vault. You can see what I wrote about them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 talked about the equally classic metallics, and you can
read what I wrote about them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 3 introduces the much less famous and much newer Catastrophic
Dragons. I believe they are new to 4e, though they might also have shown up in
some late supplement for a previous edition. You might already have noticed I’m
a bit lazy when it comes to researching monster publication histories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m sure about is that these are the first 4e dragons that have the
“correct” math from the start. They’re also notable for being generally &lt;em&gt;weaker&lt;/em&gt;
than chromatics and metallics despite the impressive name. Your typical
catastrophic dragon is an Elite monster rather than a Solo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in previous articles about dragons, when the god Io was split in two
during the Dawn War his followers also split along ideological lines based on
which of the two new deities they preferred: Tiamat the greedy or Bahamut the
just. I imagine the initial decision was easy for most of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most, but not for all. Some of Io’s orphaned followers were gripped by fear
when they saw how easily their lord had been slain, and they decided that the
best way to survive would be to beseech the Primordials for protection and join
their side of the Dawn War. These turncoats were transformed by the “blessings”
of the Primordials into the first catastrophic dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Primordials were defeated most surviving catastrophics scattered across
the multiverse and turned to their own selfish purposes. The typical
catastrophic in the present day is somewhat less formidable than a chromatic,
but more outwardly destructive. They tend to live in extremely hostile
environments that befit their individual natures, and from the point of view of
surrounding civilians their behavior looks a lot like that of a natural
disaster: they occasionally emerge to wreak havoc and destruction on people and
their environment, and then return to their lairs for an unknown amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legends and myths dating back to the Dawn War tell of catastrophic dragons of
immense size and power, capable of sinking continents and destroying entire
astral domains. No one knows whether these stories are true, and even the gods
refuse to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dragons&quot;&gt;The Dragons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry is structured a lot like previous dragon entries, with each type of
dragon presented getting stat blocks for all of its age categories. That’s about
where it stops, though. Catastrophic dragons are more like personified natural
disasters than like the traditional dragons we saw in previous books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones we see here are clumsy fliers, and even lack the traditional breath
weapon! Instead, they’re surrounded by an aura that’s like a miniature version
of the disaster they embody. During a fight, this aura grows in size as time
passes and then explodes in a, well, catastrophic manner before returning to its
initial size and beginning the cycle anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having bodies largely made up of elemental matter, these dragons lack
any elemental resistances. Instead, damage of their associated type triggers a
reaction ability that punishes the attacker in some form. I would however say
that they are immune to &lt;em&gt;environmental&lt;/em&gt; damage of their associated type even
though that’s not made explicit in their stat blocks, because it just wouldn’t
do for a blizzard dragon to die of frostbite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last major mechanical difference between these dragons and their
predecessors is that catastrophics are Elites instead of Solos. Whether this is
just bad luck or a punishment from the gods, it means that fights against them
will include a bigger supporting cast of other monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more age categories here than in the previous books: Wyrmling, Young,
Adult, Elder and Ancient. Wyrmlings are Medium in size, and are regular monsters
instead of Elites. Young’uns and Adults are Large, and the last two are Huge. I
guess a wyrmling isn’t quite a “baby dragon”, but I’d still be a bit wary of
placing them as enemies, as I commented earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their thematic link to natural disasters and their destructive demeanor,
catastrophic dragons are typically Unaligned, which says interesting things
about their mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/11/dragon-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/11/dragon-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Vizier</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-vizier.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember seeing these specific devils in earlier editions, but that
might just mean they were from a late 3e book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the first silver-tongued manipulative devil we’ve seen, not by far,
but it seems to be the most specialized one. Vizier devils are rarely found in
the Nine Hells - they’re always out in the world serving and tempting ambitious
mortals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all other MM3 devils, the lore text on this one is a bit obsessed with sin
and with the idea that sinners going to hell and becoming devils is a natural
occurrence, which isn’t really something that was present in earlier 4e monster
books. As we saw in previous readings, in 4e Hell is a cosmic aberration. Devils
don’t come from sinners, and they get their souls either by having mortals sign
contracts or through force. Those souls get used as currency, fuel, and magic
item ingredients, not to make new devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes these creatures members of Hell’s sales department, just like
imps. The main difference is that viziers are stronger, smarter, and bolder in
their suggestions. I imagine having a bound vizier devil instead of a mere bound
imp is a major status symbol among deluded diabolists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re into the sin thing (which was the standard in 3e and maybe earlier),
they you can go with the lore in this entry that says that vizier devils are
genuinely helpful at first but then begin to steer their “masters” down more
evil and sinful paths with the goal of making them go to Hell after they die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you prefer the standard 4e lore, then the main difference is that vizier
devils will try to get their masters to sign a soul contract either as a
pre-condition to their service, or as an “upsell” in exchange for greater power
or greater hellish support at some point after they begin their work as
advisors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 4e-style, contract-based vizier devil is ironically less treacherous than the
temptation-based 3e-style one. Their mortal bosses are likely to &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; be
evil in the first place, so they need little tempting. And after the contract is
signed there is even less need for deception, as the devil already got what it
wanted and only needs to fulfill its part of the bargain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vizier devils look like tieflings with slightly exaggerated fiendish features,
and that actually makes them good at blending in. In combat, they’re
spellcasters with a repertoire focusing on fire and charm magic. They always
have a contingency plan or two to escape if the fight goes against them, and
never fight to the death if they can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vizier devils are Medium Immortal Humanoids (devils), and Level 7 Controllers
(leaders). They have Resist Fire 10, Darkvision, a ground speed of 6, and a
teleport speed of 4. That’s more or less the same set of traits as a legion
devil, so maybe they’re related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wield &lt;strong&gt;Scepters&lt;/strong&gt; that work as implements and can be used to bash people
in melee. This does physical damage and slides the target 1 square on a
hit. Their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Helfire Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; that does fire damage and
forces the target to grant combat advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Word of Command&lt;/strong&gt; at will, which lets them choose a
creature within 2 squares, slide it 3 squares and have it make a free melee
basic attack against another creature of the devil’s choice. The text says “a
creature”, which means this can target either an ally or an enemy with this. And
the thing is an &lt;em&gt;effect&lt;/em&gt;, not an &lt;em&gt;attack&lt;/em&gt;, which means it works
automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Word of Command does require a standard action, but it’s still a good choice if
the vizier is accompanied by big bruisers or if the party includes PCs with good
basic attacks. It’s even better if the party includes some of those Essentials
martial classes, since they’re all about having awesome melee basic attacks with
all sorts of special riders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vizier’s leader-ish abilities are &lt;strong&gt;Hellfire Enchantment&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Infernal
Advice&lt;/strong&gt;. The first is a minor action that grants an ally within 5 squares a +5
fire damage bonus to all its melee attacks until the end of its next turn. The
other is a reaction that allows an ally to reroll a missed attack with a +2
bonus. Hellfire Enchantment is an awesome ability to use on allies that have
multiple attacks on their turns! All of them will get the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not gonna lie, these devils feel a bit redundant. Their concept is exactly
the same as all the other sly manipulators, and the only difference is their
power level. They’re the “level 7 sly manipulator”, where imps are “level 3” an
the others are stronger. I also don’t like the emphasis on sin in this book,
because it’s a 3e-ism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, a vizier devil’s stats make it an interesting monster to fight and
they can easily be reskinned into infernal warlord types. They go really well
with melee bruiser monsters that can make multiple attacks. Those can be part of
the entourage of their mortal bosses, or other devils.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/10/devil-vizier.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/10/devil-vizier.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Swarm</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-swarm.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another devil that breaks the “morphology” guidelines, but it’s kind of
unavoidable this time. After all, they’re associated with Baalzebul, Lord of the
Flies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each swarm devil is a singular mind controlling the bodies of an entire swarm of
acidic fiendish flies. According to the book, they’re formed when an angel is
caught lying to its divine master and is torn apart as punishment. The angel’s
soul falls to the Hells and the bits of its body become flies. They roam the
stagnant pools of Maladomni, the Seventh Hell, eternally starving but unable to
die. They can only leave when their master orders them on a mission, which makes
them very happy because it allows them to fly free and eat people for the
duration. It helps that “eating people” usually &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the mission. It’s what
swarm devils do best, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swarm Devils fight by just kinda walking into enemies’ spaces and letting their
flies do the work, and by spewing flies at people they can’t easily reach that
way. As swarms, they’re hard to fight unless you have area-effect weapons and
spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are Large Immortal Magical Beasts (Devil, Swarm) and Level 18
Skirmishers with 174 HP. They have Darkvision and a flight speed of 10 (hover),
and 20 acid resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have the standard swarm traits on top of that: half damage and
immunity to forced movement from melee and ranged attacks; Vulnerable 10 to
close and area attacks; a swarm aura; the ability to occupy the same space as
other characters; and the ability to squeeze through small openings without
slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) deals 10 acid damage to enemies caught inside. I
think being in the same space as the swarm also counts as being inside the
aura. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; do no immediate damage, and inflict 10 ongoing acid
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can channel &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Curses&lt;/strong&gt; through their acid, targetting someone taking
ongoing acid damage with a ranged attack that deals psychic damage and inflicts
a -2 penalty to attacks for a turn. Twice per encounter they can &lt;strong&gt;Spew Flies&lt;/strong&gt;
in a Close Burst 3, inflicting ongoing acid damage and forcing targets to grant
combat advantage (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “just walking into people” tactic is represented by &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Shift&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+), in which it shifts its speed and deals 15 acid damage to anyone
they pass through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good tactic for them is to move in, hit a few people with the slam or spew,
use Swarm Shift to move out of the scrum and keep flinging curses at anyone
who’s melting. Reapply the acid as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fly-themed fiends for the Lord of the Flies, nothing unexpected. The
acid/psychic damage mechanic is mildly interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/07/devil-swarm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/07/devil-swarm.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Slime</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-slime.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another one of those monsters that’s all about blurring the lines
between fiends. These monsters are devils, but they break the design rule that
says devils have a human-like appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slime Devils are amorphous oozes, though unlike most “true” oozes they’re
sapient and rather smart. They probably originated in some past edition as well,
because they’re the second devil said to be formed from the souls of dead
sinners (which is not a 4e thing). They arise from the mixture of the toxic mud
in the swamps of Minauros with the hatred that seeps from the souls of corrupt
inquisitors who are stuck there. Their abilities make them adept interrogators
and torturers, since they can read the minds of people they envelop and inflict
intense pain on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re often summoned to act in this capacity by villains in the world, so
they’ll be found alongside those villains’ guards and jailers. In Hell, they
travel with burlier devils, and with those whose controller-y powers can hold
enemies down to be engulfed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Slime Devil is a Medium Immortal Humanoid (Devil, Ooze), and a Level 16 Lurker
with 123 HP. The lore does say their base form is vaguely humanoid, but still
I’d probably classify them as Magical Beasts instead. Either way, it doesn’t
change their other stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have Darkvision, ground and swim speeds of 6, and Resist Acid 20 instead of
the usual devil fire resistance. Their &lt;strong&gt;Mercurial Body&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows them to
ignore difficult terrain and not provoke opportunity attacks when
moving. They’re still vulnerable to a Fighter’s Combat Challenge or other
similar abilities, but non-defenders can’t hold them in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Caustic Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude and does acid
damage. They can also stretch into &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Tendrils&lt;/strong&gt; that attack up to three
creatures at Reach 3, deal immediate and ongoing acid damage, and pull them 2
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slime devil’s main trick is &lt;strong&gt;Diabolical Engulfment&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets reflex
and grabs on a hit. Grabbed targets are dazed and take ongoing 10 acid damage
while the grab lasts. The creature occupies the same space as the victim, and
pulls the victim along when it moves. Attacks that hit the slime devil deal half
damage to it and half damage to the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action (1/round), the slime devil can use &lt;strong&gt;Scour the Mind&lt;/strong&gt; on its
grabbed victim. This targets Will. On a hit, the devil poses a question to the
victim, who must choose between answering truthfully and taking psychic
damage. The amount of damage is the same as a basic attack, which is a lot for a
minor-action power. The creature can do this and still use its basic attack to
fight off the victim’s friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, kinda meh. I’m not a fan of bringing the old “fiends come from the
souls of sinners” cliches back into D&amp;amp;D. They’re more interesting mechanically,
because I love attack powers that force PCs to choose between two bad outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/03/devil-slime.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/03/devil-slime.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Rage</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-rage.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like the Monster Manual 3 is all about blurring the lines between
fiends. We have a devil who became a demon lord, demons who became devils, and
now a devil who behaves like a demon. I haven’t run into rage devils before. If
they appeared in previous editions, it must have been in a late MM or a
specialized supplement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Rage Devil is what happens when you take a standard Hell Knight and inject
demon ichor into it. They’re hulking brutes who are constantly angry and delight
in carnage. In other words, they’re pretty much demons, or they would be if
their flesh wasn’t bound with empowered Supernal sigils that keep them pointed
in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are the result of an infernal experiment to create more powerful
shock troops to throw into the meatgrinder of the Blood War. They’re actually a
little weaker than a standard hell knight, making them a bit of a failed
experiment. Maybe they adapted the process for the mass-produced version so it
works on legion devils instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rage devils are used as heavy elements attached to legion devil forces, and are
often placed under the command of hell knights. In their free time, these things
roam Avernus in search of demon stragglers or anyone else they can get away with
smashing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rage Devils are Large Immortal Humanoids (Devils), and Level 11 Brutes with 138
HP. They have Darkvision and Resist Fire 20, but they can’t fly. Their ground
speed is 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These devils are heavily armored and fight with &lt;strong&gt;Disrupting Mauls&lt;/strong&gt; whose basic
attacks strip all of the target’s resistances for a turn! They have a special
technique named &lt;strong&gt;Demonscourge Crush&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), which deals the same
damage as a basic attack, weakens, and strips all resistances (save ends
both). Another maneuver is &lt;strong&gt;Maul Storm&lt;/strong&gt; an at-will Close Burst 2 that deals
some damage and pushes targets 3 squares. If they’re bloodied, they’re also
knocked prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Blood Rage&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait makes them deal extra damage on all attacks
against bloodied opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rage devils are indeed an excellent weapon both against demons and against other
devils, as well as any creature type that relies on high elemental
resistances. Behavior-wise they tend to be on the shallower end of the &lt;em&gt;demon&lt;/em&gt;
cliche pool, with only their binding rituals preventing them from turning on
their devilish masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said above, I’d probably say most rage devils are modified legion devils,
because baseline Hell Knights are both stronger and smarter than these things,
so turning a Hell Knight into a Rage Devil is a bit of a waste.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/03/devil-rage.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/03/devil-rage.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Passion</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-passion.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first time I come across passion devils, but they give me strong 3e
vibes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want to employ seductive and manipulative devils in your villainous
schemes, but feel that succubi are too nice? Fierna, archdevil ruler of
Phlegethos, sure did! In order to fulfill her very specific needs, she created
Passion Devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason these creatures give me a strong 3e-or-earlier vibe is that they feel
like the sort of grid-filling exercise that was very common in those
games. Succubi were considered demons back then, so when they needed to fill the
“seductive manipulator” niche on the devil side they created a completely new
creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 4e, passion devils are kinda like a specialized succubus variant tied to
Fierna. As incarnations of her vanity, they’re made in her image but always have
some extra imperfection in their forms so their mistress remains the fairest of
them all. They’re sent to infiltrate mortal societies just like a succubus, and
they’re also used to replace the leadership of Fierna’s own cults so she can
keep tabs on them. When used as official emissaries and ambassadors, they are
often protected by a unit of bearded devil bodyguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference between a baseline succubus and a passion devil is that the
latter have serious anger management issues. When their tempers flare, their
disguises tend to melt away as the passion devil abandons all subtlety and
resorts to force. This is obviously what happens when the PCs thwart their
plans, but it could also happen if they run out of patience while trying to
employ standard succubus strategies. At least their fire powers make them better
combatants than succubi when the jig is up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are Medium Immortal Humanoids with the Devil keyword, and Level
16 Controllers. They have Darkvision, Resist Fire 20, and move at speed 6 on the
ground or in the air. A pretty standard devil toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They project a charm aura (1) that makes others see them as a &lt;strong&gt;Object of
Desire&lt;/strong&gt; and take a -2 penalty to saves against dazing effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex and does fire damage. They
can also be “gentler” and employ a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Touch&lt;/strong&gt; that does less damage and
dominates for a turn. The ability that combos with their aura is &lt;strong&gt;Beckoning
Whispers&lt;/strong&gt;, a non-damaging attack against Will that pulls targets 5 squares and
dazes them (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally they have an area attack named &lt;strong&gt;Passion’s Flames&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Burst 3
that deals fire damage and forces any dominated enemies it hits to make melee
basic attacks against targets of the devil’s choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the passion devil can &lt;strong&gt;change shape&lt;/strong&gt; to appear like a
Medium humanoid. The DC to see through the disguise is a respectable 36, but
it’s less stable than that of a succubus and ends when the devil attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a Succubus Plus with a temper. Lore-wise they’re Fierna’s trademark
servants, so they fit into any adventure where she’s the main enemy. Otherwise
you might want to use leveled-up succubi from the Monster Vault, or reskin these
into succubi as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/29/devil-passion.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/29/devil-passion.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Hellwasp</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-hellwasp.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember seeing hell wasps before, but they sound like the sort of
monster that might have debuted in 3e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In past editions the Blood War was this eternal alignment-based conflict, but
here it’s part of Asmodeus’ safety net. You see, the other gods don’t
like Asmodeus very much, both because he’s an evil asshole and because he got
his position by murdering a popular non-evil deity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the measures he took to prevent them from ganging up on him was to commit
the considerable armies of Hell to the task of containing the demons of the
Abyss. As we mentioned before, demons are too busy with infighting to launch
regular invasions on the rest of the universe, but when they do manage to
briefly get their shit together and spill out, they find a few legions of devils
waiting to fight them. Hell also launches occasional raids into the Abyss to
prevent demons from organizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a war that rages on eternally, but a series of sporadic conflicts
that flare up whenever one of the two sides feels a bit stronger. The gods lets
Asmodeus be because he provides a valuable service, and because providing that
service also serves as a check on his power. Asmodeus and his underlings in the
meantime keep enacting diabolic schemes to acquire more power in an attempt to
dominate the other gods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most enthusiastic participants in the Blood Wars seems to be Glasya,
Asmodeus’ daughter. Because of this she tends to be involved in stories where
demons and devils switch sides, corresponding to her failures and successes. We
already heard about Graz’zt the devil who became a demon lord. And now we get to
hear about a whole species of demon who became devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellwasps were once a species of demon related to the insectile mezzodemons,
servants of a wasp-like demon lord whose name was lost to time. Glasya fought
and killed this demon in one of her raids, and its spawn immediately swore
allegiance to her. She took the lot of them to Hell and converted them into
devils. Now they inhabit the Garden of Delights, a region of Malbolge. As loyal
servants of Glasya, they can be found alongside any of her other servants or
allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellwasps are Medium Immortal Magical Beasts (devils). They have Darkvision and
a Flight Speed of 8 (hover), but their ground speed of 0 means they can’t
actually &lt;em&gt;walk&lt;/em&gt;. They fight with their natural weapons: a pair of sword-like
talons, and a huge venomous sting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hellwasp-colony-guard&quot;&gt;Hellwasp Colony Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 19 Minion Skirmisher of the kind you can find by the score in
hellwasp hives. Their &lt;strong&gt;Sword Talon&lt;/strong&gt; attack allows them to shift 1 square
before or after the attack, and their &lt;strong&gt;Sting&lt;/strong&gt; deals poison damage, slows, and
prevents the target from shifting for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re good for slowing the PCs down and setting them up to be surrounded by
sturdier allies. The ability to shift away after a talon attack makes them
slightly less vulnerable to melee-centric PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hellwasp-devil&quot;&gt;Hellwasp Devil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regular version is a Level 23 Skirmisher with 212 HP. Since it’s higher
level it probably represents an exceptional individual within a hive, of the
kind that gets loaned out to allies and sent on away missions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from a somewhat weak &lt;strong&gt;Sword Talon&lt;/strong&gt; attack, the hellwasp can also perform
a &lt;strong&gt;Talon Skewer&lt;/strong&gt;. This also counts as a basic attack. It allows the wasp to
fly its speed and make two talon attacks at any point along the movement. The
wasp doesn’t draw opportunity attacks when moving away from the target of these
attacks. If both attacks hit the same target, the wasp grabs them, and the
&lt;strong&gt;Drag Off&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows it to pull the grabbed victim when it moves without
drawing opportunity attacks from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is another one of those fliers that allows you to have fun with
cliffs. And at epic level we’re probably taking the cliffs of Hell itself, which
have lava pools or other layer-appropriate hazards at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellwasp regulars also have a stronger &lt;strong&gt;Sting&lt;/strong&gt;. It deals more poison damage,
slows, prohibits shifts and deals ongoing 15 fire damage (save ends all). This
is a “recharge 5+” attack, and a good one to use on a PC that was dragged off to
an isolated position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs with sword-arms that slot neatly into the same slot as Swordwings. Perfect
for those players who dislike monsters that lack ties to AD&amp;amp;D lore. You can
reskin these into swordwings, or take inspiration in swordwing abilities when
building more hellwasp varieties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they’re interesting without overstaying their welcome. It’s always
fun to see a monster who can carry PCs off and drop them into lava pits.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/28/devil-hell-wasp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/28/devil-hell-wasp.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
