<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 19:10:26 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 19:10:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Underwater Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/geoffrey-ernault-skeletonpirateslq.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/3dvodY&quot;&gt;Illustration by Geoffrey Ernault&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underwater adventuring is one of those things that older editions of Dungeons
and Dragons seemed to like more than their players did. Lots of monster books
included a selection of monsters that could only be encountered under the sea,
but every bit of commentary I read on those was always about how no one ever
bothered to include submarine delves in their campaigns. If a sea monster
couldn’t go up to the surface to attack a ship or climb on its deck, it was
usually ignored by GMs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dungeon Fantasy lines learned this lesson well, and don’t spend a lot of ink
on support for underwater adventures. This was a big problem for me when I was
GMing Hell’s Rebels to a group of friends. This particular adventure path
follows the old tradition of making PCs spend a chunk of levels 5-8
underwater. When I got to that part in my GURPS conversion, I had no idea what
to do and got a bit stressed out trying to figure this out on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frantically researching rules in real time is no fun at all even when I am the
only player, so for the benefit of my solo Hell’s Rebels game and any future
run-throughs with actual players, I’m going to collect everything I know about
fighting underwater in GURPS right here in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit I don’t have all the officially published primary sources that discuss
underwater adventuring. The ones I’m using are &lt;strong&gt;DF: Exploits&lt;/strong&gt; and the
simplified rules that can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2019/01/simplified-df-underwater-combat-revised.html&quot;&gt;Dungeon Fantastic&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
reference the sources I don’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;underwater-fighting-for-land-lubbers&quot;&gt;Underwater Fighting For Land-Lubbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not an aquatic creature, you use these rules when fighting underwater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your Move is limited to your Swimming move: Basic Speed/5, minimum 1.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of your skills are capped at the level of your DX-based &lt;strong&gt;Swimming&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thrusting and unarmed strikes receive no penalties.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some grappling techniques won’t work. Others work as normal. GM adjudicates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swinging attacks with Reach 1+ weapons are impossible. This does cover pretty
much every weapon listed in DF: Adventurers, as even small knives have a Reach
of “C, 1” when swung.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shield bashes are -2 x DB to hit and do half damage. Don’t bother trying.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blocks are impossible but you still get your shield’s DB.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parries with Reach 1+ weapons are impossible. Parries with close-combat-only
weapons like daggers, and unarmed parries, are allowed and suffer no
penalties.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dodge is possible and not penalized, but you can’t Retreat.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No thrown ranged attacks, even from Missile spells. Special underwater ranged
weapons exist and use specific stats.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ranged attacks into our out of water have -4 to hit, 1/10 range, and do half
damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All through this, you’ll be holding your breath under Heavy Exertion (DF:
Exploits p. 21)!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;underwater-fighting-for-fish-and-fish-people&quot;&gt;Underwater Fighting for Fish and Fish-People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water adaptation in GURPS has two main components. One is the ability to
&lt;em&gt;breathe&lt;/em&gt; underwater. The other is the ability to &lt;em&gt;move freely&lt;/em&gt; while
submerged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In monsters, the first is handled by traits such as &lt;strong&gt;Gills&lt;/strong&gt;, some variety of
&lt;strong&gt;Doesn’t Breathe&lt;/strong&gt;, or the ability to hold their breath for a really long time
even in combat. A combatant with one of these traits doesn’t need to worry about
the standard Breath Holding rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is handled by the &lt;strong&gt;Amphibious&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Aquatic&lt;/strong&gt; traits. If you have
one of these traits, you get a lot of advantages over land-lubbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your get to use your full Move and skills, not limited by your Swimming.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are exempt from most skill penalties from being underwater and from many
Swimming tests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can Retreat!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your other attacks and defenses are limited as for land-lubbers. This is
important for weapon users, not so much for aquatic beasts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-delver-to-diver&quot;&gt;From Delver to Diver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a typical delver belonging to one of DFRPG’s standard ancestries, then
you fall squarely in the “land-lubber” category, and you have to solve a couple
of problems before you can dive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breathing&quot;&gt;Breathing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want your underwater life expectancy to be measured in seconds, you
need to find a way to breathe in there. In most typical DF settings, that means
magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;spells&quot;&gt;Spells&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DFRPG boxed set includes two main drowning-prevention measures: the
&lt;strong&gt;Breathe Water&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Hold Breath&lt;/strong&gt; spells. They have different
prerequisite chains but work the same, letting you ignore that part of the rules
for as long as they last. Both have a base duration of 1 minute and an energy
cost of 4 to cast and 2 to maintain, reduced by skill as normal. Hold Breath
is a little better because it also let you survive in non-watery environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main disadvantage is that their duration is relatively short. Unless the
PC casting these spells has a skill of 20 or more with them, the affected
character is only going to be able to remain underwater for a few minutes at a
time. That’s nowhere near enough for a full delve, and it’s an even shorter time
if you need to maintain this spell for multiple PCs. If the caster &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have
skill 20 then things get a lot easier, but that costs a lot of points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;items&quot;&gt;Items&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we expand our scope a little to look at DF supplements, then we see that
Dungeon Fantasy Magic Items 1 has an alchemical &lt;strong&gt;Water-Breathing Amulet&lt;/strong&gt;. You
can breathe underwater as long as you wear it… but it costs an amazing
$23.400. Outfitting a party of 5 with that is a very expensive proposition,
unless you find them as treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A reusable casting item like a wand or ring with the Breathe Water spell would
cost at least $8200. This basic version would be powered by the user, so it has
the same duration limits as the spell. Doubling the price would halve the energy
cost, which is better but not perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if we expand our scope even further and break out of the DFRPG bubble,
we can go to GURPS Magic and find an alchemical &lt;strong&gt;water-breathing elixir&lt;/strong&gt; that
costs $600 in a setting with common magic and gives you the ability to breathe
water for 1d hours! Even a minimal roll gives you a nice amount of time to
explore, and per that book’s rules you’ll know the duration is about to expire 5
minutes in advance, which is better than nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That elixir is clearly the best approach for campaigns where underwater delves
are a sometimes thing. They’re a little less convenient than the amulet, but the
price can’t be beat. I’m definitely including this in my campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving&quot;&gt;Moving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless your delvers are willing to spend the time and points to become
better-than-Olympic swimmers, solving their underwater movement issues also
means resorting to magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;spells-1&quot;&gt;Spells&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DF: Spells gives us two options here: &lt;strong&gt;Swim&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Ethereal Body&lt;/strong&gt;. The first
makes the subject effectively Amphibious, the second makes them intangible and
thus able to ignore all that water. GURPS Magic additionally gives us &lt;strong&gt;Walk
Through Water&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes the user intangible only to water and ice. This
means you don’t enjoy 3D movement while underwater… but your maneuvers in
combat are unrestricted! I think I can kinda see why this one didn’t make the
cut to the DFRPG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with water-breathing, our biggest limitation here are spell maintenance
costs, which limit our unimpeded movement to a few minutes at most. These are
also harder to completely eliminate, since Ethereal Body costs 4 energy per
minute to maintain and the others cost 3. Still, a caster could conceivably save
these for when a fight is about to start, and only cast it on the group’s
physical fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;magic-items&quot;&gt;Magic Items&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find an always-on item with a Swim enchantment in the books I own. A
basic casting item for Swim will cost at least $20500, almost as expensive as
the always-on water breathing amulet. Lowering its casting/maintenance cost from
6/3 to 3/2 doubles the price, lowering it to 2/1 quadruples it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might built this as a charged item instead, with each charge giving you 2
minutes of Swim time and costing 9 energy. A non-rechargeable item would cost
$1350 per charge, a rechargeable one $2700 (plus $180 per charge to reload).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Walk Through Water is allowed in the campaign, an item with the same duration
per charge would be a tad cheaper: $910/$1820/$140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any of these cases, the item is best used sparingly, in the same manner as
the spell. You activate it when it’s time for a big fight or a crucial skill
test, and rely on your Swimming lessons the rest of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optimal-strategies&quot;&gt;Optimal Strategies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all of the above, I think we can pretty easily arrive at an “optimal”
strategy for underwater expeditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your group is about to embark in a &lt;strong&gt;campaign centered around underwater
delving&lt;/strong&gt;, your PC party should include a caster who can use Breathe Water at
Skill-20, and also someone who can use Swim at Skill-15. A druid or wizard could
do both, a cleric can use Breathe Water and leave Swim to someone else. This is
a hefty investment, but worth it for the amount of use they’ll get out of
it. Every PC, caster or not, should also consider investing points into the
Swimming skill, because it can help conserve spell energy and is pretty useful
in itself. You might want to give them extra points for these purposes depending
on your desired power level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative here is for you to allow players to make PCs from ancestries that
have an easy time underwater. Both Sea Elves from GURPS DF 3 and &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/10/10/elder-scrolls-others.html&quot;&gt;Argonians&lt;/a&gt;
from this blog have Gills and are Amphibious. &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/09/17/dfrpg-warforged.html&quot;&gt;Warforged&lt;/a&gt; are a bit less
nimble but don’t need to breathe at all. Each delver who is a natural-born diver
will make the rest of the party’s life that much easier. For those who aren’t,
Water-Breathing Amulets make excellent treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re planning a standard campaign that features a &lt;strong&gt;one-off underwater
dungeon&lt;/strong&gt;, Water-Breathing Elixirs are the way to go, possibly supplemented by
one or two rechargeable Wands of Swimming. The elixirs should definitely be
easily available in a nearby town (perhaps it’s a coastal fishing village?). The
wands might be for sale as well, or might be found as treasure either before or
during the delve. Proper safety procedure is to carry two elixirs per
PC, saving the second one for the return trip if the first one wears off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only have &lt;strong&gt;isolated underwater encounters&lt;/strong&gt;, we’re back to learned
spells, but they don’t need to have high levels. The submerged environment
becomes an additional challenge, but no one is going to spend too long inside
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell’s Rebels in particular fits the second category, so I’ll be using that
solution.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>gm-hat</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Play Hell's Rebels!</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started a Let’s Read of Hell’s Rebels way back when it was new, in 2017. I had
gotten the campaign’s first three volumes with alongside a huge pile of other
Pathfinder PDFs in one of Humble Bundle’s offerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to publish articles about the first three of those books here, though
I kinda stalled out between volumes 2 and 3. I still want to “Let’s Read” the
rest one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post, and the series it starts, are about something a bit different. You
see, ever since I got those books I also had a desire to &lt;em&gt;run&lt;/em&gt; this campaign,
but I didn’t want to do so using Pathfinder 1e’s default system. No, I wanted,
and still want, to use the Dungeon Fantasy RPG for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually did it, too! This was during the thick of the pandemic here in
Brazil, so I ran it on Roll20 with a group of friends. We got through the first
two adventures, but I ended up stopping that campaign because the combined
workload became a bit too heavy for me. I had to convert everything, prepare
battle maps and tokens for Roll20, adjudicate setting developments in response
to PC actions, and do all of that on time for the next session in two weeks
while juggling all the other stress sources those interesting times produced for
me and my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still wanted to go through the whole thing, whether as a GM or as a player. As
a GM, I no longer had any confidence I could prepare everything I needed on
schedule. As a player, I had that peculiar problem where the only person I knew
who wanted to run that adventure in the exact way I wanted to play it was
me. Clearly, there was only one solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;running-this-thing-as-a-solo-campaign&quot;&gt;Running this thing as a solo campaign&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually decided to run Hell’s Rebels for myself as a solo campaign way back
at the beginning of 2023, but it took until the start of June for me to finally
find the inspiration I was lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This won’t be my first “solo” campaign: I ran through the first two Zeitgeist
adventures that way between 2015 and 2017, give or take a year. That attempt
lost steam due to the issues I’m about to discuss, but it was pretty fun while
it lasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solo campaign attempts don’t have much in common with others I’ve seen
online. Those games tend to be quite minimalistic, with a single protagonist run
by the solo player, a setting sketched in broad strokes, and some sort of
“divination engine” taking the place of the GM. There is no pre-defined plot at
all - it’s entirely decided by asking questions to the engine and interpreting
its answers. The protagonist might have a starting goal, but how hard that is to
reach and what happens on the way are determined randomly. Note-taking seems
pretty minimal, unless the player in question wants to post actual play reports
online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, there is absolutely nothing wrong with that approach and it is in
fact the one I would recommend to most people who want to do a solo game. All of
the solo game products out there support it, and it is excellent at replicating
the experience of being a player in a game and not knowing what will happen
next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also not the approach I’m going to use for myself. I guess I’m built
different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest difference between this game and one using the “best practice”
approach outlined above is that I have a pre-defined module I want to run: the
Hell’s Rebels Adventure Path. Not only do I want to play that, I’ve already read
the first four volumes quite closely. While I find it easy to “forget” this
stuff when I’m just a player, here I’m also the GM, which makes separating this
knowledge impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I have this weird desire to run it in a way that mirrors a
standard party-based campaign with multiple players as closely as possible. I
want a &lt;em&gt;party&lt;/em&gt; of heroes, and I want to be both player and GM at the same
time. I want it to be GURPS, and I want to interact with the mechanical widgets
of that system because I find them fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I don’t want to just keep a minimal set of notes. I’m not gonna
write things as a novel or anything, but I kinda want to see the game’s events
rendered as a reasonably comprehensive actual play report of the sort I see in
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Dungeon Fantastic&lt;/a&gt; blog. I’d do that even if I &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; intend to post
them publicly - it’s what I did for Zeitgeist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-im-doing-this&quot;&gt;How I’m doing this&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My strange preferences bring two big risks to this endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is the lack of an “information barrier” between player and
GM. This barrier and the dramatic tension it brings do not exist when player and
GM are the same person. The usual strategies for separating in-character
knowledge from out-of-character information do not work here, at least for
me. This gives me the strange simultaneous feeling that I’m “cheating” (as a
player) and “going too easy on the PCs” (as a GM). This is obviously an obstacle
to fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other issue is with preparing maps and tokens. Sure, this would be much
easier on me if I ran everything in the theater of the mind, but I like moving
figures around on a battle map. The problem on my earlier attempts was that I
would usually leave the &lt;em&gt;building&lt;/em&gt; of those battle maps to the very last second,
when I’d be in a rush to get on with the action. This also means I never took
the necessary time to familiarize myself with the software I was using. So I’d
stall, and procrastinate, and take two months to finish something that could
have been done in a couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve both of these issues, I’m going to make a resolution to never wear the
GM and player hats at the same time. The GM hat is for preparation. The player
hat is for “actual play”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gm-hat&quot;&gt;The GM Hat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During preparation, I’m going to consider myself a mix of GM and designer and
I’m going to lean on my newly-discovered feelings of Miniature Envy. You see, a
lot of the online friends I’ve made in the past year and a half are very much
into tabletop wargaming. They have extensive miniature collections and extremely
well-organized workspaces for assembling and painting them. They often post the
results of their work online and it always looks awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have neither the space, skill, nor the budget to do the same thing, but I
&lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; look at the process of building battle maps and actor tokens in GCS,
TokenTool and Foundry with the same sort of perspective. Learning how to use the
software and actually building the things, then, becomes a hobby in itself. And
there’s no time or schedule pressure, so there’s no problem if I take a bit
longer in this part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will also be when I actually convert enemy stats, tests, and treasure from
the adventure’s original Pathfinder 1e to GURPS Dungeon Fantasy. I’ll try to
make them useful to others who want to try running the adventure in a more
traditional manner, but I won’t bother converting rules material for those paths
my PCs never take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also perform some significant “condensation” in the campaign. Like all
Pathfinder adventure paths, Hell’s Rebels includes a lot of filler fights
placed to give your PCs enough XP for them to hit the expected character levels
at the right times. It also features lots of elements that get added only on
later books but which could be relevant from the start. Neither of these things
are necessary in a Dungeon Fantasy campaign where the PCs already start out
powerful and advance in a completely different manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I have a large enough chunk of unplayed material, I’m going to take
off my GM hat and become a player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-player-hat&quot;&gt;The Player Hat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve the information barrier issue, I’m going to just learn to stop worrying
and love the cheese. When I’m wearing my player hat, it will be like I’m playing
a computer game with a walkthrough open. Sure, I might know what’s coming, and I
might even have a party custom-tailored to overcome those challenges, but the
&lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of overcoming those challenges can still be quite fun. It can even
still be surprising, depending on what the dice tell me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps that this is the campaign whose main goal is punching fantasy
Nazis. Even if I know what’s coming, the actual process of going through it can
still be fun. Let us make awesome heroes tailored to the challenge and
completely stomp those fascist fuckers into the fucking ground! Let’s kick their
asses all the way to the Hell they came from! I want catharsis, dangit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also try to pay special attention to my characters’ disadvantages and
other traits, and obey the dictates of those self-control rolls. And when some
kind of question appears during the “actual play” part, I’m going to use
the Mythic GM Emulator to answer it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-in-this-for-you&quot;&gt;What’s in this for you?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This effort is going to generate a lot of material for this blog! I expect
readers will get some use out of my premade PCs, and out of the enemy stat
blocks I generate. Everything from those stats to the “actual play” reports and
design commentary is going to be published here.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/08/lets-play-hells-rebels.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/08/lets-play-hells-rebels.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>solo-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wealth in D&amp;D and Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve done pretty often these past few years is converting D&amp;amp;D and
Pathfinder adventures for use with Dungeon Fantasy (either version). These
conversions didn’t have nowhere near the level of rigor of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/projects/dragons-dogma/&quot;&gt;Dragon’s
Dogma&lt;/a&gt; adaptation, but that larger project did give me a solid grounding on
the basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Converting from one tabletop system to the other is fairly easy, for the most
part, but there are some aspects of it that I found harder to do, especially on
the fly. One of these is converting wealth between the two systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll be comparing the Dungeon Fantasy RPG and Pathfinder 1st
Edition and trying to come up with a way to convert monetary amounts from the
latter to the former. I chose the DFRPG because I use its monetary system in my
games, and I chose Pathfinder 1e because I want to convert Hell’s
Rebels. Pathfinder 1e, of course, shares most of its base assumptions with D&amp;amp;D
3.5, the system from which it is derived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-money-looks-like&quot;&gt;What Money Looks Like&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy purposefully makes its coins have the exact same dimensions as
those of D&amp;amp;D, and therefore Pathfinder. They both use chunky standardized coins
that weight 1/50th of a pound (around 10 grams). These come in copper, silver,
gold, and a few other exotic materials that we don’t need to look at right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dimensions are apparently universal standards, and their value comes from
their precious metal content. If you find a chest of thousand-year-old gold
coins in an ancient dungeon, you can carry them back to town and spend them on
the market right away. Finding “non-standard” coins is usually a rare special
case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, though their physical dimensions are identical, their values seem
to be derived from completely different assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-money-buys&quot;&gt;What Money Buys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all variants of GURPS, Dungeon Fantasy expresses its prices and values in
“GURPS dollars”, or “$”. The exact value of this unit of currency varies with
the setting. Here, $1 is the worth of a copper piece. Silver pieces are worth 20
copper pieces each ($20). Gold pieces are worth 20 silver pieces each
($400). This means GURPS is effectively on a copper standard. The vast majority
of Dungeon Fantasy characters gets $1000 to buy their starting gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Pathfinder we have the classic decimal setup where 1gp == 10sp == 100cp. The
most common coin is the gold piece, and nearly everything in the core book’s
gear chapter has its price expressed in gp. So here we’re on a &lt;em&gt;gold&lt;/em&gt;
standard. Starting money is determined by a random roll that varies per
class. Fighter-types start with an average of 175gp, others start with less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases, this starting money is meant to let you buy your main weapon,
perhaps a backup or shield, a suit of armor, and the miscellaneous sundries that
make up your typical adventurer’s kit: a pouch or pack, some camping supplies
and rations, and maybe some tools like the thief’s lockpick set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there on out, things start to diverge quite sharply, and the way I see it
it’s mainly the fault of Pathfinder’s Wealth By Level table. It subjects PCs to
the tyranny of inflation. This plus the difference in base value means that
while a haul of a thousand gold pieces is a fantastic fortune for even veteran
Dungeon Fantasy delvers, it starts out at “pretty nice” for low-level Pathfinder
adventurers and quickly becomes “pocket change” for high-level ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-our-exchange-rate&quot;&gt;So What’s Our Exchange Rate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can start with the guidelines presented in the Exploits book: an adventure
should pay at least enough for the party to recoup their expenses with
consumables, power item recharge, and the cost of staying in town during
downtime. It’s perfectly OK for it to pay more than that, even &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more than
that, because it’s relatively easy to get rid of “excess” money by giving them
opportunities to spend it. Maybe a weird old man has a treasure map to sell, or
a mystical artifact or something. Magic items don’t count as part of character
wealth for this, as the game’s attitude to them is more similar to early D&amp;amp;D
than modern Pathfinder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after all of that I think we can safely say that a Pathfinder 1e gold piece
should be worth around &lt;strong&gt;$5&lt;/strong&gt; in Dungeon Fantasy. This leads to amounts of money
that are sufficient to cover expenses with a little left over in low-level
adventures, and to increasingly bigger hauls in higher-level ones, but as we
established that’s OK. Some of those Pathfinder adventures even helpfully
provide us with domain mini-games of their own that can soak up that extra cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performing-the-actual-conversion&quot;&gt;Performing the Actual Conversion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that basic exchange rate in mind, we can think about how that affects the
actual treasure our delvers find in the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coins&quot;&gt;Coins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piles of coins change to reflect their new value. The two main approaches you
could take here are to prioritize keeping the same value, or prioritize keeping
the same weight (which means keeping the same number of coins). Getting &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt;
value and weight to match is very hard, so I strongly recommend sticking to only
one unless you like solving &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knapsack_problem&quot;&gt;multi-dimensional knapsack problems&lt;/a&gt; in your
spare time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prioritizing &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; means those coin piles will end up smaller and lighter
than the originals. This will make hauling them off easier. I recommend against
condensing the pile as much as possible, because you don’t want to make
logistics &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; easy. Also, finding a single gold coin can be a bit of a letdown
even if it is worth a lot. This is the easiest approach to take on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prioritizing &lt;strong&gt;the number of coins&lt;/strong&gt; means the pile will have exactly the same
size and weight, but it will be made of a smaller denomination coins. Its actual
value will probably be a little higher or lower than that of the original, but
that’s OK as long as the value remains close. This could lead to a situation
where the group only takes the most valuable portions of the pile, but I guess
that’s true to how it was done in Old D&amp;amp;D too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: A chest containing 100gp in Pathfinder should contain $500 in coins
when converted to DF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prioritizing value might give us a bag containing 25 silvers. That’s a
satisfying number of coins that still has a non-negligible weight.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prioritizing weight might give us a chest containing 80 coppers and 20
silvers, with a total worth of $480.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gems-jewelry-and-art-objects&quot;&gt;Gems, Jewelry, and Art Objects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things tend to have pretty arbitrary values in both systems! The biggest
difference in how they handle selling this stuff in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Pathfinder, you can generally exchange them for their full listed value in
cash, making them perfectly efficient forms of portable wealth. PF adventurers
are quite likely to convert their coins into fancy jewelry when they need to
travel long distances, since it’s much lighter for its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dungeon Fantasy, the only thing that fetches its full value is coin or bulk
precious metals. Everything else, including gems, jewelry, and art objects, is
subject to the rules for appraisal and haggling. This means typical delvers are
likely to get less than full value for this stuff back in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My recommendation here is to use a doubled exchange rate: each gp of gems,
jewelry and treasure is worth $10. That’s the treasure’s &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; value, which
means a typical party will get half of that on average when they sell it back in
town. I feel this preserves the “original intention” of the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;magic-items&quot;&gt;Magic Items&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both systems have a lot to say about magic item pricing, so my strategy here is
to not attempt a conversion of the price at all. I convert the &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt; of the
item and figure out how much that would cost in Dungeon Fantasy if it was a new
item. Saying it like this makes it sound easy, but this can be complex enough to
warrant its own post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an item can be replicated with the standard enchantments from DF, it has
those enchantments and is priced accordingly. Items with unique functions might
be a bit harder, but I always have the “easy escape” there of just not assigning
a fixed price to these. Like DF Artifacts, they’re either impossible to sell in
the first place, or will be worth some arbitrary amount that matches what I want
the PCs to have at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/25/dungeon-fantasy-wealth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/25/dungeon-fantasy-wealth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Hell's Rebels Adventure 3, Part 3</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we come to the final part of our Let’s Read of the third Hell’s Rebels
adventure, “Dance of the Damned”. With the “regional support” missions complete,
the Rebellion’s stats can grow to their maximum values. We’re almost at the
point where things get real serious in Kintargo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution starts with a party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-5-the-ruby-masquerade&quot;&gt;Part 5: The Ruby Masquerade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barzilai Thrune has been organizing a grand masquerade ball to be hosted at the
Opera House ever since the start of this adventure. He advertises it as a way to
reconcile with his critics and to show everything is fine in Kintargo, but of
course it’s a dastardly trap. After the PCs close the Menador Gap he steps up
his time table and announces a date for the event. He might also end up doing it
on his original schedule if the PCs take too long to complete that key mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His plan is to use a troop of dottari and disguised devils to massacre the
ball’s attendants at the party’s climax, and doctor the evidence to blame the
Silver Ravens. This will give him an official excuse to begin hunting them down
in earnest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barzilai sends invitations to every noble or other prominent citizen he knows
does not support him. He’s not stupid enough to believe the PCs would attend if
he invited them directly, so he makes invitations relatively easy to acquire by
other means as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s at this point that the private investigator Tayacet Tiora makes contact
with the PCs. Barzilai had hired her to look into the Silver Ravens, and it’s
even possible they ran into her in previous adventures if the GM decided to use
that scene. This time, she’s found out enough to become convinced the PCs are in
the right, and she comes to warn them that the Masquerade is a trap. Her
recommendation is for the PCs to not attend, but she promises to help if they
insist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply not going is certainly an option. It ensures the safety of the PCs but
lets the trap spring on the innocent guests unopposed. The book also
contemplates the possibility that the PCs will want to break into the Opera
House early, which is actually a good call. The same security forces will be
present and they will be patrolling more aggresively, but there will be no
bystanders. The PCs would miss out on a few extra hob-nobbing opportunities but
would be in a much better tactical position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the adventure assumes the PCs do attend, however. It should be
fairly easy to get invitations for the whole party plus any allies they wish to
take. Tiora will also attend in this case, and be ready to help if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masquerade starts at 9 PM, and whatever day is most convenient for the
GM. The PCs should have ample time to prepare for this one, growing the
rebellion and aiming their NPC teams at the Opera House to provide
information. It’s even possible to plant an infiltrated saboteur among the
guards. With good rolls they should have a pretty good idea of the security
inside the place, and an extra ally on the inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;party-mechanics&quot;&gt;Party Mechanics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual ball is a bit of a skill challenge in the same vein as the Vyre
banquet. There’s an official dress code: outfits should include the color red,
everyone must wear a mask, and both should be fancy. Fortunately they can pass
anything up to medium armor and shields as part of the costume, but it’s
definitely worth it to have it adorned and to splurge on extravagant
masks. These give bonuses to social skills during the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like we had Banquet Points in Vyre, here we have Masque Points. PCs start
with an amount between 4 and 16 depending on how fancy their costumes are. NPC
allies they bring with them also affect this total. The ball is split into
half-hour segments, and each PC can perform one of several available actions
during this span of time. Some of these actions cost Masque Points, some can be
used to acquire more with good skill rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless the PCs have been making an effort to ingratiate themselves with the
noble houses during “strategic” play, this is their last real chance to do so
before things heat up. The Kintargo-aligned house heads should all be here, so
the party’s socialites can identify them and chat them up. Having to do this now
does add a layer of complication to the procedures, which is why I like the idea
of introducing this element early in the campaign instead and let players make
their own interaction opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;opera-house-layout-and-security&quot;&gt;Opera House Layout and Security&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Opera House has three floors and an extensive basement. The main seating
areas had all of their seats removed to host the ball. Most guests stay on the
ground floor, but the nobles gravitate towards the second floor balcony because
they like to look down on commoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two floors have a lot of backstage areas off to the sides, and the
third floor and basement are all “backstage”. Many of these areas were converted
in living spaces for Barzilai and his staff. All backstage areas are off-limits
to party guests, so PCs need to be sneaky when exploring them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a total of 22 dottari in the house, half of which attend to the guests
while wearing smiley masks. The other half stands in reserve, waiting for the
trap to spring. The dottari here use the same stats as the Menador soldiers,
with slightly different gear. This means the PCs should be able to handle small
groups of them just fine - the challenge is doing so without raising an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a troop of devils in here: two bone, six bearded, and a single
erinyes. One of the bone devils, Crizmerkis, has a few class levels on him and
is wearing an illusory disguise to look like Barzilai. The real Thrune has
relocated to the temple of Asmodeus, and does not appear in this adventure. The
other bone devil is in the orchestra pit, using his illusion magic to provide
the music for the ball. The remaining monsters are scattered through several
side rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the rooms also contains suspended cages for Barzilai’s pet cockatrices,
which can be released at the press of a switch. Unless the PCs or an ally break
the switch, these creatures will be released when the trap is sprung.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are a bunch of secret rooms in a sub-basement that used to belong
to the original Silver Ravens. Barzilai is using them to stash his treasures and
house his “prize” henchthings. Former Mayor Jilia Bailinus sleeps here as a
vampire, and the long-missing singer Shensen is also here as a statue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of additional secret chambers Thrune’s lackeys haven’t been
able to find, and which contain valuable Silver Ravens stuff. This includes the
crypts for the original Ravens, which confirm their fates and the fact that
Jackdaw, the last remaining member, might still be alive. And it also includes
the musical score for the Song of Silver, a potent ritual that will greatly help
the PCs in the climax of the rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using rebellion actions the PCs can arm themselves with plenty of information
before going in: a Covert Action can give them the map to the whole building,
even the secret-secret chambers with a good enough roll. And a Sabotage action
can place an infiltrator among the dottari. Once the PCs link up with the
infiltrator during the party, they can learn the composition and location of the
place’s entire security detail, devils included. The saboteur can also break the
cockatrice release switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several rooms that are noted as being rarely visited by both guests
and patrols, which makes them perfect places to hide bodies. So yup, time to
Assassin’s Creed it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;delving-the-masquerade&quot;&gt;“Delving” the Masquerade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say those covert actions are so vital that the GM should push for them
to happen if the players have been neglecting that aspect of the game. The PCs
are on the clock here and every little advantage helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party starts at 9PM. At 10PM, they have a special “Dance of the Damned”
event that takes up half an hour. At midnight an unmasking ceremony happens and
Crizmerkis springs the ambush with the aim of killing every single guest in the
house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs should carefully manage their masque points, with some of the party making
an effort to mingle and gain more while the rest spend them on exploration
actions. It’s important that the minglers manage to maintain the point total
above 0, and that the explorers avoid raising a general alarm. Either of these
things will cause Crizmerkis to spring the trap immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participation on the dance is optional, but winning the contest gives a ton of
Masque Points so the minglers will want to participate. This leaves them with 5
other segments on which to decide their actions before the trap is sprung.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explorers who refuse to take part in the contest have 6 segments on which to
act. Their priority target here should be taking out the dottari, because
they’re weaker and have less means of raising the alarm (several of the devils
are telepathic and can do so instantly). The less enemies there are at midnight,
the easier the final fight will be. Looting and detailed exploration of the
basement should wait until after the main ambush force is defeated. There are a
few extra monsters down there that will not take part in the ambush, so they can
be safely ignored for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-stroke-of-midnight&quot;&gt;The Stroke of Midnight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At midnight, Crizmerkis (disguised as Barzilai) will stop the music and make an
ominous speech. During the speech, the dottari will split into 11 pairs and
stand guard over every one of the building’s exits, locking those doors in the
process. Attacking them before the speech is done will cost the party a bunch of
Masque Points but will give them a surprise round and a tactical advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of the speech is that the guests present here have graciously
volunteered themselves to help maintain public order, by being massacred so the
blame can fall on the Silver Ravens and Barzilai can go after them. As soon as
it ends, the devils attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 300 guests in the house, not counting the PCs. The “spare” bone devil
and the erinyes will focus on slaughering them, while the bearded devils and
Crizmerkis will come for the PC directly. Most of them will be disguised as good
outsiders using illusions, but additional summoned devils and such will not have
disguises on. The PCs can draw the attention of the bone devil and erinyes by
engaging them in combat. If cornered, Crizmerkis might summon the vampire Jillia
Bailinus to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why killing the dottari early helps: if there are less of them, they’re
going to leave some of those exits unlocked and unprotected. The PCs &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; open
the exits so guests can leave: 1d6 guests escape every round for every unlocked
exit. With no open exits, 2d6 of them die every round to sheer crushing crowd
pressure. Those two devils kill even more per round if left alone. If you’re
using GURPS, read “every round” as “every six seconds”, otherwise things might
get a little impossible here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results-and-consequences&quot;&gt;Results and Consequences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event will go down in history as the Ruby Massacre. Whether the PCs or
Thrune are blamed for it depends on how well they do in this final fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs win the big fight they should have plenty of time to explore the rest
of the opera house. They’ll get to fight a pack of hellhounds being used as
guard animals in the basement, find Vampire Jilia’s coffing and stake her, and
find Shensen and the Song of Silver. There’s also a lot of other cool loot to be
had, including a scroll of resurrection that can be used to bring the former
Mayor back to life after she’s destroyed as a vampire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs loose, they’ll find themselves waking up inside a cell in Castle
Kintargo. Either way as soon as they leave the opera house we transition
directly to Volume 04, where we go full Assassin’s Creed: Brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Notes and Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book makes that final battle sound quite difficult, particularly if the PCs
didn’t prepare for it by coming into the party armed and taking out some of the
opposition ahead of time. Even if they did, it’s going to be hard to save all
the bystanders. Dungeon Fantasy delvers should have it a bit easier because
the GURPS version of these opponents won’t have HP in the triple digits, but
it’s going to be tough even for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same emphasis on etiquette from the Vyre banquet is present here, but here
it makes less sense given the surrounding context. The Silver Ravens only get
diplomatic/strategic benefits from thwarting the ambush if they have more than
20 Masque Points by the time the ambush starts. I guess this is supposed to
represent the final impression left on the survivors about who is to blame for
the massacre, but it feels odd to have the party save these people in a very
obvious manner and not be recognized for it. I’d say that saving the heads of
the noble houses at least should be more than enough to get them on-side for the
next adventure, if that hasn’t happened yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs have been buttering up the nobles on their own initiative prior to
this point, then the best strategic decision they can make is to break into the
opera house days before the ball, preferrably during daylight hours so the
vampire isn’t a factor. All the same enemies will still be there, but the whole
party can focus on exploring the area and taking them out. They’ll completely
forfeit the possible diplomatic rewards from the Masquerade, but not having to
split their focus between delving and socializing or rescuing bystanders is more
than worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 18:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/24/hells-rebels-3-part-3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/24/hells-rebels-3-part-3.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Hells Rebels 3, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go to the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/hells-rebels/&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt; to see all entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s continue our reading of Dance of the Damned! I expect this to be the
second of three posts for this adventure. In the last one, we covered two
chapters of the book. Let’s aim for two more here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-3-the-vyre-accord&quot;&gt;Chapter 3: The Vyre Accord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vyre is a city located in the same province as Kintargo. There’s a whole
mini-guide on it attached to the book, but the only thing we really need to know
is that it’s pretty much Fucked-Up Fantasy Venice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though technically part of Cheliax, Vyre is almost entirely independent. Cheliax
tolerates this because the city is a prime vacation destination for Chelish
elites. On the other hand, Vyre’s slice of coast makes for a shitty port, so
they’re almost entirely reliant on nearby Kintargo for the sea trade that gets
them most of their food and luxuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vyre’s government is extremely self-interested, but Cheliax has good reasons to
maintain good relations with them, and they have good reasons to maintain good
relations with Kintargo. If Vyre backs the rebellion, they can exert pressure on
those Chelish elites to back off from the province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;allies-and-information&quot;&gt;Allies and Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advance information on the city comes from two sources. Captain Sargaeta, whom
the PCs befriended in Adventure 02, can tell them the basics, and give them a
ride there on his ship. Molly Mayapple can provide them with extensive and
invaluable advice on their actual goal in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCs haven’t met Molly yet, but they should have recovered a bunch of
documents belonging to her from the Lucky Bones. These are deeds for a set of
waterfront warehouses, which were stolen by the extinct Gray Spiders decades
ago. Even though Molly has since rebuilt her fortune (she owns a successful
hotel), she’s still going to be extremely grateful when the PCs hand the deeds
back to her, and will provide a lot of insider information and help. They can
track her down from the information on the deeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The Basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vyre is ruled by five monarchs, each tasked with an aspect of government. The
one they want to meet is Manticce Kaleeki, the Queen of Delights, who is in
charge of the city’s economy and foreign relations. Vyre’s laws are simple yet
baroque, creating an environment where non-lethal duels and eternal feuds are
common, all sales are final, but prejudice of any sort is frowned upon. However,
you can get away with anything if you follow the last and most important rule:
don’t get caught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Queen of Delights is set to host a banquet in the near future, and that will
be the PCs’ opportunity to talk to her. The GM determines how long the PCs have
until the banquet. Most of this time is probably going to be spent looking for
outfits, gifts, and information, but the GM can also introduce a few Vyre
sidequests to spice things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-banquet&quot;&gt;The Banquet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Banquet might be an entirely non-violent scene, but it’s as difficult to
navigate as any dungeon. Vyre high-society etiquette is weird, and the Queen of
Delights heaps even more weird on top of that because she’s basically Morticia
Addams as a Tiefling in Fucked-Up Fantasy Venice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molly’s help is absolutely vital here. The book doesn’t even mention how the PCs
get invited to the banquet, but I assume she’s instrumental in arranging
invitations for them and for herself. She’s also an excellent source of
information on the complex etiquette surrounding the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This starts with what to wear and what gifts to bring. Molly knows what the
Queen likes, and PCs good at gathering information might learn about Manticce’s
less well-known preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are nine other guests in the banquet aside from Molly and the PCs. We get
personality notes for each one. Most are only sources of roleplaying color, but
one of them will be important in the next adventure: Hei-fen, former
guildmistress of the Gray Spiders. Tough it’s been decades since she escaped the
destruction of that guild, she’s still a spiteful old wererat and is angry at
the PCs for stealing “her home”. She’s here to size them up for future reprisal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other “special” guest, not counted among those nine, is the Queen’s long
dead husband, whose skeleton adorns one of the table’s chairs. The correct move
here is to not acknowledge poor Gomez in any way. To do so is considered crass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While roleplaying should be first and foremost in this scene it also has a
mechanical component. The banquet is effectivelly a long and colorful skill
challenge. PCs get a number of starting “banquet points” depending on how they
dress, what gifts they bring, and whether or not they participate in a standing
ovation when the Queen appears (they should!). After that, each course in the
banquet allows them several opportunities to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a knowledge skill test to identify the dish in question and how to
eat it (probably &lt;strong&gt;Area Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Current Affairs&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Savoir-Faire&lt;/strong&gt; in
GURPS). Careful PCs can just wait for one of the other guests to start eating
and skip the skill test, but succeeding shows they know what they’re doing and
earns them a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is a series of tests to actually eat the course, which varies with
each dish. There’s no way to skip this one, though the PCs doesn’t need to
succeed at them all to earn a point. If they do, they earn extra. If they fail
badly enough or just decide to forgo rolling and eat the thing wrong on purpose,
they lose points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third is a social skill test to do well in the conversation that accompanies
that dish. This would likely be &lt;strong&gt;Fast-Talk&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Diplomacy&lt;/strong&gt; or even &lt;strong&gt;Public
Speaking&lt;/strong&gt; in GURPS, modified by what the players actually say. Success makes
them come off as smooth operators and earns points. Failure loses points and
leaves them embarrassed. Again careful characters can just keep quiet and skip
this part, but it earns them nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dishes range from the merely bizarre to the horrific:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We start with &lt;strong&gt;quicksoup&lt;/strong&gt;, a bowl of boiling hot soup accompanied by a water
bowl containing five small live fish and a set of peculiar utensils. This
requires tests involving manual dexterity to properly poach the fish in the
soup and eat them. Probably plain &lt;strong&gt;DX&lt;/strong&gt; modified by &lt;strong&gt;Manual Dexterity&lt;/strong&gt; in
GURPS, though I’d also let a daring PC test &lt;strong&gt;Surgery&lt;/strong&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Next is &lt;strong&gt;Galtan Squash&lt;/strong&gt;, which looks like a severed head but is just a
carved pumpkin full of extremely spicy red soup. This is a straight-up
Fortitude save/&lt;strong&gt;HT&lt;/strong&gt; roll to endure the spice. A bad enough failure leaves
your face swollen and penalizes your talky rolls for the rest of the feast!
I’d probably let it be modified by &lt;strong&gt;Resistant to Poison&lt;/strong&gt; and other
advantages that include it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Then you get the &lt;strong&gt;Unseen Feast&lt;/strong&gt;, meat pies made from the flesh of an
invisible stalker. I’m pretty sure invisible stalkers are sapient, which makes
this the most horrific dish of the lot. It’s quite possible some PCs will
refuse to eat this one on moral grounds. Those who decide to forge ahead need
to be fast and perceptive. They have to eat the invisible meat before it turns
visible and loses its flavor. PCs who can see invisibility can pass this one
automatically, though it’s considered crass to cast a spell for it while on
the table. Others must succeed at a difficult &lt;strong&gt;Perception&lt;/strong&gt; check, which I
guess I would modify for &lt;strong&gt;Acute Smell/Taste&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, you get &lt;strong&gt;Sweefats With Honey Sauce&lt;/strong&gt; for dessert. Sweetfats are
candied spiders - this is an Underdark dish. The most difficult thing here is
opening the honey sauce container, which is a mundane replica of a
Hellraiser-style puzzle box. Time to break out the &lt;strong&gt;Thaumathology&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Hidden Lore (Demons)&lt;/strong&gt; skills, though I guess &lt;strong&gt;Traps&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Lockpicking&lt;/strong&gt;
might also work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Vyre allies with the Silver Ravens or not depends entirely on how many
banquet points the characters manage to get. They need at least 20. A party of 5
who arrives properly dressed will start out with 10, and might get a few more
from bringing optimal gifts. Even so, they will still need to take active part
in at least some of the banquet in order to succeed at the mission. I’d probably
give them a sign that they succeeded once they get enough points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the party succeeds, the Queen might invite the individual who gained them the
most points for an intimate night. Ties go to the prettiest or most charismatic
PC, and if they’re still tied she invites all of the tied PCs. If the party has
more than 30 points &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the propositioned PC(s) accept Manticce’s invitation,
she will also offer the group her personal alliance, providing extra mechanical
boosts to the strategic rebellion layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Notes and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part is very different than what you would expect from a standard dungeon
fantasy adventure. It can be really fun for PCs who like role-playing, so even
in a condensed approach I’d recommend keeping it. If you want to make the Unseen
Feast part less objectionable, you could perhaps say the “meat” is gelatinous
cube jelly, which is almost as hard to see and doesn’t come from something
sapient. And if you don’t want to feature sexual themes at all in the adventure,
you could remove Manticce’s invitation at the end and just say that the party
gets her personal support if they get more than 30 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside when using GURPS is that if your PCs are overly focused on dungeon
delving they might not have the skills necessary to cause a good impression
here. In this case I suggest being generous: if none of the delvers has the most
appropriate skill, ask for a roll on the closest skill one of them does have, or
perhaps even roll against DX or IQ. That said, characters who followed the tips
from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/01/hells-rebels-player-guide.html&quot;&gt;Player’s Guide&lt;/a&gt; or who used earned points to become a bit sneakier
and more social shouldn’t have too much trouble covering their bases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-4-breaking-the-menador-gap&quot;&gt;Part 4: Breaking the Menador Gap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Menador Gap is a mountain pass in the mountains separating Ravounel from
central Cheliax. It’s the only viable route for marching an army through those
mountains, so it must be closed. The PCs start the adventure at level 7, and the
book says they should be level 8 before tackling this chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gap is protected by a fortress named Menador Keep. It used to be an old
dwarf fort, but is now occupied by Chelish military. Rexus, who studied those
old Silver Raven documents extensively, can tell the PCs that there’s a dwarven
self-destruct mechanism deep within the bowels of the fort. The PCs’ goal here
is to get to that mechanism, activate it, and get out. This will demolish the
fort in a way that ensures the pass is completely closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s theoretically possible to demolish the fort from a distance using spells
like Earthquake, but a) this might not block the pass completely and b) it will
bury all the sweet loot located inside the fortress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dungeon-menador-gap&quot;&gt;Dungeon: Menador Gap&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fortress itself has two above-ground floors and an underground level. Its
ground floor contains a courtyard with two large gates on either side, which
blocks the mountain pass. Inside the building are a large number of guard posts,
utility/storage rooms, and a couple of monster pens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fort is defended by a garrison of 23 soldiers, commanded by Lucien Thrune, a
wyvern-riding cavalier. He also has a bound erinyes devil with him, and a very
unhappy bound jann servant. Another devil acts as a stationary sentry at the
entrance to the treasury. The soldiers are weak individually, but dangerous in
large groups. They wear mail and are armed with halberds and crossbows, favoring
ranged attacks over melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to handle this might be as a Metal Gear-like stealth mission. The
PCs are very likely to have the necessary magic to turn the whole party
invisible and levitate them for a short time. Clever PCs might find the entrnce
to the wyvern’s stable down on the cliffside and enter through there, bypassing
a lot of the security measures on the surface. The same technique might allow
them to land atop the fort’s battlements and begin from there, bypassing the
courtyard kill box. Even if they immediately go loud and begin a frontal
assault, they’ll begin doing that from a hugely advantageous position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third-best option is for them to disguise themselves as someone authorized
to cross the Gap and ride into the courtyard, from which they can force their
way into the fort. It’s less than ideal because they can be targetted by
crossbow and ballista fire from the battlements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting an overt assault will sound a general alert and have every soldier
converge on the party’s position. It’s easier to deal with them piecemeal,
though that might require magic to prevent the sounds of fighting from spilling
out. Stealth might also allow the party to fight the “elites” (Lucien, his
wyvern, the devils) while they’re alone and isolated. The jann servant, Zorumar,
is a potential ally here. He can’t do anything against his master directly, but
he can give all sorts of information about enemy locations and the layout of the
fort, including all secret doors. Killing Lucien will set Zorumar free, and he
will return in the future to gift the party with magic items in thanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a secret door in the fort’s armory leading to the ancient dwarven
mechanism in the “basement” level. The only one of its current inhabitants who
knows about this is Zorumar.  The device, called the Anvil of Unmaking, is
protected by ancient guardians and traps, some of which can be bypassed by
proper prayers to the dwarf god Torag and by diplomacy. Activating the
contraption will cause it to completely destroy the fortress in 10 minutes. The
PCs have that long to run away and get clear. Also the tremors and rumbling will
definitely put every remaining enemy in the place on high alert, if they weren’t
already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loot-wise, the most valuable places to hit here are the treasury (obviously),
the war room, and Lucien Thrune’s person. Lucien has a sweet flaming sword, lots
of bling, and the key to the treasury chest. The treasury has a bunch of magical
gear and the fort’s payroll. And the war room has an extremely valuable dagger
lying around next to a pile of important strategic documents full of classified
Chelish military info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes-and-impressions-1&quot;&gt;Notes and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good old tactical espionage action romp, with the potential to turn into a
wonderfully chaotic battle if the PCs trip the alarm. It’s likely to be the most
time-consuming scene in the entire adventure, and could conceivably take more
than one session to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest playing the enemies with a modicum of intelligence here, but remember
that raising the alarm is not an automatic action. If a single guard spots the
PCs, the rest of the fortress won’t automatically know they’re there. An alarm
must be raised, which takes time and is susceptible to disruption from the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/10/hells-rebels-3-part-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/10/hells-rebels-3-part-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fuzzy turns in GURPS Combat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As you might know from reading here before, I hang out on the RPG.net forums a
lot. Whenever a discussion about GURPS starts there, some people often complain
they feel intimidated or annoyed by the 1-second combat turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other games tend to have a less granular concept of turn duration and of what
exactly constitutes an action, so players used to them usually expect to be able
to do one “complete thing” in each turn without bothering with detailed setup
steps. For example, a ranged attack with a bow in D&amp;amp;D takes a single action that
includes aiming, shooting, drawing a new arrow, and nocking it, all of which are
distinct steps in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually like 1-second turns and will be keeping them in my games, but I
present here a possible way to make them fuzzier for those groups who don’t
enjoy them as much. This is a fairly fundamental change to the base GURPS
system, probably lends itself better to games that used simplified combat rules
instead of things like detailed hex maps and range measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also helps combat feel a bit more like what you might see in action movies
or similar media, which tend to slow down things to make them easier to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fuzzy-combat-in-gurps&quot;&gt;Fuzzy Combat in GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this rule, a combat round is no longer exactly 1 second long. Now it takes
an unspecified amount of time between 5 and 10 seconds long - enough for
everyone to act once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-maneuver actions that can be resolved in a 1-second turn under the
original rules still take 1 turn to resolve here. This includes most melee and
ranged attacks, movement, and the Aim and Evaluate maneuvers. Advantages such as
Extra Attack and techniques like Rapid Strike work exactly as written, with the
same limitations, but read “seconds” as “turns”. The RoF stat retains its value
for all weapons that have it, but read it as “shots per turn” instead of “shots
per second”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actions that would take multiple consecutive maneuvers over several turns to
perform now take 1 turn per 10 seconds or fraction thereof they would originally
take. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swapping magazines on a modern gun took 3 seconds, so now it takes 1 turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reloading a musket took 40 seconds, so it takes 4 turns now.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any spell that would require less than 10 seconds to cast can be cast in a
single turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Searching through your pack for an item took 2d seconds. As the average of
that roll is less than 10, it only requires a turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Picking a lock takes a minute, which means 6 turns. Accepting a -5 penalty to
do it in 30 seconds means it takes 3 turns. This makes it possible to do
during a fight.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fast-Draw skill now encompasses a series of actions taken to speed up a
given process. It can reduce the time an appropriate action takes by 1 turn, to
a minimum of 0. So you can still use it to draw a weapon and attack on the same
turn, or to reload a pistol and keep firing on the same turn. That musket is
still going to take 3 turns before it can fire again. You might want to make it
Average instead of Easy since a single roll covers a larger set of actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes make characters such as archers and wizards more powerful in
combat, since the number of things they can do over a given amount of turns has
increased, while melee-focused character can still take more or less the same
number of actions. Note that I have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; tested how these changes interact
with the magic system, so I can’t measure how much of an impact it’s going to
have on spellcasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-we-avoided&quot;&gt;Things we Avoided&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that we didn’t attempt to increase the effective number of actions by the
same multiplier as the turn duration. If a character could attack every second
under the standard rules, they don’t get to make 5-10 attacks in a single turn
here. Aiming or Evaluating for multiple seconds gave you extra bonuses, but you
don’t get them automatically here - you must perform those maneuvers for the
same number of turns. Our goal is to remove multi-step complex procedures, not
to keep counting seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is more abstract and perhaps less realistic, and that is the point. If
you want to keep tracking events second-by-second, stick with the standard
rules.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/19/gurps-fuzzy-turns.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/19/gurps-fuzzy-turns.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Warforged Variants for Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/warforged_knight_by_will_e_h-d6ewj3b.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://will-e-h.deviantart.com/art/Warforged-Knight-387829415&quot;&gt;Illustration
  by Will-E-H&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way back in the olden days of 2017, I published a post presenting the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/09/17/dfrpg-warforged.html&quot;&gt;Warforged&lt;/a&gt; of D&amp;amp;D and Eberron fame as a racial template for the Dungeon
Fantasy RPG. I’m still particularly proud of that post, and have used it in
actual play, but I also think I can expand upon it a bit now. So here’s a couple
variant warforged templates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/10/18/peoples-of-tamriel.html&quot;&gt;2018 post&lt;/a&gt; where I explained how I came up with the stats for the
peoples of Tamriel, I mentioned that I’m no longer a fan of including attribute
adjustments and mental or cultural disadvantages in GURPS racial templates. The
original 2017 Warforged template still includes both, even though it’s a bit
more restrained with them. So our first variant is an updated template that
removes those adjustments. It ends up being cheaper! Our second variant adds a
lens on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-20-points&quot;&gt;Warforged (20 points)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the story-related descriptions remain the same as in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/09/17/dfrpg-warforged.html&quot;&gt;original
post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages&lt;/strong&gt;: Composite Plating 1 {5}; Doesn’t Breathe {20}; Doesn’t Eat or
Drink {10}; Unsleeping Watcher {10}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/strong&gt;: Dependency (Mana, Constantly) {-25}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/09/17/dfrpg-warforged.html&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;, Composite Plating is simply DR 1 without
the Though Skin limitation, and Unsleeping Watcher is Less Sleep 4 with a +25%
enhancement that allows the character to remain conscious during their sleep
period. Check out the link for more flavorful and detailed descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lens-dreaming-doll--2-points&quot;&gt;Lens: Dreaming Doll (-2 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/plain-doll.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://www.deviantart.com/enijoi/art/Plain-Doll-634134454&quot;&gt;
  Illustration by Enijoi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lens represent living constructs that do require actual sleep, though they
still require less of it than us fleshbags. This replaces Unsleeping Watcher {10}
with standard Less Sleep 4 {8}. The character is not aware of their surroundings
when sleeping, but they are capable of dreaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting lens if you want a character who resembles the Doll from
Bloodborne more than a standard Eberron warforged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-gifts&quot;&gt;Warforged Gifts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These optional traits are available to any warforged. They are individual rather
than racial traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optional traits from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/09/17/dfrpg-warforged.html&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt; remain options
here, and are still good to represent the social awkwardness of recently
activated individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged with access to the proper tools could spend 5 points/level to increase
their innate DR up to 3. The same tools might allow them to change their outward
appearance and presentation in ways that let them acquire levels in the
Appearance advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters wanting more protection might buy the Accessory (Armor Hardpoints)
perk for 1 point. This lets them use custom armor that weights 25% less than the
normal humanoid version, but can’t be used by others or removed on the
fly. Attaching or removing this custom armor can only be done in town. It costs
the same as the normal equivalent. Warforged with the perk can still choose to
wear normal armor, but can’t wear normal and attached armor together on the same
location.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/02/07/warforged-variants.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/02/07/warforged-variants.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shadowrun: Goncharov</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently read about a fun Tumblr meme. It’s about Goncharov, a 1973 Martin
Scorcese movie that never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It began when someone posted a picture of these bootleg boots they bought
somewhere. The brand label had one of those word salads copied from somewhere
and edited by someone not too familiar with the target language. In this case,
it was copied from a poster for Gomorrah, a real movie. And it read “Martin
Scorcese presents Goncharov”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tumblr &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tumblr.com/hussyknee/701454778540146688/im-so-confused-rn-can-you-explain-the-goncharov&quot;&gt;kinda ran with it&lt;/a&gt;, so now you have a lot of people making things up about
the movie and fabricating screenshots, posters, bits of soundtrack, talking
about all of this as if it was a real cinematic masterpiece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone in a Discord server I frequent suggested Goncharov should become a
standard name for someone who doesn’t exist, the opposite of John Doe. And this
got me thinking about Shadowrun again. Here are two uses for the name Goncharov
in a Shadowrun-like setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mundane&quot;&gt;The Mundane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Shadowrun, “Mr. Johnson” is shadowrunner slang for a person who hires
shadowrunners. The stereotypical Mr. Johnson is a shady fuck in a suit who talks
in vague businesslike terms&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but it can be anyone who is willing to be the
“client” for a runner group. That’s an established part of the game already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how about we say Goncharov is the “reverse” term? Goncharov is Johnson code
for shadowrunners! Sure “shadowrunners” is canon and also works well, but you
can’t really write “shadowrunner payoff” in your official corporate ledger, can
you? So instead you write “payment to Goncharov for services rendered”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just like no self-respecting mysterious client calls themselves Mr. Johnson,
no self-respecting runner calls themselves Goncharov. Someone who takes that as
their handle or even as an alias is telling the whole world they’re a clueless
poser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little bit of culture works well in the Shadowrun setting itself, and on
any other setting that has stylish urban mercenaries as characters, including a
lot of GURPS Action or GURPS Cyberpunk campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numinous&quot;&gt;The Numinous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go a bit further, shall we? Here’s a mystical explanation that’s a bit
more mystical than even Shadowrun’s default setting allows for&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and is a bit
closer to Exalted’s take on spirits and magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goncharov is the Small God of Shadowrunners. He started out as an abstraction,
as above, but at some point became a real part of shadowrunning culture. Either
an existing spirit took on the mantle, or folk belief made him real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real&lt;/em&gt; runners, those who are more than amoral assholes doing horrible things
for money, they have an understanding with Goncharov. They never forget the
corps and the big syndicates are the enemy even when circumstances force them to
work for these groups. They never sell out. They know who their community and
friends are, and they look out for them. And after every successful job, they
give Goncharov his cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goncharov looks like a fit but somewhat scuffed up man in a nice but somewhat
scuffed up suit. The details vary, but he never looks overly fancy or
arrogant. In other words, he might look like John Wick after a fight or three,
but never like the Continental Hotel guy - that’s the god of Mr. Johnsons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magicians can take Goncharov as a mentor spirit. He provides bonuses to combat
spells and Spirits of Man, whatever form those bonuses take in your edition of
choice. Non-magicians can also have “an understanding” with him for a slightly
cheaper price. This gives them access to the Goncharov’s Cut rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goncharovs-cut&quot;&gt;Goncharov’s Cut&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have an understanding with the god of Shadowrunners, and keep to his
code, can gain extra Karma for giving him his cut. This includes magicians who
take him as a mentor spirit, or any character who spends points to buy a
slightly cheaper Edge representing the covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the Karma for Cash rule in your game, such characters gain an
extra point of Karma when using the rule, if they would already gain at least
one point normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s not a general campaign rule, such characters still gain access to it,
becoming able to exchange money for a single point of Karma after every run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases the money goes to support and improve the runner’s community, or
to help out fellow shadowrunners in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-gurps&quot;&gt;In GURPS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a GURPS Action or Cyberpunk campaign with supernatural elements, The
Understanding is a -10-point Code of Honor, since it’s informal but applies to
interactions with people who are not your peers. Give Goncharov his cut and use
it to support your community and fellow runners; hunt down and punish any who
betray them&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; never sell out; even if you need to do a job for a corp or a
crime syndicate, never forget they’re the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code can work as a “pact” limitation for supernatural or cinematic traits
related to being stealthy, discreet, or good at combat (yes, even Gunslinger or
a talent like Smooth Operator). It would provide a 10% discount on their price,
as normal, and would make these abilities unavailable until atonement if the PC
breaks the attached code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monetary value of Goncharov’s cut is 10% of any earnings from
“shadowrun”-like missions. GMs and players who don’t want to bother with
accounting can just remove it from the PC when it’s given, and assume it gets
spent properly. In games where more detailed tracking is important, the PC
doesn’t need to spend the money immediately, just set it aside for use when
necessary. Using it for personal benefit after it’s been set aside is a
violation of the Code, though. If the protected community has its own
organization stats, the player might want to consider transferring this money
from the PC to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the code might also lead to acquiring traits such as positive
reputation among your community or fellow runners, or Enemies in the form of
traitorous villains and amoral mercenaries who think you’re weak for having a
conscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atonement from breaking the code usually takes the form of a dangerous mission
to aid an oppressed community or fellow runner in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And who betrays you at the end. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though I understand it was kinda moving in this direction in its latest
editions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, you are totally following the code if you track Clockwork down and
shoot him in the head after telling him “Goncharov says hi”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/22/goncharov.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/22/goncharov.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 01</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been playing a lot of Wolfenstein games these past few days. There’s
something cathartic about unapologetically fighting Nazis. I first did it to
de-stress, and then to celebrate the results of our most recent election (go
Lula!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since I do occasionally want to post something here that’s not Let’s Read
the Monster Manual, I decided to talk a bit about the various guns you use to
kill Nazis in all of these games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re dealing with two separate continuities here: one that starts with Return
to Castle Wolfenstein (2001) and another that starts with Wolfenstein: The New
Order (2014). You could, if you’re so inclined, include both of them in the
GURPS Infinite Worlds framework. I’d call then Wolfenstein-1 and Wolfenstein-2
respectively, though I guess Infinity might call the latter Reich-6 at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we’ll cover the stuff that appears in Return to Castle
Wolfenstein (2001), AKA the Wolfenstein-1 setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-overview&quot;&gt;Game Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a flashier remake of Wolfenstein 3D, the game that more or less started
the FPS genre back in 1992. It’s the first game in the franchise to have a more
fleshed out story wrapped around its gameplay, with voiced dialogue and
cutscenes elaborating on the simpler “you must escape the castle and kill Nazis”
plot of the 1992 game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game takes place in a pulpier version of WWII, where the Nazis are working
on a large variety of scary secret projects and the OSA (a joint Allied spy
agency) is sending agents to stop them from hitting the field. The player
character, as always, is William “B. J.” Blazkowicz. He gets sent along with a
British agent to Castle Wolfenstein to find more about these projects, they get
captured, and the game starts with Blazko’s escape attempt and moves on to
thwarting those projects to the Allies can win the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two sinister things going on here: an attempt by the Thule society to
resurrect ancient evil undead knights, and a mad science lab working to build
cyborg supersoldiers. The final boss is, of course, a bunch of cyborg
supersoldiers possessed by the spirits of ancient evil undead knights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-weapons&quot;&gt;Historical Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfenstein-1 is mostly a pulpier version of WWII, so a lot of the weapons we
see are historical and present on GURPS High-Tech. Though sometimes you’ll start
a level with some Allied weapons issued by the OSA, the vast majority of the
time you’ll be using captured German hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSA-issue weapons include the &lt;strong&gt;Colt M1911A1&lt;/strong&gt; pistol (p. HT99), the &lt;strong&gt;Thompson
M1&lt;/strong&gt; submachine gun (p. HT122), and the &lt;strong&gt;Enfield Sten Mk IIS&lt;/strong&gt; submachine gun
(p. HT 125). The integral suppressor of the Sten works according to cinematic
principles here, making it completely silent to enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, one of the “elite guard” units you face in the game also
uses Stens, because they’re meant to be sneaky and the Sten is the only
suppressed SMG in the game. The other OSA weapons are used exclusively by the
player character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;German weapons include the &lt;strong&gt;Luger P08&lt;/strong&gt; pistol, (p. HT98), the &lt;strong&gt;ERMA MP40&lt;/strong&gt;
SMG (p. HT 124), the &lt;strong&gt;Mauser Kar98K&lt;/strong&gt; rifle (p. HT111), the &lt;strong&gt;Rheinmetall
FG42&lt;/strong&gt; battle rifle (p. HT 115) and the &lt;strong&gt;Panzerfaust&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT147). The player
also uses these extensively, since every enemy drops ammo for one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FG42 is the signature weapon of the other “elite guard” unit in the game,
and has the scope described in its High-Tech entry. It’s also possible to find a
suppressor for the Luger and a variable-power scope for the Mauser, which you
can stat up using the generic rules in p. HT 156 and p. HT 158.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can occasionally also find a few &lt;strong&gt;MG42&lt;/strong&gt; machine gun (p. HT 134)
emplacements in the game. There is also a flamethrower similar to the &lt;strong&gt;M2-2&lt;/strong&gt;
(p. HT179), though this is probably the German equivalent rather than the
American version in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grenades also see use, with most of them being the German &lt;strong&gt;Stielhandgranate
24&lt;/strong&gt;, and the rest American &lt;strong&gt;AMC Mk II&lt;/strong&gt; models. Both are on p. HT190-191.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fictional-weapons&quot;&gt;Fictional Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of pulpy arms research going on here on both sides, so we also get
to see some weapons that don’t exist in reality. We’ll cover these in a bit more
detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snooper-rifle&quot;&gt;Snooper Rifle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a prototype sniper rifle issued to Blazkowicz by the OSA early in the
second mission of the game. You also find captured rifles later on while
breaking into one of the games’ many secret lab facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Snooper is the most down-to-earth of the experimental weapons here, being an
exaggerated version of the &lt;strong&gt;M3 Carbine&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT113). Even the fancy infrared
sight is real! The biggest changes are the addition of a cinematic integral
suppressor that makes the gun completely silent, and making the infrared sight
more advanced than it really was. The one in the game has variable magnification
and requires no external batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venom-machine-gun&quot;&gt;Venom Machine Gun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first entirely fictional weapon we encounter in the game, and the
second most unrealistic one. It’s a portable, six-barreled, belt-fed minigun. It
has relatively short barrels, a shoulder stock and rifle-style grips. There’s an
in-game document that describes it as firing 7.92mm saboted armor piercing
rounds, but the ammo for it is labeled as “12.7mm” in game. You first find the
Venom as a prototype in one of the secret labs that make up the game’s levels,
and after that it starts appearing in the hands of some enemy human
soldiers. Most of the cyborg supersoldiers you meet towards the end of the game
also carry one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll need custom stats for this one! Let’s go with the assumption that it fires
7.92mm ammo, to make it minimally plausible for it to be portable. To make it a
little easier on the user, we can further say it fires the 7.92x33mm Kurz round,
instead of the longer 7.92x57mm Mauser round from the Kar98K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The in-game Venom takes up to 500 rounds. These would probably be in a
disintegrating belt inside a metal can that can be worn as a backpack. The whole
thing weights around 16kg, more than the weapon itself. More reasonable 200 and
100 round belts with their smaller containers might weight in at 8 and 4kg
respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll actually base the stats for it on the Minigun from page 138 of GURPS
Ultra-Tech, making the Venom a TL 7+2 weapon. The one on the table fires APDS
ammo, which is also TL 7+2 in this caliber, and has a 500-round belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d+2(2) pi-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000/4000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15kg/16kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25!&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Venom requires Guns (LMG) to operate, or Guns (Longarm) with the Burst-Fire
technique if using the alternate gun skill rules from Pyramid #3/65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tesla-gun&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weapon used by the advanced cyborg supersoldiers you meet at the very end of
the game. Unlike the Venom this doesn’t bear even the tiniest resemblance to any
real gun. Pull the trigger and it fires a stream of lightning until you release
it or until it runs out of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tesla Gun draws power from a superscience backpack battery equivalent to a
TL 9 D cell, but four times heavier. Its damage follows the same rules as the
Lightning spell: metal armor only provides DR 1, and the target must make a HT
roll with a penalty of -1 for every 2 points of injury taken from it. Failure
means they’re stunned, and must attempt an HT roll every turn in order to
recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d+2 burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;600/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;35kg/10kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50 (5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;18M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tesla Gun requires Gunner (Beam) to operate, even when carried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-for-these-fancy-guns&quot;&gt;How much for these fancy guns?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that I ommitted any price information for the Venom and the Tesla
Gun above. That’s because in Wolfenstein-1 they’re secret prototypes with very
limited production runs. You don’t buy them, you pry them from the hands of dead
Nazi assholes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use them on a different setting where they are available for
purchase, use the following costs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom MG&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$12.500&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom Ammo (100-round belt, APDS)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$180&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom Ammo (100-round belt, solid)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$60&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$60.000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Battery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$400&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are for a setting with a tech level of 7+2. If you’re in a “plain” TL9
setting you might want to use the Minigun and Semi-Portable Electrolaser from
Ultra-tech, which have slightly better stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your setting is like Wolfenstein-1, where the overall TL is a plain 7 and
these are secret superscience prototypes, multiply all prices by 4.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Orchard of Time</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had an interesting dream recently that gave me what I think is a neat idea for
a dungeon location: The Orchard of Time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s started out as your standard divine orchard, a bit like the Garden of the
Hesperides. It was owned and operated by a powerful spirit or minor deity, and
its trees gave fruit that ranged from “mundane but high-quality” to “outright
miraculous” the further in you went. If you got to the very center, you could
harvest the Peaches of Immortality or something equally awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something happened to the Orchard’s original owners and they left, abandoning
the place. Monstrous fauna from the surrounding regions moved in and either
overwhelmed the previous guardians or entered some sort of symbiosis with
them. These new monsters found ample food in the trees of the Orchard, whose
energies mutated them to be larger and stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, a powerful arch-wizard found the Orchard’s location and decided to go
for the Peaches. This extremely arrogant individual was sure he would succeed
where all others have failed. After all, the others weren’t him! He armed
himself with his best spells and his best magic items, and teleported to the
Orchard’s entrance (can’t teleport into it from outside). Then he boldly strode
past the gate, and cast his most powerful magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a custom spell that would stop time everywhere in the Orchard except
for an area five meters or so in radius around the wizard himself. The idea was
that, with time stoped, the archmage could just walk up to the really good trees
in the center while dodging the place’s many inhabitants. If he needed to remove
any of them, he could bring them into the “active time” circle and use his other
magic to handle them one individual or small group at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the wizard’s hubris got the better of him at exactly the worst
time. Maybe he had miscalculated when creating the spell, or maybe he made a
critical error when casting it. The fact is that our wizard just
kinda… exploded, leaving behind only his ornate metal staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the spell itself worked exactly as planned. Even better in fact, as
the same error that deleted our wizard made it last forever. It’s centered on
the wizard’s staff, which stands planted on the ground just inside the Orchard’s
entrance gate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;layout-and-hazards&quot;&gt;Layout and Hazards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orchard is located in a hidden valley and is bordered by tall forested
mountains. The climate can range from temperate to tropical depending on what
kind of fruit you want it to contain. As mentioned above, vestigial divine wards
prevent people from finding it with divination or from teleporting into it from
outside. It can still be found via good old-fashioned research, as its location
is recorded in ancient religious texts and in the unfortunate wizard’s own
notes. The wizard has also helpfully dispelled any magical defenses that
prevented people from just walking through the main gate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orchard of Time was a little overgrown from its period of abandonment, but
still retains its characteristic layout. There are many trees but they’re spaced
far apart. Cobbled paths wind their way among them. Grass and other wild plants
reach up to a human’s knees between the trees and paths. This space used to be
taken up by a lawn and flower beds, but these have been overwhelmed by native
plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that despite covering a very large area, the Orchard has excellent
sight lines and a clearly navigable layout. You can see a good deal of its
significant landmarks from the entrance gate and it’s impossible to get lost
inside. These excellent sight lines work against intruders such as the PCs,
because they allow the many, many monsters and guardians that live here to see
them from far away. These creatures are all hostile, territorial, and generally
incapable of dialogue either because they have animal intellect or because
they’re some sort of construct. In the dream I had these monsters definitely
included a variety of Rodents of Unusual Size. There are almost more monsters
than there are fruit, and they all more or less converge on the location of any
intruders they can perceive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or they &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt;, if time hadn’t stopped inside. The wizard’s staff is just
inside the entrance, and it projects a field of “normal time” in a 5-meter
radius around itself. Everything outside this bubble and inside the orchard’s
outer walls is frozen in time, and has been for a long time (decades?
centuries?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs who want to succeed where the arrogant wizard failed need to carry the staff
with them. Getting close enough to a monster that it enters the “bubble” will
unfreeze the creature, and it will imediately attack. There might be a route
that allows them to avoid most of the creatures, but not all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the copious monsters, the permanent time stop might have created
hazardous areas inside the Orchard, where space or time itself behave in harmful
ways. These might be almost impossible to detect until they’re inside the active
time bubble, which would make them reveal themselves in a dramatic fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-go-there&quot;&gt;Why go there?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious reason to delve the Orchard of Time is to get its most awesome
fruits from the big trees at the center, like the wizard wanted to do. The
Orchard might also contain buildings of interest (such as libraries or treasure
vaults), along with the bodies of ancient adventurers who tried to delve the
place before the ill-fated wizard. Some of these might be legendary themselves,
and have died carrying their equally legendary gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slightly alternate Orchard would have been invaded by the wizard while it was
still operational! In this case it’s going to be in pristine condition, with all
of its original guardians and security systems still in place. Even its &lt;em&gt;owners&lt;/em&gt;
will still be around, frozen in time like flies in amber. Freeing them is an
excellent goal for more heroic sorts, or at least for sorts who need the
specific help whose divine entities are able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since those owners are frozen in time, they’re still going to be under
the impression that they’re being invaded by a cheeky wizard. And look at you,
carrying his staff around like that. Better talk fast!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/10/23/orchard-of-time.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/10/23/orchard-of-time.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
