<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 18:20:38 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 18:20:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dune Reaper</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dune-reaper.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A dune reaper. This image is mirrored from the one in the book.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of other Athasian fauna, dune reapers are predatory
insectile/reptilian pack hunters. However, they lean a lot more towards the
“insectile” side, and their origins are clearly unnatural even to contemporary
inhabitants of Athas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book says they “came to existence through defiling magic”, though it doesn’t
specify whether they were an artificially engineered species or whether some
side effect of defiling brought them to the world. Their Aberrant origin kinda
hints at the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures have a complex social structure. They organize into large
familial groups known as prides, who build large hives from sand, rocks, and
organic secretions near a water source that becomes the center of their
territory. The pride then splits up into smaller packs, which roam that
territory looking for food. A pack is composed of a large female “warrior”,
accompanied by smaller male “drones” and “shrieks” who are her mates. The
pride’s dominant female is known as its “matron”, and it’s her who makes
decisions that affect the whole pack, like where to build the hive or when to
seek new territory. A matron rules the pride until her death, which is usually
in a duel with an up-and-coming warrior who challenges her for the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune reapers are a scourge on the local ecology. Their menu includes just about
everything they can reach: humanoids, animals, plants, wagons, buildings… they
even eat rocks to store in their gizzards and aid in the digestion of tougher
food. A humanoid settlement in dune reaper territory is only safe if they can
provide the creatures with an ample alternate source of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune reaper reproduction happens on an annual cycle, and they’re even more
dangerous during mating season. The pride’s females need to lay their eggs
inside the bodies of living creatures, you see. When the eggs hatch, the newborn
reapers eat their host, and then set upon each other. Only the strongest
hatchlings survive this process. After about two months they’re already as
dangerous as a fully grown adult. At this time, they’re driven from their birth
hive and must either join another pride or form a new one with other young
reapers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune Reapers are Aberrant Beasts with Darkvision. Their basic melee attack
always uses their &lt;strong&gt;Arm Blades&lt;/strong&gt;, which do standard damage for their level and
might have other effects depending on the stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-reaper-drone&quot;&gt;Dune Reaper Drone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These relatively small males are Medium and make up the dune reaper worker
caste. They build the hive and carry food back to it, but as Level 12
Skirmishers with 120 HP and Speed 8 they’re certainly strong enough to take part
in the hunt as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;arm blade&lt;/strong&gt; attack also lets them shift 1 square on a hit. They
can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping Slash&lt;/strong&gt; that lets them jump 4 squares without provoking
opportunity attacks and use Arm Blade at the end of the movement. This recharges
when they’re first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy grants Combat Advantage to the drone, it can use a minor action to
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, dealing light physical damage on a hit. If an enemy makes a melee
attack against the drone, it can &lt;strong&gt;Leap Away&lt;/strong&gt;, jumping 4 squares without
drawing OAs, as an immediate reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drones want to leap into melee at the start of the fight, and seek positions
where their chosen target grants them CA. They’ll leap away when attacked and
come back from an unexpected angle. When fighting drones, shoot them or surround
them. Don’t let them surround you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-reaper-shriek&quot;&gt;Dune Reaper Shriek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not a role you usuall find among mundane insects. The book considers them
specialized drones that can leap not just through the air, but through time and
space. When they do this, they emit an ear-splitting scream that gives them
their name. They’re Level 14 Lurkers with 106 HP and Speed 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;arm blades&lt;/strong&gt; are standard attacks with no riders, and are a lot more
dangerous when used in conjunction with the shriek’s freaky powers. A
&lt;strong&gt;Shrieking Reap&lt;/strong&gt; lets them make two arm blade attacks against the same
target. If one hits, it teleports the target 2 squares and inflicts 10 ongoing
damage (save ends). If both hit, the teleport distance increases to 5, and the
ongoing damage to 15. A &lt;strong&gt;Shrieking Warp&lt;/strong&gt; removes the shriek from play until
the start of its next turn, when it appears at a spot within 10 squares of its
previous position and makes a Close Burst 2 attack that deals thunder damage and
pushes 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shrieking Warp is an at-will ability, but it’s disabled for a turn when the
shriek takes force damage because of its &lt;strong&gt;Forceful Silence&lt;/strong&gt; trait. Shrieking
Reap recharges whenever the creature uses Shrieking Warp. Our lurker loop here
is Shrieking Reap -&amp;gt; Shrieking Warp -&amp;gt; Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book reminds us that forced movement is always voluntary for the attacker,
so shrieks arriving from a Warp will often choose to push all but one of the
enemies they hit with the attack, to isolate it from its allies. Clever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-reaper-warrior&quot;&gt;Dune Reaper Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Large female will lead a pack of drones and shrieks when hunting. She’s a
Level 15 Brute with 180 HP, Speed 7, and the Leader tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She exudes an aura (3) of &lt;strong&gt;Inciting Pheromones&lt;/strong&gt; that grants all dune reapers
inside a +2 bonus to Will, and makes them immune to the Dazed condition. She
also has the &lt;strong&gt;Unhindered&lt;/strong&gt; trait we saw before, which lets her drag grabbed
characters around when she moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her &lt;strong&gt;arm blade&lt;/strong&gt; is Reach 2 and extra-strong. She can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping
Slash&lt;/strong&gt; similar to the drone’s, which also inflicts 10 ongoing damage if either
attack hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her triggered actions make her even more dangerous. &lt;strong&gt;Snapping Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt;
triggers when someone hits the warrior with a melee attack. As a reaction, she
attacks their Fortitude and grabs them on a hit. Grabbed targets take 10 damage
when they fail an escape attempt. Her &lt;strong&gt;Compelling Musk&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is
triggered when she misses with an Arm Blade attack, and lets another dune reaper
within 3 squares make a melee basic attack as an opportunity action. I’m not
going to make a joke about that power name, it’s too easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune reaper packs number between 5 and 12 (!) individuals. Only one will be a
warrior, though you could say the PCs found more than one pack together if you
want there to be more of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reapers are impossible to train, but sapient humanoids still capture them for
use as arena beasts, and hunt them as a source of leather, organic armor plates,
and blades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These seem to me like yet another pack-based predator, the third or fourth we
saw in this reading. I do like the ominous aberrant touches in both their lore
and mechanics, though. The shriek in particular reminds me a lot of a Hound of
Tindalos.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/24/wir-dscc-dune-reaper.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/24/wir-dscc-dune-reaper.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dwarf</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dwarf.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A Dark Sun dwarf. This world is too hot for big beards.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s customary for Fourth Edition monster books to include entries for playable
species. After all, they may show up as enemies or allies. In this book, they
also serve to flesh out some of the Dark Sun-specific story of each species. As
you can see from the illustration, dwarves here are a little different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwarves probably had a pretty typical culture in Athas’ distant past, as the
book says they ruled “great mountain kingdoms”. However, the genocidal wars of
the Red Age pretty much destroyed their civilization. While modern-day dwarves
are still extremely resilient and dedicated workers, the knowledge of reading
and writing the Dwarven language has been lost. While you can still find Davek
runes in their ruins, no one alive knows how to read them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book kinda conflates this with dwarves not knowing how to read at all, and
therefore not knowing any magic, but that’s a giant leap that I think is
incorrect. Dwarven writing is a lost art, but Common and a lot of other
languages still have written forms and magic lore doesn’t have to be encoded in
Dwarven. I’d say dwarves are as likely to be literate and to know magic rituals
as any other person in this setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True, when you’re talking about typical civilians that’s still not very likely,
but Dwarven PCs and major NPCs will still be literate. And it does sound
flavorful for modern dwarven culture to include an element of pride about not
needing magic to do their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwarves are a fairly common people. Every city state has hundreds or thousands
of dwarven laborers and artisans, both free and enslaved. They also live in
small communities in the wastes, some of which are also mining camps. Whether
your interaction with them is peaceful or violent depends entirely on the
behavior of the PCs and on the objectives of that specific group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the differences, Athasian dwarves are still Medium Natural Humanoids
with a ground speed of 5 and Low-Light Vision, just like the ones from the
PHB. They retain the PC traits that make them hard to move: &lt;strong&gt;Stand the Ground&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Steady-Footed&lt;/strong&gt;, which reduce forced movement by 1 and let them roll a
save against being knocked prone, respectively. They also have +5 to saves
against poison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier editions spent a lot of time describing how each dwarf had an obsessive
focus on one kind of task, to the point where it restricted their actions. That
makes an appearance here but it’s not as dominant as before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dwarf-conscript&quot;&gt;Dwarf Conscript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically a civilian, the conscript still has a body hardened by countless
hours of heavy labor, and will not hesitate to pick up weapons in defense of
their mine or their home. This is a Level 2 Brute with 47 HP, wearing hide armor
and wielding a Dark Sun polearm known as a “gouge”, which is basically a
sharpened shovel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;gouge&lt;/strong&gt; is a standard brute attack, but if it scores a critical hit it
also pushes the target 1 square and knocks it prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conscript also has a &lt;strong&gt;Singular Focus&lt;/strong&gt; minor action that’s the last vestige
of the 2e rules. This lets the conscript choose an enemy as the target of their
focus, and gain +5 damage against that enemy while they remain the conscript’s
focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power recharges when the chosen enemy drops to 0 HP, and it lasts until the
end of the encounter or until the conscript uses it again. It makes the
conscript punch &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; above their weight class when attacking their chosen
enemy, and is a very nice incentive to behave obsessively in a fight. Since they
can only switch focus when the previous enemy dies, targeted enemies should keep
away to make the conscript waste actions chasing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dwarf-sunpriest&quot;&gt;Dwarf Sunpriest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern dwarven religion venerates primal spirits and elementals, particularly
those associated with the sun. Sun priests are venerated spiritual and political
leaders among them, and often lead other dwarves into battle when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sunpriest is Level 5 Artillery with 52 HP and the Leader tag. They wear hide
armor and wield a mace in one hand and a totem in the other. Their basic melee
attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Burning Mace&lt;/strong&gt; that deals fire damage, and their main ranged
attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Bright Ray&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10) that deals radiant damage and inflicts a
-2 attack penalty on the target for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can apply a &lt;strong&gt;Sun Blessing&lt;/strong&gt; to an ally within 5
squares. That ally regains 10 HP, deals 5 extra fire damage with their attacks
for a turn, and any enemy that hits them in the same time span takes 5 fire
damage. Praise the sun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dwarf-war-chief&quot;&gt;Dwarf War Chief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the name, not all war chiefs are commanders, but they’re all renowned
champions. They’re Level 6 Elite Soldiers with 144 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war chief fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; made from giant bone, and its basic
attacks grant them 5 temporary HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;Spinning Club&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge
5+) attacks enemies in a Close Burst 1. If it hits an enemy marked by the war
chief, that enemy is immobilized until the start of the warchief’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how do they mark enemies? Via &lt;strong&gt;Battlefield Focus&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action that
lets them automatically mark up to 2 enemies within 10 squares. It recharges
when one of these enemies drops to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a marked enemy adjacent to the war chief moves, shifts, or makes an attack,
&lt;strong&gt;Brutal Club&lt;/strong&gt; gives the dwarf a basic attack against them as an interrupt,
which also immobilizes for a turn on a hit. This triggers &lt;em&gt;even if the enemy
attacks the war chief&lt;/em&gt;, and even if the enemy makes one of those moves that
doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks. This means it’s more powerful than a PC
fighter’s Combat Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwarves can be part of any encounter group whose theme is “a bunch of people”,
be they villainous, allied, or bystanders. Dwarven communities, like everyone
else, also domesticate a number of Athasian beasts that might see use in a
fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these stat blocks! They’re low-level but each has some very interesting
tricks they can use. The “focus” powers ended up being more useful than I
thought at first.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/20/wir-dscc-dwarf.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/20/wir-dscc-dwarf.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Drake</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athas only has one dragon: The Dragon of Tyr. He’s the setting’s main bad guy,
over and above the Sorcerer-Kings. As such, he’s immensely powerful,
intelligent, and evil. Prime Final Boss material!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, you might not want to wait until your PCs are level 30 demigods before
they can fight a nasty giant lizard with elemental powers. That’s where Drakes
come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athas has a lot of things that would be called drakes in standard 4e, but here
the name refers to something else entirely. The things Athasians call “Drakes”
are, essentially, nonsapient dragons. They fulfill many of a dragon’s narrative
functions. They’re big and tough enemies that make splendid boss fights for
high-Paragon or low-Epic parties. There are several types associated with
different elements. They lair in areas dominated by their associated element and
possess psychic powers that let them summon and control orbs of that element
from the Elemental Chaos. They even have a hoarding instinct!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roles they &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; fulfill are those of being a Machiavellian plotter or a
big player in regional politics, which are things you’d expect a powerful enough
dragon to be. They’re animals, not people. A text box informs us drakes were
written this way because the Dark Sun setting is very geographically limited,
and has a relatively small number of movers-and-shakers who are all accounted
for. Adding an arbitrary number of traditional sapient epic dragons to this mix
would wreck the setting’s delicate equilibrium, and that’s a job for the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of drakes not being sapient is that there’s no guarantee
their hoards will be &lt;em&gt;valuable&lt;/em&gt;. There might be some good loot there, but it’s
going to be mixed with a mountain of trinkets and souvenirs that are merely
shiny or pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All drakes presented here are Huge Elemental Beasts with the Reptile tag, and a
tag corresponding to their associated element. They all have a &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a
&lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that act as basic attacks, and the signature &lt;strong&gt;Drake’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; power
that lets them spend a single action to use two Claws against one target and a
Bite against a different target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their elemental orb powers are area attacks that create a hazardous zone in the
affected area, but their exact powers vary with each stat block. They always
have a &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; reaction that lets them immediately rechage and use
an elemental power when first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same text box that discusses why drakes are nonsapient tells us we can take
any dragon from other books and add them as drakes in Athas by declaring them
nonsapient. Good candidates include brown, gray and red dragons from the
chromatics; adamantine, iron, and orium dragons from the metallics; and any of
the catastrophic dragons. You might want to change the appearance of the
metallics too, since their default coloration stands out too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;water-drake&quot;&gt;Water Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-water.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A water drake ready to ambush you from its oasis hideout.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water drakes like to lair in oases. A possible sign of their presence is the
total &lt;em&gt;absence&lt;/em&gt; of the small animals that usually live in such an
environment. If you find such a place, you should either keep moving or be very,
very sneaky when filling your waterskin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This crocodile-looking beast is a Level 18 Solo Controller with 680 HP. It has
Resist 10 Cold, a ground speed of 8, and a swim speed of 12. It’s &lt;strong&gt;Aquatic&lt;/strong&gt;,
meaning it can breathe underwater and gets +2 to attacks against non-aquatic
creatures in underwater combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake’s elemental attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Water&lt;/strong&gt;,
which is a fireball-sized area attack (area 2 within 10, recharge 5+). It comes
in two versions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;boiling&lt;/strong&gt; orb deals fire damage despite being made of water, and creates
a damaging zone that lasts for the rest of the encounter or until the drake
uses another boiling orb.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;ice&lt;/strong&gt; orb deals no immediate damage, but inflicts ongoing 20 cold damage
and restrains (save ends both). It creates a zone that repeats the orb’s
attack against any creatures start their turn in the zone and are not
restrained. Again, this lasts until the end of the encounter or until the
drake uses another ice orb.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this means the drake can have both a boiling and a frozen zone in place
simultaneously, though I’d rule they can’t overlap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake’s other power is &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Clone&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action, recharge 4+), which
lets it create a duplicate of itself on a solid or liquid adjacent space in the
map. The copy can acts independently and can take a full turn on an initiative
count 10 lower than the original’s. It has all the original’s stats and powers
with the following exceptions: it only has 1 HP; and it shares the original’s
recharge roll for its powers instead of having its own. If the original has any
spent powers when it uses this power, the copy’s powers will also start out
spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water drake’s &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; recharges &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; the Orb and Psionic
Clone, letting the drake use both as a free action right then and
there. Double the orbs, double the fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-drake&quot;&gt;Fire Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-fire.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A fire drake roaring atop a patch of flaming ground.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flavor text here has a fire drake living inside an active volcano and
worshipped as a god by a halfling tribe, who try to sacrifice a human to it only
to be eaten along with the intended victim. Cliches aside, this shows us you can
find fire drakes in volcanos and other such places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire drakes are Level 20 Elite Lurkers with 298 HP, a Speed of 9, and Resist 15
Fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; does standard damage for its level. The &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; is a
little weaker but grabs on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Drake’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; works as normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creature’s &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Fire&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is an Area Burst 1 within
10 that deals fire damage and creates a damaging fire zone that lasts until the
end of the encounter or until the drake casts another orb. While it waits for
the power to recharge, it can use minor actions to move the existing magma zone
4 squares. The drake’s &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; recharges this orb and lets the
beast use it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire drake’s last power is not elemental: it’s &lt;strong&gt;Living Shield&lt;/strong&gt;, an
opportunity action that lets the beast use a grabbed victim as a shield if
anyone other than that victim damages it. This makes the victim take half of the
attack’s damage, with the other half still affecting the drake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing terribly lurkery about the fire drake. With that grab and the
mobile zone, you could have made it a controller instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;air-drake&quot;&gt;Air Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-air.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An air drake in a menacing stance.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air drakes live in tall mountains and canyons. They love to hunt animals and
people who try to walk the precarious passes of these places, knocking them down
with their wind powers and devouring the tenderized remains. They’re Level 22
Elite Skirmishers with 404 HP, a ground speed of 8, and a flight speed of 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures deal extra damage when they have CA on an enemy, and this bonus
increases when they’re bloodied. Their physical attacks are otherwise pretty
standard for a drake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Air&lt;/strong&gt; has a wider radius than usual (area burst 3
within 10), and deals untyped damage on a hit. On a hit it also slides the
targets 5 squares, and creates the usual damaging zone. The zone cannot be
moved, but slides targets 3 squares when it damages them. This recharges when
the drake is first bloodied, but it has to be used during the drake’s actions
after this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When pressured, the drake can use &lt;strong&gt;Wind Veil&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action (recharge
4+). This lets it shift its speed and gain concealment against non-adjacent
enemies until the end of its next turn. &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; recharges this,
and lets the creature use it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt odd for Bloodied Response to be such a defensive power here… but then
I saw that it’s because the drake can use &lt;strong&gt;Control the Wind&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction
when damaged. This is a Close Burst 5 vs. AC that deals the same damage as the
bite to the triggering enemy, and lets the monster slide the target 3
squares. Exceptionally, this slide can be &lt;em&gt;vertical&lt;/em&gt;, which means the target
will take a bit of fall damage when it falls back to the ground… or a lot of
fall damage if tossed diagonally into a chasm. A merciful GM could probably
still allow the usual save vs. hazardous terrain to let the victim cling to an
edge before being tossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;earth-drake&quot;&gt;Earth Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-earth.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An earth drake.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spicy bullette with earth control powers. Earth Drakes are Level 24 Elite
Controllers with 456 HP, a ground speed of 8, and a burrow speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their physical attaks work as usual. Their &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Earth&lt;/strong&gt; is an Area
1 within 10 attack vs. Fortitude. It damages and restrains (save ends) on a hit,
deals half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting zone is difficult terrain, and the drake can use minor actions to
make secondary attacks against anyone inside. This deals a tiny bit of physical
damage and knocks the target prone. This is what &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt;
recharges, but it’s not the only thing that happens when the earth drake is
bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, when that happens the drake &lt;strong&gt;Expands&lt;/strong&gt;. It goes from Huge to
Gargantuan, pushing any targets that were adjacent to it out of its new occupied
space. While this lasts (until the end of the drake’s next turn), the drake’s
melee reach improves from 3 to 4, it gains +2 to AC, and anyone hit by its
attacks is immobilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone damages the drake it can use &lt;strong&gt;Immovable Stone&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction,
ignoring up to 4 squares of forced movement and using its bite against the
attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Athasian Drakes lack sapience, it’s harder to justify them being
accompanied by minions. However, all but the Water Drake are elites, which means
it’s very easy to set up an encounter against a mated pair of them. It might
also be possible to add elementals of an appropriate level to any drake
encounter as extra minions or regulars. The beasts wouldn’t be interested in
eating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I like their mechanics. Taking one of these drakes and turning them into
a sapient dragon for outside of Dark Sun is as easy as taking a foreign dragon
and turning it into an Athasian Drake.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/16/wir-dscc-drake.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/16/wir-dscc-drake.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dragonborn (Dray)</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dragonborn.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A dragonborn sorcerer in the Athasian desert.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the title of their entry, these Dragonborn are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a new
addition. Dark Sun is one of two 2e settings (that I know of) that had draconic
humanoids in it since its initial publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite using dragonborn stats for the PC version, these are not the same
dragonborn as the ones from the standard Points of Light setting. Athasian
dragonborn are known as Dray, are lankier than the standard variety, and have a
completely different origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dray species was created by the sorcerer-king Dregoth to be his perfect
servants and minions, but he was dissatisfied with the result and cast most
of them out of his city-state of Giustenal. Those he allowed to stay kept
serving him until the other sorcerer-kings banded together to destroy Dregoth
and his city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s Dray are descended both from the outcasts and from the survivors of
Giustenal’s destruction. Their total population is relatively small and few
people know of their existence. Their communities are either small scattered
tribes in the wastes or the rare enclave embedded in a larger settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their reputation among those who know about them is as slavers and
sorcerers. Not All Dray (TM) deserve this reputation… but a significant
majority of them do. They practice defiling magic and slavery, and frequently
act as mercenaries for other groups who are okay with this. In this, they
continue the cycle of abuse, inflicting on others what their creator inflicted
on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dray, like standard dragonborn, are Medium Natural Humanoids with a Speed
of 6. They can use a &lt;strong&gt;Dragon Breath&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter, a Close Blast 3
vs. Reflex that deals some sort of elemental damage and whose details vary with
the stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can easily use standard dragonborn stat blocks from the other monster books
as more dray varieties if you need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-slaver&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Slaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These assholes roam the desert looking for easily taken captives that they can
sell to the sorcerer-kings in exchange for money and prestige. They’re
frequently found in mixed-species slaver parties as their rank-and-file muscle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slavers are Level 16 Minion Soldiers that fight with &lt;strong&gt;Bastard Swords&lt;/strong&gt; which
damage and mark for a turn on a hit. Their &lt;strong&gt;Dragon Breath&lt;/strong&gt; deals lightning
damage and marks (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re tougher than your average minion too - the first time they drop to 0 HP,
their &lt;strong&gt;Determined Defender&lt;/strong&gt; trait lets them recover, clear any effects on
them, and get back on at the start of their next turn. This makes them more
willing to risk harm when surrounding the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-scorned-champion&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Scorned Champion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few dray take pride in being scorned by their creator, making that part of
their identity. I’m guessing these are the nicer ones, since it would make sense
for them to reject the ways of the sorcerer-kings. The Scorned Champion is an
example of someone who might rise to lead a community of these Dray. Still, he’s
sensitive to anything he perceives as a challenge to his position, and is quick
to strike down the source of that challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scorned Champion is a Level 16 Skirmisher with 151 HP. This cocky fighter’s
&lt;strong&gt;Bravura Poise&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (1) that forces enemies inside to grant combat
advantage. He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; that damages the target and lets him
shift 1 square on a hit. The &lt;strong&gt;Dray Fury&lt;/strong&gt; special attack (recharge 4+) lets him
shift his speed and strike twice with the scimitar at any point during this
movement. His &lt;strong&gt;DragonBreath&lt;/strong&gt; can exclude one creature of his choice from the
blast, and deals fire-and-lightning damage. Finally, his &lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable Force&lt;/strong&gt;
power lets him immediately end any Slow or Immobilize effect on him once per
round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-defiler&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Defiler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drays like this one go in the other direction - they look fondly upon the past
when they could walk the streets unchallenged, openly displaying their arcane
might. They want the power to do that again, and see defiling as the quickest
way to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defiler is Level 18 Artillery with 129 HP. They use &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; as weapons
and implements, and the damage roll on this attack has a funky format that mixes
physical and cold damage. Their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Dragonfear Ray&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 10 vs. Will) that deals psychic damage and causes the target to take 5
damage each time they damage the defiler or one of its allies, until the end of
the target’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their dragon breath has been corrupted into a &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5
vs. Reflex) that deals immediate and ongoing cold-and-necrotic damage (save
ends). While at least one target is taking this ongoing damage, the defiler has
+2 to all attacks and +5 to all damage rolls. This recharges if the defiler
misses every target with the power, so it will keep doing it until it hits
someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter the defiler can cast &lt;strong&gt;Flight of Dragons&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action,
allowing every ally within 5 squares to fly 5 squares, and flying 10 squares
itself. It doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks when it leaves its starting
square, but obeys the rules normally from that point on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action it can also use &lt;strong&gt;Hurled Dragon Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) to do
just that with a less corrupt form of its breath. This is either a Close Blast 5
or an Area 2 Within 10, both targetting Reflex. It deals cold damage on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-atavist&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Atavist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dray like this one prefer to focus on the bestial nature of their dragon
heritage, using ritual techniques to tap into that inner beast and bring it
forth during combat. Why use weapons when you have the power of a dragon at your
disposal? This one’s a Level 19 Brute with 220 HP and Resist 10 Acid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attacks are a strong &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a slightly less strong &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;,
both of which deal ongoing acid damage on a hit (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Draconic Fury&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) lets them use both attacks with one action, or even engage in a
classic claw/claw/bite routine if they’re bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their dragon breath, as you might expect, does acid damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems the only stat block here that’s actively Evil is the Defiler - everyone
else is unaligned, even the slavers. I’m not sure I agree with that last part,
but I suppose you can use the slaver stat block for a more conventional non-evil
warrior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad the game gives us some tools to stat up a non-evil group of Dray. PCs
have to come from somewhere, and it’d get a little samey if all of them were
nonconformist rebels fleeing their evil upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/11/wir-dscc-dragonborn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/11/wir-dscc-dragonborn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read The Dark Sun Creature Catalog: (Not) The Dragon of Tyr</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At this point in our &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;read-through of the Dark Sun Creature Catalog&lt;/a&gt;, it the
next entry in the book would be the Dragon of Tyr. As I mentioned in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.rpg.net/index.php?threads/the-4e-dark-sun-creature-catalog.925701/post-25475185&quot;&gt;corresponding RPG.net thread&lt;/a&gt;, however, the Dragon’s touches upon the
setting’s deepest secrets. These only appear at the very end of the Dark Sun
Campaign Setting book, which forum user zedturtle is reading in another
thread. I don’t want to spoil him ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other reason for this is that the Dragon of Tyr is a singular character and
a very important one in the setting, so he should really be over on the
Personages section of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both of these reasons, I’m discussing the Dragon at the end of this Let’s
Read.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/08/wir-dscc-dragon-of-tyr-notice.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/08/wir-dscc-dragon-of-tyr-notice.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dagorran</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dagorran.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A dagorran, which is a cross between a lizard and a large dog with wicked
    sharp teeth.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagorrans are carnivorous reptilian quadrupeds the size of large dogs. They can
track prey by its “psychic scent”, which they can memorize either through direct
contact or by stumbling into a creature’s psychic trail (i.e. through
psychometry). Once a dagorran has its chosen prey’s scent, they will chase it
relentlessly, across great distances, until they catch it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, these creatures live in wide-ranging packs. Dagorran packs sleep
for a handful of hours every couple of days, and spend the rest of their time on
the hunt. They only stay at a single place for a while when they have to rear
their young, but as soon as the pups can run with the pack they’re on the move
again. Unlike some of the other magical beasts in the book, dagorran packs don’t
cooperate with other predators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young dagorrans are sometimes captured and trained by templars, who prize them
as peerless trackers and use them to track fugitives or wanted
dissidents. They’re much better at this job than cilopses, who must lay eyes on
the prey to start tracking and can only follow the trail for a short time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagorrans share some similarities with baazrags (dog-like pack hunters) and with
cilopses (favored templar pets), but they’re a lot more dangerous with levels in
the mid-Paragon tier. They’re Natural Magical Beasts so we can consider them
sapient, though I guess their thought processes are pretty alien. The creatures
can understand Common, and they can communicate telepathically with other
dagorrans but not with anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have a ground speed of 8, low-light vision, and the &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Scent&lt;/strong&gt;
signature trait. This is a minor-action power that lets them choose a living
creature &lt;em&gt;or its tracks&lt;/em&gt; within 10 squares of the dagorran. The dagorran can
ignore any level of concealment or invisibility on its chosen target, and knows
the creature’s location until it either dies or the dagorran uses the power
again. No wonder templars like them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dagorran-mindhound&quot;&gt;Dagorran Mindhound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These robust specimens charge in packs to surround and distract their chosen
prey, opening them up for attack by their sneakier relatives (below). They’re
Level 16 Brutes with 194 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their only attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does respectable brute-tier damage, but
that and Psychic Scent are enough to make them a threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dagorran-ambusher&quot;&gt;Dagorran Ambusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sneaky specimens move a bit ahead of the pack and position themselves for
an ambush, striking once their beefier relatives (above) begin their own part of
the attack. They’re Level 17 Lurkers with 132 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambushers deal extra psychic damage against any creature that cannot see
it. This trait is somewhat confusingly named &lt;strong&gt;Combat Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;. I mean, if
you cannot see the ambusher you will most likely be granting it CA, but if you
can see it you won’t take bonus damage even if you’re granting it CA for other
reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That difference will soon cease to matter, however, because their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; makes
them invisble to the target for a turn on a hit. If they’re too far away to
bite, they can use their standard action to &lt;strong&gt;Fade to Nothingness&lt;/strong&gt; and become
invisible either until they attack, or until the end of their next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a classical lurker setup, but the rider on their bite attack means that
they can keep biting you with bonus damage for as long as they keep hitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagorran encounters are simple. A wild pack is an all-dagorran encounter. You
can also find one or two of them as part of a Paragon-tier templar encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagorrans feel a lot more “dog-like” than baazrags lore-wise, but not
mechanics-wise as they lack the ability to knock people prone or any Pack
Tactics style power. I think they work better as pets brought in by mixed
humanoid encounter groups, since those can be more varied than a wild pack. A
chase scene or skill challenge involving dagorrans is a much more drawn-out
affair than one involving cilopses, as the PCs will likely have to kill or
discourage the dagorrans before they can attempt to lose their pursuers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find a bit surprising that they’re mid-Paragon monsters, but their stat
blocks are simple enough that you could reduce their level by 10 or so and still
have them work just fine as Heroic threats.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/03/wir-dscc-dagorran.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/03/wir-dscc-dagorran.html</guid>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Crodlu</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-crodlu.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A cilops, which is a giant centipede with one big angry eye on its head.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crodlus are what Athas has instead of horses. Fans of Final Fantasy might
compare them do Darker and Sunnier chocobos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, crodlus roam the wastes in small herds of about a dozen members,
led by a dominant female. Females make up most of the other members of the herd,
and are all related to the leader. One of the males will be the leader’s mate,
with the others being mostly younger individuals who have not yet reached
adulthood. When that happens, the newly adult males set out to seek mates in
other herds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creatures are omnivores, with herds cooperating to hunt those creatures they
judge to be weaker or smaller than themselves, and running away from stronger
predators. They’re also frequently beset by human raiders trying to capture
their young for training as mounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that crodlu are a common sight among groups of sapient
humanoids. They make for ornery mounts, but that’s a good trait to have in
something you want to ride into battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crodlus are Large Natural Beasts with the Reptile tag and a ground speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crodlu&quot;&gt;Crodlu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could represent a typical wild specimen, or perhaps a domesticated one that
wasn’t trained as a mount. It’s a Level 3 Brute with 55 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crodlu can attack with its &lt;strong&gt;beak&lt;/strong&gt; or with &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; that do a little less
damage. Whenever it can it will use a &lt;strong&gt;Pounce&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets it move up to its
speed, and use both Beak and Claws against the same target even if it stands
still. If both attacks hit, the target falls prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;war-crodlu&quot;&gt;War Crodlu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one was trained as a mount, and compares to the normal crodlu in the same
way a war horse compares to a draft animal. It’s a Level 5 Brute with 76 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The War Crodlu has the same three abilities described for the normal version,
and one more: &lt;strong&gt;Pouncing Mount&lt;/strong&gt;. If the war crodlu charges a target while
mounted, its rider can make a melee basic attack as a free action against that
same target. The Pounce ability does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; count as a charge, but this makes the
charge of a mounted war crodlu a bit more dangerous than a standard Pounce,
depending on who the rider is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crodlus don’t strike me as the type of animal who’d attack wandering PCs without
provocation, so they’ll mostly likely be found serving as mounts for bad guys or
for the PCs themselves. Fighting wild ones would be something that happens when
the PCs decide to play hunter and steal hatchlings to sell or domesticate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically they’re very simple, about on par with horses really. I’ve been too
desensitized by FF chocobos to see terror bird mounts as a mind-blowing
innovation, but they’re still kinda cool.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/02/wir-dscc-crodlu.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/02/wir-dscc-crodlu.html</guid>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Cloud Ray</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-cloud-ray.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A cilops, which is a giant centipede with one big angry eye on its head.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud rays look like gigantic flying stingrays, and are among some of the rarest
and most majestic specimens of Athasian fauna. They float in from the Sea of
Silt to feed or rest, and despite their prodigious size they’re rarely dangerous
unless bothered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures subsist mostly on psychic, entropic, and magical energy, so they
only need a comparatively tiny amount of physical food to keep going. They land
on the ground to sleep, covering themselves in sand and debris for
camouflage. There are many stories about travelers who pitched their tents on a
nice spot of high ground only to later find themselves desperately clinging to
the back of a cloud ray when the creature took flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud rays dream of distant places when they sleep, and sometimes they disappear
to those places instead of taking flight the usual way. When threatened, the
creature can consciously tap into this ability to teleport short distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud Rays are Elemental Beasts, whose size varies depending on their age. They
can crawl on the ground at speed 4 and fly at Speed 12 with Hover
capability. They have an affinity for storms, with Resist 15 Lightning and
Thunder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going through the entries here in increasing order of level, which is the
reverse of what the book does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cloud-ray-pup&quot;&gt;Cloud Ray Pup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This young individual is Large, translucent, and relatively delicate for its
size. It’s a Level 21 Minion Skirmisher. Pups fly around in clusters near other
creatures that can provide them with food - most commonly cloud ray elders, but
sometimes other aerial predators that tend to leave lots of left-overs. If their
intended prey is still moving, they sting it until it stops, and then set down
to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;sting&lt;/strong&gt; is Reach 3 and deals thunder damage. They can employ it as part
of a &lt;strong&gt;Gliding Attack&lt;/strong&gt; that lets them move their speed and make the attack at
any point along the way. They don’t provoke opportunity attacks when moving away
from the target of their sting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minion, a single hit will take the pup down, but it can use &lt;strong&gt;Dream
Resurgence&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter to remove itself from play when it reaches 0 HP
and reappear at the start of its next turn within 10 squares, with its 1 HP
restored. It will probably use this opportunity to run away if nothing is
forcing it to stay, so the PCs don’t need to feel bad about giving this
beautiful creature a good whack to get it to bother someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cloud-ray-adult&quot;&gt;Cloud Ray Adult&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults cruise the skies continuously, only descending to rest or to attack
land-bound prey. Sure, it eats little for its size, but for a Huge creature that
can still mean its infrequent meals consist of a whole person or similarly sized
animal. Adults are Level 23 Elite Skirmishers with 424 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adult has a much stronger version of the pup’s &lt;strong&gt;Sting&lt;/strong&gt;, with Reach 4. It
can also use a Reach 1 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that deals more damage and grabs the
target. Targets grabbed by the bite have a -4 to their escape rolls, which have
escape DCs of 34 for Athletics and 36 for Acrobatics. The ray can grab at most
one target like this. The &lt;strong&gt;Unhindered&lt;/strong&gt; trait lets the cloud ray pull the
victim along when it moves. Either of these attacks can be used as part of
&lt;strong&gt;Gliding Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets it attack twice during the movement and otherwise
works like the pup’s version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ray that finds itself surrounded can use &lt;strong&gt;Wing Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 3
vs. Fort, recharge 5+) to deal thunder damage and push targets 3 squares on a
hit, also knocking them prone. This creates a lightly obscured zone that lasts
for a turn, from all the dust it kicks up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, while bloodied, the ray can use &lt;strong&gt;Dream Flight&lt;/strong&gt; to teleport
15 squares, carrying its grabbed victim with it if it has one. It makes Close
Burst 2 attack vs. Fortitude on arrival, dazing an slowing those it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grabbed victim can be attacked with further bite attacks and with &lt;strong&gt;Crush&lt;/strong&gt;, a
minor action attack vs. Fortitude that deals as much damage as the bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An adult on the hunt will try to grab its chosen prey and fly away, biting and
crushing the victim until it’s dead. If their prey proves too feisty, they’ll
drop it from a great height to soften it up, and then grab it again. Repeat
until done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cloud-ray-elder&quot;&gt;Cloud Ray Elder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This majestic Gargantuan beast is a Level 25 Solo Controller, on par with elder
dragons from other worlds. Its control over storms lets it project an aura (3)
of &lt;strong&gt;Undulating Winds&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals 15 thunder damage to enemies that start
their turns inside and lets the elder slide them 3 squares to another square
within the aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, its &lt;strong&gt;Flat Body&lt;/strong&gt; lets other creatures enter and occupy the elder’s
space - they’re standing on top of the ray! This means it’s equal parts enemy
and terrain during a fight. If it took flight because you tried to camp on its
back, it will be the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; terrain for the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously if you’re on top of the ray, you’re also inside its aura, so it will
try to slide you off its back. This follows the rules for forced movement into
hazardous terrain, so you get a save to grab on before you tumble to the
ground. If you pass, you end up prone at the ray’s edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elder’s is Reach 5 &lt;strong&gt;Sting&lt;/strong&gt; deals immediate and ongoing thunder damage
(save ends). Its favorite attack enhances the sting with magic for a &lt;strong&gt;Thunder
Lash&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals physical damage to its primary target and triggers a
secondary close burst 5 centered on that target that deals thunder damage to all
enemies it hits and pushes then 3 squares. On a miss it deals half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also large enough that its bite upgrades to &lt;strong&gt;Scooping Bite&lt;/strong&gt;: this is a
Close Blast 5 instead of a melee attack, and it can grab up to three targets it
hits. &lt;strong&gt;Unhindered&lt;/strong&gt; is here and lets the elder fly away with its mouthful of
victims. &lt;strong&gt;Gliding Menace&lt;/strong&gt; works like Gliding Attack, but lets the elder
specifically use Thunder Lash and Scooping Bite as its two flyby attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the adult, the elder can &lt;strong&gt;Crush&lt;/strong&gt; its grabbed victims with a minor
action. Fortunately they don’t have penalties on their escape rolls, but the
base DCs are higher since the elder is higher level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If bloodied, the elder uses &lt;strong&gt;Dream Flight&lt;/strong&gt; to teleport away. It works just
like the adult’s version, but the daze upgrades to Stunned on the first failed
save and Unconscious on the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud Rays are almost always only found together with other cloud rays, with a
flock of pups following a group of adults or a single elder around. They’re not
sapient but I think they’re smart enough not to attack heavily armed PCs without
provocation. Encounters are more likely to start when a PC runs into a ray at
rest, and even then a fight is not certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine you can have a good adventure about PCs trying to prevent another
armed group from killing cloud rays, and in this case the creatures would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
be smart enough to distinguish the PCs from the hunters if a fight broke out.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/03/13/cloud-ray.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/03/13/cloud-ray.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Cilops</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-cilops.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A cilops, which is a giant centipede with one big angry eye on its head.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cilops (not to be confused with the cyclops) is the Darker and Sunnier
version of Ye Olde Giante Centipede. That means it’s larger, spikier, and has
psychic powers. Their name comes from the huge single mammal-like eye they have
instead of the more usual compound eyes you find in arthropods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other monstrous centipedes, the bite of the cilops is not venomous. The
touch of its antennae, however, can psychically paralyze victims or muddle their
minds. They can also psychically track victims over short distances - it’s very
hard to hide from these things once they caught your scent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, cilopses gather in the same places you can find mundane
centipedes - any area where there’s a reasonable amount of shade and
water. You’re more likely to find them &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of the wild, however, as
Templar patrols from every city love to use trained cilopses as both trackers
and attack animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some templars or sorcerer-kings are also fond of raising particularly large and
vicious specimens and letting them loose on the city to wreak some havoc and
terrorize the population into compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cilopses are Large Natural Beasts. They have Darkvision, some sort of antenna
power that varies with the stat block, and the signature power &lt;strong&gt;Follow Psychic
Trail&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a minor-action encounter power that lets them choose a creature
they can see. Until the end of the encounter that creature grants combat
advantage to the cilops, and cannot hide from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combat advantage is pretty useful during a fight, but remember that a skill
challenge to run away from a cilops-equipped patrol is also an encounter. Don’t
let they catch your scent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cilops-creeper&quot;&gt;Cilops Creeper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical specimen such as one might find in the wild, or accompanying a templar
strike force. It’s a Level 5 Skirmisher with 60 HP. It has ground and climb
speeds of 7, and Resist 5 Psychic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the creeper’s attacks deal 1d6 extra damage if it has &lt;strong&gt;Combat
Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;, which is yet another reason for not letting it track you. Its basic
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; damages on a hit and lets the creeper shift 2 squares as an
effect. Once per encounter it can use its &lt;strong&gt;Paralyzing Antennae&lt;/strong&gt; against a
creature granting combat advantage to it, targetting Fortitude. On a hit this
damages, dazes, and immobilizes the target for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creepers really want to start tracking a specific PC as soon as the fight
starts, and then focus fire on their chosen victim starting with an antennae
attack and then proceeding to spam the bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cilops-stalker&quot;&gt;Cilops Stalker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A chunky terror weapon, the Stalker is a Level 7 Elite Skirmisher with 154
HP. It’s slower and less agile than the Creeper, with a ground speed of only 6
and no climb speed or psychic resistance. However, it makes up for that in bulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stalker’s &lt;strong&gt;pincers&lt;/strong&gt; have the same bonus against targets granting CA, and
its &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Rush&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge 5+) is excellent against tight
formations. It allows the Stalker to shift its speed and move through enemies
space during this shift. Whenever it does so, it makes a melee attack vs. the
enemy’s Reflex, dealing heavy damage and knocking prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can still only &lt;strong&gt;Follow Psychic Trail&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter, but unlike the
Creeper it can use its Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Dazing Antennae&lt;/strong&gt; once per round with no
targeting restrictions. This does lightning damage equivalent to the bite on a
hit, and dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stalker also wants to track and focus on one target, and Sudden Rush lets it
reach that target even through the party’s defender front line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, you’re much more likely to encounter these things being used
as trackers and attack animals by templars than to meet them in their natural
habitats. If you do meet them in the wild, they’re likely to be accompanied by
other varieties of giant bug, or by swarms of smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they’re giant centipedes with a bit more character, and I imagine
they can get pretty annoying when paired with other teammates that specialize in
tying PCs down and preventing them from helping the cilops’ chosen victim.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/03/09/wir-dscc-cilops.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/03/09/wir-dscc-cilops.html</guid>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Chathrang</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-chathrang.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A chathrang reeling in a small mammal it just caught.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chathrangs are big carnivorous tortoises with built-in anti-air artillery. The
many spiny protusions on their shells are tubes that can spit out sticky
envenomed quills, with or without a tether that lets them reel in their
catch. Their usual hunting method is to hide in an oasis amid natural reeds or
other plants, wait for small birds or large insects to fly overhead, and shoot
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If no suitable flying critters are present, they’ll go for land-based prey. They
tend to become too enthusiastic or desperate at these times, and might try to
reel in something they can’t handle. Like a PC, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chathrangs usually live and travel in groups of about three. They don’t have a
lot of combat ability outside of their one neat trick, so it’s common for them
to enter symbiotic relationships with other creatures to share prey in exchange
for a bit more protection. When hurt, they behave like other tortoises and hide
inside their shells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charthrangs are impossible to train, but some people keep them around to “milk”
their venom. If a battle against their keepers ends up bursting into the
charthrang enclosure, the creatures will follow their instincts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These critters are Medium Natural Beasts with the Reptile tag and a stately
ground speed of 4. They’re Level 9 Artillery with 81 HP, so I guess even a
monster described as “relatively weak” rates high-Heroic stats in this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creature’s &lt;strong&gt;Spiny Shell&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (1) that deals 5 damage to anyone
who starts their turn inside, but they charthrang doesn’t really want PCs to get
that close. Instead, it wants to stay far away and shoot its Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;spine
shots&lt;/strong&gt;, which do poison damage on a hit. The beast can increase its rate of
fire and use a &lt;strong&gt;Spine Volley&lt;/strong&gt; instead, attacking two targets with one action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attaching a sticky strand to a spine turns it into the &lt;strong&gt;Poisoned Tether&lt;/strong&gt;
attack, which does the same damage and immobilizes the target. While immobilized
by this attack, the target cannot be pushed, pulled, or slid by anything other
than the &lt;strong&gt;Reel In&lt;/strong&gt; minor action, which pulls it 5 squares. Escape requires
either passing a save as normal, or teleporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the charthrang is damaged by an attack, it can &lt;strong&gt;retreat into its shell&lt;/strong&gt; as
a reaction. Until the end of its next turn it’s slowed, can’t attack, gains a +5
to AC, and doubles the damage done by its aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the standard encounter disposition mentioned in the lore, chatharangs
are also very amenable to reskinning. If you read the Cactus entry and felt that
you needed cactus artillery to complement the lurkers, you can just replace
Reptile with Plant on the chathrang stat block and call it a day. Describe them
as big spherical cacti that move by rolling around and otherwise behave the
same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanics are interesting. Range 20 is a lot! A cluster of three of these
machine-gun tortoises can sit very far back behind a line of 2-4 soldiers or
brutes and wreak havoc on the PCs by directly targeting their squishies, and
reeling them towards Team Monster’s frontline. Multiple charthrangs can stick
their tethers to the same PC and alternate their use of Reel In to bring the
victim closer that much faster, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, of course, if the GM plays them smart. This is absolutely not required,
as these are simple animals with a reputation for trying to catch things too
dangerous for them to handle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still… anti-air tortoises. What a world.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/03/03/wir-dscc-chathrang.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/03/03/wir-dscc-chathrang.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
