<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 16:40:59 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 16:40:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Troll</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-troll.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D Trolls are inspired by the writings of Poul Anderson and have been in the
game since the beginning. Here, they are present in both the Monster Manual and
the Vault. I’m telling you in advance: I’m not gonna make jokes about rude
Internet posters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls are large humanoid creatures with amazing regenerative powers, able to
survive just about anything and thrive just about anywhere. This same remarkable
metabolism makes it so trolls are always hungry and in search of food. They’ll
eat anything that’s smaller than themselves and made of meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only things that can temporarily overwhelm a troll’s regeneration are fire
and acid. One of these is required to kill a troll permanently - it can come
back from anything else. This makes them pretty much fearless in combat. Trolls
attack even when they’re outnumbered and when the enemies seem strong, because
they’re confident in their survival. Even the presence of fire and acid doesn’t
get them to back off right away, though in this case they might retreat if they
get too hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine this made trolls into dangerous puzzle monsters back when they were
new, but now pretty much any D&amp;amp;D veteran is going to know about their
weaknesses. Many arcane characters have easy sources of fire or acid at hand,
and other “caster” types might have an encounter power or two that deal those
types of damage. If your wizard is one of those charop types that went all in on
psychic and force spells, though, you’re in for a tought fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have no other source of fire you can “kill” the troll with
conventional weapons and stick a lit torch in it to finish the job, but even
that is easier said than done. And adventurers these days tend to prefer those
alchemical glow-sticks as light sources, so they might not even have torches
available if they don’t know a troll is around!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls are sapient, but not very smart. Still smarter than ogres,
though. Tricking the typical troll is easy, provided you can get it to talk to
you instead of immediately ripping you apart and eating the pieces. All sorts of
villains and tyrants like to recruit trolls into their forces, since they’ll
readily work for a bit of money and a lot of food. Such trolls are all too glad
to receive additional training and gear from their bosses, and though they make
for undisciplined and rowdy soldiers, they’re deadly in a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evil wizards also love trolls, for a different reason. They can survive all
sorts of disturbing magical experiments, which tend to result in weird mutants
much stronger and much less mentally stable than a standard troll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s perfectly possible for there to be trolls who aren’t evil and who don’t eat
other sapients, though even them they’d have a hard time coexisting with those
sapients since they require large hunting areas to sustain themselves. Even nice
trolls are likely to make their home in the wilderness far away from any
settlements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls are Large Natural Humanoids, and their signature traits are
&lt;strong&gt;Regeneration&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Troll Healing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I explained in a previous entry, 4e Regeneration is more or less equivalent
to 3e’s Fast Healing: the monster recovers the specified amount of hit points at
the start of its turn as long as it has at least 1 HP remaining. For MM trolls,
this is either 10 or 15 depending on the stat block. For MV trolls, this is 5
across the board. Troll regeneration stops working for a turn if the monster
takes fire or acid damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troll Healing is what makes them immortal: if a troll is reduced to 0 HP by
anything other than fire or acid damage, it recovers the specified amount of HP
and rises again at the start of its next turn. It can still be killed before it
rises if it takes fire or acid damage while down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these, they can usually do something interesting when their basic
attack bloodies a target. Being Large creatures, all their attacks have
Reach 2. They only speak Giant, which is another barrier to nonviolent
communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troll-both&quot;&gt;Troll (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 9 Brute with 100 HP. The MV version has regeneration
10 and troll healing 10, while the MV version has regeneration 5 and troll
healing 15. Both have speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls attack with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, and if their basic attack bloodies the
target they get to make another one against it as a free action. They have no
other special abilities, being quintessential brutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battle-troll-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Battle Troll (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A troll who received extra training and equipment from its patrons. It’s a Level
12 Soldier with 124 HP. Its speed is reduced to 7 by armor, and its
regeneration/troll healing values are 5/15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle troll wears scale and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;broadsword&lt;/strong&gt;, which marks the
target for a turn. If a broadsword attack bloodies the target, the troll can
make another free attack against it. It can also use the sword to make
&lt;strong&gt;sweeping strikes&lt;/strong&gt; which hit in a Close Blast 2 and knock targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bladerager-troll-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Bladerager Troll (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product of twisted Cocaine Wizard experiments, this is a troll who had tons
of sharp blades implanted all over its body. It’s a Level 12 Brute with 151 HP,
Speed 7, and Regeneration 5 &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; Troll Healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bladerager attacks with its augmented &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which can also perform a
&lt;strong&gt;Bladerager Rend&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter for massive immediate damage and ongoing
10 damage (save ends). A miss does half the immediate and ongoing damage. If the
basic claw attack bloodies a target, the Rend recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the bladerager reaches 0 HP, it explodes into a cloud of shrapnel! This
&lt;strong&gt;Death Burst&lt;/strong&gt; targets affects a Close Burst 2 around the troll, doing a bit
less damage than the rend to everyone caught by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghost-troll-render-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Ghost Troll Render (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This troll died but didn’t even notice. It’ll still try to eat you. You can make
any regular troll into an elite of sorts by having one of these rise up from its
corpse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost Trolls are Level 13 Brutes with 161 HP and the Undead keyword. They have a
flight speed of 7 with Hover and Phasing, and are immune to disease and
poison. Lacking a body, they no longer regenerate and are instead
Insubstantial. This means they take half damage from anything but force
attacks. Getting hit by a radiant, fire or acid attack makes them substantial
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex, and they can
perform a &lt;strong&gt;Terror Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. Will) that does a massive amount of
psychic damage and slows on a hit (save ends). The first failed save turns that
slowed status into unconsciousness, which ends on a sucessful save or if the
victim takes damage. This is an encounter power that recharges if it misses, so
chances are the ghost &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; scare someone this way during the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;war-troll-monster-manual&quot;&gt;War Troll (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An earlier but slightly more flexible version of the MV Battle Troll. This one
is a Level 14 Soldier with 110 HP. It wears plate, wields a greatsword, but also
carries a longbow and a quiver full of arrows. Its speed is 7 and its
regeneration/troll healing values are 10/15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has the same &lt;strong&gt;greatsword&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sweeping strike&lt;/strong&gt; attacks of the Battle
Troll, and it also has &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt; (2) and can use &lt;strong&gt;Blood Pursuit&lt;/strong&gt;
as a reaction to shift 1 square closer to a bloodied enemy within 2 squares who
shifts. It can also fight at range with its &lt;strong&gt;Longbow&lt;/strong&gt;, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-troll-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Fell Troll (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest and baddest among trolls. They’re Huge, and Level 20 Elite Brutes
with 360 HP. Their speed is 10, their regeneration/troll healing values are
10/20, and they gain a +1 to attacks and a +2 to damage against bloodied
enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can use Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;backhand
slams&lt;/strong&gt; as a 1/round minor action for extra damage and to push fools up to 4
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it’s possible for a game to call itself D&amp;amp;D without including
green regenerating trolls in its bestiary. Non-D&amp;amp;D games can still have them, of
course: GURPS Dungeon Fantasy does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual has three sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 3 trolls and 2 destrachans. The destrachans are slightly smarter than
the trolls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 16: 2 war trolls, 1 night hag, 5 grimlock minions, a drow priest, and a
drow blademaster. A group so diverse it could be an evil adventuring party.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: 1 fell troll, 2 enormous carrion crawlers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War and battle trolls can be found alongside anyone who is willing to pay
them. The others would be found with more trolls, and with creatures they might
have decided to keep as pets. Mechanically, they need that company to make for
more interesting fights, because their abilities aren’t very varied on their
own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding some trolls to a “wilderness” region you’re populating might work as a
fine explanation for why all those other deadly monsters don’t spill out and
overwhelm nearby “points of light”. If anyone would hunt and eat bullettes, dire
boars, roaming gricks and maybe even the occasional drow scouting party, it’s a
bunch of trolls.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/09/troll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/09/troll.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Troglodyte</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-troglodyte.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troglodytes appear on the Rules Cyclopedia, so they’ve been around at least
since BECMI and likely since the beginning. Here, they are in both the Monster
Manual and the Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troglodytes are sapient reptilian humanoids native to the Underdark, one of the
notable minority that seems to have evolved there instead of being a Far Realm
or surface import. They secrete a foul-smelling mucus over their scaly hides,
and seem to be resistant enough to disease that they don’t really care about
personal hygiene on top of that. Their settlements present the unprepared
visitor with a nightmarish olfactory experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troglodytes reproduce by laying eggs, with the female laying close to a hundred
of them at once. Only a minority of those will both hatch and survive to
adulthood, which they reach in two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troglodyte culture is at a paleolithic level of technological development, and
though it’s egalitarian when it comes to gender it’s extremely
xenophobic. Anyone not of the same tribe is an enemy to be killed and eaten, or
captured and sacrificed to Torog (god of suffering and imprisonment) in an long,
torture-filled ceremony. Troglodyte tribes fight each other as bitterly as they
fight anyone else - when two tribes move into the same area, the most likely
outcomes are for one of them to be annihilated or for the two to be so weakened
they ironically end up merging under a strong leader. When resources grow scarce
in their current territory they will gladly raid the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes a little bit of sense for troglodytes to be this horrible when you
think about it. Any less powerful Underdark culture is likely to grow a
xenophobic streak when their most frequent neighbors are drow, duergar, and mind
flayers. And if these three big empires base all of their power on slavery and
torture, it’s not inconceivable that a culture they prey on would try to do the
same, and venerate the god that presides over these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this stops the Big Three from regularly enslaving troglodytes and using
them as muscle. I imagine it could also be possible to find bands of troglodytes
who aren’t xenophobic Torog worshippers and who are on friendlier terms with
other species. Perhaps they might even live on the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another instance where the Monster Vault breaks out the full
Lovecraftian Racism Vocabulary, calling them “degenerate reptile folk”,
“loathsome primitives”, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troglodytes are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Reptile keyword. They have
darkvision and a land speed of 5. Their signature trait is of course
&lt;strong&gt;Troglodyte Stench&lt;/strong&gt;, an aura (1) that inflicts a -2 penalty to the attacks of
any living enemies inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They mostly fight with claws or stone weapons, though they also have
spellcasters who use Torog-themed magic. We have a total of 6 unique stat blocks
between the two books (4 each, with 2 appearing in both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troglodyte-mauler-both&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Mauler (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Vault version is by far the best one, so we’ll start with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Level 6 Soldier with 74 HP, the mauler fights in melee with a &lt;strong&gt;greatclub&lt;/strong&gt;
and with its &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which are considered basic attacks. Both are
equivalent damage-wise, but the club marks for a turn on a hit. The mauler also
carries a pair of &lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt; for throwing at range 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the mauler has combat advantage against an enemy, it can use a minor-action
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; against them 1/round. This targets Fortitude, damages, and makes the
target regain only half HP from healing for a turn. Bacteria, baby!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual version is a lot less interesting, since its damage suffers
from the bug and it lacks the javelins and the bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troglodyte-grunt-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Grunt (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grunts are Level 6 Minion Skirmishers, with all the standard troglodyte
traits. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;clubs&lt;/strong&gt; that do minion-level damage and allow they to
shift 2 squares as an effect. When targeted by area attacks they can &lt;strong&gt;scatter&lt;/strong&gt;
as an interrupt, shifting up to 2 squares to a place outside the area of
effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last bit should give you some laughs the first time the party wizard smugly
tries to hit them with an area spell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troglodyte-thrasher-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Thrasher (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrashers are Level 7 Brutes with 100 HP. They don’t bother with weapons, and
fight with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;. They also have a &lt;strong&gt;Tooth and Claw&lt;/strong&gt; at-will attack
that does roughly half the damage of a basic claw, but can attack one creature
twice or two creatures once. If one of these attacks bloody the target, the
troglodyte can make a basic claw attack against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So depending on how you spread Tooth and Claw around, you could end up doing
three times the damage of the basic claw in a round (1.5 times base damage to
each of two targets you just bloodied)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troglodyte-impaler-both&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Impaler (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impalers are Level 7 Artillery with 69 HP. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;spears&lt;/strong&gt; in melee
and throw &lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt; at range (they start with 6). The MM also gives them a
useless claw attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from making basic attacks, the impaler can use a javelin to make an
&lt;strong&gt;Impaling Shot&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. AC; recharge 3-6), which does the same damage
and restrains the target (save ends) by going right through it and into the
ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troglodyte-curse-chanter-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Curse Chanter (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spellcaster, likely a priest of Torog or a primal caster who communes with
underground spirits. It’s a Level 8 Controller with the Leader keyword and 93
HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse chanter wields a &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaff&lt;/strong&gt; and also fights with &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, but
the real firepower comes from its magic. It can shoot &lt;strong&gt;poison rays&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Fortitude) that do poison damage and weaken (save ends). It can call down a
&lt;strong&gt;cavern curse&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Fortitude; recharge 3-6) that inflicts ongoing
necrotic damage and slows (save ends both). It can bless its allies with
&lt;strong&gt;Tunnel Grace&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 10; minor action 1/round; recharge 4-6) to give
them +5 speed for a turn. And it can sing a &lt;strong&gt;chant of renewal&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5;
encounter) to heal all bloodied allies in range for 15 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troglodyte-warrior-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Warrior (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 12 Minions, which makes them suitable to represent enslaved
cannon fodder in the service of drow or mind flayers. They have the common
traits of darkvision and the stench, and a basic &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt; attack, being
otherwise unremarkable. You’re better off leveling up the Grunts from the MV and
using those instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the MM’s sample encounters are assorted troglodytes, though sometimes
they’ll have a rage drake or some gricks as pets. There’s also one that includes
drow and a gaggle of troglodyte warriors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narratively, it feels like Troglodytes flesh the Underdark out a little bit, but
the way the books refer to them does them no favors. In the end I feel like
using them in a subterranean campaign mostly so I can defy their awful canonical
description, which I guess is something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, most of their statistics are interchangeable with those of other
humanoids. Replace their signature abilities with darkvision and the stench
aura, and you have an instant novelty troglodyte. The reverse is also true.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Tiefling</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-tiefling.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tieflings rose to prominence during 2e, and were added as a playable option
right in the Fourth Edition PHB, though they’re a little different from their
previous incarnations here. As opposition, they’re featured in both the Monster
Manual and the Monster Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in other entries, Nerath is only the latest empire to fall in the
long story of the 4e setting. One of the many others that preceded it was the
human empire of Bael Turath, which fought for supremacy with the dragonborn
realm of Arkhosia a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There came a time when Bael Turath was engulfed in turmoil, both because of that
war and because of its own decadence. In a desperate bid to retain control, its
leadership made sinister pacts with the forces of Hell. This worked for a time,
but it only delayed the final fall of the empire. Things turn ugly when both the
human nobles and the devils tried to break their side of the bargain. In the
end, both Bael Turath and Arkhosia met their end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the effects of that diabolic compact was that the humans of Bael Turath
had their bodies infused with infernal power, transforming them into the
tieflings we know today. This transformation is hereditary and it persisted even
after the compact was broken and the empire fell. Today tiefling communities are
spread all over the world, either mixed in with larger multi-species settlements
or in small enclaves of their own, similar to dragonborn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to their distinctive looks, they retain a tiny bit of infernal
power. Both these things give them a bad reputation among other sapients, but
the truth is that modern tieflings are no more disposed to evil than any other
people. A tiefling could be a great champion of good just as they could choose
to embrace their bad rep and become evil diabolists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiefling looks are a lot more uniform here than they used to be in previous
editions: red skin, prominent horns, solid red orbs for eyes, and a thick
muscular tail. They look like a less extreme version of a legion devil (which is
hairless with clawed hands and hooves for feet in addition to the other traits).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tieflings are Medium Natural Humanoids, and all of them have low-light vision
and some degree of fire resistance. The MM stat blocks also have the same
&lt;strong&gt;Infernal Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; power tiefling PCs get. This is a minor action encounter
power that gives them a +1 attack bonus and a damage bonus against someone who
just hit them. It’s a “revenge” booster, essentially. Like PCs, they also get +1
to hit bloodied targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each book gives us two tiefling stat blocks. As is the case for all playable
humanoids, they can be of any alignment and could be used as allies or
enemies. However, all of them seem to lean into their infernal heritage at least
a bit, so even the good ones will have the same air of ambiguity around them as
the party’s infernal warlock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiefling-fury-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Tiefling Fury (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a duelist type, and a Level 5 Soldier with 63 HP. Its speed is 6, and it
has all common tiefling traits with 10 fire resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fury fights with a &lt;strong&gt;longsword&lt;/strong&gt; whose attacks mark for a turn, and if a
marked enemy shift it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Trip&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Reflex) as an
interrupt to knock them prone and make a free longsword attack against them. If
an enemy hits the fury, it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Defiant Curse&lt;/strong&gt; as a free action to mark
them for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiefling-heretic-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Tiefling Heretic (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An infernal warlock. It’s Level 6 Artillery with 60 HP, all common MM traits,
and a fire resistance of 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heretic fights with a &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and with bolts of &lt;strong&gt;Balefire&lt;/strong&gt; at
range that deal immediate and ongoing fire damage (save ends). Once per
encounter it can conjure a &lt;strong&gt;Serpent Curse&lt;/strong&gt; on a target (ranged 10 vs. will),
causing illusory snakes to appear and deal both immediate and ongoing psychic
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hit by a melee attack, the heretic can use &lt;strong&gt;Cloak of Escape&lt;/strong&gt; as an
at-will reaction to teleport 5 squares. It also has &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Wrath&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiefling-darkblade-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Tiefling Darkblade (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An assassin-type, and a Level 7 Lurker with 64 HP and fire
resistance 12. Darkblades fight with &lt;strong&gt;poisoned shortswords&lt;/strong&gt; that allow a
secondary attack against Fortitude on a hit, doing ongoing poison damage (save
ends). They can use &lt;strong&gt;Cloak of Lurking&lt;/strong&gt; (move action; recharge 6) to teleport 5
squares and become invisible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems they don’t have any powers that allow them to do increased damage when
attacking from hiding or with CA, so they’re in effect slightly weaker
skirmishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiefling-occultist-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Tiefling Occultist (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another infernal warlock! This one is a Level 8 Controller with 87 HP and fire
resistance 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occultists fight in melee with a &lt;strong&gt;Hell Rod&lt;/strong&gt; that does immediate and ongoing
fire damage (save ends). They attack at range with &lt;strong&gt;Soul Fire&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1
within 10 vs. Reflex), which does no immediate damage. Instead it does 10
ongoing fire damage (save ends), and deals 10 psychic damage to the target if it
moves closer to the occultist on the target’s next action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action it can use &lt;strong&gt;Baleful Teleport&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Will) to
teleport a target 10 squares and teleport itself to the square the target just
left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy hits the occultist, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Transposition&lt;/strong&gt; to deal 5
fire damage to all enemies in a close burst 3, and swap places with the enemy
that hit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters And Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter goes all in on the hellish imagery: 1 heretic, 1 darkblade,
2 cambion hellswords, and a succubus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like tieflings, though more as a playable race than as an enemy. The enemy
stat blocks work well enough, however, and could also represent human warlocks
or other similar baddies.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/07/tiefling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/07/tiefling.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Treant</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-treant.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treants are inspired by Tolkien’s ents and have been in the game since at least
the days of BECMI, and likely earlier. Here, they are both in the Monster Manual
and in the Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treants are indeed very similar to the ents we see in The Lord of the Rings:
they’re sapient tree-like creatures who live in primeval forests. The main
difference between them (especially in 4e) is that treants are a lot quicker to
arrive at decisions, and a lot angrier with trespassers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treants love the forests where they live, and act as their guardians. They
spend much of their extremely long lives in a dormant/meditative state in which
they’re pretty much indistinguishable from normal trees. In this state, they can
feel the general state of the surrounding forest and its creatures, and know
when it’s in distress. When that happens, they rise to defend it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though treants love their forest and its creatures, they hold no particular
regard for any outsiders. They’ll be friendly towards those who demonstrate the
proper respect for the wild, and violent towards anyone who has the temerity to
chop down trees or otherwise despoil their territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Vault goes a little further here, saying that treants view
civilization in much the same way “civilized” people view the untamed wild: a
source of danger best removed. Their prefer nature in its wildest and most
unspoiled state, and will work to protect their territories even from natural
disasters like floods or fires caused by lightning. They’ll ally with anyone who
shares their values and opposes their enemies. They’re also very easy to anger
(particularly when they feel they’ve been betrayed) and very hard to placate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A treant’s most frequent allies are dryads, who share their general
disposition. Eladrin and other fey are often allies as well, though in this case
both sides tend to view each other more warily. You could even have a treant
protecting the lair of an orc tribe, as long as the orcs focus their destruction
outside of the treant’s domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treants are Huge Fey Magical Beasts with the Plant keyword. They have low-light
vision, Forest Walk, and a &lt;strong&gt;Wooden Body&lt;/strong&gt; trait that makes them take ongoing 5
fire damage (save ends) whenever an attack deals immediate fire damage to
them. The trait only gets a name in the Monster Vault, but is also present in
the MM versions. If the attack in question already does ongoing fire damage, I
guess this trait doesn’t stack with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treants fight using a combination of their great strength with primal magic that
grants them a measure of control over their surroundings. They’re fairly smart
at Int 14, and though grumpy and aggressive they’re Unaligned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bramblewood-treant-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Bramblewood Treant (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the other treants, this one is “only” Large. It could be a younger
specimen, or a different species that inhabits forests with smaller trees. It’s
a Level 10 Soldier with 108 HP and all common treant traits. It has speed 8 and
a &lt;strong&gt;Bramble Branches&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that turns the covered area into difficult
terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bramblewood treant attacks with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; that mark the target for a
turn, and can throw &lt;strong&gt;stones&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 20 vs. AC) for some ranged damage. If an
enemy within 2 squares moves, the treant can use &lt;strong&gt;Entangling Branches&lt;/strong&gt; (melee
2 vs. Reflex) as an interrupt and grab them with an escape DC of 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This treant is at the right level to pal around with most dryads, some of the
eladrin, or the banshrae.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;treant-both&quot;&gt;Treant (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is Huge, and a Level 16 Elite Controller with 316 HP and all
common traits. Its land speed is 8, and it projects a &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Roots&lt;/strong&gt; aura
(3) that makes the covered area difficult terrain for nonflying enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It fights with powerful &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt;, and can use an &lt;strong&gt;Earthshaking Stomp&lt;/strong&gt; (close
burst 2 vs. Fortitude) to do a bunch of damage and knock enemies prone. In the
Monster Manual this is an encounter power, and in the Monster Vault it recharges
if the attack misses every target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The treant’s other trick is &lt;strong&gt;Awaken Forest&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 3 within 10 vs. AC),
which causes the vegetation in the area (trees included) to animate and attack
enemies within. In the MM this is an encounter power that creates a zone which
can be sustained with minor actions, and which makes new attacks against enemies
inside whenever the treant sustains it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the MV, it’s a simple at-will standard action attack, and it creates a zone
of difficult terrain that lasts either until the end of the encounter, or until
the treant uses this power again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Vault version of the treant is by far the better one, since it has
updated damage values and is also a better controller. Other than “use fire”,
there isn’t much you can do to get the upper hand over it, since it can make
solid attacks and impair movement both in melee and at range. Treants pair
really well with other creatures that have the Forest Walk ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;treant-grove-guardian-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Treant Grove Guardian (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess this is the sort of creature you can find guarding a powerful druid’s
home base. It’s a Level 18 Brute with 212 HP and all common treant traits. Its
speed is 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grove guardians are all about physical combat. Their basic attack is a Reach 3
&lt;strong&gt;Sweeping Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that can target one or two creatures, damaging and knocking
them prone on a hit. Once per encounter they can perform a maneuver called
&lt;strong&gt;Stump Stomp&lt;/strong&gt;, in which they move their speed, can enter other creature’s
spaces, and make a sweeping slam attack against each creature whose space they
enter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blackroot-treant-both&quot;&gt;Blackroot Treant (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an &lt;em&gt;undead&lt;/em&gt; treant. You know those haunted forests where the trees seem
to have evil faces? These guys are those trees. Unlike living treants they’re
actively Evil, and actually a bit smarter at Int 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blackroot treants are Huge Level 19 Elite Soldiers with 368 HP and all common
treant traits. They have Speed 6 and the Undead keyword in addition to being
Plants. They project a &lt;strong&gt;Killing Roots&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) which does 10 necrotic damage
to enemies caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; also do ongoing necrotic damage (save ends), and mark the target
for a turn. They have &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, and so can use two of those per
action. As a minor action they can use &lt;strong&gt;Entangling Roots&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 4 vs. Reflex)
to knock someone prone and restrain them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual version is a less powerful, since it lacks Double Attack, its
slams don’t mark, and the effect of Entangling Roots ceases if the treant gets
more than 4 squares away from the target. Always use the MV version if
possible. Used well, they can keep most of the party locked down tight, since
they can use Entangling Roots 1-3 times per turn and have no limit to the number
of people they can keep restrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM sample encounter is level 19 and all about that haunted forest vibe: 1
blackroot treant, 2 slaughter wights, and 2 sword wraiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like treants, even though this iteration of them is a bit more aggressive than
I would like. Mechanically speaking, the MV versions are clearly superior to the
MM originals, and you should use them whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/06/treant.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/06/treant.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Swordwing</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-swordwing.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swordwings are a 4e original, I believe. They’re only on the Monster Manual,
though I think they get some extra lore in a Dragon article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swordwings are a species of humanoid arthropod who lives in the deep
Underdark. Their name comes from their wings and from the fact that one of their
arms is shaped like a sword and can be used as such. They’re sapient, and their
alien culture is focused on building and displaying collections. Of what? It
varies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every individual swordwing has its own preferences. Some are specialized in a
single type of object, while others are more eclectic and keep several different
collections. The book says typical examples are collections of skulls, weapons,
gems, magic items, eggs, or victims’ hearts. A swordwing’s collection is what
defines it as an individual, and I guess the quality of that collection might
also act as a measure of status in their society. This implies that every
swordwing is a connoisseur and an expert curator in its chosen field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swordwings build nesting spires using the same biological processes a wasp would
use: chew the surrounding material and transform it into a paper-like substance,
which gets molded into the final structure. Each home in these spires is a small
museum of its inhabitant’s collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures fly out of their nests in groups to find more items suitable for
display, and as you might expect they don’t much care for the feelings of those
items’ current owners. Sometimes, they’ll ally with other denizens of the Deep
Underdark who don’t own anything they collect but can help them increase their
hoards in exchange for certain favors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I remember, these monsters were responsible for starting one of the battles
in the Edition War, since they were showcased in an article as an example of the
sort of all-new monster you would see in the new edition to better support epic
play. Detractors complained a lot about how swordwings made no sense because any
world where these things lived would end in short order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a point, that’s true - any epic monster that gets loose in the sort of
setting one imagines for a low-level game can theoretically turn into an
unstoppable, apocalyptic menace. However, this is supposed to be the game whose
settings have a place for epic creatures. And for Swordwings, that’s the deep
Underdark, where they get to pal around with eye tyrants, gibbering orbs, and
alien gods from the Far Realm. Preventing these fine folks from invading the
surface is the type of thing an epic campaign is supposed to be about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swordwings are Aberrant Humanoids, and prove that the Aberrant origin isn’t
&lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; about tentacles. Sometimes it’s about sword arms!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swordwings are Evil and communicate using Deep Speech. They have a ground speed
of 6 and a dragonfly-like air speed of 10 with Hover. They have low-light
vision, and their main attack is of course the &lt;strong&gt;armblade&lt;/strong&gt;, tough different
stat blocks do different things with it. There’s two of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;swordwing&quot;&gt;Swordwing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is Medium, and a Level 25 Soldier with 234 HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;armblade&lt;/strong&gt;
is a Reach 2 high-crit weapon and gains a +2 to attack bloodied targets. It also
marks the target for a turn, and benefits from a couple of passive traits that
increase its damage in certain situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of them is &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows the swordwing to attack an
adjacent enemy that shifts as an interrupt, with a damage bonus. Thanks to
&lt;strong&gt;Vicious Opportunist&lt;/strong&gt;, the swordwing also gains the same damage bonus on
opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These critters are awesome at fighting in a square formation two bugs deep,
where both rows can attack. They’re also good in a wedge formation, since
they’re so effective at punishing enemies who try to slide around them. Both of
these are better in tight quarters - wide open spaces might make then
susceptible to ranged attacks, though they can close the gap really fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give them some artillery and controller allies who can stand behind that tight
formation, and the PCs should sweat a bit. If the heroes have lots of area
attacks at their disposal, basic swordwings are also really effective in a
looser skirmish formation, since each individual can exert some control over its
immediate area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crownwing&quot;&gt;Crownwing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Large specimen is likely a high-status individual. It could be because of
simple genetics, though I think it’s more interesting if they mutate as their
collections grow fancier and more prestigious. Their average Int is 18 instead
of the basic model’s 10, and they have more skill training. It’s plausible they
know and can use magic rituals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crownwings are Level 26 Skirmishers with the Leader tag and 238 HP. Their
&lt;strong&gt;armblade&lt;/strong&gt; is still a Reach 2 high-crit weapon, and this time it does bonus
damage against flanked targets. They can make the standard &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt;
maneuver where they fly their speed without drawing opportunity attacks and make
an armblade strike at any point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their leadery skill is the &lt;strong&gt;Mark of Death&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10, encounter), which
always hits and grants allies a +2 to attack and +10 to damage against the
target. This lasts until the end of the fight, which suits an encounter power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crownwings are a perfect complement for a troop of basic swordwings, and they
also work really well in command of a gaggle of minions, who suddenly become a
lot more dangerous against a PC afflicted by the Mark of Death. Multiple
crownwings can mark multiple PCs and switch targets so they’re always hitting
someone who gives them a damage bonus. Smart PCs should try pin these things
down ASAP, and either attack from range or keep switching back to avoid the
bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 25:  4 swordwings and 1 crownwing. Your basic patrol or raiding squad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 29: 3 swordwings and a gibbering orb. Boss-and-bodyguards, with the
guards acting as a nice force multiplier.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be my bias towards 4e speaking, but I really like swordwings. They
fulfill a needed role of “high-level regulars”, and their collecting obsession
makes them more than just “Orcs, but Epic”. It also helps that they can fly.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/05/swordwing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/05/swordwing.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Spider</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-spider.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spiders have been in the game since the beginning. Here, they’re present in both
the Monster Manual and in the Monster Vault’s animal appendix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some real-world spiders can have a pretty dangerous bite, they’re not
really suitable as a combat encounter. The books concern themselves with
monstrous giant spiders instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many species of monstrous spider in D&amp;amp;D and they’re
everywhere. Deserts, forests, caverns (“surface” or Underdark), ruins, anywhere
a tiny spider would like can be home to a monstrous variety as well. The vast
majority of them are simply natural creatures, but some are the blessed of
Lolth and enjoy her divine gifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predictably, drow love spiders and frequently train them or control them through
magic to serve in all the same capacities someone on the surface would use a
dog, horse, or drake for. Kobolds and goblins might also employ them if they’re
part of the locally available fauna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All spiders shown here, with one exception, are Natural Beasts with the Spider
keyword. That keyword is important because, among other things, drow tend to
have lots of powers that buff spider allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The individual stat blocks vary a lot, but all have some level of Tremorsense,
and a climb speed equal to their ground speed with the Spider Climb tag
(obviously). Their basic attack is always a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and almost always has some
sort of venom effect associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Monster Vault spiders have &lt;strong&gt;Web Walk&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to ignore
web-based difficult terrain. While this isn’t explicitly listed in the Monster
Manual entries it would be fair to assume all of them have it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spider-swarm-mv&quot;&gt;Spider Swarm (MV)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The least monstrous of the bunch, this is a lot of normal-sized aggressive
spiders acting as a swarm monster. The swarm is a Level 3 Soldier with 44 HP,
tremorsense 5 and a speed of 6, along with the usual swarm resistances and
vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) slows enemies caught inside instead of granting
extra attacks. They attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Fangs&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex because
they get inside your armor. It has an ongoing poison damage rider (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deathjump-spider-both&quot;&gt;Deathjump Spider (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Medium spiders are Level 4 Skirmishers with 55 HP. They have tremorsense
5, resist poison 5, and a speed of 6. Though they have Web Walk, they’re not big
spinners themselves, and hunt by jumping on their prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stats for the spider’s bite are a bit wonky in the MM version: compared to
what the updated math says, their attacks are woefully inaccurate and abnormally
strong. The MV version fixes this. In both cases, the rider is ongoing poison
damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deathjump spider’s special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Death From Above&lt;/strong&gt;, in which the
spider shifts up to 6 squares by jumping and makes a bite attack at the end. If
that hits, the target is also knocked prone. The MM version also does increased
base damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Prodigious Leap&lt;/strong&gt; as a move-action encounter power, which
allows it to shift 10 squares. So this spider could initiate combat by jumping
at the party’s wizard from a full 16 squares away!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM gives it another trait, &lt;strong&gt;Soft Fall&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing it to ignore the first 30
feet of height of any fall. This is absent from the MV version, probably because
they thought it was a bit too finicky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bloodweb-spider-swarm&quot;&gt;Bloodweb Spider Swarm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more powerful version of the MV swarm, these spiders have been brought
together and are controlled by magic. Without orders, they’ll default to
attacking the nearest living creature until it dies before moving on to the next
victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This swarm counts as a Level 7 Soldier with 80 HP. It otherwise works just like
the level 3 swarm, except that it’s slower at speed 4 and its aura &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; grant
free basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;doomspinner-spider-mv&quot;&gt;Doomspinner Spider (MV)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chunky Large spider does spin elaborate webs to catch prey with. It’s a
Level 7 Controller with 82 HP, Tremorsense 10, Resist Poison 5, and speed 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their bite also has an ongoing poison damage rider, which increases if the
target of the bite is restrained, immobilized, stunned, or unconscious. Its
special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Web Casting&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within 5 vs. Reflex), which does
no damage but restrains everyone it hits. The area of the burst becomes
difficult terrain until the end of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action the doomspinner can also shoot a strand of webbing at someone,
in an attack named &lt;strong&gt;Drawn to Doom&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 5 vs. Fortitude), which does no
damage but pulls the target 4 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though doomspinners can restrain enemies by themselves, they also pair really
well with other monsters that can inflict the conditions that increase the
effectiveness of their venom. “Multiple doomspinners” is the obvious setup, but
there are plenty of other options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blade-spider-mm&quot;&gt;Blade Spider (MM)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Large spiders have two blade-like front legs, and attack with them instead
of biting. They live in the Underdark and are popular drow pets, having the
Mount keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blade spiders are Level 10 Brutes with 130 HP, tremorsense 10, and
speed 6. Unlike most of their relatives, they have no resistance to
poison. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; with a rider that does ongoing poison
damage and weakens (save ends both). They can make &lt;strong&gt;double attacks&lt;/strong&gt; with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When used as mounts, they can make &lt;strong&gt;combined attacks&lt;/strong&gt;, which means they attack
with a claw as a free action when their rider makes an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cave-spider-mv&quot;&gt;Cave Spider (MV)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Medium spiders likely behave as a scaled-up swarm, with their size and
numbers being such that you can track them individually. They’re level 12 Minion
Skirmishers with tremorsense 5, resist poison 10 and speed 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; does the usual fixed minion damage, with additional poison damage
on top if the target is immobilized, restrained, stunned or unconscious. They
can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Tethering Web&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex) as a minor action to
immobilize someone for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine a small horde of these with a leveled-up doomspinner or three, and your
PCs are going to have a bad time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;demonweb-terror-mm&quot;&gt;Demonweb Terror (MM)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Native to the Demonweb Pits, these are the true blessed of Lolth. They’re Huge
Elemental Beasts with the Spider keyword. All the other spiders in this entry
are simple Unaligned animals with Int 1, but terrors have Int 8 and are Chaotic
Evil. You can try to talk to them if you know Abyssal, but that will do you no
good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demonweb Terrors are Level 14 Elite Controllers with 296 HP, tremorsense 10, and
a speed of 6. Interestingly, they have no poison resistance, though perhaps they
should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their bite carries a venom that does ongoing poison damage and slows (save
ends). As a 1/round minor action they can shoot a &lt;strong&gt;web&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex)
that does no damage and immobilizes (save ends). After they’re first bloodied,
they can use the &lt;strong&gt;Poison Spray&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude)
that has the same effects as the bite’s rider over the whole area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These feel a tiny bit underpowered - they were likely only made Elite to pad out
their HP. However, they likely work well when accompanied by other monsters who
can capitalize on the immobilization and slowness they inflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM gives us 2 sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 11: 2 blade spiders, 2 bloodweb spider swarms, 1 drow blademaster.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 15: 1 demonweb terror, 1 drow arachnomancer, 2 drider fanglords and 3
drow warriors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the book goes all-in on the whole Lolth connection. Any
encounter with drow is likely to involve spiders. And while the lower-level
spiders will likely be found as dungeon wildlife, the more powerful ones will
very often be accompanied by drow as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think giant spiders are a classic dungeon denizen, and work well when used in
moderation. Of course, drow are known for despising the concept of moderation
when it comes to arachnids.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/05/spider.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/05/spider.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Are Mecha Silly?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I saw someone start a thread on the RPG.net forum, with the title “Why
are mecha silly?”. The person in question was of the opinion that not only were
mecha not silly, they were &lt;em&gt;plausible&lt;/em&gt;, and went on to list reasons they thought
so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of those were swiftly debunked by posters, but I think the thread
kinda got away from the main point after a while. So I thought I’d write a bit
about this subject here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thread’s title had a bit of an unfortunate framing, because it started from
the premise that mecha &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; silly even though its opening poster didn’t think
so. A better question to ask might be “Are Mecha Silly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My answer is somewhat nuanced, but it can still be summed up as “No”. Giant
robots are definitely &lt;em&gt;cinematic&lt;/em&gt;, but they’re not inherently sillier than any
other cinematic trope. It’s all about the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using “mech” and “mecha” here to mean a humanoid (or at least legged)
piloted machine that’s used in about the same role as an armored fighting
vehicle or tank. Non-combat versions are usually used as heavy construction
equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the traditional excuses for mecha: Legs make them able to
handle any terrain type better than wheels or threads. A humanoid form makes
them more agile and versatile than traditional vehicles. Something about the
specific technology used to build them makes them better weapons than
traditional vehicles (this last one varies per setting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these would hold up under scrutiny under a strictly realistic
setting. While some people are building smaller autonomous robots and
experimenting with load-bearing skeletons, building a giant mech is still far
beyond us and the general consensus on that seems to be that it’s not worth the
effort. Better to work at improving the specialized vehicles we know than
worrying about leg movement and the ground pressure exerted by two giant metal
feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you get more cinematic mecha become a better fit. An “action movie setting”
that makes you accept some people do the impossible because they’re just that
badass shouldn’t have a lot of trouble selling the idea that sometimes tanks
have legs. Full Metal Panic in its more serious moments is a good example of
this. The show itself is silly most of the time, but the robot fights are trated
in a more serious cinematic manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science fictional settings have more leeway than contemporary ones, because the
same classical excuses are still valid and it’s easier to assume that the
practical engineering concerns have been solved in the future. A lot of the
Gundam shows are in this territory, as are many other similar franchises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s just the shows that even bother to offer up excuses! You see, there
are two main “sub-genres” of mecha shows. The ones that bother to think about
excuses and to insert their mecha into a wider military context are called “Real
Robot” shows. The original Mobile Suit Gundam back in 1979 was the first of
these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other side of the coin are “Super Robot” shows, who don’t even bother with
that. Sometimes a 12-year old kid just inherits a fifteen story tall robot from
his dad, and flies that robot out of the secret hangar at the bottom of his
swimming pool to fight space monsters. Super Robot shows date from the early
seventies, and their overall aesthetic is closer to that of a gold or silver age
supers story than “proper” science fiction. They require the same kind of
suspension of disbelief. If you can accept Superman, you can accept Mazinger Z.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Real or Super, no type of mecha is inherently silly as long as you place
it in the type of story it was meant to go in. Just like any other cinematic
trope.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/01/mecha.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/01/mecha.html</guid>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lancer</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Stirge</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-stirge.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stirges have been in the game at least since the days of Basic. Here, they are
both in the Monster Manual and in the Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stirges are another example of dangerous fantasy wildlife in the implied Fourth
Edition setting. Looking like a cross between a large bat and a mosquito, these
things feed on blood and will attack any nearby creature in search of it when
hungry. While a mosquito can be dangerous because it transmits diseases, a
stirge is large enough for the blood loss it causes to be worrying. A flock of
them could exsanguinate an adult human in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like bats, they nest in dark places and tend to hunt at night. They’re a common
enough threat that anti-stirge measures are a part of every culture. Ship crews,
for example, spread unpleasant-smelling unguents in their cargo holds to prevent
stirges from nesting there. Sheperds and ranchers absolutely hate them and have
their own set of measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any dark dungeon might be home to a flock of stirges, making them one of the
many dangers adventurers must always be wary of. A large enough flock can
threaten even seasoned veterans!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since they’re considered vermin by the people of the world, they also have all
the same sinister associations worms and rats and such get. Particularly gross
necromancers love filling the body cavities of a large, bloated zombie with a
flock of stirges, which burst out when their carrier is slain. Optionally the
stirges might be zombies as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stirges are Small Natural Beasts, which does mean they might get as big as three
feet across (halfling-sized!). They have darkvision, a flight speed of 6 with
Hover, and a pathetic ground speed of 2. Their main attack is always a “bite”
with their blood-sucking proboscis-beak thing, but the exact mechanics of that
vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stirge-both&quot;&gt;Stirge (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 1 Lurker with 22 HP and the common traits above. The
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is its only attack. It does damage and grabs the target (escape DC
12). While the target is grabbed, it takes 5 ongoing damage from the
blood-sucking. While the stirge is grabeed, it gains +5 to AC and Reflex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM version has an extremely weak bite even for a level 1 monster (1d4
damage), but the MV updates that to be in line with the new math (1d4+5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a single stirge is not a big threat to a full party, it’s terrifying to a
civilian!  Non-combatants are likely minions, and if not they’re unlikely to
have much more than 10 or 15 HP. A stirge like the above could be nesting in any
given dark hole near the poor schmuck’s farm, and could kill them in one bite
and &lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt; a round or two of blood-sucking. The civilian is also more likely to
meet the stirge than a goblin or the like, and of course it will never be just
one stirge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stirge-suckerling-mv&quot;&gt;Stirge Suckerling (MV)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A young stirge that’s already quite hungry. It’s a Level 5 Minion Lurker, which
means it comes in hordes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their only attack is the usual &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which does a bit of damage and
initiates a grab (escape DC 15). While the grab persists, the suckerling can
only make bite attacks against the grabbed target, but those hit
automatically. The target also takes ongoing damage equal to the number of
suckerlings attached to it, so be sure to make them gang up on the
squishies. Now there’s a nice mental image for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;death-husk-stirge-mv&quot;&gt;Death Husk Stirge (MV)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An undead stirge used as filling for a Bloated Zombie Surprise. It’s a Small
Natural Animate (undead), and a Level 6 Skirmisher with 71 HP. It has
darkvision, an immunity to poison, and 10 resistance to necrotic damage. It has
the usual stirge ground speed of 2 and flight speed of 6, but if it’s hit by
radiant damage it loses the ability to fly for a turn (and falls if it was in
the air).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Death husk stirges won’t stick to you, but they’ll still suck your blood. The
&lt;strong&gt;Rotted Blood&lt;/strong&gt; attack (close blast 3 vs. Fortitude) allows them to spit the
blood stored inside their purulent intestines, dealing necrotic damage and
blinding those it hits for a turn. Undead in the blast can shift 2 squares as a
free action. This is an encounter power, but hitting someone with the basic
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; attack allows the stirge to recharge it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Nimble Wing&lt;/strong&gt; to fly 4 squares without
provoking opportunity attacks. When they hit 0 HP, they burst and those purulent
intestines produce a cloud of &lt;strong&gt;Necrotic Miasma&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs. Fortitude),
which deals a bit of necrotic damage and weakens for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dire-stirge-both&quot;&gt;Dire Stirge (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, like every bit of natural fauna in the setting, stirges have a dire
version. They’re larger, but not quite large enough to go up a size
category. They are however a lot meaner, being level 7 Lurkers with 60 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the usual increased numbers due to being higher level, dire stirges
do 10 ongoing damage while attached and have an escape DC of 16. They are
otherwise mechanically identical to the level 1 variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stirge-suckerling-swarm-mv&quot;&gt;Stirge Suckerling Swarm (MV)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For when you have so many suckerlings in play it becomes impractical to track
them individually. This swarm is a Level 10 Brute with 128 HP, and counts as a
Medium Natural Beast. It has a ground speed of 2 and a flight speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has the usual swarm traits. Its &lt;strong&gt;aura&lt;/strong&gt; (1) makes anyone caught inside
begin taking 5 ongoing damage (save ends). If the victim is already taking
untyped ongoing damage, that damage increases by 5, with no stated limit. It’s a
nice way to model an incresing number of tiny stirges attaching themselves to
the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Suckerlings&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack deals good damage and ongoing 5 damage
(save ends), so it can step up the aura’s timetable a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an adjacent enemy moves away from the swarm, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Hungry Flight&lt;/strong&gt;
as an immediate reaction, flying up to its speed so it’s adjacent to the target
again. This does not provoke opportunity attacks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stirge-swarm-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Stirge Swarm (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you get when those suckerlings grow up. This swarm is a Medium, Level 12
Brute with 141 HP. Being a MM monster, it’s a bit simpler. Aside from the usual
swarm traits, it has a basic attack that deals ongoing damage (save ends), and
an aura that allows it to make basic attacks against anyone caught inside as
free actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re probably better off leveling up the suckerling swarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t really tame stirges, since they’ll attack anything that has blood, but
sometimes kobolds and goblins use captured stirges as traps. Trigger the trap,
release the swarm! They can also be encountered as indiscriminate opportunists,
or in coincidental cooperation with things they won’t feed on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters provide two such examples of this: the first is 2 dire
stirges and 3 bloodweb spider swarms, the second 3 stirge swarms and a flesh
golem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Large zombie minion full of undead stirges” setup has been hinted at
above, as well. For Maximum Carnage you could add the undead traits to a stirge
swarm stat block to get a swarm of death husk stirges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually wouldn’t be very enthusiastic about stirges, but now I kinda want to
use the Zombie Surprise at least once.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/12/28/stirge.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/12/28/stirge.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Sphinx</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-sphinx.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Mufasa is having a bad day. Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sphinxes are inspired by Greek and Egyptian mythology and have been in the game
at least since BECMI. Here, they are only on the Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sphinx is a holy guardian created in antiquity to protect a sacred place like
a tomb, temple, or shrine. In this task they can be found alone or in pairs, and
sometimes they also command other, lesser guardians. The ritual that creates
them is rare and powerful, binding an angelic spirit to the body of a celestial
lion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would someone create a sphinx instead of a golem? There’s the matter of
style, of course. Golems would be preferred by a certain type of arcane caster,
while sphinxes feel like something a deity would allow its greatest servants to
make. There are also practical advantages: sphinxes are both sapient and quite
smart, so they can follow the intended spirit of their orders, and better
distinguish between people who are allowed to be there and people they should
eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way they do this is through the &lt;em&gt;sphinx’s challenge&lt;/em&gt;, where they try to
ascertain if someone has a right to be at the guarded location or not. Riddles
are a classic, but a sphinx can also ask for proof of ancestry, the solution to
an ethical or theological puzzle, or even just a specific password. The sphinx
is bound to let someone who passes the test proceed unmolested, though it’s
still going to attack if the visitors try to damage or rob the guarded location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all the book has to say about sphinxes, but I think we can speculate a
bit as well. Unlike most of other “guardian creatures” we saw so far, sphinxes
are neither constructs nor undead, yet the text implies they’re just as capable
of guarding their designed site for eternity. So I think it’s fair to say that
they are immune to age, hunger, thirst and possibly even sleep, at least when
performing their mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the books emphasize the role of sphinxes as the guardians of “ancient” and
“forgotten” places, I think it’s also quite possible for them guard places that
are neither. Maybe the Pelorite cathedral or the big Temple-Library of Ioun have
a pair of sphinxes posted at their front entrance, even though they’re built
right in the middle of major population centers. Sphinxes are perfect for this
because they’re intelligent, and so they’re not going to attack innocent
visitors by mistake like a golem would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good sphinx might be hamstrung by overly specific or ethically questionable
bindings, though, so you could also have a scenario where a party carefully
helps the creature to free itself from its duties without triggering a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s only one stat block, so we’ll get right on it. Sphinxes are Large
Immortal Magical Beasts, and Level 16 Elite Soldiers with 304 HP. They have
trained Perception, Darkvision, plus a ground speed of 6, a flight speed of 8
(clumsy) and Overland Flight 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature trait is the &lt;strong&gt;Sphinx’s Challenge&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives us mechanics
for the concept described in the lore section: the sphinx will pose an out of
combat challenge to any potential intruders, and it can take whatever form the
GM thinks is appropriate. If the challenged party refuses to answer, or gets the
answer wrong, the sphinx will gain 1 extra action point and a +2 to attack,
damage, and defenses in the ensuing combat. Note that attacking the sphinx
before it can make its challenge counts as a refusal to answer! I think the only
case where the party can fight a sphinx without these bonuses is if they pass
the challenge and are later caught robbing the guarded place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat, this sphinx is a straightforward physical threat. It attacks with
&lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, it can &lt;strong&gt;pounce&lt;/strong&gt; to make a charge and knock the target prone on a
hit, and it has a &lt;strong&gt;frightful roar&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 10 vs. will) which gives
victims a -2 penalty to defense (save ends). It can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Second Wind&lt;/strong&gt;
once per encounter, which works like the PC version: the sphinx heals 75 HP and
gains +2 to all defenses for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s of course possible for the sphinx to know all sorts of rituals, and for the
GM to create custom sphinxes with the common traits above and a more magical
selection of combat abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 15: 1 sphinx, 1 battle guardian, and 2 helmed
horrors. Indeed, a sphinx is smart enough that it could be given command of
those guardian constructs and employ them in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the concept of sphinxes, and I kinda want to run an adventure where the
sphinxes at the Temple-Library of Ioun are upstanding members of their community
and know everyone in the city by name.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/12/27/sphinx.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/12/27/sphinx.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Specter</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-specter.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specters have been in the game since the beginning, and here they’re only on the
Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I talked about ghosts, I mentioned that every single synonym for that word
used to be its own entirely separate type of incorporeal undead, and that 4e
consolidated that a bit but not entirely. Specters are one of the undead that
retained their own entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specters are incorporeal undead that can form “naturally” when an evil murderer
or other equally depraved villain dies. Unlike a ghost, they don’t retain any
memory of their life, and aren’t bound to a particular location. However,
they’re just as evil as they always were, and their new hatred of the living
ensures they keep looking for people to kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specters tend to cling to other equally malevolent undead, and will sometimes
ally with evil living beings if that would ensure a steady supply of victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specters are Medium Shadow Humanoid with the Undead keyword. They have
darkvision as well as both the &lt;strong&gt;insubstantial&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;phasing&lt;/strong&gt; traits. If
you’re using Monster Vault-era rules this means they take half damage from
everything but force attacks, but when specters were published they took half
damage from all sources. Their HP is a bit lower than their level would
indicate, so being insubstantial doesn’t make fights last that much longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As undead, they’re immune to disease and poison and have some degree of necrotic
resistance and radiant vulnerability. They have no ground speed, but they fly,
and it’s not like you can force a specter to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;specter&quot;&gt;Specter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 4 Lurker with 30 HP and all the traits mentioned
above. It flies at speed 6, has 10 necrotic resistance, and 5 radiant
vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The specter has a &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Chill&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1), which inflicts a -2 penalty to
all enemy defenses. It attacks with a &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Touch&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex and
does necrotic damage. It can also unleash a &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Barrage&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2
vs. Will) which does psychic damage and knocks prone. This is likely some sort
of scary illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a standard action, the specter can become &lt;strong&gt;invisible&lt;/strong&gt; until it attacks or
is hit by an attack. It will likely alternate between attacking from
invisibility, and retreating while invisible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;voidsoul-specter&quot;&gt;Voidsoul Specter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is either the specter of someone really evil, or a basic model that has
grown bloated through years of post-mortem murder. It’s a Level 23 Lurker with
115 HP. Its necrotic resistance increases to 30, and its radiant vulnerability
to 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spectral Touch&lt;/strong&gt; works the same with bigger numbers. The &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Chill&lt;/strong&gt;
aura is stronger, dealing 10 cold damage to enemies caught inside in addition to
inflicting the same -2 defense penalty. Its special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Life Siphon&lt;/strong&gt;
(Close Blast 5 vs. Fortitude; encounter) which deals necrotic damage and makes
the specter heal 5 HP for every target damaged by it. Finally, its
&lt;strong&gt;invisibility&lt;/strong&gt; works the same but becomes a 1/round minor action instead of a
standard one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter has a basic specter, a deathlock wight, and a bunch of
zombies and skeletons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specters feel to me like one of those monsters that should have been rolled into
the “Ghost” entry. They don’t have much to distinguish them from ghosts or from
wraiths (the other surviving synomym). I’d guess that’s why they didn’t make the
Monster Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/12/27/specter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/12/27/specter.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
