<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 15:38:35 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 15:38:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Are Mecha Silly?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I saw someone start a thread on the RPG.net forum, with the title “Why
are mecha silly?”. The person in question was of the opinion that not only were
mecha not silly, they were &lt;em&gt;plausible&lt;/em&gt;, and went on to list reasons they thought
so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of those were swiftly debunked by posters, but I think the thread
kinda got away from the main point after a while. So I thought I’d write a bit
about this subject here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thread’s title had a bit of an unfortunate framing, because it started from
the premise that mecha &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; silly even though its opening poster didn’t think
so. A better question to ask might be “Are Mecha Silly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My answer is somewhat nuanced, but it can still be summed up as “No”. Giant
robots are definitely &lt;em&gt;cinematic&lt;/em&gt;, but they’re not inherently sillier than any
other cinematic trope. It’s all about the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using “mech” and “mecha” here to mean a humanoid (or at least legged)
piloted machine that’s used in about the same role as an armored fighting
vehicle or tank. Non-combat versions are usually used as heavy construction
equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the traditional excuses for mecha: Legs make them able to
handle any terrain type better than wheels or threads. A humanoid form makes
them more agile and versatile than traditional vehicles. Something about the
specific technology used to build them makes them better weapons than
traditional vehicles (this last one varies per setting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these would hold up under scrutiny under a strictly realistic
setting. While some people are building smaller autonomous robots and
experimenting with load-bearing skeletons, building a giant mech is still far
beyond us and the general consensus on that seems to be that it’s not worth the
effort. Better to work at improving the specialized vehicles we know than
worrying about leg movement and the ground pressure exerted by two giant metal
feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you get more cinematic mecha become a better fit. An “action movie setting”
that makes you accept some people do the impossible because they’re just that
badass shouldn’t have a lot of trouble selling the idea that sometimes tanks
have legs. Full Metal Panic in its more serious moments is a good example of
this. The show itself is silly most of the time, but the robot fights are trated
in a more serious cinematic manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science fictional settings have more leeway than contemporary ones, because the
same classical excuses are still valid and it’s easier to assume that the
practical engineering concerns have been solved in the future. A lot of the
Gundam shows are in this territory, as are many other similar franchises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s just the shows that even bother to offer up excuses! You see, there
are two main “sub-genres” of mecha shows. The ones that bother to think about
excuses and to insert their mecha into a wider military context are called “Real
Robot” shows. The original Mobile Suit Gundam back in 1979 was the first of
these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other side of the coin are “Super Robot” shows, who don’t even bother with
that. Sometimes a 12-year old kid just inherits a fifteen story tall robot from
his dad, and flies that robot out of the secret hangar at the bottom of his
swimming pool to fight space monsters. Super Robot shows date from the early
seventies, and their overall aesthetic is closer to that of a gold or silver age
supers story than “proper” science fiction. They require the same kind of
suspension of disbelief. If you can accept Superman, you can accept Mazinger Z.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Real or Super, no type of mecha is inherently silly as long as you place
it in the type of story it was meant to go in. Just like any other cinematic
trope.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/01/mecha.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/01/mecha.html</guid>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lancer</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Stormtrooper Armor Conundrum</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you know what is the second hardest thing to convert when adapting Star Wars
to the tabletop? Stormtroopers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. From an in-character perspective they vastly
outnumber and outgun the scrappy rebel protagonists, with deadly blaster
carbines and that iconic heavy armor. Yet in the actual narrative they almost
never hit a shot and always get taken out in one hit from one of the heroes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their poor aim has actually made it into GURPS as an optional cinematic rule
named “Imperial Stormtrooper Marksmanship Academy”, which reduces the deadliness
of enemy shooters. But the armor thing has tied people’s brain in knots, because
it can’t be explained away with a joke. Why does their armor do nothing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost as many explanations and solutions to this as there are Star
Wars adaptations. Some say “all armor is bad, actually” and have PCs rely on
plot protection. Some have an armor system but go out of their way to explain
why trooper suits specifically are actually bad. And some have an armor system
that rates trooper armor highly but then go on to state that fun shootouts from
the movies are lies and legends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me, I think I hit on a solution that allows me to keep those fun fights while
still having armor be cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;imperial-stormtrooper-armor-drills&quot;&gt;Imperial Stormtrooper Armor Drills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cinematic rule meant for science fiction settings where highly
effective armor is common, but you want the PCs to have fun battles against
armies of heavily-armored mooks. Star Wars and stormtroopers are the most
obvious examples, but it also works for settings such as Waframe’s with its
Grineer soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this rule, armor worn by “mook” or “fodder” enemies has no protective
value, and is mostly a cosmetic detail! Any solid hit will take them down,
regardless of whether it would have penetrated their DR under standard
rules. Armor worn by PCs and other important characters still uses all the
default rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows you to frame a particularly badass trooper as a real threat and have
them survive several attacks without giving them different protective gear. It
also allows PCs to loot armor from a fallen mook and have it actually provide
benefit beyond a temporary disguise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optionally, you could perhaps take this a bit further and subject certain
stormtroopers to the Inverse Ninja Rule. See a full platoon of troopers gunning
for you? Easy. See &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; trooper approaching? Danger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The first is the Force, but we all know that. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/10/27/stormtrooper-armor.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/10/27/stormtrooper-armor.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>star-wars</category>
        
        <category>science-fiction</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Irony At the Heart of Shadowrun</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For a very long time Shadowrun was my favorite game system and setting. These
days I still like the setting, but my annoyance at a host of small details in it
is stronger than my wish to play in it as written. Still, it’s useful to think
and talk about these details. It allows me to figure out what I want to do
better in my eventual home-brewed rewrite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these details isn’t small at all, however. In fact, I’d go as far as
calling it the great irony at the heart of the game, as the title of this post
implied. It was developed from some forum posts I made on RPG.net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-first-the-good-parts&quot;&gt;But First, The Good Parts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to be unfairly critical of Shadowrun&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I know a few people who
write for it, and the last thing I want is to give the impression that I’m
attacking them. I’m not. This entire article is my personal opinion and in no
way meant to disparage any of the fine people who are passionate enough about
Shadowrun to write for it professionally. So let’s begin by talking about
something that this game does &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about the setting design of Shadowrun is that it presents
players with a very clear mission-based structure. The infamous question of “But
what do we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; in this world?” is answered very early and very clearly. This is
a game about completing dangerous missions for money, just like D&amp;amp;D is about
killing monsters and looting dungeons. Someone asks you to play Shadowrun, 99
times out of 100 you know the rough overall shape that campaign is going to
take. You see a heist movie and you start thinking about it in the context of
Shadowrun in your head, even if it doesn’t have all the same style elements,
because the premise is strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowrun nailed the answer to this important question so well that it kinda
spilled over to other similar games. It became the default playstile for
Cyberpunk 2020 against the wishes of its own authors, and it often gets adopted
as the answer to “what do we do” in Transhuman Space&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which is so adamant
about offering none in its pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of Shadowrun setting elements, though, this structure has an
excellent &lt;em&gt;premise&lt;/em&gt; but its implementation gives rise to a lot of unintentional
oddness. Or, in this case, to a Great Irony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This irony, I think, emerges when the strong premise above gets combined with
AD&amp;amp;D-style adversarial GMing, which was very popular when Shadowrun was first
written. I believe it to be entirely unintentional, since as far as I can tell
Shadowrun’s design methodology was mostly based on the Rule of Cool with a dash
of “everyone else does this”. If it’s intentional, though, it’s among the
greatest acts of trolling in all of gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;isnt-it-ironic&quot;&gt;Isn’t it Ironic?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so the Sixth World is ruled by megacorporations who control every aspect
of people’s lives. Most of these people live hand-to-mouth and work themselves
to death in order to prop up the decadent lifestyles of a few billionaire
executives. “Wage slave” is pretty much a synonym for “low-level megacorporate
employee” in this setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the flavor text tells us, player characters are supposed to have managed
to escape this cycle of misery. They live in the shadows cast by those giant
corporate towers, and they have the skills to oppose the megacorps and make
their independent way in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or do they?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit I don’t know how things are structured in the most recent
editions&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but I remember that the Shadowrun Companion for Second Edition
contained detailed advice on how much money your PCs should be paid for those
risky missions.  I call it the “rent plus change” model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the book, GMs should pay PCs enough for them to cover their
lifestyle payments (i.e, rent and food) for the next month, with a little bit
left over for resupplying consumables and eventually upgrading a piece of gear
after a while. This was &lt;em&gt;per month&lt;/em&gt;, not per run. If you had only one big run
that month, it would pay this amount. If you had several, they would pay
proportionally less so you’d receive the same “rent plus change” amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was perfectly in-keeping with the AD&amp;amp;D school of GMing and design, which
demanded PCs “earn” their power and had cool gear that cost money as a
significant part of that power. If they earn “too much” money, they would get
“too powerful”, and no one wants that! If your players look like they do, it’s
because they’re cheating cheaters who cheat and should be punished for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all published adventures started with a scene where the party met with
Mr. Johnson to discuss the job. In the vast majority of these adventures,
Mr. Johnson is a shady corporate exec working for one of the megas. And the GM
text for this scene always included the oh-so-funny “If the players refuse the
job, announce that the adventure ended, pack up your things and go home.” This
is a joke about how the PCs don’t have any choice but to take the job as
presented. In fact, the flavor text for the same scene almost always assumes
they’re hurting for cash just before they get that call from their contact
setting up the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, those fiercely independent PC shadowrunners? &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;They’re all wage slaves
too&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. And the game advises the GM to keep them that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were the original writers oblivious to these implications, or are they still
laughing today about how no one seems to have noticed? I don’t think I have seen
any official discussion about this contradiction in any of the books I’ve
read. It’s just taken as a given, and never questioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This central irony gets funnier when you add in two sets of rules that were
published in the same edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;orichalcum&quot;&gt;Orichalcum&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early SR2 sourcebook called The Grimoire contained rules for making magic
items. It required a lot of skill tests and time, and the materials were still
super-expensive, but the final monetary cost was cheaper than buying the item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Do you buy or make your items?” would have been mostly a question of personal
preference… if the book didn’t also have rules for making those materials from
raw natural resources. You could use them for enchanting or sell them for half
list price. You could even make orichalcum, the magical metal used in the
creation of the most powerful magic items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orichalcum was so expensive that a single 10-gram “unit” cost the same as a
sports car or as almost nine months of High Lifestyle. The process for making it
was time consuming and laborious, but not really dangerous or illegal. And a
skilled character could end up with multiple units of orichalcum at the end of
that process. Selling even a single unit would more than pay the cost of the
necessary equipment, which was reusable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these rules, a team of PCs that includes at least one magician has no
financial reason to run the shadows. They can just set up an orichalcum-making
operation instead, and live like kings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stolen-cars&quot;&gt;Stolen Cars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shadowrun Companion sourcebook includes rules for stealing cars and selling
them on the black market, which theoretically were meant to be used in a
campaign where the characters were gangers instead of Shadowrunners. You could
sell an entire stolen car for a fraction of its market value, or break it down
for parts and sell those over several days and get money equal to the car’s full
list price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stealing cars is of course illegal and dangerous, but it was trivial for the
typical PC party in this game. After all they have the skills to routinely break
into top-secret research labs full of intricate and deadly security measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheapest four-wheeled vehicle in the book was the Ford Americar, your
typical “generic crummy sedan” that filled every street. Stealing and
dismantling one of those every week would pay roughly five times the amount
recommended in the “rent plus change” advice in &lt;em&gt;the very same book&lt;/em&gt;. Or perhaps
you could steal one limousine or fancy sports car per quarter. In either case,
it was again much safer and more profitable than running the shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shadowrun--irony--awesome&quot;&gt;Shadowrun + Irony = Awesome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When these two “oopsies” were first discovered, I remember seeing a lot of GMs
go absolutely ballistic over them. The accusations of “munchkinism” flew thick
and fast, but in true those GMs were mad that the PCs were doing something that
wasn’t in the script. They reveled in describing the disproportionate response
law enforcement or competitors would visit upon the PCs, which was just an
excuse to punish the players for veering off the rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I think these two altertane activities are fraggin’ awesome,
precisely because they allow the party to truly break free from the grind. If
your players decide to retire from shadowrunning and make orichalcum or boost
cars for a living, I fully believe that the right response is to play along and
make the campaign be about that! All of those things mentioned as hard blocks by
curmudgeonly controlling GMs are actually excellent adventure hooks. And I’m
pretty sure any decent player group is going to keep finding non-monetary
reasons to return to the shadows. There’s still people to help and megacorps to
destroy, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I say that the first thing a team of shadowrunners needs to do is to find a
way to leave classic shadowrunning behind for good. It’s a sucker’s game. Stay
independent, take care of your community, tear down the system, make the Sixth
World better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Which already makes me nicer than most of the people who proclaim
  themselves its true fans. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though THS PCs tend to be working for government agencies or corporations
  rather than being freelance criminals. This is, after all, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/06/on-transhuman-space.html&quot;&gt;a cyberpunk setting
  as viewed by the bad guys&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I stopped at the end of Fourth. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/28/shadowrun-irony.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/28/shadowrun-irony.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cyberpunk and Plagues</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;preface&quot;&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been sitting on this one for a while now. I’m not gonna lie, writing and
publishing those Monster Manual posts is quite soothing. Particularly the
releasing part, which is just a few mechanical actions now that I have so much
pre-written material for it. Every once in a while I’ll sit and write something
that’s on my mind, and hesitate a bit before posting it. This is one such post,
which I’d say was written somewhere around late April or early May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-post&quot;&gt;The Post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the outtakes from &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/16/on-transhuman-space.html&quot;&gt;my last screed against Transhuman Space&lt;/a&gt; was a
rebuttal to the bit where it says it’s better and more realistic than cyberpunk
because it doesn’t have any apocalyptic disasters in its Very Serious history of
the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had had whole paragraphs mapped out in my mind about how yes, the insistence
of 90’s cyberpunk RPGs in inserting these catastrophes was kinda silly. About
how they probably had their roots in their authors believing in that “end of
history” bullshit just as hard as the text of Transhuman Space itself did, and
how they couldn’t see the future being a shitty place if there wasn’t a plague,
a nuclear meltdown, or a big war somewhere in there to muck things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was going to end with an assertion that no, you don’t need a big, clear,
forced disaster to head down a bad path. A lot of those cyberpunk tropes (evil
corporations, authoritarian governments disguised as democracies, and so on)
happened all on their own without needing such a push. William Gibson’s concept
of the Jackpot, presented in his novel &lt;em&gt;The Peripheral&lt;/em&gt;, encapsulates all of
this a lot better than Transhuman Space’s bright future. Well, he is William
friggin’ Gibson, and he had almost twenty extra years of history to look at, but
still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That post is all ruined now, of course, because it turns out those
disaster-licious 90’s games were on to something after all. Here we are, amid a
deadly pandemic that’s causing an untold number of tragedies and turning whole
societies upside-down as enforced quarantines and lockdowns push them to change
their habits in a rush. It’s not nearly as bad as a genuine 90’s RPG disaster,
but, in true Jackpot fashion, it doesn’t have to be. It’s not the &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; of the
evil corps’ and authoritarian governments’ rise to power, but a &lt;em&gt;consequence&lt;/em&gt; of
it. And I don’t think either THS or the 90’s games would ever have predicted
that rich capitalists would, when faced with a plague, suggest that it was OK to
let vast numbers of people die from it as long as it kept the economy
growing. THS has far too much faith in its Very Smart Neoliberals to suggest
such a thing, and it sounds too bleak even for a 90’s-style dystopia.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/19/cyberpunk-plagues.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/19/cyberpunk-plagues.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dungeoncrawl Procedures at Nature Kills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I published a post on “&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/01/24/old-school-movement.html&quot;&gt;Old School Movement&lt;/a&gt;” with a simple
set of rules I could use when GMing converted old-school D&amp;amp;D and AD&amp;amp;D dungeons
in Dungeon Fantasy. Recently, the Nature Kills blog has also published &lt;a href=&quot;https://gurpshexytime.blogspot.com/2020/06/dungeoncrawl-procedures.html&quot;&gt;their
own take&lt;/a&gt; on the same subject in a post titled “Dungeoncrawl Procedures”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find most interesting on that post, and on the sources it links, is that
they see the lack of this detailed procedure in recent D&amp;amp;D editions as a grave
omission in that system. Having a canonical procedure to crawl a dungeon or to
perform any other sort of exploration is a vital pre-requisite for properly
designing these dungeons and other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual procedure outlined there is similar to mine in nature, but differs in
some details and adds others I didn’t cover. The ones I found most interesting
are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This procedure should apply to all dungeon exploration, not just to AD&amp;amp;D
adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default movement speed is double what I guessed (encumbered Move x 20m per
turn).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traps are only sprung 2 out of 6 times. A direct translation of an old-school
mechanic that’s perfect for use when you’re not constantly using a map and
miniatures.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have convinced me to apply this mechanic to all dungeon crawls, but I
disagree with enough of their details that I feel I have to revise my own
procedure. That will happen some other time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/09/exploration-procedures.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/09/exploration-procedures.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>link</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alternative Dungeon Fantasy Reward Systems</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/studio-ghibli-dark-souls.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustration by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kyle-fewell.com/&quot;&gt;Kyle Fewell&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a lot of players, a big part of the fun of playing in the Dungeon Fantasy
genre comes from the rewards their characters acquire in play. And these in
turn fall into two main categories: treasure and experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In GURPS, “experience” means Character Points, which are usually obtained for
successfully completing adventure goals and can be directly used to improve
characters. “Treasure” in a Dungeon Fantasy context can be split into magic
items and “monetary” treasure (i.e, coins and stuff you end up selling in town).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default these two reward types are mostly unrelated. Going by the experience
rewards scheme on p. 92 of DF: Exploits, a party could enter a dungeon, win lots
of battles, find a secret area or three, and win plenty of experience even if
they never find a single coin’s worth of treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the exact nature of your campaign, you might want to mess with
this reward scheme. Here are two possible ways to do that. In both, magic items
remain pretty much as written, but a stronger relationship is established
between experience and monetary treasure. They replace the standard system from
DF: Exploits entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;old-school-money-is-experience&quot;&gt;Old School: Money Is Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the party returns to town, add up the total value in $ of all the monetary
treasure they acquired. As usual, coins contribute their full value. Other items
contribute their sale value, but only if the PCs sell them. Those items they
decide to keep should be excluded from this calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This total should be divided among the PCs. If your party is an anarchist
commune that keeps all money in a collective pile (like mine are!), then assume
an equal split for experience purposes. Most other parties probably also split
their take evenly, though if they’re really into that old-school vibe they might
have a complicated scheme set up that includes henchmen with half-shares,
seniority bonuses, and thieves who steal from the other PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCs who survived the process of splitting the loot get to earn XP from
it. Divide each PC’s share by $500: that’s how many points they get. This is the
exact same exchange rate they’d get from converting character points to money
during character creation. Depending on how much treasure your adventures
feature, you might want to adjust the rate! For example, a PC in a campaign that
follows &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2020/05/nearly-complete-thoughts-on-10x-cost.html&quot;&gt;Petter V. Del’Orto’s suggested house rule&lt;/a&gt; would earn one point for
every $5000 they earned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: Let’s say we have a party of 5 PCs that agree to split their loot
evenly. They meet a dragon shortly after they enter a dungeon, and are forced to
retreat having only found a small coin stash worth $1500. That comes out to $300
per PC, which is not enough for them to earn any points from this delve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCs prepare themselves better and try again, and this time they’re able to
kill the dragon and loot its hoard, which contains $25000 in monetary treasure
and several magic items. The magic items don’t enter into this calculation, so
each PC ends up with $5000 and earns 10 character points from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dungeon-souls-experience-is-money&quot;&gt;Dungeon Souls: Experience is Money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some campaigns take place in settings where money is worthless. One example is
the Havens and Hells setting presented in Pyramid #3/89. Another is the Dark
Souls franchise. This alternate system is inspired by the latter, taking the
usual “battle experience” mechanics and making them into an in-character
concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The metaphysics of the world are such that when you defeat a monster in battle,
you siphon off a little of its life force! Depending on the setting this might
require killing the monster, but it could also involve simply defeating it in
combat and performing a small ritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In either case, people in the setting can use this accumulated “soul energy” for
all sorts of purposes, and it can be voluntarily transferred. So it becomes the
de-facto currency in a setting that has no use for mundane money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest way to implement this is to say that victory in battle is worth 500
“soul points” for every character point it would have been worth according to
p. 92 of DF: Exploits. This means a battle against a small amount of fodder is
worth nothing, and a big boss fight with lots of extra henchthings thrown in
might be worth 1500 SP. Again, this is the same exchange rate you use to convert
points into money during character creation, and you can vary it to suit your
preferred pace of advancement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more detailed way to model it is to use the optional rules on the &lt;strong&gt;It’s a
Threat!&lt;/strong&gt; article on Pyramid #3/77, and say that a slain monster is worth soul
points equal to its Combat Effectiveness Rating. This method is a bit
math-intensive: the article has a table with values for a few published
monsters, but for anything outside of that you’ll have to calculate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter which method you’re using, an important decision you must make is
whether the “soul points” from a battle must be split among the PCs or if each
PC gets the full amount when the fight ends. The former setup results in much
slower advancement than the system in Exploits, while the latter more or less
keeps pace with it as far as combat experience is concerned. I do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
recommend fully copying Dark Souls and giving soul points from a monster only to
the PC who dealt the last blow: that works in a solo campaign, but nowhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Treasure” might still exist in this model in the form of dead adventurers with
residual soul points still present in their remains. This could lead to
entertaining scenes such as the party slaying a dragon and leaving its piles of
gold behind in favor of searching for the corpses of the previous parties that
failed to defeat it. And of course, if you’re using Havens and Hells then
Souls-like corpse runs are totally a thing that happens in that setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using soul points for advancement is a matter of converting them in town using
the reverse exchange rate: 500 SP for 1 character point. They can also be used
to buy stuff, in which case 1 SP is worth $1. So characters must choose between
buying equipment or upgrading their abilities, which will end up slowing
advancement overall and making looted gear that much more desirable. A suit of
fine armor you find in the wild is one you don’t have to spend Soul Points on!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/01/alternative-rewards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/01/alternative-rewards.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>'Superheavy' Melee Weapons in GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over- and undersized weapons are a popular trope for fantasy and
fantasy-adjacent stories. Those giants and pixies need something to fight with,
and human-scale warriors with huge swords is a itself a popular genre trope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS already has a pretty good set of cinematic rules for representing
these. The best source of these is the &lt;em&gt;Scaling Weapons and Armor&lt;/em&gt; section found
in &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Low-Tech Companion 2: Weapons and Warriors&lt;/strong&gt;. GURPS Dungeon Fantasy
uses a limited subset of those in DF1 and 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are a few other tropes that mess around with weapon weights in a
supernatural way. Let’s take a look at how to represent them in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;superheavy-weapons&quot;&gt;Superheavy Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a melee weapon that’s the same size as its mundane counterpart, but it’s
a lot &lt;em&gt;heavier&lt;/em&gt;. It’s probably made out of a non-standard material, which
depending on the weapon might be a fruit of superscience or magic. Such weapons
are usually built for legendarily strong wielders! The increased weight not only
makes the weapons more deadly, but also allows its owner to employ their full
strength when fighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To model these weapons, use the Scaling Weapons and Armor rules, with a few
modifications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Either pick a final weight for the weapon, or note the strength of its
intended wielder if you already know that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go to page 21 of Low-Tech Companion 2, and pick the line whose “Typical User
ST” column most closely matches that of the wielder.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you started with the weight, divide final weight by the “base” weight of
the weapon and pick the line whose Weight column is closest to the result.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modify the weapon’s Damage, required ST, Weight and base cost as written in
LTC2. &lt;em&gt;Do not&lt;/em&gt; modify Reach or SM.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it! And yes, you can combine this with normal weapon scaling
to make a weapon whose weight is abnormally large for its size. In that case,
two extra steps apply after completing the procedure above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiply the weapon’s Reach by the value in the table row corresponding to the
SM of the intended wielder.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cost is the &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; of the weapon’s final modified cost, or the cost of a
standard SM 0 weapon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 1&lt;/strong&gt;: We’re making a super-strong martial artist character and we want
him to use an iron quarterstaff that’s ten times heavier than the wooden
variety. Looking at the table on LTC2 p. 21, we see that the closest multiplier
is 12.25, for the SM+3 line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After applying the modified process above, we end up with a weapon that has the
following qualities: Damage sw+7 cr or thr+7 cr; Reach 1, 2; Parry +2; Cost
$122,50; Weight 20kg (40 lbs); ST 25. So our hero would need at least ST 25 to
properly wield such a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 2&lt;/strong&gt;: We’re making a pixie barbarian using Dungeon Fantasy rules. Her
ST is 13, which is legendary for a people whose SM is -6 and whose typical ST
score is 5. We want her to wield a weapon that’s superheavy &lt;em&gt;for a pixie&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chosen base weapon is a Dueling Halberd. We use the SM -6 row in the table
for the halberd’s Reach multiplier, and the SM -2 row for everything else. Our
resulting halberd will weight only a quarter of the human version, but it will
be 25 times heavier than a “standard” pixie polearm, and weight more than its
wielder! Since its modified cost of $30 is lower than its base cost of $150, it
costs the same as a full-sized halberd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final stats are: Damage sw+2 cut or sw+2 imp or thr+2 imp; Reach C; Parry 0U
or 0; Cost $150; Weight 1.25kg (2.5 lbs); ST 6++. Note that our super-strong
pixie can wield this halberd one-handed without it becoming unready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;magically-attuned-weapons&quot;&gt;Magically Attuned Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trope is popular in the Exalted roleplaying game. Magic weapons in that
setting are based both on some tales of classical mythology and on modern media
such as action anime and certain video games. The heroes who wield these weapons
“attune their essence” to them, which makes the weapons feel like they have
normal weight to their owners, while still being superheavy to everyone else -
particularly their targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that characters wielding these weapons don’t have to be generically
super-strong, and that the ability to handle one weapon doesn’t give them the
ability to wield others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create such a weapon, use the same process outlined above for “superheavy”
weapons. Attunement is represented by a new advantage, which the weapon’s owner
must purchase in order to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attunement-variable-cost&quot;&gt;Attunement (Variable Cost)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re attuned to a specific magical weapon which is super-heavy, oversized, or
both. You can wield it just as if it was a normal-sized weapon, though its
targets will still feel the full weight of your blows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the cost of this advantage, subtract your actual ST from the
weapon’s minimum ST and multiply it by 1.6, rounding up. Add 1 to the total if
the weapon is also oversized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attunement in no way “protects” your weapon! If it’s permanently lost or
destroyed, you lose all the points invested in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Details&lt;/em&gt;: This is just enough levels of Lifting and Striking ST with the
limitation “Only for this weapon” (-80%) to cover the difference between the
character’s ST score and the minimum ST for the weapon. The extra point for
oversized weapons is a specialized version of the Giant Weapons perk that
removes all penalties due to size difference, but only works for that single
weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: If the Iron Staff from the previous section was a magic artifact in
the style described here, a reedy ST 8 hero could attune to it by paying 28
character points. 25 - 8 is 17, which multiplied by 1,6 gives us 27,5, which is
then rounded up. This allows the hero to fight with the Staff as if he had
ST 25, and to ignore its great weight when carrying it, but he’ll still be ST 8
for all other purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whomsoever-wields-this-hammer-should-he-be-worthy&quot;&gt;“Whomsoever wields this hammer, should he be worthy…”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and final special weapon covered in this article are those powerful
magical artifacts that only allow those they deem worthy to even lift
them. Thor’s hammer from the Marvel comics and movies is a famous example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lifting and using these weapons is not a matter of muscle mass, but of moral
strength. When you touch them, they judge you! If you pass that judgment, then
you can lift and wield the weapon as if it was a normal specimen of its kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t actually need to make these weapons superheavy or oversized. Instead,
they look for certain traits in a prospective wielder. Those who have these
traits are worthy. Those who don’t can’t even lift the weapon, even if they’re
the strongest being in the universe muscle-wise. I generally consider this to be
a story effect and wouldn’t try to put a price tag on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weapon like movie-Mjolnir might look for one or more virtues along the lines
of Honesty, Selfless, Charitable and so on. An evil weapon would instead look
for Bloodlust or Sadism. They would of course also avoid traits opposite to
those they like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the weapon in question is also superheavy or oversized, then it could grant
worthy wielders the ST to use it, similar to how Attunement works, at no cost to
the wielder. If you’re writing up the weapon as a character, this would be a
benefficial Affliction granting the Attunement advantage described in the
previous section of this article. Simplify its cost by having it grant a number
of levels of ST equal to the minimum needed to wield the weapon regardless of
the wielder’s current ST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: The Iron Staff belonged to the Monkey King! Though it will shun
Bloodthirsty, Callous, Greedy or Sadistic individuals, it will deem worthy
anyone who shows its former master’s heroic spirit, martial prowess, or love of
mischief. Anyone with at least two of Selfless, a Code of Honor or Higher
Purpose to fight evil, Trained by a Master, Curious, or Trickster could be
deemed worthy and be considered to have ST 25 when wielding the staff.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/05/03/superheavy-weapons.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/05/03/superheavy-weapons.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Only Good Metaplot</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not much of an “OSR” person. I started playing in the 90’s, and while I
played some D&amp;amp;D here and there it was never my main system, and I moved away
from it as soon as I found others I liked more. While I do feel some nostalgia
when looking at some iterations of its rules, reading them again mostly reminds
me why I stopped playing them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one specific thing that the very earliest editions of that game did that
I feel should be ported to the present unmodified: the way they handled metaplot
and “canonical” NPCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before D&amp;amp;D was even published you basically had two campaigns being run using
draft versions of its rules. There was Dave Arneson’s Blackmoor, and Gary
Gygax’s Greyhawk. They were separate settings, but as far as I know they were
run in a similar way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each had one main GM, and started with an “original” party of players. This
original party goes on adventures, slays monsters, finds treasure. The survivors
level up and become more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then new PCs start coming in. Maybe the GM convinces another group of
friends to play on a different day of the week, or the older players roll up new
starting characters for a bit of variety, or maybe they begin playing their
henchmen when they go out on missions of their own. It’s likely a combination of
all of the above, happening over an extended period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now there are multiple PC parties having adventures in the same setting! What
each party does changes the setting in ways that can be felt by the others. If a
party delves a dungeon on Monday, loses a fighter to a gelatinous cube and
retreats, another one might go in there on Thursday and loot the dead fighter’s
cool magic sword. If the high-level originals shake the pillars of Heaven on
Saturday, the Monday and Thursday parties might hear about it and feel its
consequences in their games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s metaplot in its original, “platonically ideal” form. It’s &lt;em&gt;what
happens at the table&lt;/em&gt;, propagating to the other PC parties that are part of the
same gaming group. This is practical because the setting is owned by a single GM
or a small circle of them, who run the games for all groups involved and keep
track of it all. As for “canon NPCs”, &lt;em&gt;there are none&lt;/em&gt;. It’s PCs all the way
down, though I suppose some of them might transition fully to NPC status when
they retire, becoming less active in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, an ideal setting is one that enables groups to create their very own
shared world in that mold.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/03/02/the-only-good-metaplot.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/03/02/the-only-good-metaplot.html</guid>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dungeon Fantasy Character: Ser Alexa of the Flame, Human Mystic Knight</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/tumblr_459fae466a7d9b09883fcff85a7183d5_f1a67680_1280.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/2xLEPA&quot;&gt;Illustration
  by Nishio Nanora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years ago, Alexa’s father (a minor baron) sent her to the capital to serve as
squire to a somewhat eccentric knight. She returns to her home a knight in her
own right, skilled with sword and spell, to find her ancestral lands at the edge
of ruin. Against the wishes of her ailing father, Alexa sets forth to bring
honor, glory, and wealth back to her family name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexa is made using the spell-based &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/10/20/characters-mystic-knight.html&quot;&gt;Mystic Knight template from this blog&lt;/a&gt;,
rather than the Imbuement-based official one. Her Weirdness Magnet is a perfect
explanation for why the Odds and Sods party got together in the first place,
making her their unnoficial leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alexa-245-point-human-mystic-knight&quot;&gt;Alexa, 245-point Human Mystic Knight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ST&lt;/strong&gt; 14 {40}; &lt;strong&gt;DX&lt;/strong&gt; 13 {60}; &lt;strong&gt;IQ&lt;/strong&gt; 12 {40}; &lt;strong&gt;HT&lt;/strong&gt; 13 {30}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damage 1d/2d; BL 19.6kg; HP 14; Will 12; Per 12; FP 13; Basic Speed 6.25; Basic
Move 6 {0}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Born War Leader 1 {5}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magery 4 {45}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weapon Channeling {1}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code of Honor (Chivalry) {-15}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Obsession (Restore My Family’s Holdings) {-5}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sense of Duty (Adventuring Companions) {-5}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weirdness Magnet {-15}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impulsiveness (12) {-10}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quirks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dislikes entering water {-1}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always carries the family sword {-1}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writes letters to her departed mother {-1}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stands at attention unless she makes a conscious effort not to {-1}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hotter to the touch than usual due to fire magic affinity {-1}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Armory (Body Armor) (A) IQ+1 {4} - 13&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brawling (E) DX+1 {2} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broadsword (A) DX+4 {16} - 17&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connoisseur (Weapons) (A) IQ+1 {4} - 13&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diplomacy (H) IQ-2 {1} - 10&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fast-Draw (Sword) (E) DX {1} - 13&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forced Entry (E) DX {1} - 13&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heraldry (A) IQ-1 {1} - 11&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hidden Lore (Magic Items) (A) IQ {2} - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Innate Attack (Projectile) (E) DX+2 {4} - 15&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leadership (A) IQ {1}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Occultism (A) IQ {2} - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Riding (Horse) (A) DX-1 {1} - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Savoir-Faire (High Society) (E) IQ {1} - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shield (E) DX+3 {8} - 16&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stealth (A) DX-1 {1} - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategy (H) IQ {2}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tactics (H) IQ {2}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thaumathology (VH) IQ+1 {1}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 13&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrestling (A) DX+1 {4} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spells&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All have +4 from Magery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication and Empathy&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sense Foes (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sense Evil (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fire&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ignite Fire (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Create Fire (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shape Fire (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Heat (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Flaming Weapon (H) IQ+3 {2} - 15&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fireball (H) IQ+3 {2} - 15&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Extinguish Fire (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fireproof (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Resist Fire (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Healing&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lend Energy (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recover Energy (H) IQ+3 {2} - 15&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protection and Warning&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shield (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Missile Shield (H) IQ+2 {2} - 15&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mystic Mist (H) IQ+2 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loadout&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fine Medium Shield: DB 2. $600, 5.63kg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light Mail Suit: DR 3/1. 10 FP as a power item. $1500, 18kg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broadsword: Damage sw+1 cut or thr+2 imp. Enchanted with the Staff
spell. $630, 1.5kg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quick-Release Backpack: Holds 20kg of gear. Dropping it is a free
action. $300, 1.5kg.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blanket: $20, 2kg.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Canteen: $10, 1.5kg.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Personal Basics: $5, 0.5kg.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rope, 1cm, 10m: Supports 150kg; $5, 0.75kg.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;$430 in coin.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Combat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assumes Light encumbrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defenses&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dodge 8 (10)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Parry 11 (13)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Block 11 (13)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;DR 3/1.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attacks&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Broadsword (17): 2d+1 cut or 1d+2 imp, Reach 1.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shield Bash (16): 1d cr, Reach 1.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brawling Punch (14): 1d cr, due to mail gauntlets. Reach C.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brawling Kick (12): 1d+1 cr. Reach C, 1.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wrestling Grapple (14): 1d+1 control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fireball (15): 1d to 3d burn, Acc 1, Range 25/50. Cost 0 to 2.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Alexa doesn’t usually charge it for more than 1 turn.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;+1 from Born War Leader &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;+4 from Magery &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/01/27/alexa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/01/27/alexa.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>character</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Old-School Movement in Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been looking at some old D&amp;amp;D modules lately and wondering how to convert
them to Dungeon Fantasy. One of the things that gave me some trouble was
movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon movement in AD&amp;amp;D is by default extremely methodical and done with an
almost paranoid level of caution&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This is why even an entirely unencumbered
party moves only 120ft/40m over ten minutes. They’re moving reeal slow; they’re
trying to maintain stealth; they’re looking for traps and secret passages;
someone is mapping. You move five times faster if you don’t have to map, and ten
times faster if you throw caution to the wind and tromp through the dungeon at
combat speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important because AD&amp;amp;D wants you to track turns precisely and roll for
wandering monsters every so often. As a delver, you ideally want to get in, get
the treasure, and get out as soon as possible. Every extra turn you spend in
there has a chance of bringing in hostile enemies who don’t have any loot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy (either version) expects the party to move cautiously but
doesn’t have specific or timing rules for it&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. So, when you convert AD&amp;amp;D
modules to Dungeon Fantasy, how do you handle movement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easy solution is to just glom the AD&amp;amp;D turn and movement rules into Dungeon
Fantasy! The resulting amalgamented abomination is actually rather
playable. Check it out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dungeon-fantasy-movement&quot;&gt;Dungeon Fantasy Movement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time spent inside a dungeon is measured in ten-minute &lt;em&gt;turns&lt;/em&gt;, like in ye olde
days. When exploring a dungeon, delvers are by default assumed to be moving very
cautiously and methodically, keeping their marching order. When moving this way,
they cover a distance per turn equal to ten times the Move of the slowest party
member, measured in yards or meters. For example, a party containing a heavily
armored knight with Move 3 would explore 30 yards/meters in a turn&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving this way is slow, and costs the party 1 FP per 5 turns of movement, but
has several benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The party is assumed to be on the lookout for danger. They roll to detect
traps, enemies and other hazards automatically without having to state they
are doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Similarly, they can make Stealth rolls to avoid detection by monsters. If
they’re walking together, this is a group Stealth roll as detailed in Exploits
p. 6. All the usual factors for stealth are still at play here, such as light
sources and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is the pace that allows the PCs to map the dungeon as per Exploits p. 18.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actively investigating a room for treasure and secret doors also takes a turn
and requires the normal rolls for these procedures. Turns spent searching do
count for tracking FP cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FP cost makes ye olde routine of delving for 5 turns and resting for one an
efficient way to proceed, though the delvers can elect to push forward and take
the FP loss if they’re pressed for time. The party can elect to move at five
times this pace and still retain the first two benefits above, which makes
traversing already-mapped portions of the dungeon a lot faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These rules are perfect for playing in converted old-school modules. You can use
the modules’ own rules for random encounters with them, though obviously you’ll
still want to convert the monsters. It’s probably okay to ignore these rules in
modules made specifically for the DFRPG, since they tend to assume a faster
pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Which is the right amount of caution for Gygaxian dungeons. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Even though the headers in its dungeon exploration section are remarkably
similar to those of AD&amp;amp;D. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Divide that by 3 to get convert it to ten-foot squares. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/01/24/old-school-movement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/01/24/old-school-movement.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
