<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 18:51:33 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 18:51:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Arcanian</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-ape.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember seeing arcanians anywhere else before, though they do have that
“late-3e feeling” to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wizardry is a craft that demands great patience and care. While a warlock
“cheats” by making shady deals with dubious entities, a wizard earns every bit
of power they have. But some wizards have less than great patience and care, and
try to reach a bit too far beyond their current ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the vast majority of cases that just results in an embarrassing fizzle, but
sometimes the magic goes out of control and causes a major accident. Most of
&lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; end up turning the caster into a messy stain on the floor, but some are
worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these rare cases, the wizard absorbs most of the runaway magic, which kills
them and animates the corpse. The resulting entity is known as an Arcanian. Its
sapient and highly intelligent, but utterly consumed by whatever strong emotion
the wizard felt as they died, further warped by the nature of the magic that
killed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arcanians are Medium Natural Humanoids (Undead). Each is themed around an
element and an emotion, though ironically they have no particular resistance
against their own theme element. They have a ground speed of 6 and no special
senses. They also carry wizardly implements that give them abilities similar to
that of a PC wizard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Arcane Surge&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that triggers
when they hit an enemy with an implement power (anything but their basic melee
attack). It makes that power deal maximum damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;green-arcanian&quot;&gt;Green Arcanian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green Arcanians are half-melted monstrosities. Acid seeps from their pores, and
their footsteps leave seared footprints. Their driven by envy and a hatred of
beauty, which they use acid magic to destroy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green Arcanians are Level 8 Artillery with 67 HP. All of their attacks deal acid
damage. Their basic melee attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Acid Touch&lt;/strong&gt;, and their basic ranged
attack an &lt;strong&gt;Acid Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; that also deals a bit of splash damage to enemies
adjacent to the target. Less often they can cast a &lt;strong&gt;Stream of Acid&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
5+) that does heavy damage and inflicts a -2 AC penalty and 5 ongoing acid
damage (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their implement power is &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Denial&lt;/strong&gt;, an interrupt which triggers when an
enemy succeeds on a save and makes them fail the save instead. Thankfully this
is an encounter power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blue-arcanian&quot;&gt;Blue Arcanian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shivering corpse despises warmth, and believes that people and things can
remain forever perfect if they’re frozen. As you might imagine, it goes around
attempting to preserve everything it likes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue Arcanians are Level 10 Controllers with 105 HP. They move slightly slower
than normal at Speed 5, and all of their powers deal cold damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Frost Staff&lt;/strong&gt; that also pushes 2 squares and
immobilizes for a turn. They fight at range with at-will &lt;strong&gt;Bolts of Frost&lt;/strong&gt; that
turn the area surrounding the target into difficult terrain for a turn, and once
per encounter they can summon a &lt;strong&gt;Swirling Blizzard&lt;/strong&gt; to deal damage over an
area (half on a miss).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their implement power is &lt;strong&gt;Staff of Shielding&lt;/strong&gt;, which once per encounter gives
them +4 to all defenses against an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;red-arcanian&quot;&gt;Red Arcanian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These eternally burning undead are gripped in the throes of fiery passion or
red-hot wrath. They want to burn the world and take great pleasure in doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red Arcanians are considerably more powerful than the rest: Level 19 Artillery
with 131 HP. All of their attacks deal fire damage, and they carry wands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their melee basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Touch&lt;/strong&gt;, and their ranged spells will be
familiar to PC wizards: &lt;strong&gt;Scorching Burst&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will area attack, and
&lt;strong&gt;Burning Hands&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that hits a close blast 5 that deals
heavy damage and pushes 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their implement encounter power is &lt;strong&gt;Wand of Accuracy&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives them a +4
bonus to their next attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because liches are the most iconic undead wizards, it doesn’t mean they’re
the only ones. Arcanians seem like a good monster to use when you want to make
an adventure themed around wizards who dug too deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could have a whole ruined academy filled with a variety of them and with
other supporting undead or summoned extra-planar monsters. It’s easy enough to
change the ruling element of the stat blocks presented here, or to adjust their
level so you can have all three in the same dungeon. Maybe there’s a tome or
artifact in its vaults that the party must recover, or maybe it’s just a place
they need to pass through on their perilous journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprinkle in journal entries that hint at the disaster that destroyed the place,
and add a big lich with multiple elemental attacks as the “end boss”. And there
you have it, an instant Dark Souls level for your 4e table.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/09/arcanian.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/09/arcanian.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Apocalypse Spell</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I remember correctly, some monster books from 3e introduced the notion of
living spells, creatures made from pure magic and patterned after one of the
commonly available spells in the game. I guess Apocalypse Spells take some
inspiration from those, but the end result is very different. The classificaion
of Apocalypse Spell is only applied to those living spells that arise from the
most metal of magics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every once in a great while, someone manages to cast a truly epic spell. We’re
talking the sort of thing that can slay a god, bind a primordial, instantly
destroy an empire, create an astral dominion from nothing, and so on. These
spells are so powerful the residual energy left in their wake can attain
sentience and become a construct of pure magic whose powers and personality are
modeled after the effects of their progenitor spell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their godlike power, apocalypse spells are simple creatures at
heart. The kind of magic that gives birth to them is usually destructive and
indiscriminate, and so are they at their cration. The passage of years allows
them to develop distinct personalities and goals. Thus they can end up allying
with other creatures who share those goals, or who manage to persuade them to
help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all else fails, there are certain rituals that allow a powerful enough caster
to assume full control of an apocalypse spell. They’re most commonly cast by the
Forsaken, a society of epic villains who get an entry further into this
book. Angels, devils and demons also frequently try to influence these living
spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book doesn’t say it, but I would guess the population of each type of
apocalypse spell is fixed. The spells that generated them were unique, and were
only cast once. Killing one of them permanently reduces that population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-apocalypse-spell-01.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Apocalypse Spells are Animates with the Construct keyword, but that’s where
their similarity ends. Each stat block described here represents the progeny of
a different epic spell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do have a common signature trait, however: &lt;strong&gt;Unfettered Apocalypse&lt;/strong&gt; is a
reaction that triggers when they are first bloodied or when they take a critical
hit, once per encounter. It creates a perfect duplicate of the spell that lasts
for a turn. During this turn, it has the same HP and abilities as the original,
and can act right after the original’s action. The duplicate can’t create
another duplicate itself, however, so no infinitely spawning epic monsters for
you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prison-of-mual-tar&quot;&gt;Prison of Mual-Tar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primordial Mual-Tar was defeated by the gods in the Dawn War, but couldn’t
be killed. So it was bound in chains forged by Moradin himself and enchanted
with a unique binding ritual. As Mual-Tar strained against these chains, shards
of them broke off and fell into the Astral Sea, where they gained life. Prisons
of Mual-Tar are born with opposing impulses to imprison and destroy, and their
individual goals are related to one of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These apocalypse spells are Large Immortal Animates with the Construct
keyword, and Level 26 Soldiers with 242 HP. They have a ground speed of 6 and
Resist Force 15. Very few creatures have resistance to force damage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prison is surrounded by an aura (5) of &lt;strong&gt;Cloying Chains&lt;/strong&gt;, who marks all
enemies caught inside. As an &lt;strong&gt;Agent of Divine Will&lt;/strong&gt;, it ignores
insubstantiality, concealment and partial cover (but not full cover or
concealment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It attacks with a Reach 4 &lt;strong&gt;Fettering Lash&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals physical damage. If
the target tries to make an attack that doesn’t target the Prison in its next
action, the Prison pulls it up to 10 squares to a square adjacent to itself. It
can make this attack twice per action against different targets, thanks to
&lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. When the Prison is subject to forced movement, it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Reactive Coils&lt;/strong&gt; to pull the triggering enemy adjacent to itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prison’s divine origin makes it a bit reluctant to attack divine characters,
and it might be convinced to lend its aid against elementals and demons. Their
Double Attack ability makes them heavy hitters, and all the long-range pulling
they can do makes them excellent at isolating PCs from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;herald-of-colorless-fire&quot;&gt;Herald of Colorless Fire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ancient history of the Greyhawk setting, there were two great empires who
were at war with each other, and who ended up using apocalyptic spells to erase
each other from the world. The Rain of Colorless Fire was the more spectacular
of the two, so it’s the one that gets mentioned most often in other
publications. It turned the entire territory of the empire of Suel into a desert
of ash and dust that was still a big feature of Oerth’s geography in its
narrative present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heralds of Colorless Fire arose from the ashes of that desert and began
wandering the planes. They are made from that same fire, and their innate
motivation is simple: burn everything. They are, however, smart enough to toy
with their victims and to lure powerful targets into favorable terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heralds are Medium Natural Animates (construct, fire) and Level 27 Skirmishers
with 244 HP. They have a Speed of 8 (fly 6), and 15 fire resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their attacks deal damage of the “fire and force” combined type, meaning
you need resistance to both types to stop it. Fire or Force Resistance alone
do nothing. This is a pretty good way of modeling supernatural fire that burns
anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Caress of Flame&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Storm of
Colorless Fire&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that allows them attack a Close Burst 1, shift
half their speed, and repeat the attack. Each of these bursts does more damage
than the basic melee attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Herald can use &lt;strong&gt;Flickering Flame&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 4 squares as a minor action,
but this ability gets shut down for a turn if it takes cold damage. I do notice
it doesn’t have the usual 1/round limitation of minor-action movement abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat, these are zippy fraggers, well-equipped for constant hit and run
tactics. They should never stay still, and should never use a move action while
Flickering Flame is active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shard-of-uralinda&quot;&gt;Shard of Uralinda&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, there was a Winter Fey named Rodielle who was a member of the
Winter Court. Rodielle tried to woo a member of the Summer Court and was
spurned. He became so angry at this that, instead of resorting to the usual fey
courtly intrigue, he did something truly terrible instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rodielle devised a spell of ice and death, and cast it upon the eladrin city of
Uralinda, the place which his former beloved liked the most in all the
worlds. Ice shards rained upon the city and ripped it apart, killing
thousands. That part was on purpose. Then the shards were animated by the souls
of the slain and began wandering all the worlds. That part was an
accident. Whoops!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tormented souls inside the shards seek the release of final death, but they
only have limited control over their icy cages. So they throw themselves at
anyone who seems like they can put up a fight, hoping to be slain and
released. Sometimes they also get controlled by spellcasters to do their
bidding, which I imagine must be even less pleasant than their baseline state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shards of Uralinda are Medium Fey Animates (construct, cold), and Level 28
Minion Soldiers. Their basic attacks deal damage of the “cold and psychic”
combined type, and despite being minions they also have the Unfettered
Apocalypse ability. In practice, this means they last for an additional turn
after you kill them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;godslayer-inferno&quot;&gt;Godslayer Inferno&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-apocalypse-spell-02.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the product of one of the many spells wielded by the primordials
themselves during the Dawn War. It created a torrent of white and violet flames
that prevented deities from discorporating and suppressed their immortal
natures. As an unintended side effect, the flames also ended up absorbing some
of the divine essence they burned away and became imbued with the spark of
life. They remain steadfast in their original purpose of murdering the gods and
their servants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the description, it seems that this was one of the few “apocalyptic” spells
that was used repeatedly as a weapon of war, so I’d guess there’s a higher
population of Godslayer Infernos than of the other monsters in this entry. Yay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Godslayer Infernos are Medium Elemental Animates (construct, fire), and Level 28
Artillery with 194 HP. They have Resist Fire 15 and a ground speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both their &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Claws&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;Fire Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; they shoot inflict a large
chunk of ongoing fire damage (20 aned 25, respectively) without dealing any
immediate damage. They can also use a special attack named &lt;strong&gt;Godsbane Inferno&lt;/strong&gt;
(area burst 2, range 10) which does deal immediate damage as well as inflicting
more ongoing fire damage. This ongoing damage is more presistent - it’s reduced
from 15 to 10 with the first save, and only disappears after the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inferno’s main source of immediate damage is &lt;strong&gt;Cloying Flames&lt;/strong&gt;, which
causes all targets taking ongoing fire damage within 10 squares to immediately
take an amount of fire damage equal to that of ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being artillery, the inferno also has good cause to stick close to the
PCs. Its Elemental Inferno aura (2) strips all enemies inside of any fire
resistance they might have and prevents them from rolling saves against ongoing
fire damage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think ongoing fire damage stacks, so it’s unlikely the inferno itself
can inflict more than the 25 its fire bolts cause. But Cloying Flames makes them
pair &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; well with other epic fire monsters. If nothing else fits, you
could add multiple infernos in an encounter, but their danger level grows very
fast in proportion to their numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;light-of-amoth&quot;&gt;Light of Amoth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already heard of the dead god Amoth during Demogorgon’s entry. He was
responsible for splitting Demogorgon’s original head in two, just before being
himself slain by the demon. Here we learn that there’s more to this story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No less than three demon princes stormed Amoth’s domain to kill him: Orcus,
Demogorgon, and Rimmon. They all fought Amoth at the same time, and while
Demogorgon did strike the final blow in the fight, it didn’t kill Amoth
immediately either. The god had time to unleash a death curse, one so powerful
it consumed his remaining life force in order to take the three demon lords
along with him in a universe-shaking explosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three tried to get clear of the blast, but didn’t manage in time. Orcus and
Demogorgon were a little quicker on the uptake than Rimmon, so they betrayed
Rimmon first and used him as a shield to protect themselves from Amoth’s
curse. Rimmon was disintegrated, which is why we never heard of him before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might imagine, that curse generated living spells of its own. These
crystalline giants also incorporate fragments of essence from both Amoth and
Rimmon, so they’re compelled to hunt down demonic and divine creatures in equal
measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lights of Ammoth are Large Immortal Animates (construct), and Level 30 Brutes
with 341 HP. They’re almost gods themselves! They have a ground speed of 6, but
no special resistances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with their Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Fists of Wrath&lt;/strong&gt;, which do a lot of
damage. &lt;strong&gt;Fury of the Dead&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) allows them to attack every creature
in range with their fists. They can also use an ability called &lt;strong&gt;Legacy of
Kalandurren&lt;/strong&gt; that targets everyone in a Close Burst 2 for cold damage equal to
that of a punch, and immobilizes them. Kalandurren was Amoth’s domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a Light of Amoth takes damage, it releases a &lt;strong&gt;Wave of Retribution&lt;/strong&gt; that
does an automatic 5 damage to everyone within 2 squares of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to let them get surrounded by the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these monsters are really cool! I don’t know if any more apocalypse
spells were ever published, but I really like the basic idea behind them. I
wonder if there is one for Karsus’ Avatar (FR) or the Mourning (Eberron). These
magical disasters feel like they’re about the right scale for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, I find them fairly interesting. They’re not mind-blowing but they
display the consistently higher level of quality that would become standard from
this point on.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/04/apocalypse-spell.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/04/apocalypse-spell.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Apes</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-ape.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great apes are real world animals, and they’ve also been in D&amp;amp;D pretty much
since the beginning. This MM3 entry is the first I’ve seen them in 4e, though by
this point in the edition we might have gotten stats for them in some other
non-Monster Manual publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM3 doesn’t really try to model real-world great apes. Their depiction seems
more inspired by pulp stories and the Jungle Book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D great apes are natural animals, and have inhabited the world’s jungles since
the dawn of time. Some revere them as manifestations of the primal spirits,
others enslave them as laborers and gladiators. Goblins kidnap young apes and
raise them as guardians. Other humanoids might use them as slave labor, and some
spellcasters enslave them with magic to use as bodyguards or gladiators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, great apes are very territorial and fiercely defend their homes
from intruders using surprisingly sophisticated teamwork. Groups of apes are
usually led by a “silverback”, a larger and older male who fights even more
fiercely than the others to protect his family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs might meet a group of apes when traveling through jungle terrain,
particularly mountainous jungle. Communication is likely to be difficult unless
they have a druid or another primal character with them. If they do, it might be
possible to convince the apes to stand down. If they don’t it’s a fight, though
I guess the apes in this case will be trying to drive the PCs off rather than
kill them. Apes being used as attack beasts by sapient villains will usually
fight to kill, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also have the slightly less natural Ape Temple Guardians, who a long time
ago used to be sapient humanoids but were twisted into their current form by
some ancient curse. Now they make their homes in certain ruined temples,
compelled to guard their treasures. Unlike natural apes, temple guardians are
carnivorous. They fight to kill and will usually eat dead intruders, leaving
their bones lying around as warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the apes depicted here are Medium Natural Beasts. They have low-light
vision, and a climb speed (whose value varies per stat block). Their signature
trait is &lt;strong&gt;Swift Climber&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes them immune to opportunity attacks when
climbing. Needless to say, be sure to include plenty of climbing opportunities
in combat encounters against apes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great-ape&quot;&gt;Great Ape&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “basic model” is a Level 4 Skirmisher with 55 HP. It has a ground speed of
7 and a climb speed of 6. They don’t have Spider Climb, but I’d be amenable to
letting them use their climb speed to brachiate through the forest canopy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great apes fight with &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; and they can also attack &lt;strong&gt;On The Run&lt;/strong&gt;, which
allows them to shift or climb half their speed and make a slam attack at any
point during the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Felling Blow&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), which allows them to make
two slam attacks against the same target. If both hit, the target also falls
prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great apes should rarely stand still when fighting - it’s On The Run all the way
with them. The exception is when they stop a bit to use Felling Blow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silverback-ape&quot;&gt;Silverback Ape&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silverbacks don’t run around. Their goal is to be a very visible and very
intimidating threat, drawing all the attention and allowing their non-combatant
family members to escape, and give their fellow combatants room to
maneuver. They’re larger than regular ape but still Medium, and are Level 5
Brutes with the Leader keyword. Their speed is 6 on the ground or 4 while
climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; do heavy damage and make the target grant combat advantage for a
turn. They can sometimes &lt;strong&gt;Fling&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) a creature away, dealing even
more damage than the slam, pushing them 3 squares, and knocking them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, once per encounter silverbacks can use &lt;strong&gt;Chest Beat&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor
action, which gives all beast allies within 5 squares a +2 bonus to attacks for
a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ape-temple-guardian&quot;&gt;Ape Temple Guardian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temple Guardians are Level 6 Soldiers with 75 HP, a ground speed of 7, and a
Climb Speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Clubs&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals average damage and knocks the target
prone on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Swaying Strike&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make a club attack and shift 3
squares. And then can also &lt;strong&gt;Feast&lt;/strong&gt; on a prone target, dealing light damage but
gaining 10 temporary HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do these apes use weapons, they also coordinate really well. They’ll
try to surround the PCs and avoid becoming isolated from each other. If a PC
gets too close to whatever they are protecting, they’ll focus fire on that PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can combine them with regular great ape stat blocks for a bit more
variety. Story-wise they’d all be temple guardians. They might also be under
control of a naga or another eternal guardian who was responsible for cursing
them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normal great apes have too much of a “pulp gorilla” vibe for me to enjoy them as
monsters. I kinda like the lore of temple guardians, though.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/04/ape.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/04/ape.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I write this, I’ve just finished writing all of the articles of my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;Let’s
Read series on the Monster Manual 2&lt;/a&gt;. So now I’m going to start on the
Monster Manual 3!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 3 is obviously the third big monster book for Dungeons &amp;amp;
Dragons 4th Edition, and it was published in June 2010, about a year after the
MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the stuff I’ve written on the intro to the MM2 linked above also
applies to the MM3. Monster roles remain the same, as does the gradation that
goes from Minion to Regular to Elite to Solo. The encounter design system is the
same as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things have changed dramatically, though! While you still have the lore
tables with skill DCs, the surrounding flavor text has gotten a lot bigger,
replacing the minimalist sentences of past books with larger paragraphs written
in a more dramatic tone. The extra space taken up by this text means we no
longer have sample encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks themselves also changed a lot, with monster abilities separated
and listed according to the type of action they use (passive traits, standard,
move, minor, triggered, always in that order).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the math for basic monster numbers has finally reached its
final, fully fixed form. Attacks, defenses, HP and average damage all follow the
basic formula in the legendary &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogofholding.com/?p=512&quot;&gt;Monster Manual 3 in a Business Card&lt;/a&gt;
post. This updated math was also published as an errata update to the Dungeon
Master’s Guide, but the Business Card has it in even more condensed
form. Chronologically, this is the first book where you wouldn’t need to apply
any blanket fixes to monster damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were following my Let’s Read posts while reading the actual books, you’ll
be familiar with all of these changes from the Monster Vault, which I read in
parallel with the first MM &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The MV would be published in November
2010, updating the most “iconic” monsters from the first two books to the new
format and collecting some from this one as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Vault would in turn be followed by “Monster Vault: Threats to the
Nentir Vale”, the final monster book I intend to cover in my readings. But
that’s still a ways away. For now, we look to the MM3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book has monsters of all levels, but focuses a bit more on the higher
end. The index in my PDF copy is a little wonky because it lists each individual
stat block in alphabetic order, but I’ll still read them in the order in which
the larger entries appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes in math also mean that monsters are much less likely to have healing
powers. Leader monsters from the MM3 are much more likely to provide combat
buffs than to heal their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/23/mm3-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/23/mm3-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Traits Appendix</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the last in a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the first Monster Manual before it, the Monster Manual 2 ends with a short
appendix containing rules for using some of the humanoids from the book as
playable characters. This one is a lot smaller than the MM’s appendix, and I
don’t think any of the races in it got much in the way of subsequent support or
more complete versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three writeups and their notable traits are listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bullywugs&lt;/strong&gt; have Swamp Walk and get Primordial as a bonus language. Their
racial power is the Rancid Air aura from their monster writeups. +2 to CON and
DEX.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duergar&lt;/strong&gt; are predictably similar to dwarves, but they get Deep Speech as a
bonus language and the Infernal Quills racial power. +2 to CON and WIS.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kenku&lt;/strong&gt; get the Flock Effect and Mimicry abilities from their monster
writeups, but don’t have any bonus languages. Flock Effect is a pretty awesome
ability for a rogue. +2 to DEX and CHA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with this we can finally close the MM2, and move on to the next book in my
planned series. See you on the Monster Manual 3 Let’s Read!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/13/traits-appendix.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/13/traits-appendix.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Xorn</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-xorn.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see xorns in my copy of the AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition monster manual, so they date from
at least that far back. This is their 4e debut, and they’re the last monster in
the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xorns are earth elementals native to the Elemental Chaos, but they long ago
spread to the deep subterranean tunnels and caverns of the world. Their
three-lobed radial symmetry makes them seem quite bizarre to natives of the
world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xorns can swim through rock and earth as if it was water, and must feed on
certain rare metals and gems. They’re sapient, and will often bargain with other
people, aiding in their mining or smelting efforts in exchange for their
“food”. It seems they’re not very concerned with much beyond their own survival,
so they’ll happily ally with creatures of all dispositions, from dwarves and
galeb dhur to duergar and fire giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xorns found in the wild are likely to be drawn to the gems and magic items
carried by PCs. The PCs might be able to negotiate with them and avoid a
fight… but some less scrupulous xorns tend to use these negotiations to help
set ambushes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two stat blocks here, but they’re very similar, so I’ll discuss the first
one and then note how the second one differs from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xorn&quot;&gt;Xorn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Medium Elemental Magical Beast (Earth), and a Level 9
Skirmisher with 102 HP. Its senses include darkvision and all-around vision,
which prevents it from being flanked. It has a relatively low ground speed of 5,
and a burrow speed of 5 that’s enhanced by the &lt;strong&gt;Earth Glide&lt;/strong&gt; ability. It
allows the xorn to burrow through solid rock as if it was loose earth, using its
full burrow speed at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The xorn’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Triple Strike&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make
three of those against different targets. If there’s only one foe in range, it
will use its &lt;strong&gt;Earthy Maw&lt;/strong&gt; instead since it does about double the damage of a
claw strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the xorn can &lt;strong&gt;Submerge&lt;/strong&gt;, partially burying itself and
gaining a +2 bonus to AC until it moves. When it’s missed by a melee attack, it
can &lt;strong&gt;retreat&lt;/strong&gt;, burrowing its speed as a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight, a xorn will jump from inside a wall or floor, submerge for the AC
bonus, and claw or bite the party’s squishies. If a missed attack doesn’t make
the creature retreat automatically, it will do so on its next turn so it can
repeat this pattern. Earth Glide makes it extremely mobile despite its poor
speed, particularly in an underground environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diadmondhide-xorn&quot;&gt;Diadmondhide Xorn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an older or simply well-fed specimen, who lives in a place of the
Elemental Chaos where its preferred food is more plentiful. Its hide glitters
with the minerals it has ingested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamondhide xorns are Large in size, and are Level 16 Skirmishers with 160
HP. They have all the same attacks and abilties as the basic xorn, with bigger
numbers. They also have a new attack named &lt;strong&gt;Undermine&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) in which
the xorn burrows its speed and attacks a creature it passes under. This targets
Reflex, does heavy damage, and restrains the target (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 9, and consists of a pair of xorns in cahoots with
a troop of duergar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to see xorns here. Their weird looks make them an iconic D&amp;amp;D monster
in my mind. A nice way to close the book.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/05/xorn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/05/xorn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Exalted Martial Arts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s this post on Mailanka’s Musings that talks about two different ways of
modeling martial arts in RPGs. The first is something he calls “Move-Based”, and
the second “Skill-Based”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based martial arts is how most RPGs in the 90’s did it. You bought a style,
and that gave you access to a series of “moves” that were essentially special
powers with individual rules for what they did. Some systems made you buy each
individual move as well, usually as a way to model your progression in the
style - advanced practitioners know more moves. Your move set is as or more
important than your raw skill level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skill-based martial arts are what GURPS does. Everyone uses the same skills to
fight, and knowing one style or another is mostly a matter of flavor with a few
minor mechanical bonuses thrown in. What really matters are your skill levels:
people with different style familiarities but similar skill levels are equally
effective. The same applies to someone who “knows” a style and someone who just
has the combat skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based rules might allow you to emulate some classic kung-fu stories that
are all about how some styles are objectively superior to others, or how there’s
a secret style or ultimate technique that’s jealously guarded by a cranky old
master. Skill-based rules are closer to Bruce Lee’s philosophy, or modern views
of martial arts in general, where individual skill is more important and the
“ultimate power” is learning from multiple sources and combining everything into
something that works for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer skill-based rules, largely due to my exposure to GURPS
Martial Arts for Fourth edition. Everything it introduces can be done by someone
who isn’t using the style rules. It covers styles from the whole world without
treating any of them as inherently superior, and it acknowledges that basically
any organized system of fighting counts as a “style”. The “generic swings” other
systems describe as the standard form of fighting only happen if you’re
completely untrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this preference, it comes as no surprise that I have a few weirdly
specific hangups about how Exalted handles its martial arts. Let’s talk about
them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exalteds-martial-arts&quot;&gt;Exalted’s Martial Arts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exalted’s &lt;em&gt;whole system&lt;/em&gt; is entirely move-based. Every PC has a large set
of “Charms” that are usually linked to skills, and represent magic techniques
they can use to enhance uses of that skill. Getting to the maximum possible
skill level is trivial, and it’s your Charms that make the difference when going
against similarly supernatural opposition. This goes even for non-combat skills,
though the fighty bits tend to take up a lot of attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martial Arts are part of this system, but the game still takes pains to make
them extra-special, even as it struggles to explain what makes them different
from standard combat powers. Exalted First Edition had a separate Martial Arts
skill, whose associated Charms were structured as “Martial Arts Styles”. They
didn’t really “mix” with charms of other skills. As a result, a lot of each
style’s Charms end up duplicating the effect of basic combat Charms in different
ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second Edition merged “standard” unarmed combat and Martial Arts, and made it a
little easier to mix and match charms from a few different styles. Third Edition
doubled down on the original position and made it so each style had its own
separate skill, thus coming full circle on the ‘martial arts cost more because
they are exotic and special’ trope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-id-do-it&quot;&gt;How I’d Do It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had I been writing these rules, I’d probably take them in a different direction
entirely, and more towards the way GURPS sees things. There would be no Martial
Arts skill. Each style is associated with a single standard combat skill, and
consists of exactly three Charms representing its advanced or iconic
techniques. The basic stuff is already covered by the standard skill and
standard Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Charms I’d reuse the “lotus” metaphor, so they would be the Root, Bulb
and Blossom Charms. You learn them in this order. Each has the previous one as a
prerequisite, and probably an increasing Essence score. They’re meant to be
combined with the standard Charms for that skill, relying on them for the basic
dice-adding mechanics and such. If you know Charms of multiple styles you can
explicitly combine them as long as the combination is otherwise rules-legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who learns to fight is a martial artist, even if they never pick up
style Charms. Every martial artist ultimately develops their own personal style
by learning from as many sources as possible and keeping what works for
them. And you can certainly describe the way your kung-fu looks as being a
certain style even if you don’t have the Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example-snake-style&quot;&gt;Example: Snake Style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t originally plan on doing this, but what the heck, let’s go! Snake Style
has traditionally been the main corebook style, so let’s see how it would look
in this format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what the lore says about it: it’s a style focused on speed and
precision, aiming to take down better armed and armored opponents before they
have time to act. It uses two-fingered strikes to hit pressure points and
exposed tendons. Masters of the style can “pierce through armor”, “paralyze
opponents with pressure point strikes”, and “deliver poisonous Essence through
their fingertips”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of what to keep in our new format is pretty easy - each of the things
masters of the style can do references a specific Charm. We want those. All the
others increase basic numbers in different ways and can be replaced by standard
charms from Brawl and other trees. Want to dodge like a snake? Take Dodge
Charms. Want the “tough scales” effect? Take Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our new Snake Style is an unarmed style linked to Brawl. Our Root Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Crippling Pressure Point Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (Ex3 p. 428). Our Bulb Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Armor-Penetrating Fang Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Our Blossom Charm is &lt;strong&gt;Essence Venom
Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Their skill level and Essence prerequisites remain the same, but read
Brawl in place of Martial Arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quick and dirty sketch, and some additional work would be
required. Essence Venom Strike needs to be rewritten a bit, since half of its
effects reference Charms we’ve eliminated. We might also want to rewrite some of
the base Brawl charms, though I haven’t looked at them in much depth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>exalted</category>
        
        <category>martial-arts</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Wood Woad</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-wood-woad.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I remember seeing mention of Wood Woads in AD&amp;amp;D somewhere, but I
couldn’t find them in my books. This is their 4e debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood Woads are fey creatures distantly related to dryads. Like dryads, they
devoutly protect the natural environment of their home region. Unlike dryads,
they all look male and have absolutely zero chill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do wood woads attack would-be despoilers of nature with murderous
intent, they tend to blame each new intruder for the crimes of all the previous
ones. So even if you’re careful with the environment and try to approach them
peacefully, they’ll still try to kill you because some fool cut a tree down
years ago and managed to run away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood woads tend to ally with other sworn protectors of nature, like dryads,
centaurs and some elves or other fey. So I guess you could still deal with them
peacefully if you manage to approach those allies first and get them to vouch
for you, or have them act as intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a single Wood Woad stat block. It’s a Medium Fey Humanoid with the Plant
keyword, and a Level 8 Soldier with 92 HP. It has trained Perception, and a
ground speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood Woads wield wooden shields and clubs. Their basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt;,
which does average damage and has no special effects. They can channel magic
through it to inflict &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Judgment&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+, Reliable) on a
target. This is an attack that does more damage than the basic club,
immobilizes, and inflicts ongoing physical damage on the target. When the target
takes this ongoing damage, the closest fey or plant ally of the wood woad heals
the same amount of HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reliable keyword means this power isn’t used up if the attack misses. The
wood woad can keep trying to use it until it hits someone, and only them will it
need to make recharge rolls. This attack becomes more useful if all of the wood
woad’s allies are either plants or fey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can also curse someone with &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Mystery&lt;/strong&gt; as a
minor action. This inflicts a -2 penalty on all of the target’s attacks,
defenses, and saves. The save to end this effect has an &lt;em&gt;additional&lt;/em&gt; -5 penalty
unless the target can succeed at a DC 20 Nature check before rolling it. Guess
this spell has a loophole somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is different from the sphinx ability we saw earlier in this Let’s Read,
because no one else can make the Nature test in the target’s place. This makes
Nature’s Mystery an excellent ability to use on most defenders, since they tend
to have low-to-middling Wisdom and no training in Nature. Wardens are the big
exception to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Targets affected by this Nature’s Mystery are also prime targets for Nature’s
Judgment. Make sure to surround them with plant and fey monsters after they get
hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: Two dryads, two vine horror spellfiends, 2 wood woads. Did the vine
horror manage to convince the fey it’s part of the local natural environment?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 1 Gnome Entropist, 1 Satyr Piper, 1 Shambling Mound, 3 Wood Woads. I
guess the gnome is a actually a druid using the entropist stat block.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the feel of the mechanics on this one, but the lore is once again a bit
uninspiring. It’s another humanoid fey plant that’s fanatical about protecting
nature, just like dryads and treants. I guess they can round out the cast when
you want to focus a game on a faction of such beings, but we already have a lot
of other possible creatures that belong there as well (satyrs, centaurs, elven
druids, and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use the wood woad stat block but don’t want to say they’re a
completely separate species, just say they’re small treants instead.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Winter Wolf</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-wolf-winter.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual already gave us &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/13/wolves.html&quot;&gt;wolves normal and dire&lt;/a&gt;, and it also gave
us &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/19/worg.html&quot;&gt;worgs&lt;/a&gt;. Now the Monster Manual 2 continues to climb the wolf power
ladder. I first remember seeing Winter Wolves in the 3e monster books, but I’m
pretty sure they’ve been around longer than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I tried to explain how all of these monsters fit together I suppose I’d say
it all starts with the Sons of the Spirit Wolf. The Great Spirit Wolf is a
godlike primal spirit, and his progeny wander the world forever trying to
satisfy their endless hunger. I guess they’re more or less equivalent to the
various wolf spirits worshipped by the Uratha from Werewolf: The Forsaken, only
not nearly as nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These primal spirits probably had descendants themselves, which would be your
“standard” winter wolves. These fit above worgs in the Wolf Power
Ladder. They’re a bit smaller than worgs, but are much deadlier, much smarter,
and just as evil. They also have ice powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point a primordial entity of ice and cold might have taken a look at
the Sons of the Spirit Wolf and thought hey, I want me some of that. So it
developed a process where it takes the living heart of an elemental blizzard and
fashions a Rime Hound out of it. Unlike the creatures they are modeled after,
Rime Hounds are entirely made of ice. Their creators give them as gifts to loyal
servants and worshippers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the creatures in this entry are Magical Beasts. Winter wolves are Natural,
and the others are Elemental. They all have low-light vision and a ground speed
of 8 with Ice Walk, which means they ignore cold-themed difficult terrain. Sons
of the Spirit Wolf have Resist Cold 30, all the others have Resist Cold 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their powers are a combination of the usual wolfy bites and takedowns with a
suite of frost breath weapons and the like, but the specifics vary with each
stat block. Their Int scores are in the average human range. We’ll look at them
by order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winter-wolf&quot;&gt;Winter Wolf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winter Wolves are Medium, and are Level 14 Skirmishers with 141 HP. They attack
with &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; that deal bonus cold damage, and deal about double damage to
prone targets. They can get people prone with a &lt;strong&gt;Takedown&lt;/strong&gt;, a charge attack
that’s stronger than the basic bite and knocks the target prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a winter wolf is adjacent to a prone target it can use &lt;strong&gt;Drag&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will
minor action that allows the wolf to shift 1 square and pull the prone victim
along with it. It’s more than smart enough to use this to put the victim in a
position to be surrounded by its wolf buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, winter wolves can use a &lt;strong&gt;Freezing Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a Close
Blast 5 that targets Reflex and deals cold damage (half on a miss). This
attack’s damage is smaller than the wolf’s cold resistance, so a pack of winter
wolves is going to try to get the party all bunched up and then hit them with
multiple blasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winter-wolf-snowfang&quot;&gt;Winter Wolf Snowfang&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snowfangs are Level 16 Lurkers with 124 HP, representing the sort of wily wolf
that keeps out of sight and nips at your heels until you’re too weak to fight
back. Rather than relying on takedowns, it tries to freeze its victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do bonus cold damage, and are stronger against victims who are
taking ongoing cold damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;Frigid Breath&lt;/strong&gt; works like that of the
standard winter wolf with an added ongoing cold damage rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snowfang’s lurker-y ability is &lt;strong&gt;Snow Zephyr&lt;/strong&gt;, a reaction that triggers
when it gets damaged and turns it into a whirlwind of snow. This causes the
snowfang to become insubstantial, and to gain the ability to shift its speed as
a move action. In this form it can only attack with Frigid Breath, which also
causes it to revert to wolf form. It can also revert voluntarily as a minor
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These powers allow snowfangs to act as very effective harriers: they charge in,
use Freezing Breath, and fight until damaged. Then they shift away in Snow
Zephyr form, and vanish for a while. Then they come back, perhaps even still in
zephyr form, use Freezing Breath again, and repeat the process. You could use
them like this as persistent foes who refuse to have a stand-up fight to the
last, and who pop up to make opportunistic attacks in the middle of other
encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rime-hounds&quot;&gt;Rime Hounds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These knockoff winter wolves are quite well-made! They’re Huge in size, and are
Level 17 Elite Skirmishers with 332 HP. They have the Earth, Cold, and Mount
keywords, so they’re appropriate mounts for ice giants!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have Reach 2 Bite and Takedown attacks identical to those of a winter wolf,
with bigger numbers. They have the same Drag ability as well. Instead of a
Freezing Breath, they have &lt;strong&gt;Frost Storm&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Burst 3 that targets
Fortitude and deals cold damage (half on a miss). This creates a zone of frozen
difficult terrain that lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, their “elite multi-attack” power is actually a reaction: &lt;strong&gt;Ice
Spikes&lt;/strong&gt; which extend whenever the hound or its rider are missed by an enemy
melee attack. This acts as a free attack on the triggering enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;son-of-the-spirit-wolf&quot;&gt;Son of the Spirit Wolf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Large wolfy demigods are Level 26 Elite Skirmishers with 486 HP. Their
surrounded by an aura (1) named &lt;strong&gt;Everfrost Coat&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals 10 cold damage
to enemies who enter it. Enemies damaged by the aura can’t make opportunity
attacks for a turn, which allows this wolf to freely disengage from most PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do the usual physical/cold damage mix and grab the
target on a hit. They can then use &lt;strong&gt;Drag Away&lt;/strong&gt; to either shift 1 square or
move their speed while pulling the victim along. They can also use &lt;strong&gt;Rending
Jaws&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) against the grabbed victim, a much stronger attack than the
basic bite that also pushes the target 5 squares and knocks them prone as the
wolf ends the grab and flings the victim away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing in the text forbidding the wolf from using normal bites on other
enemies while it has a victim grabbed. You are of course free to forbid it since
it only has one mouth… but what if it doesn’t? What if this is a vaguely
wolf-shaped ball of dark spirit stuff instead of being just a big wolf? What if
it can grow extra mouths to bite people with? Maybe it’s not canon, but it’s
metal as fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the thing’s last attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Black Ice Breath&lt;/strong&gt; which is kind of a
hybrid between the breaths of the other two varieties: big cold damage in a
Close Blast 5, and it leaves a zone of frozen difficult terrain that lasts for
the whole encounter. This is an encounter power that recharges when the wolf is
first bloodied, just like dragon breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the links between the different monsters here are purely my
invention. Judging from the descriptions of the book alone, they don’t have
anything in common other than being generally wintery and wolfy. The individual
stat blocks have good mechanics, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 14: a Chillfire Destroyer elemental and a pair of
winter wolves being bossed around by a Beholder Eye of Frost.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wolf-winter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wolf-winter.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Witherling</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-witherling.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witherlings feel like a new monster to me. They’re certainly new to 4e, making
their debut in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, those deranged cannibals who worship Yeenoghu don’t
actually eat everyone they kill. Sometimes they raise their victims as undead
abominations. This is a relatively new development, as the technique was only
recently handed down from the demon lord to its cultists. They are both a new
weapon in the war brewing between Yeenoghu and Orcus, and a way for the former
to muscle in on the latter’s territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process to create a witherling involves replacing the corpse’s head with
that of a hyena, and summoning the essence of a demon into the resulting piece
of “art”. Gnolls and other Yeenoghu cultists prefer to do this to the corpses of
their slain foes, not those of their own side. The result tends to be a lot
faster, smarter and more versatile than that of your typical zombie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All witherlings are Natural Animates with the Undead keyword. They have no
particular resistances or vulnerabilities. Their signature trait is a lesser
form of the gnoll &lt;strong&gt;Pack Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, giving them a +2 damage bonus when two or
more of their allies are adjacent to the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling&quot;&gt;Witherling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is usually made from the corpse of a Small humanoid like a
goblin, kobold, or halfling. It’s a Level 4 Skirmisher with 56 HP and a Speed of
8 (Climb 6).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witherling &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are a bit weak, but they slow on a hit (save ends) and the
creature can make a &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; with them. It also deals extra damage when
it has combat advantage. While bloodied, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Blood Dance&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 2
squares instead of 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its final ability is a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Leap&lt;/strong&gt; that allows it to jump 4 squares and gain
a +5 to AC against opportunity attacks during the jump. If an enemy misses the
witherling with an opportunity attack while it’s jumping, the witherling gains
combat advantage against that enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So these things will come at you en masse from the walls and the bottoms of
pits, and use Sudden Leap to jump juuust a bit past the PCs and attack them from
behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-death-shrieker&quot;&gt;Witherling Death Shrieker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made from the corpse of a Medium creature, the Death Shrieker is a Level 5
Controller with 65 HP and the Leader keyword. Its a bit slower with a ground
speed of 6 and no climbing ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are just a typical basic attack, but it shrieks do damage over a
wide area (close blast 5). The most common one is the &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Shriek&lt;/strong&gt;, which
targets only enemies, does thunder damage, and pushes 2 squares. There’s also
the &lt;strong&gt;Death Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which also targets only enemies and does
untyped damage. Any undead ally adjacent to an enemy hit by this recovers 5
HP. There’s a note saying allies can only benefit from this once per round, so
if you have multiple shriekers they should coordinate and stagger their screams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-horned-terror&quot;&gt;Witherling Horned Terror&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is Large, and made from a minotaur. Since Yeenoghu is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; locked in
eternal battle against Baphomet, they’re more common than you think. Minotaurs
of all alignments hate these things, which is perfectly understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horned Terrors are Level 8 Brutes with 107 HP and a ground speed of 7. They have
a decent &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack, and can use their &lt;strong&gt;Horns&lt;/strong&gt; to the same amount of
damage and push the target 2 squares. They can also perform a &lt;strong&gt;Rampaging
Charge&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which uses the horns to attack and allows them to make
up to three additional attacks against different targets who happen to be in
reach at the end point of the charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-rabble&quot;&gt;Witherling Rabble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a witherling whose creation process glitched out, producing an inferior
specimen. I guess they’re stockpiled and sent out as a huge mob against
enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This defective undead has the exact same attacks as a standard witherling, but
is a Level 9 Minion Skirmisher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eh… I guess witherlings are okay mechanically, and they’re a nice addition to
a campaign focused on battling Yeenoghu and evil gnolls, but they don’t do much
for me personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are different groups of gnolls with witherling
support. One of them also has a cambion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/witherling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/witherling.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
