<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 18:31:32 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 18:31:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fuzzy turns in GURPS Combat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As you might know from reading here before, I hang out on the RPG.net forums a
lot. Whenever a discussion about GURPS starts there, some people often complain
they feel intimidated or annoyed by the 1-second combat turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other games tend to have a less granular concept of turn duration and of what
exactly constitutes an action, so players used to them usually expect to be able
to do one “complete thing” in each turn without bothering with detailed setup
steps. For example, a ranged attack with a bow in D&amp;amp;D takes a single action that
includes aiming, shooting, drawing a new arrow, and nocking it, all of which are
distinct steps in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually like 1-second turns and will be keeping them in my games, but I
present here a possible way to make them fuzzier for those groups who don’t
enjoy them as much. This is a fairly fundamental change to the base GURPS
system, probably lends itself better to games that used simplified combat rules
instead of things like detailed hex maps and range measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also helps combat feel a bit more like what you might see in action movies
or similar media, which tend to slow down things to make them easier to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fuzzy-combat-in-gurps&quot;&gt;Fuzzy Combat in GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this rule, a combat round is no longer exactly 1 second long. Now it takes
an unspecified amount of time between 5 and 10 seconds long - enough for
everyone to act once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-maneuver actions that can be resolved in a 1-second turn under the
original rules still take 1 turn to resolve here. This includes most melee and
ranged attacks, movement, and the Aim and Evaluate maneuvers. Advantages such as
Extra Attack and techniques like Rapid Strike work exactly as written, with the
same limitations, but read “seconds” as “turns”. The RoF stat retains its value
for all weapons that have it, but read it as “shots per turn” instead of “shots
per second”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actions that would take multiple consecutive maneuvers over several turns to
perform now take 1 turn per 10 seconds or fraction thereof they would originally
take. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swapping magazines on a modern gun took 3 seconds, so now it takes 1 turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reloading a musket took 40 seconds, so it takes 4 turns now.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any spell that would require less than 10 seconds to cast can be cast in a
single turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Searching through your pack for an item took 2d seconds. As the average of
that roll is less than 10, it only requires a turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Picking a lock takes a minute, which means 6 turns. Accepting a -5 penalty to
do it in 30 seconds means it takes 3 turns. This makes it possible to do
during a fight.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fast-Draw skill now encompasses a series of actions taken to speed up a
given process. It can reduce the time an appropriate action takes by 1 turn, to
a minimum of 0. So you can still use it to draw a weapon and attack on the same
turn, or to reload a pistol and keep firing on the same turn. That musket is
still going to take 3 turns before it can fire again. You might want to make it
Average instead of Easy since a single roll covers a larger set of actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes make characters such as archers and wizards more powerful in
combat, since the number of things they can do over a given amount of turns has
increased, while melee-focused character can still take more or less the same
number of actions. Note that I have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; tested how these changes interact
with the magic system, so I can’t measure how much of an impact it’s going to
have on spellcasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-we-avoided&quot;&gt;Things we Avoided&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that we didn’t attempt to increase the effective number of actions by the
same multiplier as the turn duration. If a character could attack every second
under the standard rules, they don’t get to make 5-10 attacks in a single turn
here. Aiming or Evaluating for multiple seconds gave you extra bonuses, but you
don’t get them automatically here - you must perform those maneuvers for the
same number of turns. Our goal is to remove multi-step complex procedures, not
to keep counting seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is more abstract and perhaps less realistic, and that is the point. If
you want to keep tracking events second-by-second, stick with the standard
rules.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/19/gurps-fuzzy-turns.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/19/gurps-fuzzy-turns.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I'm done with Threats to the Nentir Vale! Now what?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wolf Runners were the last monster entry in the book, and after that there’s
only a glossary index. So we’re done with this book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only that, we’re also done with my big project of reading all of the
main D&amp;amp;D 4th monster books. I remember I started it January 1st 2019, with the
first posts going into an RPG.net thread and appearing here shortly
afterwards. So it took us a little over 4 years, 4 months, and 15 days to get it
all done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing all of this was an interesting experience. The idea for the project came
at a time when I was having a bit of a hard time coming up with subjects for
posts to this blog, mainly because I was getting anxious about writing good
articles. I’d think of something, then I’d begin writing, and then I’d get
blocked or mired in an endless round of revisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writting commentary on D&amp;amp;D monsters, in contrast, felt extremely easy. I could
sit down, cover a bunch of entries, and have them ready for a regular release
schedule. Granted, I had a hard time sticking to any sort of schedule for most
of the project’s runtime, but I think I did a pretty good job of it in Threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people who read these entries here in the blog were probably 4e fans
instead of the usual GURPS crowd, unless they happened to follow my RSS feed
directly or something like that. None of those posts had a GURPS tag, so they
didn’t appear in the aggregator I’m a member of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still want to have a ready source of posts for Octopus Carnival, and I also
really like the conversations I had in the RPG.net threads for the project, so
I’m going to begin a new Let’s Read. There’s voting going on in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.rpg.net/index.php?threads/lets-read-threats-to-the-nentir-vale.904788/&quot;&gt;RPG.net
thread&lt;/a&gt; for Threats, with the following candidates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neverwinter Campaign Setting&lt;/strong&gt; for 4e. I have it, and I have opinions about
it, so it’s a good subject.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hell’s Rebels&lt;/strong&gt; for Pathfinder, with commentary about converting it to other
systems. Extremely convenient because I’ve already written a lot about it in
this blog. Might also give me more incentive to actually finish the adventure
path too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dungeon Fantasy Roleplaying Game&lt;/strong&gt;: A large enough effort that I’d need to
give it serious thought. It would probably not be a page-by-page affair, but
it &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; merit the GURPS tag.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check the thread linked above if you want to vote or comment on any of the
entries. Otherwise sit back and enjoy the knowledge that there will soon be a
new thing to occupy your usual Let’s Read slots.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/17/tnv-done.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/17/tnv-done.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>meta</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Wolf Runners</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-wolf-runners.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last entry in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like the Raven Roost bandits have some competition! The Wolf Runners are
another of the bandit gangs who prey on the Trade Road between Fallcrest and
Hammerfast. They have this name because their leader, Sylish Kreed, has somehow
gained the loyalty of a pack of grey and dire wolves, and has them aid the gang
when they attack caravans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kreed presents himself as the dashing rogue type, and tries to be civil and
good-humored when dealing with his victims. The gang vastly prefers to take its
victims’ valuables without a fight, and to leave them alive and free to go. This
both lessens the heat upon them and gives them the opportunity to rob the same
people again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The counter-balance to this, however, is that Kreed is a terribly sore loser. If
he ends up on the losing end of a battle, he’ll become sullen and obsessed with
taking revenge on whoever beat him. He doesn’t necessarily want to kill the
offender, but he won’t rest until he’s re-established his superiority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of alpha-asshole behavior and the wolves might have tipped you off to
the gang’s big secret: Kreed is a werewolf, having caught lycanthropy from a
bite a few years back. He can transform at will most of the time, but for three
days on every full moon he loses control, changes into a wolf, and goes off to
live with his pack until his rational mind returns. Kreed’s condition is not
public knowledge, though I guess his gang-mates know of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His main lieutenant certainly does: that’s Eveni Redblade, a tiefling whom he
rescued from the Dark Drake of the Moon Hills some time ago, and who as a result
is completely loyal to him. Speaking of loyalty, the wolves are also loyal to
Kreed personally, though they tolerate the gang and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolf Runner ambushes tend to consist of a troop of archers hidden in the woods
off to both sides of the road, while Kreed and his wolf pack block the path and
handle the intimidation plus melee fighting that proves necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the unusual nature of their leader and his “understanding” with those
wolves, the Wolf Runners are a typical bandit gang that uses typical bandit stat
blocks. The wolves are also typical, using standard stats for grey and dire
wolves from the Monster Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this section, we get stats for Kreed, Eveni, and the Runners’ archers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wolf-runner-swiftarrow&quot;&gt;Wolf Runner Swiftarrow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the wolves acting as melee muscle, many of the Runners focus on archery
instead. Swiftarrows are Level 5 Artillery with 50 HP. They have decent melee
and ranged attacks with a &lt;strong&gt;short swords&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;longbow&lt;/strong&gt;, and their &lt;strong&gt;Close
Shot&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver lets them make a free bow attack whenever an enemy moves
adjacent to them, without provoking attacks of opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eveni-redblade&quot;&gt;Eveni Redblade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tiefling lieutenant is a Level 5 Skirmisher with 60 HP. She’s always &lt;strong&gt;On
The Move&lt;/strong&gt;, ending any slowing or immobilization effects on her at the start of
her turns. She also does extra damage against targets granting combat advantage
to her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eveni fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; whose basic strikes let her shift 1 square
before or after the attack, and she can also use &lt;strong&gt;Dazing Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
6+) that as the name implies damage and daze for a turn. Rounding out her
arsenal is the default &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; power tieflings get, which lets her do
a bit of automatic fire damage to someone who hits her once per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a standard mobile combatant package. Eveni works best with plenty of
people to set up flanks and other advantageous situations for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sylish-kreed&quot;&gt;Sylish Kreed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The (wolf)man of the hour is a Level 6 Elite Skirmisher with 144 HP. He has all
the werewolf signature traits, starting with &lt;strong&gt;Regeneration&lt;/strong&gt;, which as usual
shuts down for a turn if he takes damage from silvered weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He can also &lt;strong&gt;Change Shape&lt;/strong&gt; to assume human, wolf, or hybrid forms. In human or
hybrid form he can use a &lt;strong&gt;Greatsword&lt;/strong&gt; that provides standard basic attacks. In
wolf or hybrid form, he can &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt;. The claw does more damage to
bloodied targets and lets Kreed shift &lt;em&gt;4&lt;/em&gt; squares on a hit. The bite knocks
targets prone and exposes them to werewolf moon frenzy as described in the
Monster Vault. The &lt;strong&gt;Bloodmoon Fury&lt;/strong&gt; ability lets him either attack twice with
the sword or make a claw and a bite attack on the same action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the Wolf Runners a lot more than I like the lizardfolk, that’s for
sure. I also think it’s interesting that the Wolf Runners have a lot of other
factions to worry about even if the PCs never fight them directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they really operate on the Trade Road, they’re in direct competition with the
Raven Roost gang and/or the Blackfang Gnolls, both of which are a lot more
murderous than themselves. If we instead move them to King’s Road, they’re going
to contend with the Iron Circle in Harkenwold and possibly with the Daggerburg
Goblins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Wolf Runners presented here are Unaligned, so you can easily play
them as rogues with hearts of gold and have them as possible allies against an
unjust lord or against some of the other factions, Robin Hood-style.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/16/wolf-runners.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/16/wolf-runners.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Witchlight Lizardfolk</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-witchlight-lizardfolk.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll get this out of the way first: this entry fully buys into all the tired
racist stereotypes for D&amp;amp;D humanoids. Already in its second sentence, it calls
them “primitive, tribal, cruel” and cannibalistic. I’m going to strip all of
this out and try to present a less bad version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several lizardfolk tribes living in the Witchlight Fens. A good number
of them are under the rule of the dragon Shadowmire, but not all. All of them
are territorial and tend to distrust outsiders, as mentioned in the Monster
Manual 1 version of their writeups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Witchlight Fens got this name because the local fauna includes several
different times of “witchlights”, mundane or magical creatures that are capable
of producing spheres of glowing light visible in the distance. One species,
known as “fastlights”, usually tries to flee from living creatures, but the
lizardfolk of the Fens have learned to trap and tame them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three largest tribes in the area are the &lt;strong&gt;Brackmarsh&lt;/strong&gt;, who
enthusiastically swore loyalty to Shadowmire and as a result have been able to
conquer much of the northern and western portions of the Fens, driving their
rivals out; the &lt;strong&gt;Mistkillers&lt;/strong&gt; who live in the eastern sector and feud with the
Daggerburg goblins, only occasionally obeying the dragon; and the
&lt;strong&gt;Crushwater&lt;/strong&gt;, who live in the fens’ central region and fiercely resist
draconic dominance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of them are likely to receive PCs who don’t belong to the same tribe with
open arms, but I think it should at least be possible to negotiate with
them. The Brackmarshes or other tribes you add that are more directly controlled
by Shadowmire are even less likely to be friendly to people who don’t also serve
the dragon, and will probably make a good portion of his ground troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the tribes mentioned here have a mix of all three standard lizardfolk
ethnicities, and can contain a mix of the standard stat blocks from the Monster
Vault or other sources. We also get a new batch of stats that apply to them
specifically and can be used elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, the lizardfolk here have a speed of 6 and Swamp Walk, and have no
special senses or resistances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-mire-scout&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Mire Scout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick but fragile scout with a pet fastlight. It’s a level 3 Minion
Skirmisher. It fights in melee with &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; that let it shift 2 squares as an
effect, but prefers to keep away and harass enemies with &lt;strong&gt;Fastlight Shots&lt;/strong&gt;
that do radiant damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-bog-walker&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Bog Walker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beefier warrior who’s more at home than usual in the water. This is a Level 3
Soldier with 44 HP and a swim speed of 4 in addition to its normal movement
described above. The bog walker can make basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks, but it prefers
to grab its does and drown them with &lt;strong&gt;Drag Down&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can only be done if the bog walker is in water at least 1 square deep, and
doesn’t already have a grabbed victim. It’s a melee attack vs. Reflex, and on a
hit it damages and grabs the target (escape DC 13). Until the grab ends, the
target must make a DC 13 Endurance check at the start of their turns, and take
10 damage if that check fails. Even on a miss with the initial attack, the
target is still immobilized for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 damage per turn is a lot for the early Heroic tier. PCs are at a real risk of
drowning if they have a run of bad luck on their rolls and don’t get help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-fen-spy&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Fen Spy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 4 Lurker is also proficient in the use of fastlights as a weapon.  It
can use its &lt;strong&gt;Witchlight Mists&lt;/strong&gt; ability to become invisible as an at-will
standard action, and from there it can use a ranged &lt;strong&gt;Fastlight Strike&lt;/strong&gt; to deal
heavy radiant damage, inflict ongoing 5 radiant damage, and blind (save ends
both). If it can’t become invisible again due to PC pressure, it will use basic
attacks with its &lt;strong&gt;thorn dagger&lt;/strong&gt;, which deal poison damage and inflict a -2
penalty to AC and Reflex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-shocker&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Shocker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spellcaster specializing in lightning magic, it’s Level 5 Artillery with 50
HP. The shocker wields a &lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and slings lightning spells at
range. There’s the single-target at will &lt;strong&gt;Witch Lightning&lt;/strong&gt;, and there’s the
encounter &lt;strong&gt;Ball of Lightning&lt;/strong&gt;, which is basically a fireball with a different
element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone hits then with a ranged or area attack, they can react with a
&lt;strong&gt;sudden jolt&lt;/strong&gt; that deals automatic lightning damage to the attacker, which
means you want to close on them fast instead of trading shots from afar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-dreadtail&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Dreadtail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A warrior who believes you shouldn’t skip tail day at the gym. Dreadtails are
Level 5 Soldiers with 52 HP. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;spears&lt;/strong&gt; that damage and mark for
a turn, but they can also use Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;tail slaps&lt;/strong&gt; that do less damage but
target Reflex and knock prone on a hit. Their &lt;strong&gt;Slap Down&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge
5+) allows them to use both in a single action. If someone marks the dreadtail,
its &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Interference&lt;/strong&gt; reaction marks the offender right back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dreadtails want to mark dangerous PCs, and then keep them prone with repeated
tail slaps. There’s no special ability to punish a PC who ignores the mark, but
it’s hard to fight anyone while prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-dreadnought&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Dreadnought&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A chieftain or lieutenant whose Large size ensures it’s a terrifying sight in
battle. It’s a Level 7 Elite Brute with 190 HP and the Leader tag. The
&lt;strong&gt;Dreadnought’s Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; is a palpable thing that acts as an aura (2) which
gives allies inside a +2 bonus to hit and damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most brutes, dreadnoughts want to be right in the thick of the melee. Their
skills make them excellent at disrupting the enemy front line and opening the
way to the squishies at the back. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; attacks do heavy
damage, push the target 2 squares, and let the dreadnought shift 2 squares to
chase the enemy. As minor actions, they can distribute &lt;strong&gt;Low Blows&lt;/strong&gt; that target
Fortitude, do the same damage, and knock prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the way is opened, they can the &lt;strong&gt;You Fight Now!&lt;/strong&gt; minor action to let an
ally within 5 squares make a free charge attack. This ally and any others who
make it through will then stick close to their boss to enjoy that attack bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-chief&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Chief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more sophisticated leader with a simpler stat block, the chief is a Level 7
Soldier with 156 HP. It fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Battleaxe&lt;/strong&gt; whose blows slow for a turn
on a hit, and can make &lt;strong&gt;Double Attacks&lt;/strong&gt; with it. If an enemy adjacent to the
chief shifts, it can attack them with a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Lash&lt;/strong&gt; that does light physical
damage and knocks prone. Once per encounter it can use &lt;strong&gt;Fighting Spirit&lt;/strong&gt; to
allow every ally in a close burst 2 to make a free basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chief works well as the core of the enemy front-line, using its slow and
trip powers to keep PCs from reaching its squishier buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lizardfolk-marsh-mystic&quot;&gt;Lizardfolk Marsh Mystic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a variant of the Bog Mystic from the Monster Vault, of a lower level and
with some abilities replaced by Witchlight-specific traits. It’s a Level 4
Controller (Leader) with 53 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its first novel trait is &lt;strong&gt;Marsh Mist&lt;/strong&gt;, a very wide aura (10!) that prevents
allies inside from being surprised and gives them a +5 to Perception and
Stealth. Its &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; can damage and slide targets 2 squares on a hit, and its
main ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Fastlight Shock&lt;/strong&gt; that deals lightning and radiant
damage, and immobilizes for a turn. If the target was already immobilized, it’s
dazed instead. On a miss, it slows for a turn with no damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystic can also cast a &lt;strong&gt;Bog Cloud&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter Area Burst 1 that deals
poison damage and dazes (save ends) on a hit. On a miss, it deals half damage
and forces targets to grant combat advantage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are excellent ambush leaders whose presence will all but guarantee the
PCs are surprised, and whose riders on their many attacks will keep them locked
down for Team Monster’s strikers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s good mechanical variety here, but I am very unimpressed with the book’s
default portrayal of lizardfolk. This is a big let-down after the Wandering Tower.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/12/witchlight-lizardfolk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/12/witchlight-lizardfolk.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Wandering Tower</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wanting to write this entry ever since I started doing the Let’s Read
of the first Monster Manual and Monster Vault, more than four years ago. It’s my
favorite entry in the entire book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-wandering-tower.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the dawn of Nerath, a number of knights went a-questing for the fabled
Sunspire, a tower sacred to Pelor that was said to house a beautiful maiden. The
knight who found it would receive the god’s blessings and the maiden’s hand in
marriage. One such knight eventually found the tower, and went inside at the
maiden’s invitation. He was never seen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the armies of evil encircled Gardmore Abbey, they managed to get a
messenger through the siege, carrying a map to the location of their most
precious artifacts to be delivered to the Emperor of Nerath. The messenger ran
until a thunderstorm forced him to seek shelter. He found an inn he didn’t
remember seeing before, whose rotund proprietor promised he’d find all he
desired inside. That night, the messenger laid down on his bed and was never
seen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prince Rande the Lost of Nerath gained his noble title after tracking down and
slaying a foul doppelganger. He found it disguised as a lady of noble bearing
living in a fancy manor house. He slew the creature and took her manor for
himself, moving in with his entire household. Servants and nobles alike began
disappearing one by one, giving rise to rumors that the Prince had usurped an
innocent woman and her ghost was seeking vengenace. Finally, the Prince himself
vanished along with the whole house, leaving an empty plot of land behind and
adding “The Lost” to his titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years after the fall of Nerath a group of dwarven adventures came to the Nentir
Vale seeking the Lost Tower of Fastormel. They found the tower, but their
initial attempts at gaining entry failed. An old dwarven wizard eventually
answered the door, claiming she hadn’t heard the visitors knock. She invited
them inside. The party’s rogue sensed something was wrong and tried to convince
his friends to stay out, but they didn’t listen to him. The last thing the rogue
heard before fleeing were the screams of his companions. When he later returned
there with a well-armed rescue party, the tower was nowhere to be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that mimics never die of old age, and never stop growing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the Wandering Tower is a centuries-old mimic. It’s helped along by a group
of mirror mimics who play host in order to lure potential victims inside. It’s
also followed by a swarm of blood ravens who feast on any remains it
leaves. These appear in every one of the more detailed vignettes in the book
itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blood-raven-swarm&quot;&gt;Blood Raven Swarm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Large swarm of Tiny creatures, and a Level 14 Skirmisher with 138
HP. Blood Ravens are Natural Beasts, and their main reason for following the
tower is for access to easy meals. Their &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) deals 10
damage to enemies caught inside, and if they start their turn on the space of a
bloodied creature they can take move actions as minor actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The swarm’s sole attack is &lt;strong&gt;Blood Beaks&lt;/strong&gt;, which damages the target and weakens
it for a turn if it’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mirror-mimic&quot;&gt;Mirror Mimic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting variant of the Impersonator Mimic from the MM3. It’s
weaker and more suitable as a hench-thing for the tower, but it also has
different psychic tricks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirror Mimics are Level 15 Lurkers with 118 HP. They have a ground Speed of 6
and Phasing, meaning they can move through walls. They attack with &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt;
that do decent damage, and their main mimic power is &lt;strong&gt;Body Duplication&lt;/strong&gt;. This
lets them attack the Will of an enemy. On a hit, they take the target’s form and
teleport up to 3 squares. They also create 3 duplicates of the target within 3
squares of it. The duplicates can be attacked and have the same defenses as the
mimic, but any damage destroys them. Telling them apart from the original mimic
requires a DC 35 Insight check. The mimic can make all of them move its speed
with a single minor action, and can use &lt;strong&gt;Body Transfer&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to
discreetly switch places with a duplicate. When it does this, its next attack
deals extra damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By a strict reading of the ability, the PCs need no rolls to pinpoint their
duplicated friend - they are only required to distinguish between the original
mimic and one of its illusory duplicates. That’s not a problem, however, because
when a duplicate is destroyed, the duplicated PC takes damage as if the mimic
had hit them with an attack!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Body Duplication recharges when the mimic has no active duplicates, so keeping
it active is going to be its main priority. After that, it’s going to constantly
switch places with a copy and focus its attacks on the duplicated PC. It’s going
to be very annoying to fight unless the PCs can consistently make those Insight
rolls. If the party doesn’t have an Insight specialist, this thing is going to
punch above its weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;core-of-the-tower&quot;&gt;Core of the Tower&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wandering Tower can replicate any medium-sized building. Once its mimic
servants have lured one or more victims inside, the Tower waits until they are
at rest with their guard down, and then its core will attack them. That’s the
part that actually does the eating and digesting, and houses the being’s vital
organs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core is a Huge Aberrant Magical Beast, smaller than the building it’s
mimicking (which will be part of the battle map!). The walls and furnishings of
the building remain part of the mimic and can also attack the PCs. This is
modeled in several different ways in this stat block and the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Core of the Tower is a Level 18 Solo Controller with 716 HP, a ground speed
of 6 with Phasing, Darkvision and Tremorsense 10. It’s immune to domination and
has 15 acid resistance. It’s &lt;strong&gt;One With the Tower&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning it can’t move out
of the Tower and is immune to any effects that would transport it
outside. Rounding out its Solo Survival Kit, we have the &lt;strong&gt;Undaunted&lt;/strong&gt; trait,
which downgrades any stuns inflicted on it to dazes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core fights by extending tendrils from itself and manipulating the
surrounding terrain, which is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; itself. Its basic attacks are Reach 3 and
consist of &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; that slide the target 3 squares and &lt;strong&gt;Grabs&lt;/strong&gt; that do
almost the same amount of damage and have an escape DC of 23. It can also, as a
free action on its turn, target a grabbed PC with the &lt;strong&gt;Maw of Doom&lt;/strong&gt;, sliding
it 3 squares to a space adjacent to itself or to a wall and dealing a big chunk
of acid damage. This requires an attack roll against Fortitude, but does not end
the grab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most combat-relevant minor action the core can make is use its &lt;strong&gt;Rippling
Architecture&lt;/strong&gt; to attack every enemy in a Close Burst 5 and knock them prone on
a hit. It can also create additional doors on the map, which start out jammed
shut (break DC 25), or shapeshift into something suitably large, using the same
rules as an object mimic: can’t attack, has 10 resistance to all damage, DC 32
to notice it’s a mimic. It will likely start the fight this way, and the door
ability will be used to place any doors the PCs see when they enter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;living-wall&quot;&gt;Living Wall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hazard that’s sure to be present on any fight against the Wandering
Tower, since it represents its non-core natural weapons. The book recommends
choosing 8 contiguous squares of wall on the map and designating them as this
hazard. Pseudopods and acidic maws extend from this wall to attack PCs when it
activates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Living Wall is a Level 18 Hazard that has slightly lower defenses than the
mimic’s core, and 25 HP per square (200 for those 8 recommended squares). It’s
very tough, being immune to necrotic, poison, psychic and ongoing damage, as
well as to all forced movement and conditions. It has Resist 10 acid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its attack is Reach 3 and though it deals only light physical damage it has
cruel riders: hit targets are pulled 1 square, restrained, and take 10 ongoing
acid damage (save ends both). It can attack two targets with one action, and
each attack can originate from any of the wall’s squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A square that takes 25 damage is destroyed and can no longer serve as the origin
point for an attack, though I guess it still blocks perception and movement. If
the core is dazed or first bloodied, the wall is disabled for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this! It really stretches the mechanics of the game to give you an
encounter against an actual building who wants to kill you. The most likely
fight against the Wandering Tower will involve every stat block in this entry:
the Core itself on a building interior map with a number of Living Wall squares,
a mirror mimic servant, and the Blood Ravens ready to attack anyone who tries to
get out. That’s a very chaotic Level 20 Encounter for 5 characters, going into
the epic levels if your party is smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/09/wandering-tower.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/09/wandering-tower.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Vestapalk</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-vestapalk.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth and final dragon described in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vestapalk is an adult green dragon who lairs in the Cairngorm Peaks. He’s very
typical of his demographic in that he’s an evil asshole whose favorite food is
the flesh of sapient mammals. Every time he kills an opponent he considers
worthy, he marks another scar on the inside of his right forearm to remember the
occasion. He currently has nine, most of which are ill-fated adventurers who
tried to loot his hoard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, Vestapalk used to hunt in the Stonemarch region beyond the vale,
but he’s begun flying into the Vale more and more often, which has the
population of Winterhaven in a fright. One of the reasons for this is that the
dragon has started receiving prophetic visions in his dreams. These showed him
sitting proud as the overlord of a kobold tribe, and he decided to see if there
was any truth to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most kobold tribes Vestapalk encountered ran scared from him, but one did
not. The Greenscale tribe was led by a wyrmpriest named Tiktag, who had been
receiving similar visions, and who welcomed Vestapalk as his awaited ruler. The
dragon’s support turned the Greenscales from just another embattled kobold tribe
to a local power that’s busy securing territory between Winterhaven and Lake
Wintermist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiktag has great ambitions - he wants all others to fear him as his tribe fears
Vestapalk. I’m not sure he believes the dragon is a god, like his followers do,
but he does definitely think there’s something mystical about their partnership,
since Tiktag’s divination rituals have become amazingly accurate when done at
the dragon’s behest. The dragon, meanwhile, believes he might have been chosen
for greatness by the Elder Eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though they would be loathe to admit it, the kobold and the dragon have come to
see each other as friends. They’re almost always together and Vestapalk even
allows Tiktag to ride on his shoulders for safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for both Vestapalk and his tiny friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiktag&quot;&gt;Tiktag&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wyrmpriest is much more powerful than is typical, being a Level 6 Artillery
monster with 56 HP. As a kobold, he’s Small, has a Speed of 6, Low-Light Vision,
and the &lt;strong&gt;Shifty&lt;/strong&gt; ability that lets him shift as a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiktag will always be found close to his dragon friend, and the &lt;strong&gt;Prophet of the
Elemental Eye&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives him 5e-style Advantage on saves when he’s within 10
squares of Vestapalk. He’ll fire &lt;strong&gt;Poison Orbs&lt;/strong&gt; that do poison damage from the
safety of his perch, and use his poison &lt;strong&gt;Dragon Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3) when
they happen to be close and bunched up. If an enemy moves adjacent to him he can
use &lt;strong&gt;Fierce Rebuke&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter to attack their Will. The enemy is
pushed 3 squares as an effect and either immobilized on a hit or slowed on a
miss. When that power is spent, the priest needs to resort to his &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; to
discourage melee attackers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter he can use &lt;strong&gt;Incite Faith&lt;/strong&gt; to give every kobold ally within
10 squares 5 temporary HP and allow them to shift 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vestapalk&quot;&gt;Vestapalk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our main event is a Large green dragon, and a Level 13 Solo Skirmisher with 524
HP. Most of his abilities are similar to the green dragon described in the
Monster Vault, but he’s the first Adult example you’re likely to see if that’s
the only other monster book you have (the MV has Young and Elder variants). He
has a speed of 10 with Forest Walk, and a flight speed of 14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a typical green dragon, Vestapalk can use &lt;strong&gt;Action Recovery&lt;/strong&gt; to shake off
the Dazed, Stunned, and Dominated conditions at the start of his turn, and the
poison in his veins works as a damaging aura when he’s bloodied. He can also use
an &lt;strong&gt;Instinctive Flyby&lt;/strong&gt; at his Initiative count +10, flying his speed with a +4
bonus to defend against opportunity attacks and making a bite or claw attack
along the way. This is a free action - if a condition prevents him from using
free actions, that condition ends instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; inflicts ongoing poison damage and his &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack
lets him shift 2 squares on a hit. His &lt;strong&gt;breath weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) deals
immediate and ongoing poison damage, halving both on a miss. He can use a
&lt;strong&gt;Luring Glare&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to slide a target 3 squares, and has the
standard &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt; ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that is standard green dragon stuff. He also has two exclusive abilities:
&lt;strong&gt;Tail Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that lets him attack any enemy who ended his turn
next to him without moving, dealing decent physical damage and knocking them
prone on a hit. And instead of an in-turn flyby attack, he can &lt;strong&gt;Share The Mad
Visions&lt;/strong&gt; with every creature in a Close Burst 2, which deals psychic damage and
pushes targets a number of squares equal to their speed. This deals half damage
on a miss, and Vestapalk can shift his speed as an effect. This powerful ability
recharges when he’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sure is an odd pair. The level disparity means it’s a bit hard to fit them
both in an encounter. If you’re at the level where Tiktag would make a good
boss, Vestapalk is going to splat you. If you’re at a level where Vestapalk
makes a good boss fight, you’re going to splat Tiktag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would suggest either making them separate encounters at different times in the
PC’s career, or increasing Tiktag’s level. Note that Vestapalk would actually be
kind of reluctant to use Share the Mad Visions if the little kobold is around,
since that ability is not selective.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/07/vestapalk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/07/vestapalk.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Vampiric Mist</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-vampiric-mist.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vampiric Mists originally appeared back in AD&amp;amp;D 1e, in Dungeon Magazine 17. This
is their 4e debut, with lore appropriate to the Nentir Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancient legends tell that the Witchlight Fens mark the spot where a demon lord
was slain at the dawn of time - the region became a swamp when its corpse fell
there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In slightly-less-ancient times, a lich whose name has been lost to history
established a lair in the Fens with the goal of finding the remains of this
demon lord and reanimating them as a super-powerful undead
creature. Accompanying the lich was a coven of nine vampire lords, its loyal
retainers. These vampires were tasked with hiding and guarding the lich’s soul
vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time after that, one of the lich’s enemies, a powerful hag, came to the
fens in search of its soul vessel. She had created a custom ritual to destroy
the vampires, and she enacted it there, but it didn’t have the desired
effect. Her magic succeeded at destroying the bodies of the vampires, but their
essence remained and coalesced to form a new, more dangerous
creature. The hag left without finding the artifact, which remains in the Fens
protected by its gaseous guardian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a deserted clearing in the Fens that contains a single slab of stone in
its middle. That is the territory of the monster known as the Crimson Deathmist,
who endlessly roams it looking for new victims. It prefers the blood of elves
and other fey, but it will kill anyone it can reach. It has been a very long
time since anyone who encountered it has lived to tell the tale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stone slab conceals the entrance to a catacomb complex where the lich’s soul
vessel is hidden. The fate of the lich itself is unknown. Maybe it’s still in
the Fens somewhere, or maybe something peculiar happened to it to take it out of
the picture without destroying its vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all vampiric mists have such an epic origin. A more common and less powerful
variety appears when a vampire who is forced into mist form has its resting
place destroyed before it can get there. To avoid permanent destruction, the
vampire will sometimes shed its physical form by an act of will, becoming a
vampiric mist. This causes it to lost most of its intellect and memories, and to
become a creature of hunger and instinct. They’re still smart enough to team up
with other evil or predatory swamp dwellers like hags, vine horrors, and outcast
lizardfolk. There’s always the danger the mist will turn on these allies if they
have blood and victims become scarce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get several varieties of vampiric mist here, which I guess come from
different types of vampire, or vampires who met different ends. One of those is
the late-Paragon Crimson Deathmist, but others hover hungrily around the late
Heroic and early Paragon tiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of them have Darkvision, immunity to disease, 10 Resistance to necrotic and
poison damage, and 5 vulnerability to radiant damage. Their ground speed is 0,
but their flight speed is a 5 with an altitude limit of 2. That means they never
land, but also can’t fly beyond melee reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these creatures have the &lt;strong&gt;Mist Form&lt;/strong&gt; trait, which lets them move
through openings of any size and occupy the same space as other creatures. They
also count as &lt;strong&gt;Insubstantial&lt;/strong&gt;, taking half damage from everything but fire,
force, or radiant damage. Fire or radiant damage additionally makes them lose
this trait for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesser mists have an aura (1) named &lt;strong&gt;Siphoning Presence&lt;/strong&gt; that prevent enemies
inside from spending healing surges, and deal 5/tier necrotic damage to enemies
who end their turns inside. When the aura deals damage, the mist recovers 5
HP. Being inside the mist does count as being inside its aura. They are Medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vampiric-mist&quot;&gt;Vampiric Mist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our basic model is a Level 9 Skirmisher with 85 HP and all the standard traits
listed above. It can shift its speed as a move action using the &lt;strong&gt;Shifting
Mists&lt;/strong&gt; ability, which ensures it will never move normally. Its basic attack is
a contact &lt;strong&gt;Life Drain&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude, deals necrotic damage, and
makes the target vulnerable to necrotic damage for a turn. It can also spread a
&lt;strong&gt;Wave of Lethargy&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that attacks a Close Burst 2, deals a bit of
psychic and necrotic damage, and slows for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thing is almost impossible to pin down. With multiple mists in the same
encounter, some can “prime” targets by hitting them with Life Drain to make them
take increased damage from a Wave of Lethargy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vampiric-mist-corruptor&quot;&gt;Vampiric Mist Corruptor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess this is what you get from a more traditional D&amp;amp;D vampire who was capable
of using a dominating gaze and really leaned on this ability. Corruptors are
Level 11 Controllers with 100 HP and all standard traits described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the fight starts they’ll try to hit someone with their &lt;strong&gt;Corrupting
Gaze&lt;/strong&gt;, which dominates (save ends) on a hit and deals necrotic and psychic
damage as an aftereffect. This recharges whenever the creature doesn’t have a
dominated victim!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dominating a PC, it will attack the others with its &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals
necrotic damage and slides 2 squares on a hit. Perfect for dragging other PCs
closer to the dominated one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the mist is first bloodied, it will let loose a &lt;strong&gt;Deathly Howl&lt;/strong&gt; that hits
a Close Burst 5, pushes 3 squares on a hit and forbids targets from spending
healing surges (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t add more than one or two of these to an encounter group. It’s no fun for
anyone if the whole party ends up dominated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chillborn-vampiric-mist&quot;&gt;Chillborn Vampiric Mist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cold-themed mist. It’s a Level 9 Soldier with 85 HP and all standard
traits described above. All of its attacks do cold and necrotic damage. There’s
a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that slows for a turn and the &lt;strong&gt;Grasp of the Cold Grave&lt;/strong&gt; that
immobilizes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mists lack marking capabilities, but their attacks are still very good at
making movement difficult for PCs. It could easily be reskinned into some other
frost-themed ghost without any changes to its stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crimson-deathmist&quot;&gt;Crimson Deathmist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legendary Crimson Deathmist is a Huge entity, and a Level 19 Elite Soldier
with 328 HP. It’s faster with a flight speed of 6 and an altitude limit of 3. It
is however slightly more vulnerable to radiant damage (10 instead of 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This monster has all the standard traits, but its Siphoning Presence is renamed
to &lt;strong&gt;Impending Doom&lt;/strong&gt; and upgraded. I has a radius of 2 instead of 1, and
restores 10 HP to the mist instead of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deathmist can pull enemies 4 squares closer with its &lt;strong&gt;Hypnotic Lure&lt;/strong&gt;
(at-will, minor action), and then &lt;strong&gt;Demand Obedience&lt;/strong&gt; from them. This is a
melee attack that can target two creatures at the same time. It deals psychic
and necrotic damage, with an additional 10 damage the next turn if the targets
attack anyone other than the Deathmist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Deathly Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic and poison damage
and also slows for a turn. It can also release a &lt;strong&gt;Terror Wave&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
psychic damage in a Close Burst 2 and immobilizes for a turn. That last one
recharges when it’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mists’ mechanics are cool, but what really drew my attention was the story
about the lich. A lich whose name is unknown, who lived in ancestral times, who
was interested in undead demon lords, and who is no longer around? That could be
Vecna, whose deeds in this place let him ascend. And instead of a typical soul
vessel you’d find his Eye at the bottom of this catacomb dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that doesn’t appeal, you’ll notice that any party capable of defeating the
Crimson Deathmist guarding the entrance is at about the right level to tackle
the Tomb of Horrors… You’d need to change that clearing a bit to include the
three entrances, but otherwise it’s as good a place to put it as any.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/04/vampiric-mist.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/04/vampiric-mist.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Twig Blight</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-twig-blight.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D Third Edition made many attempts to create new monsters that would grow
popular enough to become iconic, and I think these little critters were one of
their greatest successes even though they weren’t an intentional attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They first appeared as custom opposition in The Sunless Citadel, the very first
official module for Third Edition. They had a very specific origin tied to the
overall story arc of that campaign. That origin is mentioned in version, but we
also see some lore that talks about them in the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig blights look like large woody shrubs or small trees with interlocking
branches. They can change shape somewhat to blend in with the surrounding
vegetation, and they can also uproot and twist themselves into roughly humanoid
shapes in order to hunt or migrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blights need fresh blood to reproduce and grow, using their roots to absorb it
from the soil or directly from corpses. New seedlings sprout from their root
systems, as many as a dozen at a time. They’re very fragile early on, but mature
quickly and after a few days are big enough to start ambushing small creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first blights originated from the Gulthias Tree, which grew from the stake
used to slay ancient vampire who went by that name. Some people speculate that
repeating the process to create a similar tree could create new varieties of
twig blight, though of course few are unbalanced or evil enough to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Vale-specific story is about a lonely pig farmer named Fellis, who was the
first to discover these creatures in the Vale. A strange new bush appeared
overnight in his slaughter shed, and soon it began sprouting seedlings. Fellis
loved the little scamps, giving them names and playing them tunes on his
flute. His neighbors were very worried about all of this weirdness, but still
regularly went there to trade for pig meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that winter, however, severe snow storms tore through the region and made
regular travel impossible until the thaw. When Fellis’ neighbors managed to get
to his farm again, they saw that the man, his family, his pigs, and even the cat
had all been killed. All that was left was a number of pulsating bushes
sprouting from their corpses. Several nearby villages banded together to burn
out the infestation, but a few individuals managed to escape into the
surrounding woods. So now we can add “twig blight infestation” to the list of
everyday disasters that can fall upon the people of the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig blights can survive from normal soil nutrients and sunlight like mundane
plants, but they vastly prefer to have access to a blood supply. Their numbers
increase rapidly when they can find a big source like a slaughterhouse or
battlefield, though even a single corpse is enough to let their reproduction
cycle continue. When their current blood supply runs dry, they’ll uproot
themselves to look for more. If can’t find a new victim or supply quickly,
they’ll take root again and wait in ambush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig blights can even be found in dungeons, ruins, caves, and other places never
touched by the sun. Without access to light, they become even more bloodthirsty
than usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some powerful creatures try to make use of twig blights as unguided boundary
guardians by seeding them along that boundary. However, the creatures are fickle
and as likely to follow the wind to nearby settlements as they are to stay in
place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig Blights are monsters. They have some intelligence and can even speak Elven,
but they only use that to set up smarter ambushes. They only see other
creatures, sapient or not, as food sources, and only interact with them through
violence. You might be able to keep them contained for a while if you supply
them with enough blood, like Fellis did, but their reproductive cycle will
ensure their population quickly outstrips the supply, at which point they’ll
begin hunting for live prey (which means &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig Blights are Small Fey Humanoids with the Plant tag. They have ground and
climb Speeds of 5 with Forest Walk, and Darkvision. They have Resist Poison 5
and the non-minions have Vulnerable to Fire 5. Their signature trait is
&lt;strong&gt;Rooted&lt;/strong&gt;, which reduces forced movement from pulls, pushes, or slides by 3
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like their original 3e incarnation, they’re early Heroic opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight-seedling&quot;&gt;Twig Blight Seedling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A seedling who just grew big enough to hunt. It’s a Level 1 Minion
Skirmisher. Their &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack lets them shift 2 squares before making the
roll, deals poison damage, and has a small damage bonus when the target is
granting them combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their tactics are simple: surround and kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight&quot;&gt;Twig Blight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic model is a Level 2 Lurker with 28 HP. It can turn &lt;strong&gt;invisible&lt;/strong&gt; for
a turn with a standard action, and surprise opponents with &lt;strong&gt;Blighted Claw&lt;/strong&gt;
attacks that do heavy poison damage and weaken (save ends). Even a miss still
does half damage and weakens for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the blight can’t become invisible, it can still attack with basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;
attacks that do a typical amount of poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight-swampvine&quot;&gt;Twig Blight Swampvine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new variant! It could be that classic blights adapted themselves to a
swampy environment… or it could be that someone out there did prove the
stake-tree theorem. They’re particularly common in the Witchlight Fens along the
Nentir River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swampvines are Level 3 Soldiers with 42 HP. They’ll use their minor actions to
pull targets close using a &lt;strong&gt;Swamp Vine&lt;/strong&gt;, which also grabs them (escape DC
13). If a grabbed target attacks someone other than the swampvine, they take an
automatic 5 poison damage. They can also make basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks that do
poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight-swarm&quot;&gt;Twig Blight Swarm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big bunch of classic twig blights that decided to stop being subtle. It’s a
Large Swarm made up of Small creatures, and a Level 5 Brute with 74 HP. It’s
Swarm Attack aura deals 3 damage to those inside, and while it looses its
specific vulnerability to fire it’s still vulnerable to close and area attacks
like any other swarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its version of &lt;strong&gt;Rooted&lt;/strong&gt; makes it completely immune to being pushed, pulled, or
slid, and its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Claws&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack deals poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are lots of people who will be happy to have official 4e stats
for Twig Blights. Their explicitly unnatural origin and their monstrous
disposition tends to make them better “guilt-free” low-level opponents than your
usual selection of humanoids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incarnation of them is also quite tricky for low-level PCs to handle, since
a lot of their early powers rely on forced movement for their more interesting
effects.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/02/twig-blight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/02/twig-blight.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Treants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treants appear in the MM1 in a generic form. Here we see not one but two
specific treant factions present in the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the hillfolk, before the Tigerclaw, before even the elves, the Nentir
Vale was covered by a single, vast forest. And in this forest, the treants
ruled. They feared no one, not even the mighty dragons, for the entire region
was under the protection of Malorunth the Eternal Ash, a gigantic tree who as
also a powerful archfey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One spring evening, however, Malorunth died under mysterious circumstances. The
once vigorous tree was now entirely petrified, leaves falling from its brittle
branches in droves. With Malorunth dead, its blessing left the Vale, and the
dragons who coveted it were quick to capitalize on the opportunity, arriving in
large numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle that followed between treant and dragon was called the War of Endless
Branches, and it’s because of this war that the Nentir Vale looks like it does
today. Draconic magic and breath weapons cut a swathe of devastation across the
center of the region that created the large open area there, and separated
Winterbole Forest to the north from Harken Forest to the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragons would go on to win the war and move into the “cleared” area. They
were powerful, but what really brought them victory was the growing distrust and
suspicion among the treants themselves, which caused them to stop working
together and turn on each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the deciduous treants began to think their coniferous relatives had
something to do with the death of Malorunth, and this suspicion festered enough
that they began voicing it aloud for everyone to hear. Arguments turned to
fights, and soon the treants were more concerned with their brand new civil war
than with keeping the dragons out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This civil war caused the conifers to migrate north to Winterbole forest, where
they would eventually begin venerating the archfey of winter known as the Prince
of Frost. The deciduous treants stayed in Harken Forest, paying homage to the
petrified corpse of Malorunth, which still stands today. They believe the
Eternal Ash will be brought back to life if its murder can be avenged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war technically still rages, but it does so at a treant’s pace. There’s a
battle every century or two, when one of the group manages to organize a Great
March to attack the other’s territory. The fact that they must cross the entire
Vale to do so makes these marches even harder to organize, and slower to
happen. The last one was two hundred years ago, when Harken attacked
Winterbole. The next one will probably be a Winterbole attack, but sometimes it
happens that the same side will launch two attacks in a row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the last battle in this war is older than the fall of Nerath, and there
probably are no surviving Nerathi records of it. Maybe there are a few very old
elves and eladrin who remember it. And maybe the Frost Witches or Harken’s Heart
druids might know, since they live in those forests. But almost no one else has
any idea that a new Great March might be in their future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;winterbole-treants&quot;&gt;Winterbole Treants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-treants-winterbole.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These conifer creatures consider fleshy humanoids to be annoying pests and
parasites, and try to keep their territory free of them. This is made more
difficult by the fact that their slice of Winterbole Forest has a lot of
Arkhosian ruins and Shadowfell crossings in it, so delvers and explorers often
seek those out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have an alliance with Bitterstrike, whom we already met. The dragon
believes the treants to be her vassals, and they put up with this delusion as
long as she holds up her end of the bargain and assists them in the next Great
March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all treants, they are Fey Magical Beasts with the Plant and Treant tags. In
addition to low-light vision, they have both Forest Walk and Ice Walk, ignoring
difficult terrain with either or both of these themes. Needless to say this type
of terrain is plentiful in their home ground. They also have Resist Cold 10 -
even the minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winterbole-sapling&quot;&gt;Winterbole Sapling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Medium saplings are energetic and aggressive, and often team up with
Winterbole-aligned Wood Woads in raids against the Tigerclaw and other
trespassers. They’re Level 11 Minion Soldiers with a Speed of 6. Their &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt;
deal a bit of damage and immobilize for a turn, and their &lt;strong&gt;Numbing Branches&lt;/strong&gt;
aura (1) deals 3 damage to immobilized enemies that start their turns inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes for enemies who likes to mob and surround a single target. If even
one of them hits, all of their auras will deal damage that round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winterbole-rimeneedle&quot;&gt;Winterbole Rimeneedle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rimeneedles are the most intelligent of the “lesser” conifers, and tend to act
as scouts. They’re Large, and Level 12 Skirmishers with 122 HP. It has a Speed
of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rimeneedles are probably going to start the fight with &lt;strong&gt;Winter’s Step&lt;/strong&gt;, a move
action encounter power that lets them teleport 5 squares and make a Close Burst
2 attack on arrival. This deals cold damage, half on a miss. It probably
involves forcefully ejecting those rime needles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is a move action, the treant can immediately follow it up with a
basic &lt;strong&gt;slam&lt;/strong&gt; or with &lt;strong&gt;Tree Stomp&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets it shift its speed and move
through enemy spaces while doing so. The rimeneedle can make one slam attack
against an enemy along this path, and will additionally knock the enemy prone if
it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately as a non-minion treant, it has the &lt;strong&gt;Wooden Body&lt;/strong&gt; weakness, which
causes it to ignite and take ongoing 5 fire damage (save ends) from any attack
that deals fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winterbole-frostbeard&quot;&gt;Winterbole Frostbeard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaders of the Winterbole treants are the venerable Frostbeards, who can
command the winter. They’re rare and seldom seen by others, but they’re out
there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forstbeards are Level 16 Elite Controllers with the Leader tag and 308 HP. Their
size is Huge, their speed is 8, and they’re immune to being knocked prone. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Deep Roots&lt;/strong&gt; reduce any forced movement inflicted on them by 2 (which can
negate the movement entirely), and when they spend their action point every ally
within 10 squares can make a free basic melee attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their opening move is likely a &lt;strong&gt;Howling Blizzard&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that
deals heavy cold and thunder damage in an Area Burst 2 within 10 squares, and
knocks prone on a hit. The blizzard lingers as a zone that deals 10 cold damage
to people who end their turns inside. The frostbeard can move the zone up to 5
squares with a move action, and sustain it with a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the zone is in the battlefield, the frostbeard will likely wade inside it
and begin hitting people with &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt;, which it can make as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. If things begin to look dicey, it can call upon the &lt;strong&gt;Spirits of the
Forest&lt;/strong&gt; (move action, recharge 6+) to teleport itself and up to 3 nearby allies
up to 5 squares, granting them +2 to all defenses for a turn on arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess their main weakness, aside from the usual Wooden Body, is that they have
three different things they can do with their move action: move the blizzard,
use Spirits of the Forest, or make normal moves. If they’re doing one of them,
they can’t do the others unless they give up their standard action. Therefore,
it’s possible to play “keep-away” with them to make them fight at less than
optimal strength. If you stay rooted to one spot, though, they’ll fight you with
slams while pulling the blizzard to sit on top of themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;harken-treants&quot;&gt;Harken Treants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-treants-harken.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deciduous treants of the Harken forest are quite standard as far as rules
go. They use the standard stat blocks for the Treant and Bramblewood Treant from
the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/06/treant.html&quot;&gt;Monster Vault&lt;/a&gt;. They do often work alongside wood woads, so we have a
couple of stat blocks for those in addition to the (by now slightly outdated)
basic stats from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their leader is the most exceptional thing about them: Mysteriphal is the oldest
living creature in the entire Vale. He was there when Malorunth fell, and swore
to forever protect his petrified husk. As mentioned above, Mysteriphal believes
Malorunth will return to life once his murder is avenged. In our narrative
present he’s a huge fire-and-curse scarred thing, any hints of his former
kindness and nobility long gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wood-woad-druid&quot;&gt;Wood Woad Druid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess the existence of these guys explains why the Harken treants wouldn’t be
allied with the Harken’s Heart druids. They’re Level 14 Skirmishers with the
Leader tag and 145 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The druid only has a speed of 5 and no Forest Walk, but it’s immune to the
Immobilized, Restrained, and Slowed conditions. It will likely try to approach a
squishy PC and use &lt;strong&gt;Polymorph Into Plant&lt;/strong&gt; on them. This targets Fortitude, and
does what it says on the tin. It lasts for a turn or until the druid drops to 0
HP, whatever comes first. The polymorphed target is considered stunned, and
gains Vulnerable 15 to fire. This recharges whenever the druid misses with it,
so he can keep trying until it sticks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the polymorph attack doesn’t look like an attractive option, the druid can
hit people with his &lt;strong&gt;cudgel&lt;/strong&gt;, using either basic attacks or a &lt;strong&gt;darting
strike&lt;/strong&gt; that lets him shift 2 squares before or after the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His leaderly options include &lt;strong&gt;Earthen Stride&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will, move action), which
lets the druid and an adjacent ally shift 2 squares; and &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Boon&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor, encounter) which gives a plant ally 25 temporary HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wood-woad-juggernaut&quot;&gt;Wood Woad Juggernaut&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 15 Brute is Large instead of Medium. He has 160 HP and fights mostly
with his powerful &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt;. He will charge if at all possible, since he has
Resist All 15 while charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once his preferred opponent is within his melee reach of 2, the juggernaut will
try to tag them with &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Reign&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a more damaging strike
that also inflicts ongoing 10 damage (save ends), and heals the juggernaut for
the same amount whenever the target takes this ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mysteriphal&quot;&gt;Mysteriphal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leader of the Harken treants is a Huge specimen, and a Level 20 Solo
Controller with 768 HP. This probably makes him the most powerful individual in
the whole Vale. Everything about him hints at his tremendous age, from his
scarred look to his stats. He ponderously drags himself at a speed of 4 without
Forest Walk, but is immune to poison since he has had time to build a tolerance
to all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an &lt;strong&gt;Ancient Entity&lt;/strong&gt;, Mysteriphal automatically downgrades the Dominated and
Stunned conditions to Dazed. His long fighting experience gives him
&lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach 3&lt;/strong&gt;, but he’s even more flammable than a typical treant. He
takes ongoing 10 damage (save ends) when he takes fire damage, but while on fire
his melee attacks also deal an extra 10 fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mysteriphal’s powerful Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; damage and push the target 1 square,
and he can make &lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; of them with a single standard action. If someone in
reach deals fire damage to him, he can make a free slam against the offender as
a reaction (which will already benefit from that bonus fire damage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has several other tricks he can surprise his opponents with. Instead of
slamming he can use a &lt;strong&gt;Reverberating Word&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks all nonplants in a
Close Burst 3, deals heavy thunder damage, and dazes for a turn. This is perfect
for use with an action point, since it lets him do &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; and still punch his
enemies. It also recharges when Mysteriphal is first bloodied, so that second
solo action point also has an easy pre-defined use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can use a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Root Grab&lt;/strong&gt; to grab a target (DC 25)
and pull them up to 2 squares. He can have up to four different creatures
grabbed this way. This doesn’t deal damage… unless Mysteriphal is on fire,
when it benefits from the bonus. And if you think you’re safe by putting some
difficult terrain between Mysteriphal and yourself, the wily old treant can
&lt;strong&gt;Teleport&lt;/strong&gt; 4 squares as a move action (recharge 4+) and reach you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs fighting Mysteriphal might want to consider &lt;em&gt;avoiding&lt;/em&gt; fire attacks. While
they’re still effective, they also make him much more dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a tragic story all around. Probably only the treants themselves remember
why they’re fighting, and barely anyone else would remember they’re fighting at
all due to the long quiet periods between Great Marches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth about Malorunth’s death is a mystery literally older than mortal
civilization, making it almost impossible to solve. And even if our nearly-Epic
PCs manage it, it’s probably still not enough to get the treants to end their
war. It might have started over this murder mystery, but after millenia of
conflict both sides have plenty of reason to keep hating each other.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/31/treants.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/31/treants.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Tigerclaw Barbarians</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-tigerclaw.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve heard about these people in several previous entries, and now is the time
to take a more detailed look at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tigerclaw people claim direct descent from the Hunter of Winter, a powerful
primal spirit in the shape of a sabertooth tiger who roamed the world when it
was young. Their stories tell of Hota Swiftstripe, one of their first
chieftains, who ran into the Hunter while he was tracking a bear near a
glacier. The spirit lashed out with a claw and took out one of Hota’s eyes
before he could even blink, but the chieftain proceeded to lure it to a frozen
lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tiger’s great weight cracked the ice and caused it to fall in, but Hota fell
compassion for such a great hunter and reached out with his spear to help the
beast get out. The Hunter of Winter told Hota that from that moment on they were
brothers, since Hota bore the Hunter’s mark and had saved its life. Hota himself
would be blessed with the blood of the tiger, and so would all his
descendants. When Hota returned to his tribe, he was no longer a human, but one
of the first razorclaw shifters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of Hota’s descendants were shifters as well, so today the Tigerclaw are
divided into two sub-groups. The Tigerbloods who occupy important roles such as
chieftain, shaman, and several types of elite warrior; and the Tamed,
non-shifters who work as gatherers, artisans and rank-and-file warriors. These
are not quite castes despite being called such by the book: there is a way for
one of the Tamed to become a Tigerblood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a Tamed has proven themselves worthy, the tribe’s chieftain invokes a rite
of initiation where the candidate must hunt and attempt to subdue a sabertooth
tiger. They must not &lt;em&gt;kill&lt;/em&gt; it - this is seen as a grave offense punishable by
death. Those who succeed are elevated to Tigerblood status. While they do not
become shifters themselves, they’re paired with a Tigerblood shifter so that
their children are born shifters. There doesn’t seem to be any gender-based role
division within the Tigerclaw, or at least the book doesn’t mention any. The
important one is the Tigerblood/Tamed distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tigerclaw used to live all around the Vale, but were driven north when
Nerath began to encroach on their territory. Chief Scargash’s tribe lives in
Winterbole Forest in our present, and has been there for 70 years after
returning from the frozen wastes north of the forest. Presumably there are other
tribes who still live up there. The book says they sometimes kidnap worthy
outsiders as mates to keep their numbers up, or adopt orphans from other
communities for the same reason. The first alternative is a horrible cliche, so
I’d suggest focusing more on the second and saying they also take in willing and
worthy adult outsiders instead of kidnapping them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the Tigerclaw are usually distrustful of outsiders. They remember
Nerath and the empires that came before, all of whom tried to impose their ways
on their people only to eventually crumble to dust while the Tigerclaw
endured. They consider all “creatures” outside their tribe to be hunters
competing for territory, whether those creatures are monsters or people. These
“competitors” can be negotiated and traded with, but never fully trusted. And if
they threaten the tribe, the Tigerclaw think no more of raiding a human or elven
settlement than they would of cleaning out a nest of snakes or culling an uppity
wolf pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their society also has its own criminals and outlaws, too. Tribe members who
slay their kin or steal from the tribe are either put to death or exiled,
depending on the severity of the crime. Those who are exiled are known as the
Riven. Most of them are quite evil and resort to worship of evil spirits or
demons to survive when cut off from the tribe. While some live as lone hunters,
others band together in marauder groups who make a living raiding both their
former kin and the outsider communities found south of Winterbole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest of these groups is led by a shaman named Shadowfang, who was exiled
for worshipping a giant demon lord named Kostchtie. They are based west of the
Winter River and frequently go south to raid villages and towns. The Lord Warden
of Fallcrest has a standing bounty on Shadowfang’s head. The book doesn’t
mention whether the people of the Vale distinguish between Riven and standard
Tigerclaw, so you can vary your answer there depending on what sort of story you
want to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their biggest internal conflict right now comes from the fact that Chief
Scargash and his shamans are making a serious attempt at opening diplomatic
channels to the other sapient inhabitants of Winterbole: the Frost Witches, the
Treants, and Bitterstrike. This appears to be working, but it has the more
traditionalist of the Tigerblood worried because they fear this will make the
Hunter of Winter see them as “soft” and withdraw its gifts. In other words,
they’re like fighting and know successful diplomacy will leave them with less
excuses to pick fights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already saw how Bitterstrike and the Frost Witches see these attempts, and
we’ll look at the treants in a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get several stat blocks for Tigerclaw warriors here, spanning most of the
Heroic tier. I’ll look at them in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks are either humans or shifters. Shifters get low-light vision and
might have transformation-related abilities that kick in while they’re bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-hordling&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Hordling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likely a Tamed warrior of no particular distinction, this human is a Level 3
Minion Skirmisher. They attack with a battleaxe that crits on a 18-20, though
the damage increase from the critical is not spectacular since this is still a
minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-brave&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Brave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This human is a skilled warrior, which means they might one day undergo the
Tigerblood initiation ritual. They’re a Level 3 Soldier with 49 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Braves fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Broadsword&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and throw  &lt;strong&gt;Sabertooth Spears&lt;/strong&gt; at
range (they carry 2). The sword makes basic attacks that mark for a turn on a
hit. The spear targets Reflex and immobilizes for a turn on a hit. On a miss it
deals half damage and slows for a turn. This is not an at-will attack: it
recharges when the brave is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a marked enemy adjacent to the brave shifts, they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Sabertooth
Jab&lt;/strong&gt; to make a free sword attack against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-scout&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Scout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a shifter, which means they’re definitely a Tigerblood. They’re also a
Level 4 Skirmisher with 55 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scout is an &lt;strong&gt;Adept Charger&lt;/strong&gt;, which means they’re not limited to taking
only free actions after a charge. Their &lt;strong&gt;Razorclaw Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; power gives them a
+2 bonus to Speed and a +4 to defenses against opportunity attacks while
bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouts fight with paired &lt;strong&gt;Light Picks&lt;/strong&gt;, meant to invoke the image of a
sabertooth tiger’s fangs. They do an extra die of damage if used on a charge,
and can use a power named &lt;strong&gt;Sabertooth Strike&lt;/strong&gt; to attack two different targets
at once. This recharges as long as at least one of the attacks misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy ends its movement in a square where it flanks the scout, the scout
can use &lt;strong&gt;Wild Instinct&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to shift 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-fang-wielder&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Fang-Wielder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shifter is a Level 5 Brute with 77 HP. They use a &lt;strong&gt;heavy war pick&lt;/strong&gt;, whose
attacks to extra damage while they’re bloodied. It can also be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Fang
of the Sabertooth&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge 5+), which does heavy damage, knocks
prone, and on a critical hit inflicts 5 ongoing damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Fang-Wielder first becomes bloodied, they use a reaction named
&lt;strong&gt;Winter’s Rage&lt;/strong&gt;, which is an attack on a Close Burst 1 that damages and knocks
prone on a hit, does half damage on a miss, and pushes 1 square as an effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fang-Wielders want to charge right in and actually like getting surrounded by
melee PCs, because all of their best traits kick in when they’re bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-shaman&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Shaman&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These shifters act as spiritual advisors and general spellcasters for the
Tigerclaw. They’re Level 5 Controllers with 52 HP. In combat they use a
&lt;strong&gt;Longspear&lt;/strong&gt; and some mind-affecting magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes the &lt;strong&gt;Phantom Fangs&lt;/strong&gt; at-will spell, which on a hit does psychic
damage and immobilizes for a turn, and on a miss slows for a turn. It also
includes the &lt;strong&gt;Concussive Roar&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, a minor action that attacks a
Close Blast 3 and on a hit pushes targets 3 squares and immobilizes them. On a
miss it pushes 1 square instead, but in either case it does no damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sabertooth-tiger&quot;&gt;Sabertooth Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, as implied in the lore the Tigerclaw make use of sabertooth tigers as
pets. Tigerblood candidates have to tame a wild tiger as part of their
initiation, and I imagine they also breed and raise tigers to accompany
hereditary Tigerbloods. An encounter involving Tigerclaw members is also likely
to involve these beasties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabertooth Tigers are Large Natural Beasts with the Mount keyword and Level 6
Soldiers with 72 HP. They have a ground speed of 8 and a climb speed of 4. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Charging Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; trait works like the scout’s Adept Charger, letting them
make any type of action after a charge. And their &lt;strong&gt;Tiger Charge&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives a
+2 damage bonus to the charge attacks of their rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do extra damage on a charge, and grab on a hit (escape DC
15). If the tiger has a grabbed victim, it can only bite that victim. It can
also use &lt;strong&gt;Puncturing Fangs&lt;/strong&gt; against them. This hits automatically, does some
physical damage, and inflicts ongoing 5 damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tigers are higher level than most of the humanoids in this entry, but this is
not a problem because ever since the Monster Vault mount monsters no longer have
to be of equal or lower level than their riders. You can safely drop this
restriction from all older monsters as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tigers want to charge in, grab someone, and keep using Puncturing Fangs on
them, preferrably while their rider attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scargash-tigerclaw-chief&quot;&gt;Scargash, Tigerclaw Chief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scargash seems to be a fairly typical Tigerclaw chief as far as stats go. You
could use the same stats for chiefs of other tribes if any appear in your
game. He’s a shifter, of course, and a Level 6 Elite Brute with the Leader tag
and 176 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scargash gains a +2 bonus to all of his defenses while bloodied, and his
leadership style expresses itself as an aura (5) named &lt;strong&gt;Encircle the Prey&lt;/strong&gt;,
which grants allies +2 to damage on attacks against targets they are flanking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;strong&gt;War Pick&lt;/strong&gt; inflicts ongoing damage on a hit and can be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. If both of those attacks hit the target also suffers a -2 penalty to
all defenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His encounter power is a &lt;strong&gt;Staggering Swipe&lt;/strong&gt; that damages the target and does
half damage on a miss. As an &lt;em&gt;effect&lt;/em&gt;, it also slides the target 3 squares to a
space adjacent to one or more other enemies. Those enemies take an automatic 10
damage and fall prone as the flung target bowls into them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;primal-sabertooth-tiger&quot;&gt;Primal Sabertooth Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of majestic mount a Tigerclaw chief would ride into battle. They could
be extraordinary mundane specimens, but are likely somehow blessed by the Hunter
in Winter either naturally or via Tigerclaw rituals. Primal sabertooths are Huge
Natural Beasts with the Mount keyword and Level 8 Elite Soldiers with 178 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have the same Charging Pounce trait as their smaller relatives, and also
have Threatening Reach 2. Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that damages
and inflicts 5 ongoing damage. If the target was already taking ongoing damage,
this inflicts 10 ongoing damage instead. This means that a second claw attack on
the same target will worsen their ongoing damage, or that a first attack will
already inflict the worse condition if the target was taking ongoing 5 damage
from another source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primal tiger’s &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; is a minor action. It does light damage and grabs
with escape DC 20. The tiger can pull the victim along when it moves without
provoking opportunity attacks from the victim. Only one victim may be grabbed at
a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Go For the Kill&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which targets Reflex,
deals heavy damage, knocks prone, and gives the tiger 5 temporary HP if the
attack bloodies the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the tiger hits 0 HP, it can shift its speed and use Go For The Kill one
last time. If this reduces the target to 0 HP, the tiger heals back to 20 HP
instead of dying. This ability, called &lt;strong&gt;Fierce Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;, is an encounter power,
so the tiger can’t use it again in the same fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book uses the word “barbarian” a lot, but I’ve avoided doing it here. I
suppose they’re barbarians in the D&amp;amp;D class sense, but I wouldn’t want to use
the rest of that word’s baggage with them. And if I included the Tigerclaw in a
game, I’d definitely remove the bit where they raid other communities for
“worthy mates”. It’s still a bad trope no matter how you look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing that shitty trope leaves you with a fairly complex people as far as D&amp;amp;D
cultures go. They’re not likely to be very friendly to outsider PCs, but they
have good reasons for their suspicion. Outsiders can still interact with them in
peaceful ways with a bit of work, and they would make a good origin culture for
martial or primal PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Bitterstrike decides to go a-conquering, she’ll want to force Scargash’s
tribe to act as her front-line troops. I imagine their traditionalists will
welcome this since it will mean an end to diplomacy followed by lots of battles,
but most of the tribe would resent serving under the dragon and/or being
manipulated by Frost Witches who would surely be the secret instigators of the
whole thing. They’re the first troops you fight, but they’re also the weak link
you work in order to dismantle the Army of Winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowfang’s bunch makes for a much less ambiguous enemy faction, but PCs who
like to go for the diplomatic solution would still have plenty to do in a
scenario where the people of Winterhaven and Fallcrest had trouble telling them
apart from other Tigerclaw and directed their enmity at all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/25/tigerclaw-barbarians.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/25/tigerclaw-barbarians.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
