<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 20:12:45 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 20:12:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Xinlenal and Related Locations</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post covers the city itself and several nearby locations related to the
Gray Wolf Uthgardt, who serve the Netherese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-warning-brutal-savages-nonsense&quot;&gt;Content Warning: “Brutal Savages” nonsense&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of Gray Wolf material in this section, and this is where the
mounting inconsistencies in their portrayal start to get in the way. The stuff
about them that I read so far gave me the impression of a people who were mostly
minding their own business before the Netherese turned their leaders into
fascist assholes. Most of the actual tribe members were not happy with the
situation: a significant number of them had defected, and those who hadn’t were
open to persuasion by a PC like the Pack Outcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section drops most of that and goes all in on the “brutal savages who
disdain civilization” cliches, painting the Gray Wolf as being bad guys even
before the Netherese got to them. After being co-opted, they got even worse.
Anyone who’s still a member of the tribe at this point is either on board with
the cruelty or too cowardly to ever stand against it. Even their guardian
spirits are disgusted with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to report what the book says below, but I personally would completely
change it were I to run a Neverwinter campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;xinlenal-from-the-outside-in&quot;&gt;Xinlenal From the Outside In&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw before, Xinlenal wasn’t just a Netherese flying city, it was the first
ever built. It fell here in the Wood when Netheril’s magic stopped
working. Today, when viewed from the outside, it looks like an out-of-place
60-foot tall plateau jutting up from the ground in an otherwise flat area of the
Wood. The structures atop it are hidden from view by the Wood’s vegetation,
which grew over it in the two millennia since the city crashed. The Shadovar led
by Prince Clariburnus use Xinlenal as their main base of operations in the
region, and are hard at work trying to make it fly again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-forest-of-hides&quot;&gt;The Forest of Hides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gray Wolf recognize this is the center of Netherese power even though they
don’t know what goes on in here. So when they declared war on the Forsworn, they
started hanging up the skins of their “traitorous kinfolk” in a clearing outside
the plateau. This acts as both a warning to enemies and as a show of support for
their new masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the sheer brutality of this practice has led many rank-and-file Gray
Wolf to question their leadership, and the horrible smell of dead werewolf
lingering about the place acts as a cover for Forsworn spies and makes it easier
for them to scout the plateau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act of building the Forest of Hides outraged and horrified many of the
primal spirits who used to be friends of the Grey Wolf. If the Pack Outcast,
Uthgardt Barbarian, or any other PC who uses primal powers dismantle the Forest
of Hides, those spirits will reward them with a daily power named &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the
Fallen&lt;/strong&gt;, which can be activated after an attack hits and makes the target
vulnerable 5 to all damage (save ends), including that of the triggering
attack. Once the target saves, they take another 10 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you see the first instance of what I talked about in the intro paragraphs
above. There’s more below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-city-and-the-web-of-stone&quot;&gt;The City and the Web of Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The walls of the plateau are a sheer climb, but they look natural after two
millennia of weathering. Some flying monsters even made lairs there. The city at
the top looks completely ruined when viewed from the plateau’s edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those moving towards the center will soon spot a massive suspended “web” made of
stone looming over the skyline. This acts as a gigantic crane and construction
tool used in the Shadovar’s renovation efforts. It can lift whole city blocks
for relocation, or remove an equivalent quantity of soil and vegetation to
reveal the structures buried beneath. Workers both organic and artificial are
constantly swarming all over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This web was built by the shadar-kai witch Korvina, who realized she could use
residual energy from the city’s old protection rituals to power it. Later she
would find out she was actually drawing power from the city’s broken mythallar
and delaying its repairs. When her bosses found out about the oopsie, she
managed to pin the blame for it on her colleague Qualthus, whose fate we’ll
learn in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-womb-of-stone&quot;&gt;The Womb of Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gee, these Netherese sure have a knack for naming things, don’t they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This building is an ancient construct factory reactivated by the Shadovar. This
is where they build all the thaalud constructs they’re using as a workforce. The
ones they build today aren’t as powerful as the ones from ancient Netheril
(using the thaalud constructor stat block from earlier in this book), but they
can do their job just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Womb of Stone is run and operated by a shade named Ulrukan (stats as a human
slaver with shade traits). His left arm and leg are animated prosthetic
constructs, which I think is awesome. Ulrukan discovered the problem with the
Web of Stone before anyone else, decided to keep it to himself until he could
gain something by revealing it, and lost the chance to do so when other people
found the issue and reported it immediately. Now that it’s public he’s trying to
figure out how to extract some advantage from the fact that he knew it before
anyone else did. I don’t think he knows it’s Korvina’s fault, or he’d already be
blackmailing her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cathedral-of-night&quot;&gt;Cathedral of Night&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a ancient building repurposed as a temple to the goddess Shar. The
exterior is still ruined and worn, but the interior is very fancy and all done
up in onyx and jet. It’s also protected by enchanted hungry shadows, a very
interesting hazard that can temporarily remove PCs from play and cause ongoing
psychic and necrotic damage to them while they’re gone. This security protects
the usual temple treasures and also a portal to the Shadowfell, which is used by
the Shadovar to access their supply routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthinos Eln is the priest in charge of both the temple and the restoration
project. He can be found here either meditating or communing with his boss
Prince Clariburnus, who leads the faction as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xinlenals-heart&quot;&gt;Xinlenal’s Heart&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt; is located at its very center. The tower that houses it
was the first building to be completely restored, and a small army of Shadovar
artificers is now busy restoring the artifact itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restoration process is simple to describe but very hard to execute. It
consists of mixing melted glass with large quantities of residuum, carefully
pouring the resulting substance over the &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt;, and molding it so that it
slowly recovers its original spherical shape. Right now it looks like a partial
sphere, already over 100 feet (30 meters!) in diameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the Netherese are scouring the region’s many ruins and dungeons for
magic items and other ancient enchanted relics, and also why they’re poised to
begin raiding Neverwinter. All of that loot is going to get destroyed for its
residuum. The Shadovar are burning the legacies of others to rebuild their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central tower is also where their main war room is located, as well as
Clariburnus’ quarters and throne room. He can either be found here coordinating
the faction’s overall strategy, or somewhere out in the world leading another
raid for magic items. He also sometimes brings members of the Gray Wolf
leadership here for briefings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vellosk&quot;&gt;Vellosk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the main “settlement” of the Gray Wolf tribe, located in the Wood away
from Xinlenal. The quotes are there because they are mostly nomadic, and this is
just where a few more permanent structures are built - pack leader’s homes, a
feast hall, and some other communal buildings. You can also find a number of
tents and lean-tos scattered around the area, belonging to other tribe members
who are currently staying there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book says the Grey Wolf have the technology to make weapons and tools as
sophisticated as that of Neverwinter, but that they have no real culture to
speak of beyond an obsession with behaving like D&amp;amp;D’s idea of a wolf pack. It
could be that this is what the current leadership thinks, but the way the book
phrases it kinda makes me think this is what they were like even before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vellosk’s central feature is a sloped pit whose bottom is coated in dry bones,
and also contains a totem pole decorated with animal skulls. This is their
center of worship, dedicated to Uthgar and the tribe’s guardian spirits. It’s
also where ritual combats and duels happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the permanent structures here is the home of Ormshas, a dark creeper
necromancer who is here officially as a Netherese ambassador and in reality as a
spy placed to make sure the Grey World remain under control. She has a large
group of wraiths under her control, which she uses to uncover secrets and
silence dissenters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gray-wolf-and-the-pcs&quot;&gt;The Gray Wolf and the PCs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the rank-and-file Grey Wolf are very unhappy with the direction the
tribe is taking, but they also believe their leaders’ commands are absolute and
those leaders have been completely bought the Netherese party line. Many tribe
members would rather leave than try to challenge their leaders, but these days
those who express a desire to leave are executed on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs such as the Pack Outcast or the Uthgardt Barbarian would have an easier time
convincing the Grey Wolf to reject their leadership, but they would still need
to challenge those leaders to ritual combat and win (or convince/help a friendly
Gray Wolf to do so). Ritual combat is, of course, to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a legitimate challenge would also require convincing a majority of the
tribe that their leaders are being bamboozled by the Netherese. Just going for
the leaders at once is a sure way to get the whole tribe to declare war on you
no matter what they think about those leaders, so it’s not a good option for
most groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conyberry&quot;&gt;Conyberry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conyberry is a small village at the edge of the Wood that became quite scenic
during the Spellplague when a populated slice of Abeir was isekaied there. It
gained a new lake, a bunch of floating earthmotes, and a mixed population that
learned to live well together after some initial friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately you don’t get to see that version of it, because the Grey Wolf
killed everyone long before the Netherese even got to them. According to the
book they believed the people from Abeir to be hostile invaders and the people
of Conyberry to be their co-conspirators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gray Wolf used the now empty village as a storage area for a time. No one
else went there because everyone (rightly) assumed it had been destroyed after
news stopped coming, and when someone did stumble into the place they were
killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Netherese recruited them they started using the village to, in the
words of the book, “practice civilized behavior” so that they would blend into
the communities they were ordered to infiltrate. Now when outsiders end up there
by accident they’re received by a bunch of Gray Wolf in sheep’s clothing eager
to test their acting skills. Only after the actors are satisfied, or when
they’re found out, do the murder attempts start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xinlenal itself seems like a good dungeon location. A final battle against
Caliburnus in the &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt; chamber would look awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But everything about the description of the Gray Wolf kinda ruins it. The text
is filled with the exact set of racist tropes that draw so much criticism to
D&amp;amp;D. I’m left with the distinct impression that the Gray Wolf are described as
being bad &lt;em&gt;because they’re tribal&lt;/em&gt;, in contrast to the “civilized” people they
disdain and victimize. Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s definitely something I’d completely rewrite if I ever ran a campaign in
this setting. It actually kinda tainted the good memories I had of this book,
and made me stop writing new Let’s Read material for it for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/01/neverwinter-xinlenal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/01/neverwinter-xinlenal.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Dread Ring</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the gloomiest and darkest part of the Wood, there’s a perfectly circular
clearing whose ground is ash. None of the Wood’s animals dare enter this
place. This is where the Dread Ring was built. It was both a fortress and a
ritual tool for a grand spell that would have turned Szass Tam into a
god. Though the spell failed, the ruined fortress now serves as the main base
for the Thayans in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire area of the Ring, both indoors and outdoors, is &lt;em&gt;super cursed&lt;/em&gt;. Check
it out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It counts as both defiled and necrotic ground, the rules for which are found
in the DMG 2. Basically, undead are boosted and HP gains from spending healing
surges are halved.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Powers with either the arcane or necrotic keywords crit on 19-20. Powers with
both keywords crit on 18-20. This is one of the only instances of “critical
range” boosting in the entire game, it’s an extremely rare bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Creatures take -1 to Will against powers or effects with the fear keyword.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is also Lorragauth’s grave, some smaller areas in here might also
count as acid-based fonts of power or elemental spouts, making them even more
hazardous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ring-from-the-outside-in&quot;&gt;The Ring from the Outside In&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequent clashes between Shadovar and Thayan forces have turned the outer areas
of the clearing into a blood-soaked battlefield littered with corpses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the ruined outer walls is the &lt;strong&gt;Flesh Factory&lt;/strong&gt;, where corpses,
body parts, and sometimes living victims are stored and used as materials for
Thayan necromancy and flesh-shaping projects. The place’s design lets it raise
undead at a much faster pace and a much larger scale than usual, effectively
mass-producing them. This is where most of the Thayan undead are made, and also
the facility in charge of repairing the fortress’ walls. Instead of bothering
with the logistics of procuring and shipping stone, they decided to patch the
walls with slabs of undead flesh. These walls get a stat block as a trap,
because they can sprout grabby hands that deal damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past the Factory are the &lt;strong&gt;halls of the fortress&lt;/strong&gt;, which follow no plan a
living mind would consider sane since their main purpose was to act as a ritual
tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The center is open, and it’s the current site of the &lt;strong&gt;Thayan excavation&lt;/strong&gt;
that’s trying to reach Lorragauth’s resting place. They’ve managed to reach his
bones and partially unearthed them already, but there’s plenty of work to do
before they’re free of the soil. The excavation pit is deep and hazardous, and
the book has rules for navigating it and for operating the many cranes installed
here during combat to either drop rocks on enemies or slam the crane arm into
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The undead workforce here doubles as the Dread Ring’s garrison, so they get
depleted to a, er, skeleton crew when the Netherese attack. They’re overseen by
Praddak, an battle wight (stats in DMG 2). Also here as protection is the sacred
totem of the Thunderbeast tribe, which as we saw before was a fossilized
thunderbeast skeleton. It’s been animated by necromancy, with the stats of a
rotclaw (an undead monster from the Draconomicon). This of course is a horrible
blasphemy, particularly to the Uthgardt Barbarian PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere near the pit is the &lt;strong&gt;Dread Spire&lt;/strong&gt;, the tallest surviving tower of
the Ring. It houses the Thayan war room, the entrance to Valindra’s sanctum, and
a perpetually dark room that contains a portal to the Shadowfell. It also
contains the Chapel of the Dragon, where Kroskas’ cultists research how to raise
Lorragauth as a dracolich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shadowfell portal is what lets the Thayans bring corpses from Neverdeath
Cemetery for reanimation, and to receive caravans that come from Surcross via
the Shadowfell Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valindra’s Sanctum&lt;/strong&gt; houses her library and an arcane observatory that lets
someone scry remote locations and perform astrological divination. It’s operated
by Lurrens, one of her lieutenants, who watches it 24/7. Lurrens is a former
wizard who was turned into an undead Brain in an Armored Jar (from Open Grave).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The observatory’s grinding machinery is hazardous terrain, should a fight break
out here. PCs might find information on Gauntlgrym and other campaign secrets by
either researching Valindra’s library or learning how to operate the
observatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to my earlier expectations the Dread Ring cannot rise as a floating
battlestation or giant undead mech, though the possibility of them raising a
dracolich is a decent substitute. The place is perfectly usable as an endgame
dungeon, though it could also end up being “just” an important stop on the way
to Gauntlgrym depending on the campaign’s focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I have to say “Brain in an Armored Jar” is the best monster name ever.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/28/neverwinter-dread-ring.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/28/neverwinter-dread-ring.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Ruins of Shandarar</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-errata&quot;&gt;Historical Errata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I continue, I feel a correction is in order. This one’s on me, not on the
book, since it was a detail from that long and detailed timeline at the start
that I missed. I’m correcting it here because it will be important later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know, Shandarar was the former capital of Iliyanbruen, an
elven/eladrin empire that existed in this region thousands of years ago. It
coexisted with the human empire of Netheril, and witnessed its fall when the
flying city of Xinlenal fell on the Neverwinter Wood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bit I got wrong was this: the fall of Xinlenal did not also cause the end of
Iliyanbruen. The crash site was far from the city, and though the elves explored
it soon after the event they decided to declare it off-limits after the first
few explosions and carried on with their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iliyanbruen would last for a few centuries longer. They’d manage to repel a
massive orc invasion that covered the North, but their kingdom would collapse
from the effort it spent to kick those same orcs out of the human city of Illusk
(located where Luskan is today). From here on out things proceed as previously
detailed, with the empire’s population scattering and some of them deciding to
take refuge in the Feywild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;present-day-shandarar&quot;&gt;Present-Day Shandarar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The middle world ruins of Shandarar cover a sizable area in the Wood but were
mostly hidden by the passage of time and the growth of vegetation. Sometimes a
farmer at the edges of the forest would find shards of pottery as they plowed a
field, or some village builders would end up unearthing a ruined
structure. These rumors helped the Netherese find the core of the ruins and
steal a bunch of ancient relics from it, which has the eladrin in a tizzy as we
already learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the ruins are still, well, ruins. They’re overgrown and weathered enough
to be hazardous. The oldest part of them, however, is being rebuilt and
renovated by the eladrin, since that’s where they crossed over from the Feywild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest news here is that there are still several shielded vaults in the
ruins that haven’t been found out by anyone yet. They contain extensive troves
of ancient Iliyanbruen artifacts and works of art, of immense cultural value
even when they aren’t magical, all protected against the ravages of time by
stasis spells. The eladrin themselves don’t remember their locations, and this
is the first time the book itself mentions them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is also where it goes into a little more detail on the Feywild side of the
crossing. That’s where the military outpost of New Shandarar is. It was also
built on top of ruins, after the eladrin force kicked out the evil fey that had
been living in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Shandarar’s fortifications are living vegetation shaped by magic, and the
portal opens into a courtyard kill zone. Aside from all the military defenses
you expect, built of out living and magically reinforced wood, the fort also has
plenty of facilities for long-term habitation. This includes a temple to
Corellon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hidden-serpent&quot;&gt;The Hidden Serpent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw before, Merrisara Winterwhite, the force’s commanding officer, is part
of their moderate faction. She spends most of her time in the middle world
overseeing the restoration of the city. Her second-in-command is an extremist,
and spends all of his time in the Feywild. Addemios Three-Dawn, the secret
Asmodeus worshiper, also spends all his time in the Feywild. He has a hidden
shrine to his god underneath Corellon’s temple. The evil fey who were
supposedly kicked out of the area have a hidden camp not too far from the fort,
and they cooperate with Three-Dawn because their interests align.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A side box here explains that Asmodeus presents himself in the Feywild as a
trickster god of a “better class” than the usual archetypes found there. Instead
of lying and cheating for the lulz, he encourages and teaches his followers to
do so in order to advance their own power and influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fey-and-the-pcs&quot;&gt;The Fey and the PCs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another box discusses the possible attitudes of the eladrin towards PCs. As we
already known even the moderates are standoffish and aggressive to outsiders by
default. However, they are likely have a more diplomatic stance towards a party
which includes the Iliyanbruen Guardian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the two sub-factions wins out depends largely on the actions of the
PCs. The moderates win and might become valuable allies if the PCs can offer
them evidence that the Shadovar are responsible for the relic thefts, or if they
can prove Addemios Three-Dawn is a traitor who is manipulating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if the PCs steal from the ruins, fight the eladrin or attack
Three-Dawn before proving his guilt, the Fey will adopt the extremist stance and
launch a full-scale invasion of the region, likely starting a major open war
with the other factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How important the fey of New Shandarar are depends entirely on what the group
wants for their campaign. They could be anywhere from isolated and irrelevant to
a potential region-wide threat that needs to be defused as soon as
possible. Even groups who aren’t interested in spending a lot of time dealing
with these elves might still get an adventure or two out of a visit to their
camp, perhaps as they’re traveling the Wood on the way to some other location
therein.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/24/neverwinter-shandarar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/24/neverwinter-shandarar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Neverwinter Woods</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Neverwinter Wood dominates the northern half of our regional map and is much
larger than the city that gives it its name. It’s a classic Creepy Forest, where
the canopies block out all sunlight and even in the safer trails it seems like
someone is always watching you from the shadows. And that’s just the baseline
mood - the Wood is also currently full of ill-intentioned outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters in a Neverwinter campaign might need to trek through this place for
any number of reasons. This section of the chapter covers some of the Wood’s
most notable places, but it’s large enough that you could run a full
hex-crawling campaign on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book actually includes rules for a “Creepy Woods” hazardous terrain type
that can be included in exploration or combat maps. Anyone on this terrain when
a fight starts must roll a save before rolling Initiative - if they fail,
they’re surprised during the first round. They also gain a -2 to Will while on
Creepy spaces and when they fail a Perception check there they always think they
heard something that’s not there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first post covers the “smaller” areas and “standard” geographical features
of the Woods. It also contains several faction strongholds that will each get
their own post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-crags&quot;&gt;The Crags&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a large mountain range that splits the Wood in two, running from NE to
SW. Mount Hotenow is the most notable place in the Crags, as it’s where the
Neverwinter River starts and also the source of the eruption that caused the
cataclysm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more besides the volcano though - this is a typical D&amp;amp;D mountain
range full of monsters, caves, and hidden valleys and is also rumored to contain
paths to lost Gauntlgrym. Whether those exist or not, the range does definitely
contain a lot of old Delzoun outposts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those outposts will give the Heir of Delzoun something to marvel at even if they
don’t find a path to the lost city here. They’re also targets for Netherese
plundering in their unceasing quest for magic items to burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iceless-waterways&quot;&gt;Iceless Waterways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Wood’s rivers are warmed by Hotenow’s heat, so they never freeze even
during winter, and generally act to keep the forest warm and untouched by the
seasons. They teem with non-monstrous aquatic wildlife but never gave rise to
monsters - except for the River Morgur, the northernmost tributary of the
Neverwinter. It’s still iceless, but also has river monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bones-of-thundertree&quot;&gt;Bones of Thundertree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thundertree used to be a logging village that produced a lot of quality
timber. It was completely destroyed by the eruption, and all of its surviving
inhabitants fled to never return. The place is now haunted by possessed plant
monsters (take plant monster stat blocks of your choice and give them undead
traits). Aside from them, only the dwarf Favria, leader of the more violent
faction of the Ashmadai, calls this place home. She lives in an underground wine
cellar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was given to understand her whole Ashmadai sub-faction used this place as a
base, so it looks like there was a miscommunication between different authors
here. I’d probably add them here if I ran a Neverwinter campaign. Maybe say
those plant monsters are possessed by &lt;em&gt;devils&lt;/em&gt; instead of undead. How do you
like evil treants with 20 fire resistance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tower-of-twilight&quot;&gt;The Tower of Twilight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There used to be a wizard’s tower built in the middle of a lake island. It, and
the bridge leading to it, only appeared at night, becoming more solid as the sun
set and fading out again when it rose. During the Spellplague, the tower
vanished entirely and did not return until after the cataclysm. Now, it appears
sporadically with no set schedule, and no one knows what goes on in there
anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One suggestion from the book is that the tower fades out of &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; when it’s not
visible in the physical world, and the people inside only experience the passage
of time when it appears. This mean that the tower’s wizard and their apprentices
and staff might still be there, either absorbed in their studies as if this was
still 3e or struggling with what is to them a very recent bout of “original
strain” Spellplague.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/22/neverwinter-woods.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/22/neverwinter-woods.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Helm's Hold</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re getting outside of the city proper now! Helm’s Hold is a small town
located on the edge of the Neverwinter Wood, built around a monastery and
cathedral dedicated to the god Helm. It’s about a day’s travel northeast of
Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The town’s proximity to the Wood and its traditions of rugged individualism give
it big “American frontier” vibes, tempered a bit by the monastery’s own
culture. Helm used to be the god of guardians, and the monastery’s purpose since
its ancient founding is to give sanctuary to those who have none. The monastery
came first, and the town slowly grew around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year before the Spellplague, when the inhabitants had just laid the
foundation for the cathedral, Helm died. The grieving priests and citizens
finished the huge building as a monument in his honor, and kept its purpose as a
sanctuary, welcoming people of all faiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience of Helm’s Hold from the computer games and reading this book is
that the place’s narrative purpose is to be infiltrated and secretly taken over
by the current campaign’s Big Bads. It happened in the first computer game
(ancient underground civilization), it happened again shortly before the
Spellplague (Netherese), and now it’s happening once more (the aboleths). We’re
headed for a plot pileup here because the Netherese are also trying to
infiltrate the town anew, via their werewolf minions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lurking-threats&quot;&gt;Lurking Threats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those mysterious disappearances and murders are caused not by the spellscarred,
but by the Grey Wolf Uthgardt, who have been ordered by their Netherese masters
to infiltrate the town and cause chaos. They’re proficient at disguising
themselves as locals or pilgrims, which lets them get into position to wolf out
at night and go hunting. The core of their force hides out in the Wood. The
Netherese don’t think the Hold is strategically valuable, they just want to keep
the barbarians occupied until they’re needed in their true function as
expendable muscle to throw against the Thayans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two barbarian-themed PCs are quite likely to end up here, and a peaceful
resolution to the Grey Wolf plot would involve convincing them the Netherese are
both evil and not interested in the tribe’s well-being. This has to be done
subtly, though, as they are likely to attack the Pack Outcast on sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course there’s also the cathedral itself, which is currently being run by
Rohini’s group and thus is a secret aboleth center of power. No one else knows
about this currently, though ironically the AbSov is also interested in solving
the murders because it will reduce the suspicion currently directed at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hold-and-environs&quot;&gt;The Hold and Environs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hold’s mission as a sanctuary turned into the region’s premier treatment
center for Spellplague victims, a duty which only became heavier about a year
ago when Lord Neverember made it his official policy to send any such victims he
finds in Neverwinter to the cathedral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the region tends to see the spellscarred as dangerous freaks, but
the inhabitants of the Hold see them as unfortunate victims affected by a
horrible curse. Still, the overwhelming influx of new patients has been testing
their open stance, as the city had to do a lot of rush construction to
accommodate them all, with limited success. You can find newer buildings
haphazardly constructed between older structures, their quality dubious due to
the Hold’s chronic labor shortage. Most skilled builders are over on
Neverwinter, where the work pays better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hold’s citizens are further stressed out by the recent spate of mysterious
murders and disappearances, which the more conservative among them have started
blaming on the spellscarred. A group of spellscarred activists calling
themselves the Heirs of Azure has sprung up to try to counter the distrust
heaped upon their community. However, the Mintarn detachment sent by Neverember
to help keep the peace isn’t having much success tracking down the real
culprits, tensions keep increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is governed by a council of elected Speakers who meet at a former
tavern named The Dragon’s Gauntlet. They’re also split on the issue of the
spellscarred, though the official stance is still receptive since current Chief
Speaker is in that camp. The council’s collective power is waning, as there are
enough mercs in town that they could declare martial law unopposed. Their
commander, however, is uncharacteristically responsible and dutiful, so the
order won’t come from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heartward&quot;&gt;Heartward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market plaza, so named because there’s a shrine to Sune here. Fights are
frequent because resources are scarce and prices high. Every now and then, at
night, a major haunting happens here and a bunch of ghosts goes through the
motions of market life. Some crew the stalls, some walk around making purchase
and talk to each other. Most of their words are gibberish, but some are
prophetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-dirty-dwarf&quot;&gt;Old Dirty Dwarf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And old, respected, and dirty tavern, with a reputation as the place for new
arrivals to go in order to get the lay of the land and hear the latest news from
the Hold. The owner is friendly to the spellscarred, but some of the staff
aren’t. Agents of the Prophet keep an eye here at all times and report news to
their boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scar-alley&quot;&gt;Scar Alley&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ground under this neighborhood softened during the Spellplague, causing many
of its buildings to sink and crack. Nowadays it’s a barely-standing,
precariously-patrolled slum that is home to the most deformed of the
spellscarred, those even the Hold shuns. It’s also filled with shady characters
and the occasional monster hiding out in an abandoned ruin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;helms-cathedral&quot;&gt;Helm’s Cathedral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aging faithful of Helm’s Cathedral now share it with a contingent of Oghma’s
priests who arrived to set up a sanatorium for spellscarred patients. Brother
Satarin commands the former: he’s a 160 year old dwarf who was an acolyte before
Helm’s death. Rohini the Prophet officially commands the latter, and is the de
facto boss of the whole place. As we learned a few posts ago, she’s a former
succubus turned aberrant creature, and serves the Abolethic Sovereignity, as do
all her subordinates. She holds the loyalty of Helm’s old priests because some
of her (fake) prophecies hint at his return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface levels of the cathedral are airy and well-lit. The underground is
far less pleasant and houses the sanatorium for the most “severe” cases. Rohini
spends a lot of time down there “treating” them (i.e, turning them into
foulspawn). They go out for exercise every day, and the foulspawn among them are
only detectable as such by people specifically looking for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-warrens&quot;&gt;The Warrens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a failed attempt to expand the city’s drainage system, abandoned when
the dig broke into the monastery’s old crypts and was overwhelmed by
monsters. It became a kind of unofficial sanatorium for monstrous humanoids
afflicted by the plague, who find no acceptance even in a tolerant city such as
this. Goblins, kobolds and others venture into the city to steal food for
themselves, and this has given rise to rumors of fey hauntings. I think it still
connects to the rest of the crypts, described below, and would be a good
alternate route for parties who want to sneak in. I’d probably run that as a
negotiation focused adventure rather than a classic murdery crawl, at least
until the PCs get to the crypts where the actual bad guys are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crypts-of-the-vigilant-eye&quot;&gt;Crypts of the Vigilant Eye&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These crypts lie beneath the Cathedral, and predate its construction. Though the
levels closer to the surface were clearly used by priests of Helm from the older
monastery, things get more ancient and mysterious the deeper you go. There’s a
big vertical pit full of side niches that could only be reached by flight or
teleportation, and is now full of gargoyles. There’s a hallway full of gigantic
robed skeleton statues that don’t resemble any sort of Helmite iconography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all that is without counting the twisting of the place by Spellplague
energies and its current occupation by AbSov agents and foulspawn. Or the
trapped Grey Wolf recon force that still hasn’t managed to find a way out
through all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deepest levels turn into caverns that were excavated and mutated by the
Symphony of Madness, turning into a fungal underground swamp. These are
Chartilifax’s hunting grounds, so they probably contain all sorts of creatures
that are tasty to dragons and dangerous to adventurers. From here you can enter
a pulsating tunnel to the brain-like chamber containing the Hex Locus, a bronze
coffer that acts as a repeater for the Symphony of Madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Locus chamber can also be reached via a teleportation circle somewhere in
the crypt levels, and Rohini will use that as soon as she learns someone is
inside. She is linked to the artifact and can feel when someone enters its
room. This is likely where any final confrontation against her and her pet
dragon will occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot-hooks&quot;&gt;Plot Hooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spellscarred Harbinger will most likely be told to go here soon after the
campaign starts. The Pack Outcast and Uthgardt Barbarian’s pursuit of the Grey
Wolf might also bring them here early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s werewolf problem and the creepy happenings at the cathedral should be
obvious enough to get the PCs investigating, and the growing tension between
locals and refugees would make a fine secondary plot line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rohini herself would not appear immediately villainous - she would instead
attempt to coopt the PCs and get them to help with her goals. By default that’s
serving the AbSov, but the book offers a few alternatives. Perhaps she wants to
break free of them and would secretly help them destroy the Hex Locus instead of
protecting it. She is of course still a devil, so she might double-cross the PCs
once she has what she wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent of that, Mordai Vell is working hard to woo her, aware that she’s a
devil in disguise but unaware of all the rest. So &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; might hire the PCs as
go-betweens in his courtship efforts. That’d be a fun way to introduce the AbSov
and Ashmadai to the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to be fair and write a complete summary of the material in the book, but
the truth is that I have a hard time caring about what’s going on in the town of
Helm’s Hold proper. The original Neverwinter Nights computer game colors my
perceptions here - it skipped the “town” bit entirely and placed you directly
inside the monastery, which it treated as a dungeon. I only learned the Hold was
an actual town once I read this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like most campaigns will go a similar route, focusing all of their “urban
intrigue” creative energy on Neverwinter itself and treating the Hold as a
mostly-skipped prelude to the big delve into the cathedral and the crypts
beneath. On the other hand, it would also be possible to do the reverse and
ignore the big city depending on your party composition. There are several
themes that have more reason to start at the Hold than at Neverwinter, like the
Spellscarred Harbinger, the Uthgardt Barbarian, and the Pack Outcast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/18/neverwinter-helms-hold.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/18/neverwinter-helms-hold.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New project page!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been reading this blog for a while you’ll know that I’ve been doing a
Let’s Read of the Neverwinter Campaign Setting for D&amp;amp;D 4e. This has been
generally less organized than the ones I did for the monster manuals, and it
didn’t have a project page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, now it does! If you want to see all the Let’s Read Neverwinter posts
collected and neatly linked in one single place, then you can &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/neverwinter/&quot;&gt;head over
there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/new-project-page.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/new-project-page.html</guid>
        
        <category>meta</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Underground</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We already saw several underground danger spots in the city. Neverdeath
Cemetery, the dungeons of Castle Never, and of course the Chasm. But there are
even more beyond those. The Mintarn mercs usually stay on the surface, so every
one of these places can be considered “dungeon-like”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shattered-sewers&quot;&gt;Shattered Sewers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverwinter had an extensive sewer system that’s still largely ruined. It makes
for a great way to move about the entire city undetected, but it’s hazardous to
navigate and filled with both monsters and other people who don’t want to be
discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kraken-tunnels&quot;&gt;Kraken Tunnels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an underground complex with a floor plan that vaguely resembles an
octopus. It used to be the former headquarters of the Kraken Society, a criminal
syndicate specializing in slavery. Now it’s the headquarters for the Nashers
faction of the Sons of Alagondar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complex is build right above an underground canal that links to the sea, and
this canal is the home of an actual kraken. The Spellplague reduced the monster
to bestial intelligence. The Society used to feed it and keep it as a guardian
beast, and the Nashers have continued the practice. The complex has several
floor openings through which the creature can attack intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kraken was trained by the Society to recognize anyone bearing an amulet with
its symbol as a friend - it attacks all who &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have this amulet on
them. The Nashers know this and carry Kraken Society amulets with them when
inside the complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a tunnel here that links the Kraken Tunnels to the Dead Rats’ HQ through
the sewers, which the Nashers use to talk and trade with them. The Rats don’t
yet know the trick to avoiding the Kraken, but it’s just a matter of time until
they find out and attempt to take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible the Nashers might end up releasing the kraken into the river or
the docks as a sort of weapon of mass destruction if they become desperate
enough. The aboleths could also try to get to it in order to search its mind for
secrets from back when it was sapient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dead-rat-hole&quot;&gt;Dead Rat Hole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a section of the sewers that has been taken over by the Neverwinter
chapter of the Dead Rats. It’s marked with gang signs gouged into the sewer
walls, and packed with both loot and trash collected by the gangers. Their
leader, Rsolk, holds court at a set of caves near the shores of
Blacklake. There’s a trap here that can let the waters of the lake in and
“flush” the whole complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Dead Rats are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; familiar with the Dead Rat Deserter PC, contrary to
what I thought before. Looks like word hasn’t got to them yet. A bold Deserter
might try to infiltrate the gang and perhaps even challenge Rsolk for
leadership. This starts as a one-on-one duel but turns into a standard mass
fight once he’s bloodied. And of course he flushes the lair if it looks like his
side will lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tunnels-and-trenches&quot;&gt;Tunnels and Trenches&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sewers around the Chasm area are partly collapsed, forming trenches where
the street above was destroyed and tunnels where it hasn’t. This and the influx
of non-sapient monsters provides good cover for the AbSov’s smarter agents to
infiltrate the River District or to escape the city and head to Helm’s Hold and
other places.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 10:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/neverwinter-underground.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/neverwinter-underground.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Chasm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The southeast quadrant of Neverwinter is where a huge chasm opened during the
cataclysm, a chasm which has been disgorging a constant stream of mutant
monsters ever since. As if that wasn’t enough, staying near the rift for too
long also makes people go mad. The other quadrants of the city only survive
because they managed to isolate themselves from this one somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ruined-city&quot;&gt;The Ruined City&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a “bad part of town” like the River District. There’s nothing
“town-like” about this expanse of ruined buildings and twisted streets. By
setting foot in here you’re already on a proper dungeon delve. No one does this
much any more, since few who try ever return and those who do come back changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs might be hired to search for someone who vanished here. Or they might end up
sleepwalking here due to the Chasm’s influence and need to fight their way
out. If they have a Spellscarred Harbinger, that character is going to feel an
odd connection to the Chasm and a desire to explore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already learned from the faction descriptions, the Chasm goes all the way
down to the Underdark, where it opens on an underground lake whose bottom houses
a Spellplague pocket and the AbSov research base built around it. The
Plaguechanged monsters are projects and rejects created by the aboleths - they
have been growing more powerful and “efficient” as of late, as the creatures
improve their designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if no other reason draws the characters to explore the Chasm region, they
will eventually have to come here in a campaign where the AbSov is the greatest
threat. Getting to them requires not only traversing the ruined city on the
surface, but also going down the Chasm itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-upper-reach&quot;&gt;The Upper Reach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When descending the Chasm, the first few hundred feet might seem fairly mundane,
but after that the landscape starts resembling the Elemental Chaos or Abyss more
and more. Elemental energies surge up from the depths at irregular
intervals. The walls are harder to climb, with handholds appearing and vanishing
at random and occasional blasts of fire or wind erupting from them. Earthmotes
abound, some drifting slowly and others bashing against the walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monsters can be found climbing the walls or flying from the depths. Even those
who have no flying ability can be seen floating up in bolts of chaos magic,
particularly if they were sent to attack the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creeping-madness&quot;&gt;Creeping Madness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the Spellplague radiation is already so intense that characters
are already at risk of contracting Creeping Madness, a magical disease
similar to the plague itself. They must make a DC 10 Endurance check on every
short or long rest to avoid contracting it. Further resistance rolls also use
Endurance, with a Maintain DC of 10 and an Improve DC of 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stage 1 inflicts a -2 penalty to Will and Initiative, and a +1 bonus to psychic
attacks. Stage 2 eats a healing surge and inflicts -4 to Perception and
Insight. Stage 3 inflicts a -2 penalty to all skill checks, and makes the
victim’s attacks deal +1d6 psychic damage. Stage 4 drives you mad and makes you
permanently dazed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most diseases I think it’s possible to recover from the final stage
through Endurance rolls. If a character fully recovers from stage 3 or later,
they also gain a spellscar. The Spellscarred Harbinger has a +2 on all Endurance
checks against this disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-twisted-fane&quot;&gt;The Twisted Fane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the apparent bottom of the chasm, a broken wasteland whose rock pulses
as if it was alive. There’s an alien-looking black fortress here, the Twisted
Fane, which is built around an eerily shining crystal. The Fane is guarded by a
colony of fouslpawn which will fight to repel any intruders they detect. The
monsters attack on sight and fight to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is a ruse put in place by the Aboleths to stall any would-be
heroes. They expect these interlopers to slay the disposable foulspawn, destroy
the useless crystal, and go back home thinking they solved the problem of the
Chasm. PCs can make several different skill tests to notice the crystal doesn’t
have any actual power, the foulspawn are acting strangely because of mental
domination, and that there are tunnels hidden in the area around the fortress,
leading deeper underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plaguechanged-warrens&quot;&gt;Plaguechanged Warrens&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an enormous chunk of rock wedged between the two walls of the Chasm. It
could be moved by sufficient force, but only has room to go up. The top surface
is where the Twisted Fane was built, and the inside is a maze of twisty passages
that end in gross “breeding pits” where creatures are stuffed into fleshy
cocoons and mutated by Spellplague magic directed by the Symphony of
Madness. This is where all the plaguechanged monsters that attack the surface
come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This deep into the chasm, characters have a -2 penalty to Endurance to resist
creeping madness. At the bottom levels of the rock, they also start to hear the
physical sounds of the Symphony of Madness, which inflicts a -2 penalty to Will
on all non-aberrant creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-blue-cauldron&quot;&gt;The Blue Cauldron&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underside of the Warrens opens into a large cavern mostly filled by an
underground lake. The water glows blue and bubbles as if boiling due to the
Spellplague pocket at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no physical way to safely climb down to the water; characters must
either fly or fall down the 60-foot drop. There is an “unfettered travel”
magical effect put in place by the aboleths that lets them swim in the air
inside this cave. Characters trained in Arcana might be able to hijack that and
be able to swim through the air as if it was water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a depth of 20 feet, the PCs can find bubbles holding particularly interesting
prisoners. At the bottom of the lake, is the research lab itself. Any characters
who get to this cave will immediately draw the attention of the aboleths, both
because they proved themselves a major threat and because they might make
excellent research subjects. The aboleths themselves are quite powerful and
might also be plaguechanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this depth, characters have a -4 penalty to resist creeping madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface of the Chasm could make for a decent hex- or point-crawling map as
characters try to find a safe path to the rift itself. As described, it seems
the Chasm itself is a very meaty dungeon delve. None of its separate areas
described above get maps, so the GM can make maps that suit their
purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, once you’re here you know you need to go &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt;, but depending on how long
the GM wants you to spend inside each of the named areas could vary in
complexity from the equivalent of a single “room” with a big battle in it to an
entire labyrinthine dungeon level where finding the way down is a significant
challenge in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/10/neverwinter-chasm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/10/neverwinter-chasm.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: River District</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The River District occupies the city’s northeastern quadrant and was where most
of the city’s merchant class lived, and also the location of a couple of wizard
towers. These homes were not as nice as those of the Blacklake nobles, but they
were still sturdy and are still mostly standing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s River District is much more dangerous and hostile than Blacklake. The
many guardhouses and security walls here now act as prime ambush spots. It’s
protected from the Chasm by the river, but monsters from the wilderness outside
can freely wander in. The main source of danger, however, are the Many-Arrows
Orcs. Neverember has so far failed to dislodge them, and maintains an uneasy
truce punctuated by skirmishes while he thinks of a way to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mintarn mercs mostly stay away from the River District, making it a good
place for shady deals if one can dodge the orcs. Hot-blooded youngsters also
love to go here on dares, despite their parents’ protestations. And while
scavengers have long taken all of the most obvious treasure, there’s still some
left in secret stashes all over those merchant mansions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fallen-tower&quot;&gt;The Fallen Tower&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This used to be a wizard’s tower, but it was destroyed during the
Spellplague. Some time later, its ruins became a tavern whose main attraction is
the nightly haunt showing the deaths of the wizards as they fall from a great
height into what is now the tavern’s cookfire at the center of the common
room. Charming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The place was vacant when the orcs found it but it still contained a lot of
stored food and drink, so they reopened it for their own use. Lord Neverember
and Commander Vansi have declated The Fallen Tower to be neutral ground, and
their envoys meet here when they have cause to talk. Non-orcs deemed worthy to
share a drink with the Many-Arrows are also allowed to frequent the Tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cloak-tower&quot;&gt;The Cloak Tower&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cloak Tower was once the headquarters of a mage guild called The
Many-Starred Cloaks. It vanished into thin air at the height of the Spellplague
and rematerialized six months later at a different address, without its
wizards. People who have tried to explore it in the past were turned away or
killed by its magical wards and traps, and everyone thought the same would
happen to the orcs. However, for some reason, they had absolutely no trouble
moving in and making this tower their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-shard-of-night&quot;&gt;The Shard of Night&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This black stone tower appeared high above the River District during the
Spellplague and has floated there ever since. It looks like it was cut off from
its base, with an opening at the bottom. It casts no shadow during the day, and
when people walk under it their own shadows vanish as well. It does cast a
shadow by the light of the moon, and even though no one was ever seen to enter
or leave the place, eerie sounds sometimes echo from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tower used to be part of a distant temple of Selûne, but it was cut off and
banished to the Shadowfell during a Netherese assault on that temple. After the
battle, they found out they could control where the tower appeared in the world,
so they sent it to Neverwinter during the Spellplague and left it there until
the day when it was needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is needed, and they’re using it. The Shard’s enchantments allow it to
absorb shadows during the day and use them to power a teleportation circle
inside that links it to Xinlenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creatures infused with shadow power, such as the Scion of Shadow, are immune to
the absorption effect and still cast shadows while under the Tower. They also
feel a comforting pull from it, which might help clue them in to what lies
inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This&lt;/em&gt; is the “bad” part of town. I imagine most who live here are either
Many-Arrows, allied with them, or sneaky enough to go undetected. I also think
envoys who want to go to the Fallen Tower for diplomacy with the orcs might need
some sort of token of safe passage, since it’s actually quite far from the
district’s borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profit-oriented parties could have some interesting adventures following up on
rumors of a big treasure cache still hidden in the River District, but most of
the hooks here involve dealing with the Many-Arrows somehow. Raiding the Shard
of Night is an interesting way to get to Xinlenal without a long and arduous
overland trek into the Woods, but that place is only approachable by “endgame”
parties.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/04/neverwinter-river-district.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/04/neverwinter-river-district.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Castle Never</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Castle Never sits on the northern bank of the river, in the Blacklake District
that takes up Neverwinter’s nortwestern quadrant. It used to be the seat of its
government, and home to its ruling family. The cataclysm wrecked it and killed
almost everyone inside. The surviving servants decided to seal its crypts,
vaults and grounds, hoping that a worthy heir might make use of them one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle’s ruins are still a towering landmark, and its foundations are still
solid. While many interior chambers were destroyed, some are still intact and a
lot of the interior is at least navigable - most notably the underground
bits. Now it houses several groups who compete with each other for territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book doesn’t give you maps, leaving those as an exercise to the GM. There’s
enough going on here that it could be a full megadungeon and the focus of the
campaign… or it could be “downsized” to the site of a single targeted delve
for groups who want to keep their focus elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;surface-areas&quot;&gt;Surface Areas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface portion of the castle is partly ruined but still contains a large
number of navigable areas. There are some places of interest that should feature
in whatever map you draw for it, like the &lt;strong&gt;locked armory&lt;/strong&gt; or the odd places
detailed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drow-encampment&quot;&gt;“Drow” Encampment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This used to be a campsite in a hidden spot in the city, near Castle Never. It
was originally set up by Drizzt and Jarlaxe around the time of the cataclysm,
when they were here investigating the Thayans and trying to stop their
plan. They come back every once in a while to attempt to tie off those Thayan
loose ends, usually without much success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location of the encampment was recently discovered, however… by their
&lt;em&gt;fans&lt;/em&gt;. These eager youths and would-be adventurers have made the spot into a
permanent “DrowCon” of sorts. They train together, challenge themselves by
delving the castle, and hope to become good enough to join their idols’
entourages once they return. Neither of the two celebrities have been back for a
while, but Jarlaxe has heard of these events and has sent some of his Bregan
D’Aerthe agents to mind the place and keep a watch for promising recruits from
among the fans. They are Xalbyn the quick-witted rogue, Kimmuriel Oblodra the
quiet and focused mage, and Aerlyse the half-drow psion who spies on the other
two for Jarlaxe. Xalbyn hides his drow heritage with a Hat of Disguise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book makes an effort to take this place seriously… but I just can’t see it
as anything but comic relief. It would be a funny place to use whether there are
Bregan Spies on the party or not. If there are, then I’m guessing the three
stooges here don’t know about them. Jarlaxe seems very fond of keeping his
underlings in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hall-of-ashen-mirrors&quot;&gt;Hall of Ashen Mirrors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hallway inside Castle Never. It has huge windows and used to be lined
with mirrors, being a popular spot for young Alagondar heirs to practice their
regal posture. When the cataclysm hit, air pressure shattered all the mirrors,
filling the place with flying glass and killing everyone inside right before a
pyroclasm came in through the windows and turned the corpses to ash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the hallway is very, very haunted. When living people enter, it will
reconstruct itself, and the reflections in the mirrors will re-enact the events
that happened just before the explosion. The replay ends with the
explosion-and-pyroclasm combo, just as deadly as it originally was. Anyone
lingering here for too long is gonna have a bad time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;surface-factions&quot;&gt;Surface Factions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These groups make up the inhabitants of the castle’s above-ground
portion. They’re all hostile to each other, though some are more amenable to
befriending the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghosts&quot;&gt;Ghosts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the castle’s destruction was so sudden, pretty much everyone who perished
in it ended up becoming a ghost. They can be found all over the interior, and
are a varied lot. They’re not automatically hostile, and PCs who approach them
correctly might strike up some extremely useful conversations with them. However
they tend to talk in riddles both because they like it and because their sanity
might have been a little damaged in the last 30 years. And if the ghosts come to
believe the characters are just there to loot the ruins, they &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; become
hostile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thayan-forces&quot;&gt;Thayan Forces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castle Never is Valindra’s second major focus in the city of Neverwinter (the
first is Neverdeath Cemetery, as we saw earlier). On the surface, her forces are
engaged in a small war against those of Talgath, which consists of a tense
standoff with occasional battles. There’s at least one residential area that
became isolated due to cave-ins after a battle. The ghoul troop that got trapped
inside passes its time wearing the former inhabitants’ clothes and pretending to
be nobility, waiting for a rescue that will never come. The PCs will probably
stumble upon them first. Other undead patrols can probably act as random
encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;talgath-watcher-of-castle-never&quot;&gt;Talgath, Watcher of Castle Never&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talgath the Beholder has recently moved in. He wants to be king of the castle,
starting with the ettercaps on the upper spires and working his way down. He
pays little attention to humanoid intruders like the PCs, unless they get in his
way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valindra sees Talgath as the greatest threat to her goals in the castle. She’s
sent people to kill him several times, but Talgath has defeated them all. Not
only is he a powerful monster in his own right, he also makes extensive use of
his charm ray to keep a small army of minions. He brought in a coven of harpies
and a pack of displacer beasts from outside, and has charmed many of the
assassins sent to kill him as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;independent-communities&quot;&gt;Independent Communities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle’s atrium was boarded up long ago, and the heat and darkness have
turned the garden within into a fungal paradise complete with a village of very
territorial myconids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its upper spires have been taken over by a group of ettercaps who used to live
in the dungeons but were pushed out and up by Valindra. She ignores them these
days, but Talgath is currently trying to enslave them. Their leader says he had
a prophetic dream where a group of outsiders would deliver them from the
beholder, which makes them more likely than usual to befriend the PCs (and give
them that quest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;underground-areas&quot;&gt;Underground Areas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle’s underground areas are structurally intact. The things that make
them dangerous are of another nature entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neverneath&quot;&gt;Neverneath&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle had a sizable dungeon area underneath it, protected by strong wards
that let it survive the cataclysm intact. Radiation from the Spellplague pocket
at the bottom of the Chasm has altered the wards, however, making it so they
actively trap any who enter the dungeon, causing its corridors to shift and
close around these intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space here is all wonky. A straight corridor can lead you through a circuitous
route full of loops and circles. A door might lead you to a different place than
it did the fellow PC who was just in front of you. The place is filled with
self-resetting traps, and inhabited by a large pack of gargoyles who love to
attack anything fleshy they find. It also houses a small force of desperate
gnolls that stumbled upon it several months ago and haven’t managed to escape
yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vault-of-the-nine&quot;&gt;Vault of the Nine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below Neverneath lies the Vault of the Nine, where those legendary bodyguards
have been entombed to honor their meritorious service in life. If you’re using
the subplot where Valindra plans to reanimate them, her forces are already here
and have turned the vault’s many outer chambers into their base of operations,
filling it with guardian undead. If she manages to animate the Nine, she will
order them to kill and replace all of New Neverwinter’s leadership, including
Neverember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;player-tie-ins&quot;&gt;Player Tie-Ins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would the PCs want to mess with this place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Neverwinter Noble&lt;/strong&gt; has the most reasons for wanting to do so. The ghosts
are likely to be their direct ancestors, for starters! The fabled Crown of
Neverwinter is also lost somewhere inside the castle, and it’s likely the most
definitive proof of legitimacy for anyone wanting to claim the throne. Legend
says the crown’s magic properties only work for someone of the line of
Alagondar, and that anyone else who tries to wear it gets simultaneously burned
and frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching the Vault of the Nine would also be a desirable goal for the Noble even
if Valindra’s forces are not down there. It could be possible to call the Nine
back into service through their oaths to the line of Alagondar, and if the noble
can do so that would be another excellent proof of their legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oghma’s Faithful&lt;/strong&gt; would also love to explore this place and find its many
lost historical secrets. They might be mostly interested in interviewing the
ghosts and finding any sealed off libraries, but finding a safe path to the
Vault would also be a worthy goal even if they wouldn’t actually want to loot
the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the &lt;strong&gt;Devil’s Pawn&lt;/strong&gt; might benefit from talking with the ghosts, as it’s
quite possible one or more of them have had to deal with a similar problem
in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For everyone else, Neverember is always hiring adventurers &lt;del&gt;stupid&lt;/del&gt; brave
enough to delve the Castle in search for the Crown or any other relics and
documents that might help increase his legitimacy. He also wants it to be clear
of monsters so he can move in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-crown-of-neverwinter&quot;&gt;The Crown of Neverwinter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for the Crown, and it’s indeed a nifty item (level 15, head slot,
strong protections against mental conditions and a nice bonus to social
skills). The stats &lt;em&gt;do not&lt;/em&gt; include the genetic lock from the legend, so it’s up
to the GM whether those stories are true or not. The people certainly believe
them, in any case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the GM likes the idea of the Crown but doesn’t want to bother with the
Castle, the crown might be placed in another place that’s more relevant to the
campaign. As a lost artifact, it could turn up anywhere for any number of
reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the dynamic with the different factions here. There’s a lot going on in
this castle and as in any megadungeon the situation here feels a lot less stable
than even the one in the city outside. PCs who come in here are definitely going
to have a drastic effect whether they have themed ties to the place or not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/29/neverwinter-castle-never.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/29/neverwinter-castle-never.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
