<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 19:47:54 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 19:47:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon, part 00: Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackers-cast.jpg&quot;
       alt=&quot;The protagonists of the 1995 movie Hackers.&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Getting ready to hack the Gibson.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently got into a forum discussion about hacking in cyberpunk tabletop RPGs,
as one does. This one was mostly centered around Shadowrun, and it touched on a
lot of the reasons why one might want to &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html&quot;&gt;play without a hacker PC&lt;/a&gt; even when
you want to feature hacking in your game. It also got a bit into edition
arguments, as it often does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowrun’s problems are more or less universal to the genre, as mentioned in
the other post linked above. The first three editions go heavy into the whole
Gibsonian VR Dungeon aesthetic and suffer from the classic problems from that
approach. It’s also very inspired by how 80s mainframes worked, and rules aside
it all made so much more sense to me once I realized that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth has something that visually resembles Ghost in the Shell or Cyberpunk
2077, where the hacker follows along with the group and hacks a series of
smaller devices using an augmented reality interface. My recollection is that
this is supposed to be faster, but the discussion in question had people
complaining it wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk-the-game is similar, with CP 2020 going in fully for VR dungeons, and
CP RED going in for smaller localized servers that are also supposed to only
take a small series of rolls to solve instead of an hours-long minigame. They’re
are much less inspired by reality than Shadowrun’s (though this is of course not
a knock on them, merely an observation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also more recent games that try to either capture the nostalgic feel
of old-school cyberpunk or to express the same themes in a more modern way. I’m
thinking of Neon City Overdrive and Hard Wired Island, respectively. I’m not
very familiar with them yet but I intend to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you have GURPS, which has a few hacking systems of its own depending on
which genre you’re talking about. The ones I’m interested in are the one from
Pyramid #3/21, which emulates classic cyberdecks-and-mainframes hacking but
could also work for GitS-style shenanigans, and the more streamlined one from
GURPS Action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I kinda want to see if they all match the memories and impressions I have of
them. Let’s try them all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hackathon-scenario-and-rules&quot;&gt;Hackathon Scenario and Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture a team of flawed but stylish urban mercenaries composed of a hacker, a
sneaky talker, and a pair of sneaky bruisers. They’re on a mission to take down
a corrupt and racist businessman, and they learned a company he owns stores the
sort of evidence that can’t be ignored by the government: proof of rampant
embezzling and tax evasion, in both digital and hardcopy forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mercenaries are going to infiltrate a small, single-office company, one of
the many owned by the target. It does do legitimate business but also serves as
a “stash” for records about the target’s illegal activities. Secret ledgers,
blackmail material, and so on. Some of this lives in the company’s computer
system, some of it is stored in hardcopy in a “records room” whose access is
restricted to normal employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employees and other authorized personnel can wander the legitimate business area
of the office freely, but the “records room” can only be accessed by a small
group of people who work directly for the target and drop by occasionally to use
it. There’s a back entrance with an electronic lock so that these lieutenants
can get in and out outside of business hours and/or without bringing too much
employee attention to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The records room is watched by a camera and protected by an alarm that triggers
if a stranger or even a normal employee tries to get close to it. There’s a
small guard shift here during the day which increases at night. The guards know
who the lieutenants are, and their duties involve keeping everyone else away
from the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The office’s computer system will be different in every game. In all of them
it’s supposed to be small but with tighter than expected security, because of
what it hides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team’s mission is to infiltrate this office, steal all the evidence, and if
possible drain the company’s accounts on the way out, because at the end of the
day ya still gotta eat, chummer. Here’s how things are supposed to go, with a
greater focus on the hacker’s part since this is what I’m interested in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the team enters the building disguised as a maintenance crew. We’ll
assume this part succeeds, giving them limited freedom of movement inside the
office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next they must enter the records room. For them to be able to do this, the
hacker must turn off a security camera and an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the previous step succeeds, the hacker must locate and steal the target data
from the office’s computer system. Technically, the best strategy would be to
steal the evidence first and only then drain the accounts, but our hacker will
do things in the order in which they run into the corresponding locations. The
lure of money is strong when the account is right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the hacker must unlock the back door so the team can leave. Ideally
they will do so quietly and with no one the wiser, but this could happen in the
middle of a firefight. Possibly one caused by the hacker triggering an alert in
the computer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each of the following systems, I’m going to stat up a hacker character and a
computer system that conforms to that game’s paradigm and rules. And then I’ll
roll through the target session while timing how long it takes me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 1st Edition&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk 2020&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 4th Edition, 20th Anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk RED&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 5th Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neon City Overdrive&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hard Wired Island&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GURPS Action with the Pyramid #3/21 system, both in “classic” and “modern”
modes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GURPS Action with its own system. Not sure this can accommodate the scenario,
but we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using this particular list because those are the books I happen to own at
present. I’m not sure if I want to spend money to acquire the hacking systems
used in Shadowrun 2nd and 3rd Edition, though I do remember they are notably
different from SR1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hacker and their equipment will be at roughly starting character level for
each game, possibly with a slight tweak or two, and the challenges faced should
be challenging but not impossible for the hacker. Whether the target devices are
separate or part of the same single “target system”, and whether the hacker is
even with the physical team, will depend on the system in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have more practical experience with some of these systems than with others,
but I will be studying all of them to ensure I do each run “right”. Preliminary
study doesn’t count towards the timed session, but consultations that happen
during the actual run &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;, because I’ve never been in a session where people
didn’t have to consult the books for something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be writing a lot of stuff down during the actual run, but I’ll try to be as
brief as possible there. It’s still going to take a bit more time than doing it
verbally, but I think it evens out because there will be no table talk or extra
player questions getting in the way. I’ll write wordier summaries after the run
is done, and these are the ones that will see publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All rolls will be made on Orokos, but I’m not going to save them and will just
report the results in the article.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/hackaton-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/hackaton-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Evernight, part 02</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post concerns itself with specific landmarks in Evernight. A lot of them
are “coterminous” with Neverwinter landmarks, occupying the corresponding
location in space and having the exact same boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;black-mound&quot;&gt;Black Mound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The district of &lt;strong&gt;Black Mound&lt;/strong&gt; is named that because of the hill that dominates
it. It’s coterminous with the Protector’s Enclave in Neverwinter. The houses and
manors here are larger than in the rest of Evernight, but just as
dilapidated. Undead are not known for their tidiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the city’s relevant landmarks are here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;house-of-screams&quot;&gt;House of Screams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Located in the same spot as Neverwinter’s Hall of Justice, the House of Screams
is the oldest manor in the city and the closest thing Evernight has to a
courthouse or city hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tribunal holds court in the upper levels. When it’s time to adjudicate a
dispute, they slam iron portcullises over all exits until the session is done,
because as mentioned in the previous post the ghouls eat the losers. They do
find vampires to be a particular pain in the neck to deal with, as they can
transform into mist and fly through the grates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The House’s wide open cellar works as an arena where citizens can work out their
problems without getting the Tribunal involved. There’s usually some bored
ghouls, wights and vampires hanging around hoping to watch a fight or three, and
they will gladly act as witnesses to confirm that the few rules of engagement
were obeyed by both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;temple-of-filth&quot;&gt;Temple of Filth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with the House of Knowledge in Neverweinter, the Temple of Filth
used to be dedicated to Bhaal and Myrkul, ancient gods of murder and death who
died during the switch-over from AD&amp;amp;D 1e to AD&amp;amp;D 2e. Now it’s dedicated to Orcus
and Dorensain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the temple’s decorations, including its altar and holy symbols, are built
from corpses and corpse bits. No special care is taken to &lt;em&gt;preserve&lt;/em&gt; these
bits. They’re just replaced with new ones when they rot away. Ewwww.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The undead of Evernight sometimes ask the priests here to resolve their
disputes, because they tend to demand services from both parties instead of
eating one of them like the Tribunal does. The temple’s chief priest is
Ursuntos, whose stats are those of an Adept of Orcus (Level 6 Controller, from
the MM3). He has a bunch of ghoul and vampire underlings, and his political
power in the city is second only to the Tribunal’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grounds of the Temple are considered both defiled and necrotic ground as per
the DMG2. Very cursed, but surprisingly not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; as cursed as the Dread Ring,
which has additional effects on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pool-of-daylight&quot;&gt;Pool of Daylight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep within the temple, behind a bunch of locked doors, traps and magical
darkness areas, is a literal pool of radiance (is this a name drop?) that shines
as bright as the world’s mid-day sun. Any undead entering its chamber suffers
terrible pain, and touching the pool can actually destroy the weaker among
them. This is here as the ultimate security measure, for the pool is said to
hide an artifact at its bottom that works as a weapon of mass destruction
against undead. The Temple doesn’t want anyone else getting a hold of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing living PCs don’t need to fear the light, huh? This could be just the
thing to use against those pesky Thayans and Shadovar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-graveyard&quot;&gt;The Graveyard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight’s Graveyard occupies the same area as the pauper section of
Neverwinter’s own graveyard. Despite the name, and despite being absolutely
filled with crypts and tombs and graves, from the point of view of the city’s
ghouls this place is a &lt;em&gt;restaurant&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, when an Evernight ghoul catches a living “tourist”, they don’t eat
right away. Instead, they take the paralyzed victim to a place called Lamantha’s
Mortuary, where the resident necromancer will inject them with longer-term
paralytics. Then the ghoul arranges for a “funeral procession” for the
still-living victim, who is buried alive in the Graveyard. Only after the victim
has died and “ripened” a bit does the ghoul crack open the coffin and eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;corpse-market&quot;&gt;Corpse Market&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with the “rich” section of Neverdeath in the world, this is exactly
what it says on the tin. A market where undead merchants sell meals to undead
customers who are too busy to catch their own. From preserved blood for vampires
to assorted corpse bits for ghouls to necromantic supplies, you can find all of
that here for affordable prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the place to go if you want to hire undead labor. Renting a zombie
laborer costs 10gp per day and requires leaving a chunk of your flesh as
collateral. The chunk is alchemically preserved, so it stays fresh and can be
reattached later. While it’s missing, you lose a healing surge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might also be able to hire undead guides for about 100gp per day. Some of
these guides might be able to smell specific “flavors” of death from a long
distance away, so they might be useful to an Uthgardt Barbarian who wants to
find their tribe’s missing thunderbeast skeleton, or to PCs looking for
Gauntlgrym. Undead guides charge a premium for going into particularly dangerous
places, refuse to fight for their clients and might in fact run away if a fight
breaks out. Other than that, though, they’re reliable as long as they’re getting
paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creepy old man known as the Resurrectionist wanders the Market every day,
looking for a piece of someone specific he wishes to bring back to life. He
never finds the right one, so he keeps coming back to continue searching. He’s
been at this long enough that most standard resurrection magic wouldn’t work any
more, but the man guarantees he can bring anyone back no matter how long it’s
been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a fenced off area here that contains warehouses and some of the
merchant’s residences. While anyone can walk through the market, unauthorized
people caught in this area are assumed to be prowling thieves and are killed on
sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dark-creeper-enclave&quot;&gt;Dark Creeper Enclave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This large manor close to the Graveyard is the Netherese consulate on
Evernight. The Netherese pay a family of Dark Ones, the Glumguts, to mind the
place. They don’t have any official authority - their job is to maintain the
house, serve any actual dignitaries in the rare occasions they stay here, and
receive any packages dropped off at the embassy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family members like to supplement their income with the occasional spot of
burglary or robbery, though they are careful to restrict their activities to
the living (who can do less about it). They also only target Thayans if they can
get one of them alone, to avoid reprisals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a proper gothic family too: their patriarch Blackclaw, a dark stalker
(level 10 lurker), rules them through fear. The only ones who have the courage
to defy him are his young cousins Thrax and Vinnia, and his son Blackcut. The
trio believes they’re protected by Blackcut’s relation to his father, and free
to do whatever they want. The truth is Blackclaw simply doesn’t know most of
what they’ve been up to, and will be livid when he finds out. Their shenanigans
have actually been quite detrimental to the family’s duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thayan-outpost&quot;&gt;Thayan Outpost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Thayans are based out of a warehouse near one of the city’s haunted piers in
the Black Mound. They have a permanent garrison here commanded by Katrice Ansar
(stats as a human hexer from the MM2, Level 7 Controller). She’s convinced they
are being watched by Shadovar spies besides the obvious dark creepers, but has
yet to find them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the warehouse, in an abandoned neighborhood, is an iron gate that acts as a
“dusk crevice” linked to Neverdeath cemetery. It’s guarded around the clock by a
unit that includes undead loyal to the Thayans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;locations-outside-black-mound&quot;&gt;Locations Outside Black Mound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only three of these described here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lamanthas-mortuary&quot;&gt;Lamantha’s Mortuary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentioned above in the Graveyard description, this is run by a living human
necromancer named Lamantha who works as a mortician and taxidermist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of her main jobs is preparing mortal victims for burial in the Graveyard,
which she does by injecting them with long-term paralytic drugs and dressing
them up. She can also disguise undead so they look like living people through
wardrobe and makeup adjustments, and she can turn bodies or bits of bodies into
trophies and tools (or &lt;em&gt;sporting equipment&lt;/em&gt;, as the book makes sure to mention).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since she provides valuable services, the rulers of Evernight gave Lamantha
citizenship and allow her conduct her research in peace. Only the necromancer
herself knows its precise nature - it’s something to do with observing the
nature of growth and change among undead. Maybe she’s a necro-sociologist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being completely amoral and quite unhinged, Lamantha is happy to receive
living visitors and get the latest gossip from the middle world. PCs who are
polite to her might be able to use the mortuary as a safe place to rest for a
couple of days, though she will become impatient with them if they overstay
their welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-demon-pit&quot;&gt;The Demon Pit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with Neverwinter’s Chasm, this opened up at the same time, though it
did not disrupt “life” in the cursed undead city nearly as much as it did on the
living one. Like in Neverwinter, the average civilian does not know why this
rift opened up, nor what’s down there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight’s inhabitants call their rift the Demon Pit because rumor has it that
it goes all the way down to Dorensain’s kingdom in the Abyss. No one tried to
explore it, but they sometimes throw living mortals into the Pit as sacrifices
to Orcus and Dorensain. That’s more of a folk ritual than established Temple
practice, mind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Temple of Filth, this area counts as both defiled and necrotic ground,
and is still not as cursed as the Dread Ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;castle-nowhere&quot;&gt;Castle Nowhere&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with Castle Never. It looks much more intact and much creepier than
its worldly counterpart, and not even the most ancient of Evernight’s undead
citizens can tell when it was built. Like a few other places we’ve seen in
previous posts, Castle Nowhere only exists &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt;, vanishing and appearing
in a ten-day cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one in Evernight knows much about what goes on inside the castle. They avoid
going in because, get this, they think it’s haunted. This is hilarious, but it
also makes you wonder what kind of haunting would scare an undead city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the legends about the place say that if you’re inside the castle when it
vanishes, you don’t come back when it does. Others say that the ghosts inside it
feed on &lt;em&gt;the hunger of others&lt;/em&gt;. This means they can cause the living to starve
to death, but they can also cause a ghoul or vampire to become trapped in a
state of eternal starvation and use them as permanent food sources. A fate worse
than a second death!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a box here with a power you can add to any incorporeal undead creature
to make it into a ghost of Castle Nowhere. &lt;strong&gt;Consume&lt;/strong&gt; is a melee attack vs. AC
that removes the target from play and inflicts 10 ongoing damage (save
ends both). The target reappears adjacent to the monster when they make their
save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living creatures reduced to 0 HP by this reappear normally and become immune to
the power for the rest of the encounter. They make death saves and can be healed
as normal. Undead reduced to 0 HP do not die, and remain trapped until willingly
released by the ghost, or until the ghost is destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a proper creepy city, yes indeed. There’s more than enough material to
fuel a whole horror-themed campaign, though I suspect most typical groups who
are focused on other stories wouldn’t want to linger here too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, there are good reasons to visit the place. That artifact hidden in the
Pool of Radiance would be extremely useful to wreck the Thayans, for example,
and if the PCs want to follow the Shadowfell Road to their home base they would
also need to start at the Thayan outpost in Evernight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castle Nowhere would make an awesome dungeon, but as written there’s barely any
reason for PCs to enter the place. Perhaps they could use it to lure and trap a
powerful undead foe like Valindra, or maybe the quickest way to access the Tomb
of the Nine is by entering Castle Nowhere and crossing to the world through a
dusk crevice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/neverwinter-evernight-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/neverwinter-evernight-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Cyberpsychosis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a number of tropes that are specific to Cyberpunk-the-game&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but
which many people end up thinking are integral to cyberpunk-the-genre. And
“cyberpsychosis” is the one that annoys me the most by far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpsychosis is Cyberpunk’s term for the general concept that cybernetic
implants make you less human. This concept made the way into the game because
its author Mike Pondsmith used the AD Police anime as one of his sources of
inspiration, and the anime goes heavily into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably already know how it works in the game, but here’s a refresher:
characters have an Empathy stat that determines how well they relate to other
people. This gives them a Humanity score that’s equal to Empathy x 10. Each
implant has a “Humanity cost” that gets deducted from that score when installed,
and for every 10 points of Humanity you lose you also lose 1 Empathy. This makes
it harder to succeed at social tasks. When both Humanity and Empathy reach 0,
you become a “cyberpsycho” and an NPC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with the &lt;em&gt;mechanical&lt;/em&gt; purpose of these rules, which is to limit how much
cyberware a character can have. But this is heavily entangled with the “this
stuff makes you less human” story concept, from the terms used to the in-fiction
justification to the setting elements built around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk 2020 was particularly bad about this. Cyberpunk RED is much better
about it due to thirty years of progress in popular thinking about mental
health, but I still have issues with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-which-i-talk-about-my-issues&quot;&gt;In Which I Talk About My Issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CP RED, Humanity loss is more or less equated with psychological trauma. You
can lose Humanity by experiencing traumatic events, and modifications that are
purely cosmetic or therapeutic in nature don’t cost Humanity. Therapy helps you
recover and restores your Humanity. And I’m happy to report it’s “merely”
difficult and expensive instead of the sinister tracker-injecting conspiracy it
was in CP 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the mechanics remain exactly the same as before for cyberware that has
game benefits. The explanation given is that the act of “going beyond the human
baseline” is traumatic. Cyberpsychosis is the dissociative disorder you get when
you do it too much, and makes you start seeing yourself and others as
collections of replaceable parts instead of living, thinking beings. You can use
therapy to partially recover the Humanity lost to cyberware, but to recover
those final points, you need to get rid of the implants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of “human baseline” isn’t examined very deeply here. You know it
when you see it, and your Empathy reduces when you move away from it. It’s the
act of implantation that causes harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feels really backward to me, because a theme I often see in literature or
media I like is that cybernetic implants are more like the &lt;em&gt;scars&lt;/em&gt; of trauma
than its &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molly Millions from Neuromancer has implanted mirrorshades because her traumatic
past made her wary of opening herself up emotionally. The windows to her soul
are shuttered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burton and his ex-Haptic Recon buddies from The Peripheral have a number of
twitchy combat implants that mostly serve as symbols for the PTSD they got from
their time at war. Flynne, one of the main protagonists, has similar
psychological scars from her time playing realistic military simulations for
money, but she has no implants because her trauma comes through in her viewpoint
narration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Martinez from Edgerunners was already a reckless putz with a hero
complex&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; before getting his first implant. Each one he has installed is
either a reminder of someone he feels he failed to protect, or a reflection of
his desire to be strong enough to protect those who are left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard it said that someone who gets an implanted gun or blade is declaring
themselves the kind of person who needs to be ready to kill someone at all
times, and that erodes their humanity. But isn’t “feels the need to be ready to
fight and kill at all times” a common trait to all Cyberpunk PCs, chromed or
not? It’s a lot easier to find a PC with no implants than one with no weapons,
armor, or combat skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t really matter whether your gun is inside your coat or inside your
arm. And since I don’t think a Cyberpunk character should lose Humanity for
carrying a conventional gun, they also shouldn’t lose it for carrying an
implanted one&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-id-do-instead&quot;&gt;What I’d Do Instead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said above, I still agree that there must be some sort of rule limiting
the amount of cyberware Cyberpunk PCs can get. A lot of it gives powerful
abilities and you don’t want them to be able to install the whole catalog at
once. That would make the game less fun in a variety of ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to base it on some stat other than Empathy, though, and I’m going to pick
Body for that. I find it much easier to imagine that cyberware has concrete
impacts on your body than on your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this new rule, your maximum Cyberware Capacity (CC) is your natural Body
x 10. “Natural” here means the base stat value before any modifications from
cyberware. Cyberware’s “humanity loss” stat now represents its “capacity cost”
instead. Your current Cyberware Capacity is the cost of all your implants added
together. This represents both minor health issues caused by the implant’s
presence and the increased need for maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you exceed your maximum Cyberware Capacity, you die. The good news is there
are no other game penalties until you get to that point. Note that medical exams
to measure your CC values are standard pre-op procedures even at mall clinics.
No ethical ripperdoc will ever agree to perform an operation that would kill the
patient. Not all of them are ethical, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Body-scultping (including full gender transition), medical-grade replacements,
and cosmetic mods continue to have zero cost&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The implants involved in all
of these processes are designed to be minimally invasive and to require
near-zero maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cyberware-maintenance-optional&quot;&gt;Cyberware Maintenance (Optional)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GMs who wish to make a commentary on the cruelty of capitalism might institute
this optional rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it’s in effect, you need to pay a monthly cyberware maintenance cost equal
to your current CC x 10eb. This represents anything from periodic check-ups and
implant cleaning to a regime of targeted immunosuppressors at the high end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you skip a month, your current CC increases by 1d6. If you’re also living
under harsh and unsanitary conditions during that time, such as from being lost
in the desert or having to sleep in the gutter, it increases by 2d6 instead. If
it goes over your maximum, you die as above. And yeah, this extra CC also
increases your maintenance costs next month. Field-expedient maintenance and a
Medicine roll might reduce the increase from 2d6 to 1d6, at the GM’s discretion,
but there’s no reducing it to zero without making that monthly payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excess CC from neglected maintenance can be removed through treatments that cost
and work the same as the psychological therapies from page 229 of the core book:
500eb (or 100eb and a DV15 Medicine roll) to restore 2d6, and 1000eb (or 500eb
and a DV17 Medicine roll) to restore 4d6. These consist of extensive drug
courses, therapeutic surgery, and physical rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a further optional rule, the GM could also use these stats for “tune-up”
treatments to reduce Cyberware Capacity to the minimum values described in the
book: 2 per piece of cyberware, 4 per piece of borgware. Gotta spend money to
save money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-humanity&quot;&gt;What About Humanity?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathy and Humanity continue to exist in a game where Cyberware Capacity rules
are in play. Since we’re renaming things anyway, let’s rename Humanity to
Stability because suffering from mental trauma doesn’t make you less human
either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can still suffer Stability and Empathy loss when you suffer actual mental
trauma, as described in the CP RED core book. The same therapy options are still
available and they can help you as described there. Reaching 0 EMP will cause a
breakdown that will leave the character unplayable until they can recover, but
this will not necessarily be violent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one case where cyberware still causes Stability loss is when a victim is
&lt;em&gt;forcibly implanted&lt;/em&gt;. The Maelstrom gang in CP 2077 loves doing that to random
civilians, and it definitely qualifies as a traumatic experience. In that case,
recovering from the trauma follows all standard core book rules, including the
one where you need to remove the offending implants for a complete recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-cyberpsychosis&quot;&gt;What About Cyberpsychosis?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again we follow CP 2077’s example here. Cyberpsychosis is a myth, a label
without any science behind it that gets thrown around by corps and media as an
easy explanation for a number of tragedies. Corporate strike team shoots an
activist, well, that was a cyberpsycho who had it coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can have real mental breakdowns, and these can get ugly when the victim
has a predisposition towards violence and a few combat implants and/or some
weapons on hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, violent breakdowns are never &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; by implants. They’re always a
consequence of the inherently traumatic nature of life in the shit future of
Cyberpunk. I bet a lot of “cyberpsychos” turn out to have very few or even no
implants. Just easy access to guns and no access to mental healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The original edition was named “Cyberpunk”, and it was followed by
Cyberpunk 2020 and Cyberpunk RED, with a couple of extra editions that were
considered “non-canon” between those last two. If I capitalize the word I’m
talking about this game line. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A condition also known as “Shonen Protagonist Syndrome”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A game where owning a weapon brings you closer to becoming a monster is a
perfectly valid concept, but if that’s what you want to play you’re better
off moving away from action-oriented systems like Cyberpunk RED. I suggest
Wanderhome, which does implement that very concept in one of its archetypes
and is otherwise a non-violent game. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This also applies to stuff that has no &lt;em&gt;tangible&lt;/em&gt; game benefits but still
causes Humanity Loss in the core book, like the “sex booster” implants or
the color shift cybereye option (which is purely cosmetic like shift-tacts
but costs Humanity in the book). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/on-cyberpsychosis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/on-cyberpsychosis.html</guid>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Evernight Overview</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Evernight is Neverwinter’s reflection on the Shadowfell, but it’s also a city in
its own right, inhabited by a large number of undead and undead-adjacent people
(cultists, necromancers, and the like). This book doesn’t go too deep into its
history, but it does give me the impression Evernight has existed for a long
time. It was probably described in a previous edition when the Shadowfell was
called “the plane of Shadow”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight is ruled by a Tribunal composed by its most influent citizens, all of
whom are ghouls and ghasts who worship Orcus and his exarch Dorensain. The
Tribunal makes the laws and settles disputes. It does the latter by deciding who
is right and eating the loser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is very dangerous for living mortals who aren’t citizens, though it’s a
bit &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; dangerous than you’d think. Only its vampire and ghoul inhabitants
feel the need to feed on the living, and since the ambient energies of the
Shadowfell help sustain them this happens much less often than it would in the
world. Mortals and undead alike can apply for citizenship. Mortal citizens gain
legal protection from random attacks on the street, though they should probably
keep their token of citizenship within easy reach at all times. Living merchants
who pass through the city on the way to other locations can also acquire tokens
of safe passage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legal status of a mortal who doesn’t have any of that can best be summed up
as “fresh meat”, but even that isn’t an automatic death sentence. Undead who see
the living brazenly walking down the streets of Evernight tend to assume they
belong there, and will only challenge that assumption if given reason to be
suspicious. Such as when the “tourists” make horrified faces at the deeply
fucked up stuff that happens in the city’s routine unlife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no official portals between Evernight and Neverwinter, but the planar
membrane separating the two is awfully thin and becomes fully permeable in
certain places known as “dusk crevices”. These crossings link a place in
Evernight to its corresponding worldly location, which is always in dim light or
darkness. Some are fixed, some temporary or mobile. They’re the true cause of
most spooky stories about disappearances in Neverwinter since before the
Spellplague. Mortals who fall through these crevices into Evernight make up a
significant portion of the diet of its ghoul and vampire population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its (literally!) ghoulish culture and society, Evernight is a major
Shadowfell trade hub, so it often sees passing caravans that link it to other
settlements in the plane. One of the trade routes passing through here is the
Shadowfell Road, a mystical path that has a ritual component. It only exists if
approached and traversed in a very specific way. The Thayans use it to supply
the Dread Ring, and the Tribunal allows them to use it for that purpose because
the Thayans pay them in &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;. A similar arrangement allows the Netherese to
maintain an embassy in the city and use their own share of trade and supply
routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason the Tribunal accepts these deals is that both factions
represent powerful nations who are very adept at necromancy, but the ghouls
still draw the line at permitting hostilities within city limits. Evernight is
neutral territory, and violating this edict is one of the things that would
cause the Tribunal to take drastic action against the rule-breaker. In practice
that means conflict within the city takes the form of sordid spy stories of
intrigue and assassination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city did suffer some changes during the cataclysm. A reflection of the
Chasm, known locally as the Demon Pit, opened up in the corresponding Shadowfell
coordinates. And while the eruption of mount Hotenow was a quick affair in the
world, its shadowy counterpart continues to expel a slow and steady stream of
lava that flows through the equivalent of the Neverwinter River’s bed. Sometimes
you can see crew-less ghost ships sailing the lava, docking in abandoned piers,
and leaving after a few days. All of the other horrific stuff we’ll see in the
following posts was already there before that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight comes as a bit of a surprise to me, since I think it was only
mentioned in one place in the book before this section and that mention didn’t
hint at the full scope of the thing. I’m guessing old FR hands already know all
about it, though.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/neverwinter-evernight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/neverwinter-evernight.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Gauntlgrym, Part 02</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here we cover the lower strata of Gauntlgrym, where the place’s greatest dangers
live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-mines&quot;&gt;Duergar Mines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duergar of Gauntlgrym live in this sector, which lies deeper than most of
Gauntlgrym. The book says they’ve been here for “a few generations”, which is a
lot longer than I thought before even if these are human generations. Their
situation, however, still matches: they’ve taken over old mining tunnels and dug
new ones under the direction of their leader Kholzourl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve unearthed several veins of useful metal, including iron, silver, mithral
and hellthorn (the one that likes infernal enchantments). Their work is
ceaseless, grueling, and mostly done by slaves, which they replenish by
capturing any non-duergar they lay eyes on down here. Tunnels built by the
original dwarves show their characteristic sloped walls and tend to be both safe
and clean. Duergar tunnels are slapdash and hazardous, sometimes nearly vertical
due to their leader’s need to go ever deeper. Some of these shafts are so deep
that they contain semi-permanent work camps where duergar and enslaved workers
live instead of going back to the city at the end of every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duergar don’t care about the big mithral gates. They got here from below,
via tunnels that link their camps to the deep Underdark. Some of these tunnels
have since been taken over by plaguechanged mind flayers, which are as much a
cause of injury and death as the work itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the mines is also a temple to Asmodeus built from desecrated
material taken from the Iron Tabernacle, which Kholzourl uses to commune with
his god and summon the occasional devil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why exactly are the duergar so intent on digging ever deeper? Only Kholzourl
and the GM really now. The book gives us several possible reasons - GMs can
either pick one or use them as inspiration for a bespoke sinister plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hellthorn comes from a meteorite that fell here in primeval times, and the
main body of the thing contains far more power than the mere shards that have
been found so far. Maybe it contains an alien diabolic entity, millions of
years old, waiting for the moment when it is found and awakened.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The duergar want to drain the magma from Maegera’s resting place and transport
her slumbering form to some place where she can wake up and destroy an enemy
of Asmodeus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mining is just a cover and their actual goal is to observe the mind
flayers and track down their aboleth masters. The duergar suspect they want to
open a permanent portal to the Far Realm and want to hijack the procedure so
the portal leads to Hell instead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or maybe the interaction of all the different types of bad magic that bathe
this region (infernal, aberrant, necromantic, oh my!) has created something
terrible underground that they wish to claim for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fiery-pit&quot;&gt;The Fiery Pit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lowest halls of Gauntlgrym are occupied by this enormous lake of magma, at
the center of which spins a white-hot whirlpool that marks Maegera’s resting
place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prison devised by the ancient mages if Illusk used bound water elementals
fed by a continuous stream of sea water pumped here by magical means. The system
could only be turned off by a true heir of Delzoun. The cataclysm happened when
Valindra found one to pull the lever, causing Maegera to nearly awaken. Drizzt
and his buddies prevented a full awakening back then, but the partial one was
still enough to ruin Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately one of the channels had been destroyed, and so was not reactivated
when the rest of them were. This caused the binding to become imperfect and to
slowly fade over time. Now Maegera is dangerously close to another awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maegera is meant to be used as a looming threat - the bad guys want to wake her,
the PCs want to stop that from happening. PCs could fix the broken arcane pump
by using the notes found in the Waterclock Crypt in Neverwinter, which would
make the whole thing stable once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless of course the Heir of Delzoun PC is foolish enough to pull the “off”
switch again, causing another cataclysm. Then the whole Sword Coast is due for a
TPK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-great-forge&quot;&gt;The Great Forge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the water elemental-based restraints, the structure around
Maegera also contains a complex network of pipes and wires made from all sorts
of enchanted and rune-carved metal, from copper to adamantine. These act as
conduits for the primordial’s power, which was siphoned to this sector of the
city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heat arrived at a great adamantine pyramid known as the Burning Heart, which
collected it and distributed it to the various forges and manufactories in the
sector. This heat could melt through any metal in short order, making it
extremely easy to shape and ensuring the resulting products would carry a little
of Maegera’s power with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs investigating the Forge can find remains of an ancient battle here, and will
find with the appropriate skill tests that the bones of the invading force
belong to legion devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Heart itself can also be investigated by characters competent in
Arcana. Beating a DC of 11 reveals the obvious (lots of fire magic!); beating a
16 reveals this fire magic is being moderated by water magic; and beating a 23
reveals that the energy is being drained by a third party (the aboleths, which
use it in their research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Normal” areas of the Forge are subject to the Unearthly Heat terrain effect,
and since Maegera is partially unbound some terrain here can display more
overtly supernatural fire features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaching one of the conduits from the Heart or the Forge will bathe the
offending character in primordial fire magic, making them resistant to fire and
better at using fire attacks, but vulnerable to and worse at using some other
element of the GM’s choice. Also, they get a bonus to Diplomacy with elemental
creatures and a corresponding penalty when dealing with immortal ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The character loses three healing surges when this happens, and it wasn’t clear
to me whether they could be recovered normally. The mutations are permanent
until cured by Remove Affliction or an equivalent power. A cure removes all
effects - there’s no way to keep just the beneficial ones!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-deepest-depths&quot;&gt;The Deepest Depths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part of Gauntlgrym that connects to the Underdark. The duergar
originally came in through here, but the place has since become very
inhospitable even to them. Many species of aberrant creature dwell in these dark
passages, chief among them the plaguechanged mind flayers that are giving the
duergar trouble. Their mission is to prevent anyone from messing with Maegera,
and thus from getting in the way of the AbSov’s remote experiment with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means they fight the duergar, but they aren’t any less evil than their
foes. Like most Underdark villains mind flayers are fond of slavery, and they
keep their captives here as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This region is also where the dwarves built secure vaults to store a variety of
horrors they found in their delves. Most are still secure, but some have been
opened over the centuries. One of the vaults that are already open is the one
that housed the original population of dire corbies, and which has become their
largest nest. They keep a lot of treasure there that no other faction has
managed to claim yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beneath even this, you get into tunnels that aren’t part of Gauntlgrym, and
which snake their way downwards to the Underdark. Whatever is down there is out
of scope of the campaign. It could perhaps be an interesting segue into Paragon
Tier when the PCs do finish it, should the group be willing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The areas detailed in this post have a definite “endgame” feeling. Whatever your
reasons for coming to Gauntlgrym, if you’re here you’ll need to deal with the
mess of adversarial factions described in this post, finish what Drizzt and
company could not, and make sure Maegera stays asleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be a fitting end to a campaign centered on the Heirs of Delzoun, but
others might go from here to the bottom of the Chasm as they follow the clues
left by the mind flayers to their real masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, if the group doesn’t include any heirs or anyone else who’d be
interested in the lost city, Gauntlgrym can be safely and entirely removed from
the campaign. Just say that Maegera is in no danger of waking up, and focus on
those elements that are relevant to your players.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/16/neverwinter-gauntlgrym-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/16/neverwinter-gauntlgrym-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Gauntlgrym, Part 01</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This part gives an overview of the fabled lost city of Gauntlgrym,and goes into
detail about its “upper” strata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-errata&quot;&gt;Historical Errata&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another bit I missed when I glossed over the big-ass timeline at the
beginning of the book, and now I must correct that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dwarves of Gauntlgrym found the primordial Maegera early in their habitation
of the city, but they left her sealed up for a few hundred years before messing
with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The massive project that bound her into a sort of arcane power generator was a
three-way joint project between the dwarves, the mages of Illusk and the elves
of Iliyanbruen. As we saw in the post about Shandarar, they were still around
for a few centuries after the fall of Netheril, so they took part in this as
well. The book describes this as a positive example of what the three peoples
can do when they work together, though it outlived their friendship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maegera’s power allowed the dwarves of Delzoun to create inumerable wonders, in
the form of both potent magical items and marvelous works of infrastructure for
their capital and their empire. Gauntlgrym became a big center of trade and even
saw numerous human families moving there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason it fell was because of the Orc Marches, a massive region-wide
invasion by an army of orcs larger than any seen before or since. By the time
this happened, the three peoples were no longer on speaking terms, as each had
grown more arrogant and mistrustful over time. They could have banded together
to repel the invasion, but each thought they could go it alone. Illusk fell
first, and Delzoun was next, and only at the gates of Shandarar was the
already-weakened orc army repelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iliyanbruen would end up dismantling anyway when it tried to take the fight to
the orcs in Illusk, as we saw earlier. Gauntlgrym was left alone since no one
seemed to be coming up from there. Its dwarven and humans refugees scattered all
over the Realms, with many of the humans joining Uthgardt tribes on the surface
and the dwarves ranging out further to move to their surviving nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The empire of Delzoun and its capital of Gauntlgrym are today kinda like the
dwarven equivalent of the Roman Empire in that stupid meme. No dwarf living
today has ever laid eyes on the lost city, but they think of it regularly and
describe it as the height of their civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gauntlgrym-today&quot;&gt;Gauntlgrym Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being lost to the surface, Gauntlgrym did not remain static in all these
millennia. The orcs were kicked out by mind flayers; the mind flayers by derro;
and the derro by duergar. That last one happened fairly recently in historical
terms, so the duergar still consider themselves masters of the place. However,
they are not the only people living there. There are other groups seeking to
control the city, and literal multitudes of ghosts belonging to its original
inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the city from the outside in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-great-cavern&quot;&gt;The Great Cavern&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever paths to Gauntlgrym exist in your campaign, they will always end
here. This is a massive natural cavern filled with alien Underdark vegetation
and labyrinthine formations of stone pillars and stalagmites. Small forts and
balconies are carved into the walls and around the largest pillars - the remains
of former guard posts. The bones of ancient battles litter the floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a small lake at the center of the cave, and on one of its walls stands
the massive mithral gate that leads into Gauntlgrym proper. It’s nearly
impossible to open by mundane or magical means, but a true heir of Delzoun can
open it with the slightest push. The cave is filled with your preferred
selection of Underdark monsters, and also with two sapient factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a group of old Ashmadai who came here with Valindra when she first
tried to free the primordial in that Drizzt novel. The tunnels they used filled
with magma at the end of that, so they became trapped here. Their first reaction
to any strangers they spot is violence, though some of them might be prepared to
surrender or betray the rest in exchange for a way back to the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second faction is the House Xorlarrin expedition, who arrived recently and
built a hidden camp. They’re spying on the Ashmadai while looking for a way to
open the gates. Their reaction to intruding PCs will be to remain hidden and spy
on them as well, waiting to see if they can open the gates. If they can, the
drow will follow them covertly, scattering if spotted, and will only attack if
the PCs become distracted by some other enemy inside the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-iron-tabernacle&quot;&gt;The Iron Tabernacle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iron Tabernacle was Gauntlgrym’s temple district, and was both the city’s
physical and spiritual center. Its many temples and shrines were dedicated to
Moradin and other good gods, and attended by a sizable contingent of dwarven and
human priests. This enormous multi-leveled district was a marvelous sight to
behold in its glory days, but now most of it lies ravaged by both time and by
duergar impiety. The city’s new occupants have defaced every religious image and
statue they could find, and stolen anything of value here, from precious relics
to the mithral trim in the walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the Tabernacle is so vast that some hidden shrines remain untouched and
could be reconsecrated by PCs. There’s a text box here detailing the minor boons
they can gain from doing so. An extended rest next to the restored shrine takes
only three hours instead of six, and has no danger of being interrupted by
wandering monsters. And if a member of the party is a non-evil dwarf or a
worshiper of Moradin, they might gain the attention of one of the city’s ghosts,
who will help them in battle the next time they fight (using a level-appropriate
incorporeal undead stat block). Both benefits only happen once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tabernacle is also the hub of Gaunglgrym’s ancient mine rail network. The
rails connect directly or indirectly to every other district in the city, and
are meant to be traveled by self-propelled mine carts that were used for bulk
cargo transport back in the day. They still run according to their ancient
schedules and could be commandeered by PCs. A big switching station in the
Tabernacle can let them switch carts from one track to another. It’s an easy
way to get around this vast city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps not so easy - there are some rules here that might come into play
when a fight happens during a cart ride, or when a cart &lt;em&gt;derails&lt;/em&gt; during a
fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-cemetery&quot;&gt;Ancient Cemetery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lowest level of the Tabernacle is a massive collection of crypts, laid out
according to a now forgotten scheme or tradition. Some are simple, some very
elaborate, but all of them have the names, titles, and lineage of their
occupants carved on their stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the upper levels, the crypts are intact. The many, many ghosts who roam
the place attack any would-be vandals and thieves en masse, so the duergar stay
away from here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ghosts will not bother the PCs at first, but will attack as above if they
try to damage or steal from the crypts. The group should take care to remain on
their best behavior while in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;theme-tie-ins-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Theme Tie-Ins and Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC theme that’s most interested in Gauntlgrym is definitely the Heir of
Delzoun. Finding this place is their life’s goal, so if your party includes one
or more Heirs Gauntlgrym is going to be a vitally important place for the
campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Heir and most other characters who might be interested in finding the
city, the true treasure here is all the historical and genealogical information
contained in the crypt walls. It’s a major archaeological finding all by itself,
which is reason enough for Oghma’s Faithful, but it’s even more valuable to the
Heir and perhaps even to the Neverwinter Noble. All dwarves, and a lot of human
nobles, keep pretty detailed genealogies of their own clans and families and
these would be easy to connect to the ones in display here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Noble could prove that their house is older than Neverwinter itself, then
they might have an unassailable claim to the throne! And if the Heir’s ancestors
are important enough, they might have a strong claim to &lt;em&gt;Gauntlgrym’s&lt;/em&gt; throne,
or perhaps to that of one of its successor states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not everyone would be happy with these findings. There are plenty of
dwarven nobles out there who built their prestige on forged lineages, and who
would not want the world to discover this fact. And many others who would be
more than happy to pull a Beloq and kill the PCs before they can announce their
findings to the world, so that they can claim the credit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “default” way to arrive at Gauntlgrym is to navigate the river of flame
beneath Mount Hotenow, but there could be other paths as well. Maybe they could
take a detour through Hotenow’s Shadowfell reflection, or maybe there’s a
mystical path similar to Shadowfell Road that takes those who follow it properly
to the mithral gates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next post, we dig too greedily and too deep.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/14/neverwinter-gauntlgrym.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/14/neverwinter-gauntlgrym.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Coiled Spring</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/coiled-spring.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Image source: &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://www.deviantart.com/eveyd/art/Antique-Vintage-Pocket-Watch-png-268108244&quot;&gt;EveyD
  on DeviantArt&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coiled Spring is an amulet made of brass. It’s disc shaped and about an inch
thick. On its front, there is a relief of a snake eating its own tail, the
classic Ouroboros. The inside of the ring formed by the snake is a clear crystal
panel, through which can be seen a spring like that of a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That spring can store up to ten Fatigue Points which can be used to enable
bursts of extra effort - most often &lt;em&gt;Extra Effort in Combat&lt;/em&gt; (p. B357), but also
other athletic feats. The stored FP can only be used for those purposes, and is
not affected by negative effects that would sap the user’s own FP. In other
words, it works just like the Heroic Reserves advantage from &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Dungeon
Fantasy 20: Slayers&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; like a power item for martial characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference between the Coiled Spring and a normal Power Item is that it
hijacks the natural recovery processes of the wearer’s body in order to “wind”
itself, and cannot be recharged by the usual methods for power items. While the
Spring is not at full capacity, its wearer is unable to recover their own
Fatigue Points, and the amulet gains 1 FP every 10 minutes. This is a constant
rate - traits which speed up FP recovery for the wearer have no effect on the
amulet. The wearer regains their usual ability to rest when the amulet is fully
charged, or when it’s removed (which stops the charging process).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this does mean recharging the Coiled Spring in town is effectively free,
it can make dungeon delving more complicated for martial characters,
particularly if the GM enforces rules like fatigue costs for fighting a battle
(p. B426 or DF Exploits p. 60). Characters who normally can’t use Fatigue Points
can wear the Coiled Spring and use it to benefit from the Extra Effort rules in
and out of combat, though they can’t recharge it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholars who know of the Spring speculate that it was originally meant  to allow
golems and other constructs to surpass their limits. In an adventure, it will
most likely be found worn by such a construct, or by an elite warrior who
figured out it works just as well for organics. If found in a chest or hoard,
though, it will always start out empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the delvers try to sell the Coiled Spring, or if you decide it’s available in
shops, its monetary value is twice that of a Power Item of the same
capacity. That’s $3400 for the 10 FP version described here, though you could
have versions with greater or smaller capacity. Note that you &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; double-dip
and use the Coiled Spring as a Power Item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variant Springs are possible. Maybe the Flywheel of Faith can power divine
magic, the Arcane Array wizardly spells, and the Goddess Gyre druidic ones. The
recharging mechanics and all other restrictions are the same. They could allow a
construct who can’t normally cast spells or use casting magical items due to a
lack of FP to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/10/coiled-spring.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/10/coiled-spring.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>artifact</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hacking Without a Hacker</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/lancer-horus.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    NPC hackers waiting for the PCs to arrive at the jackpoint.
    Illustration by Tom Parkinson Morgan.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether called a hacker, a decker, or a netrunner, the person who invades
computer systems and makes them do things features prominently in the stories
most cyberpunk RPGs take inspiration from, and so often ends up being a vitally
important archetype in those games. However, they tend to have a very mixed
track record when it comes to actually presenting you with a hacking system
that’s fun and bug-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means there are many possible reasons for why you might find yourself
planning a cyberpunk game but have no cause or wish to use its hacking
rules. Maybe none of the players wants to be a hacker, or maybe the group just
doesn’t like the rules of the game in question. In those cases, a popular
suggestion is to include a NPC hacker, and in this post we’ll discuss a way to
do so that keeps the rest of the group reasonably involved in the hacking. Rules
are for GURPS, but the concepts can be easily translated to other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-from-home&quot;&gt;Work From Home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current best practice in games that include hacker PCs is to devise ways to
keep the hacker together with the rest of the party, so that they can fully
participate in the game even when it’s not hacking time. When your group’s
hacker is an NPC, however, the best thing to do is the opposite. Hacker NPCs
should always do their thing remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing NPCs who constantly accompany the party is a tricky affair. A character
who’s much weaker than the party runs the risk of turning the adventure into a
video-game-style escort quest, one of the most reviled types of mission in
existence. One who is strong enough to protect themselves can end up becoming a
GMPC, a label reserved for annoying characters who overshadow the players and
make them feel like the support cast of someone else’s story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is subjective, which makes it even trickier. Your group’s fun will
be hurt if they &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; either of those scenarios is happening, even if the math
is well-balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remote hacker removes most of the risk. They’re in communication with the
group, and they can do the jobs covered by their niche, but any other challenge
that can be handled by the PC’s own skills &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be, even if it’s
technological in nature. And there are things the hacker can only do with
on-site support from the PCs, which keeps them involved in the actual hack even
if you’re not engaging with those rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact nature of these support tasks depends on how your specific setting
handles computers and hacking. Most games either go the same Retro way of early
Shadowrun and CP2020, or a more “Modern” way that uses more recent tropes such
as the ones employed by Shadowrun 4th Edition or CP2077. We’ll look at how you
can accommodate a remote NPC hacker in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future-of-another-timeline&quot;&gt;The Future of Another Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not immediately obvious to us here in 2023, but the earliest iterations of
Shadowrun’s Matrix and CP2020’s NET were based on a pre-Internet model of
networked computing. Strip all the futuristic terms from their description and
you’ll find out you’re dealing with 80s mainframes. This lies at the root of a
lot of things there that can look a bit weird or silly to modern
readers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Here’s a short and approximately correct explanation for how that
works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainframes are huge (and hugely expensive) computers that are usually
responsible for handling all data processing for an entire company or
organization. They were the dominant form of institutional computing from around
the 1950s to at least the early 1990s, and never really went away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mainframe is operated through remote terminals, which can be in the same
building or even off-site. Therefore, it must be ready to receive connections
and requests from these terminals. And the way you do that in the 80s is through
phone lines and modems. They do have &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; security measures to
authenticate users and prevent one user from seeing or changing other users’
data, but there is no such thing as a firewall because permanent Internet
connections are not yet a thing for mainframes. The most security you can add to
the connection step is to keep the numbers for your mainframe’s phone lines
unlisted&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is why both Shadowrun’s and CP2020’s descriptions of their “global
nets” are so concerned about splitting them into geographical regions and
assigning codes to them and the servers within them. That net is not the
&lt;em&gt;Internet&lt;/em&gt;, but a world-spanning phone circuit. The first step to hacking
into that corporate mainframe is to dial the unlisted number of its modem&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-school-remote-hacking&quot;&gt;Old-School Remote Hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have a PC hacker in these more “retro” games, the number of the
target’s modem line might be included with the mission briefing, letting them
hack removely. It’s more likely that no number is included, then the hacker has
to go in with the group and find an terminal in the target facility through
which they could connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a hacker NPC and they have the number, the reason the adventure is
happening at all is because the mission objectives have a physical component
that must happen at the same time. The typical setup is that you need to steal
the physical prototype while the hacker grabs the research files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don’t have the number, then &lt;em&gt;discovering&lt;/em&gt; the number becomes one of the
physical mission objectives! The place the PCs are infiltrating might not even
have any direct relation to the real, final objective, but it could be a place
that also uses the same mainframe remotely. The number is going to be written
down somewhere in there, either in an official manual, some employee’s personal
notes or even a scrap of paper that was carelessly thrown away&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Some
non-VR-dungeon hacking of a physical terminal to peek at its configuration might
be necessary, which might be resolved by a couple of rolls since dumb terminals
are less secure than the mainframe they talk to. Or you might need to find a way
to scam the info out of an someone who works there (“social engineering”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fact-finding expedition could be a whole adventure in itself, or it might
just be an intermediate step in a more complex operation where the group must
also infiltrate the final target facility at the same time as the hacker does
their thing, as outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twenty-minutes-from-now&quot;&gt;Twenty Minutes From Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent cyberpunk games tend to base their networks on the real-world
Internet and the technologies that support it. This means that every individual
device attached to a network is effectively a full-feature computer, be it an
employee’s workstation, a security camera, or a guard’s smartphone. Different
departments have their own private servers and their own internal network that
doesn’t necessarily connect to the others or to the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less sensitive facilities might allow employees to work remotely from their
homes or from other buildings by letting them connect via &lt;em&gt;virtual private
networks&lt;/em&gt;. These connections to happen over the Internet, but they’re encrypted
and protected from general snooping. Realistically, our dastardly hacker would
need to steal valid credentials to be able to access a VPN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other extreme, a top-secret secure facility might be &lt;em&gt;air-gapped&lt;/em&gt;, which
means it’s isolated and sealed in such a way that no signal can enter or leave
the building. None of its internal networks are connected to the outside world,
and they are not connected to each other either unless this is absolutely
necessary. The servers controlling the security system are isolated from the
servers housing sensitive data. Each has its own independent set of protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is both realistic according to our contemporary understanding of network
security, and an excellent way to make sure PC hackers stick with the group and
have plenty to do once inside. Individual hacking attempts tend to be shorter
but more numerous, and made against devices that are within the hacker’s
immediate reach&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Shadowrun 4th Edition goes deep into this (5th and onwards
go back to the retro model), and it’s also more or less how things work in
Cyberpunk 2077.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-school-remote-hacking&quot;&gt;New-School Remote Hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an environment so full of incentives for the hacker to stick with the party,
how can you accommodate a remote NPC hacker?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the target facility has a VPN that contains the data you want, then many of
the same “classic” techniques for acquiring those old-school mainframe phone
numbers might also work to acquire valid VPN credentials, allowing the NPC to
hack the place remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it doesn’t have a VPN or is completely isolated, then we need to resort to
quantum bullshit. Below we’ll see GURPS stats for the bullshit in question,
imported directly from Warframe. It’s easily usable in other systems, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/CorpusDatamass.webp&quot; width=200/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A datamass.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;datamass&lt;/strong&gt; is a device similar in concept to the causality communicator in
Ultra-Tech page 45, but &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; cheaper. It consists of an armored,
briefcase-sized device that incorporates several kinds of data cable plus laser
and IR micro-communicators and a small radio (GURPS Ultratech pages 43-44). All
of these are connected to a sizable amount of quantum-entangled matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Datamasses are made in entangled pairs that allow high-bandwidth communication
and data transfer between elements of the pair through any amount of barriers or
interference. They have DR 10, HP 8, cost $5000 for the pair, weight 5kg (10 lb)
each, and are LC1 (AKA &lt;em&gt;super illegal&lt;/em&gt;). They also include an emergency
self-destruct switch that melts the internals of both elements of the pair and
can be triggered from either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your typical cyberpunk setting, datamasses were first invented as
super-secret espionage tools by a major government or computer-focused megacorp,
and initially gave them a major leg up in one of the many ongoing cold wars
between such entities. The secret of their existence soon leaked, however, and
an enterprising independent engineer figured out they were quite easy to make
with a properly modified home 3d printer. Yes, even the entangled matter. The
plans for a home-baked datamasses were soon made widely available on the Net,
and they keep popping up no matter how much effort the corps spend to squash
them. That’s why they’re relatively cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Datamass technology is going to be really revolutionary when FTL travel is
invented in the distant future, but for now it’s mostly used for its original
purpose, and allows teams of plucky street mercs like the PCs to operate at the
same level as crack corporate commandos when it comes to high-level
espionage. If the PCs are hired to do a hacking mission, they will usually be
provided a datamass pair. PCs can also buy their own through the usual illegal
channels available to PCs in these games. It should be difficult, but not
impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a setting that has datamasses, hacking missions look a lot like the Warframe
“mobile defense” missions these devices come from. The PCs need to sneak into
the target facility carrying a datamass, and find a place where to connect it. A
direct cable connection to a machine in the target network is best. A wi-fi
connection will do in a pinch, but will make everything that follows take
longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the hacker is an NPC, you don’t need to roll anything for the actual
hack - you just need to give the PCs a time frame for when it will be done. And
then they must stay near the datamass and guard it until that much time has
elapsed. If they snuck in, they need to find a way to maintain stealth and
divert security attention from their access point. If they’re found out, it
turns into a fight, but they still must stay until the hack is done or it will
fail. For added Fun(TM), a difficult mission might require the party to do this
several times from different access points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-destruct switch is useful for when the hack is done, as it allows the
party to leave without having to lug the datamass back out. It can also prevent
the hacker from being traced if the device is captured. Or it can be used in a
double-cross that leaves the team stranded in enemy territory without network
support. Use that last one sparingly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Alas, it’s not related to the whole VR Dungeon thing. That’s weird and
silly for other reasons. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The real-world practice of &lt;em&gt;wardialing&lt;/em&gt; consisted of dialing every number
in a big list or an entire area code looking for accessible modems. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And you can absolutely go wardialiing there. The Genesis version of
Shadowrun even implements it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The real world hacking practice of &lt;em&gt;dumpster diving&lt;/em&gt; consists in searching
a company’s trash for discarded papers with valid passwords and credentials
written down on them. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anywhere from “directly plugged in” to “in the same local wi-fi network”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Mount Hotenow</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Mount Hotenow is a huge barely-dormant volcano on the southeast end of the
Crags, in Neverwinter Wood. The heat it produces is the reason the region’s
rivers never freeze, and therefore it’s at the root of Neverwinter’s
prosperity. It was also the cause of its downfall 27 years ago, when a Thayan
ritual caused it to erupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before the cataclysm Mount Hotenow was already the subject of many rumors
and legends. It’s an opening to Hell; it’s an opening to the Elemental Chaos;
demons live here; giants live here; dragons live here; and so on. The most
recent tale is that anyone who enters one of Hotenow’s many caves is fated to
die within a year, even if they make it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fire-cultists&quot;&gt;Fire Cultists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the original mountain in the middle world is back to its pre-cataclysm
state, its reflection on the Shadowfell has been spewing a slow and steady
stream of lava since the cataclysm. Some people believe that this shadow
eruption could cause one in the middle world if the barriers between planes wear
thin enough. Such a state of constant eruption would spell doom for Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chief among these believers are the many elemental fire creatures that do indeed
make Mount Hotenow their home. They’re led by the hunchbacked fire giant
Gommoth, who has lived here since he was banished from his clan. The eruption 27
years ago was a major ecstatic experience to him and to every other fire
creature who lived here, and since then Gommoth started a cult dedicated to
making it happen again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecstatic experience happened because it was Maegera’s near-awakening that
caused the eruption, and her power tugged at the elementals’ primordial
nature. Gommoth doesn’t know this, but the cult’s latest rising star probably
does. This is Qualthus, the shadovar outcast. Remember him? He was banished from
Xinlenal after being blamed for the accidental sabotage of their mythallar. True
to the general disposition of his former buddies, Qualthus has decided that the
best way to remedy this injustice is to cause Mount Hotenow to erupt again and
bury Xinlenal in lava.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s confident he can do it. After all he’s an arcanist of the Netherese
tradition (read: a megalomaniacal asshole). His actual chances are incredibly
small, after all it took the full might of the Dread Ring to make it happen the
first time. But he could get lucky, since Maegera’s bonds are weakened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To represent Gommoth, the book suggests using an ogre mercenary stat block with
added fire resistance, increased Charisma, and with attacks doing fire
damage. You could also level down a standard fire giant stat block to make him
fit with the campaign’s level range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-river-of-flame&quot;&gt;The River Of Flame&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep underground, beneath the territory of the fire cultists, there is a river
of liquid flame. This isn’t poetic language or a metaphor for magma, but a
literal description. The river follows a winding subterranean path, and the
important thing for player characters is that it passes by a tunnel that leads
directly to Gauntlgrym.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs who know where to disembark could take some sort of fireproof boat or
submersible through this river, and arrive at the lost city. Their main
challenge here besides the hostile environment is Karrundax, the very
territorial young red dragon who lairs in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;seekers-of-the-way&quot;&gt;Seekers of the Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that happens repeatedly in this book is that a theme description in
Chapter 2 will give us the impression that the PC in question is the only one
doing something, and then a faction or location description further down the
line will give us a whole group of NPCs with the same goal, and that’s going to
be the first time we hear of these NPCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be a disconnect between different authors, or it might be a sort of
soft “Player’s Guide/Campaign Setting” separation within the same book, since
presumably you want PCs to choose a theme without seeing any spoilers about what
they’ll encounter during the campaign. Whatever the case, we now run into the
group that ties to the Heir of Delzoun, and it’s a genuine Dwarf Fortress
expedition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Heir’s description actively lied to the player: they’re not one of the last
dwarves who are still looking for the lost city. In reality there are so many
that after their disparate teams and groups joined together to coordinate their
efforts they had to elect a government to keep them organized. Their newly
elected leader decided that Mount Hotenow was their best bet, since there were
many stories connecting it to Gauntlgrym and a few confirmed Delzoun outposts on
its slopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extremely large expedition set out from Neverwinter before the Heir got
here, and the litany of setbacks and tragedies they experienced along the way is
what gives me that Fun (TM) Dwarf Fortress vibe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First they bought a letter of safe passage from Neverember in order to pass
through Many-Arrows territory unharmed, but the dwarves and orcs just couldn’t
resist provoking each other until hostilities broke out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they arrived at the Wood and lost yet more dwarves to eladrin arrows and
miscellaneous monsters. Either Shandarar’s guardians were particularly
trigger-happy or it was those old rivalries flaring up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they got to the volcano and lost a bunch more dwarves to Gommoth’s cult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now they’re stuck at the river of flame. Can’t forge ahead because no one
packed a fireproof submersible, can’t retreat because the survivors aren’t sure
they can make it back to Neverwinter alive. To say that morale is low is a
massive understatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morale would be even lower if the expedition’s leader, Vandra Hillborn, revealed
the terrible secret she’s keeping. Many of the dwarves “lost” to the elementals
actually &lt;em&gt;defected&lt;/em&gt; to them, and now work together to bring about the volcano’s
next eruption. Hillborn believes they cracked under the strain of the trip and
went insane, but the truth is even worse: they were intentionally driven insane
by the Gauntlgrym mind-flayers through remote telepathy. The flayers believe
that a volcanic eruption is just the thing to permanently block access to
Gauntlgrym and prevent any meddlers from finding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know, the mind flayers are themselves being controlled by the
aboleths, so we have a true conspiracy onion here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to discover Gauntlgrym’s precise location elsewhere, but
the River of Flame under Mount Hotenow appears to be the most viable path to
actually go there. The fate of the dwarven expedition is a good blueprint of
what an overland journey from Neverwinter to here would involve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible to have an entire party of PCs who would be more interested in
pursuing this journey than dealing with the other hooks in the setting: not just
one or more Heirs of Delzoun but also perhaps one of Oghma’s Faithful who’s
really into archaeology, a Dead Rat Deserter who’s after the score of the
century, and even a Neverwinter Noble in a campaign where finding Gauntlgrym
will give them the popular acclaim they need to take the throne. If there’s an
extended detour to deal with the eladrin, then perhaps the Iliyanbruen Guardian
can get into the mix too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/06/neverwinter-hotenow.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/06/neverwinter-hotenow.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Xinlenal and Related Locations</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post covers the city itself and several nearby locations related to the
Gray Wolf Uthgardt, who serve the Netherese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-warning-brutal-savages-nonsense&quot;&gt;Content Warning: “Brutal Savages” nonsense&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of Gray Wolf material in this section, and this is where the
mounting inconsistencies in their portrayal start to get in the way. The stuff
about them that I read so far gave me the impression of a people who were mostly
minding their own business before the Netherese turned their leaders into
fascist assholes. Most of the actual tribe members were not happy with the
situation: a significant number of them had defected, and those who hadn’t were
open to persuasion by a PC like the Pack Outcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section drops most of that and goes all in on the “brutal savages who
disdain civilization” cliches, painting the Gray Wolf as being bad guys even
before the Netherese got to them. After being co-opted, they got even worse.
Anyone who’s still a member of the tribe at this point is either on board with
the cruelty or too cowardly to ever stand against it. Even their guardian
spirits are disgusted with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to report what the book says below, but I personally would completely
change it were I to run a Neverwinter campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;xinlenal-from-the-outside-in&quot;&gt;Xinlenal From the Outside In&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw before, Xinlenal wasn’t just a Netherese flying city, it was the first
ever built. It fell here in the Wood when Netheril’s magic stopped
working. Today, when viewed from the outside, it looks like an out-of-place
60-foot tall plateau jutting up from the ground in an otherwise flat area of the
Wood. The structures atop it are hidden from view by the Wood’s vegetation,
which grew over it in the two millennia since the city crashed. The Shadovar led
by Prince Clariburnus use Xinlenal as their main base of operations in the
region, and are hard at work trying to make it fly again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-forest-of-hides&quot;&gt;The Forest of Hides&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gray Wolf recognize this is the center of Netherese power even though they
don’t know what goes on in here. So when they declared war on the Forsworn, they
started hanging up the skins of their “traitorous kinfolk” in a clearing outside
the plateau. This acts as both a warning to enemies and as a show of support for
their new masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the sheer brutality of this practice has led many rank-and-file Gray
Wolf to question their leadership, and the horrible smell of dead werewolf
lingering about the place acts as a cover for Forsworn spies and makes it easier
for them to scout the plateau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act of building the Forest of Hides outraged and horrified many of the
primal spirits who used to be friends of the Grey Wolf. If the Pack Outcast,
Uthgardt Barbarian, or any other PC who uses primal powers dismantle the Forest
of Hides, those spirits will reward them with a daily power named &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the
Fallen&lt;/strong&gt;, which can be activated after an attack hits and makes the target
vulnerable 5 to all damage (save ends), including that of the triggering
attack. Once the target saves, they take another 10 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you see the first instance of what I talked about in the intro paragraphs
above. There’s more below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-city-and-the-web-of-stone&quot;&gt;The City and the Web of Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The walls of the plateau are a sheer climb, but they look natural after two
millennia of weathering. Some flying monsters even made lairs there. The city at
the top looks completely ruined when viewed from the plateau’s edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those moving towards the center will soon spot a massive suspended “web” made of
stone looming over the skyline. This acts as a gigantic crane and construction
tool used in the Shadovar’s renovation efforts. It can lift whole city blocks
for relocation, or remove an equivalent quantity of soil and vegetation to
reveal the structures buried beneath. Workers both organic and artificial are
constantly swarming all over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This web was built by the shadar-kai witch Korvina, who realized she could use
residual energy from the city’s old protection rituals to power it. Later she
would find out she was actually drawing power from the city’s broken mythallar
and delaying its repairs. When her bosses found out about the oopsie, she
managed to pin the blame for it on her colleague Qualthus, whose fate we’ll
learn in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-womb-of-stone&quot;&gt;The Womb of Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gee, these Netherese sure have a knack for naming things, don’t they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This building is an ancient construct factory reactivated by the Shadovar. This
is where they build all the thaalud constructs they’re using as a workforce. The
ones they build today aren’t as powerful as the ones from ancient Netheril
(using the thaalud constructor stat block from earlier in this book), but they
can do their job just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Womb of Stone is run and operated by a shade named Ulrukan (stats as a human
slaver with shade traits). His left arm and leg are animated prosthetic
constructs, which I think is awesome. Ulrukan discovered the problem with the
Web of Stone before anyone else, decided to keep it to himself until he could
gain something by revealing it, and lost the chance to do so when other people
found the issue and reported it immediately. Now that it’s public he’s trying to
figure out how to extract some advantage from the fact that he knew it before
anyone else did. I don’t think he knows it’s Korvina’s fault, or he’d already be
blackmailing her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cathedral-of-night&quot;&gt;Cathedral of Night&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a ancient building repurposed as a temple to the goddess Shar. The
exterior is still ruined and worn, but the interior is very fancy and all done
up in onyx and jet. It’s also protected by enchanted hungry shadows, a very
interesting hazard that can temporarily remove PCs from play and cause ongoing
psychic and necrotic damage to them while they’re gone. This security protects
the usual temple treasures and also a portal to the Shadowfell, which is used by
the Shadovar to access their supply routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orthinos Eln is the priest in charge of both the temple and the restoration
project. He can be found here either meditating or communing with his boss
Prince Clariburnus, who leads the faction as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xinlenals-heart&quot;&gt;Xinlenal’s Heart&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt; is located at its very center. The tower that houses it
was the first building to be completely restored, and a small army of Shadovar
artificers is now busy restoring the artifact itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The restoration process is simple to describe but very hard to execute. It
consists of mixing melted glass with large quantities of residuum, carefully
pouring the resulting substance over the &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt;, and molding it so that it
slowly recovers its original spherical shape. Right now it looks like a partial
sphere, already over 100 feet (30 meters!) in diameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why the Netherese are scouring the region’s many ruins and dungeons for
magic items and other ancient enchanted relics, and also why they’re poised to
begin raiding Neverwinter. All of that loot is going to get destroyed for its
residuum. The Shadovar are burning the legacies of others to rebuild their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central tower is also where their main war room is located, as well as
Clariburnus’ quarters and throne room. He can either be found here coordinating
the faction’s overall strategy, or somewhere out in the world leading another
raid for magic items. He also sometimes brings members of the Gray Wolf
leadership here for briefings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vellosk&quot;&gt;Vellosk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the main “settlement” of the Gray Wolf tribe, located in the Wood away
from Xinlenal. The quotes are there because they are mostly nomadic, and this is
just where a few more permanent structures are built - pack leader’s homes, a
feast hall, and some other communal buildings. You can also find a number of
tents and lean-tos scattered around the area, belonging to other tribe members
who are currently staying there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book says the Grey Wolf have the technology to make weapons and tools as
sophisticated as that of Neverwinter, but that they have no real culture to
speak of beyond an obsession with behaving like D&amp;amp;D’s idea of a wolf pack. It
could be that this is what the current leadership thinks, but the way the book
phrases it kinda makes me think this is what they were like even before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vellosk’s central feature is a sloped pit whose bottom is coated in dry bones,
and also contains a totem pole decorated with animal skulls. This is their
center of worship, dedicated to Uthgar and the tribe’s guardian spirits. It’s
also where ritual combats and duels happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the permanent structures here is the home of Ormshas, a dark creeper
necromancer who is here officially as a Netherese ambassador and in reality as a
spy placed to make sure the Grey World remain under control. She has a large
group of wraiths under her control, which she uses to uncover secrets and
silence dissenters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gray-wolf-and-the-pcs&quot;&gt;The Gray Wolf and the PCs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the rank-and-file Grey Wolf are very unhappy with the direction the
tribe is taking, but they also believe their leaders’ commands are absolute and
those leaders have been completely bought the Netherese party line. Many tribe
members would rather leave than try to challenge their leaders, but these days
those who express a desire to leave are executed on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs such as the Pack Outcast or the Uthgardt Barbarian would have an easier time
convincing the Grey Wolf to reject their leadership, but they would still need
to challenge those leaders to ritual combat and win (or convince/help a friendly
Gray Wolf to do so). Ritual combat is, of course, to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a legitimate challenge would also require convincing a majority of the
tribe that their leaders are being bamboozled by the Netherese. Just going for
the leaders at once is a sure way to get the whole tribe to declare war on you
no matter what they think about those leaders, so it’s not a good option for
most groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conyberry&quot;&gt;Conyberry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conyberry is a small village at the edge of the Wood that became quite scenic
during the Spellplague when a populated slice of Abeir was isekaied there. It
gained a new lake, a bunch of floating earthmotes, and a mixed population that
learned to live well together after some initial friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately you don’t get to see that version of it, because the Grey Wolf
killed everyone long before the Netherese even got to them. According to the
book they believed the people from Abeir to be hostile invaders and the people
of Conyberry to be their co-conspirators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gray Wolf used the now empty village as a storage area for a time. No one
else went there because everyone (rightly) assumed it had been destroyed after
news stopped coming, and when someone did stumble into the place they were
killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Netherese recruited them they started using the village to, in the
words of the book, “practice civilized behavior” so that they would blend into
the communities they were ordered to infiltrate. Now when outsiders end up there
by accident they’re received by a bunch of Gray Wolf in sheep’s clothing eager
to test their acting skills. Only after the actors are satisfied, or when
they’re found out, do the murder attempts start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xinlenal itself seems like a good dungeon location. A final battle against
Caliburnus in the &lt;em&gt;mythallar&lt;/em&gt; chamber would look awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But everything about the description of the Gray Wolf kinda ruins it. The text
is filled with the exact set of racist tropes that draw so much criticism to
D&amp;amp;D. I’m left with the distinct impression that the Gray Wolf are described as
being bad &lt;em&gt;because they’re tribal&lt;/em&gt;, in contrast to the “civilized” people they
disdain and victimize. Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s definitely something I’d completely rewrite if I ever ran a campaign in
this setting. It actually kinda tainted the good memories I had of this book,
and made me stop writing new Let’s Read material for it for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/01/neverwinter-xinlenal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/01/neverwinter-xinlenal.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
