<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 17:14:37 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 17:14:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Retriever</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrievers first appeared in the Fiend Folio for AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition. They make
their 4e debut here in the Monster Manual 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-retriever.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrievers are powerful constructs shaped like giant spiders, built by the
primordials themselves during the Dawn War to carry out kidnappings, thefts, and
assassinations. They’re not smart enough to do anything outside their intended
function, but when it comes to their mission there’s no one better in existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once given a target, a retriever can track it from anywhere in the multiverse
and teleport to its location instantly. If they’re retrieving, they can grab the
target and skedaddle. If they’re assassinating, they can count on their huge
size, bladed legs, and multi-directional eye rays to flatten almost any
opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primordials can really build things to last when they care to. A significant
number of retrievers survived the War and is still active today, which is very
bad news for the world because some demons have learned how to command
them. Back in the days of AD&amp;amp;D, retrievers were linked to Demogorgon in
particular, but now they could be found in the service of any demon lord or
other entity of similar power. Perhaps some of them still act at the behest of a
primordial, and Lolth is spidery enough to want a bunch of them working for
her. Make any of them angry enough and a few retrievers might show up at your
home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrievers are Huge Elemental Animates, but though they are described as
constructs they lack the Construct keyword. They’re Level 27 Soldiers with 248
HP, immunity to Charm and Fear, and Resist 5 to all damage. They run at speed 8,
but have no climb speed despite looking like spiders. Their special senses
include darkvision and truesight 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A retriever has Reach 3 and two basic attacks: a standard &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; strike and
&lt;strong&gt;Retrieve&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Fortitude, deals claw damage and grabs the
target. A retriever can move its grabbed victim without needing to make Strength
tests, so they can easily “grab and go”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also has access to four different &lt;strong&gt;eye rays&lt;/strong&gt;, each pairing a type of
elemental damage with a different rider: acid and blindness, cold and
immobilization, fire and ongoing damage, thunder and stun. The creature can fire
all four in the same action, but must target a different creature with each. At
the start of each turn, a random ray recharges. This means a second full blast
takes a while, but it can fire a partial one if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the retriever is hard-pressed it can take an action to engage in
&lt;strong&gt;Self-Repair&lt;/strong&gt;, recovering 20 HP and gaining a +4 bonus to AC for a turn. This
recharges once it’s first bloodied. Might be a good thing to do when it manages
to run away with its victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally we have the power that makes it truly fearsome: &lt;strong&gt;Unerring
Accuracy&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it to sense the approximate location of its target and
teleport to within 10 squares of it &lt;em&gt;from anywhere in the
multiverse&lt;/em&gt;. Demogorgon is pissed at you, gives your name to a retriever in his
throne room and bam, giant spider mech bursting through your bedroom wall. This
is a daily power, so I guess a retriever on a kidnapping mission needs at least
a few hours before it can return to its master. That’s your window to rescue
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The order doesn’t even have to be very specific. “Bring me an elf” will allow it
to teleport to the location of the nearest elf, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being an epic spider mech, the retriever is a Regular, which means it
will usually be found as part of a group. This can mean “multiple retrievers”,
or it can mean other epic assassin-types who hitch a ride on the teleport. Maybe
they’re riding a howdah atop the spider body - it’d be the perfect place for
some epic artillery or controller monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, they might be found under the command of a less sophisticated
type of demon who prefers to use them as bodyguards and extra muscle in a more
straightforward combat scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter could belong to either type: a marilith with an entourage
composed of an abyssal rotfiend and 2 retrievers (level 26).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/retriever.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/retriever.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Remorhaz</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered remorhazes in the 3e Monster Manual, though I guess they’ve
been around since AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remorhazes are yet another example of the dangerous megafauna that plagues D&amp;amp;D
worlds: gigantic predators with a somewhat centipede-like appearance that
inhabit the colder reaches of the world. They’re also one of those gotcha
monsters, because despite living in cold biomes their powers are heat-based. A
remorhaz can heat its carapace up to an extremely high temperature, which really
ruins the day of the usually-weak-to-fire creatures it feeds on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remorhaz is big enough to swallow a frost giant or adult dragon whole, and
while it use that as a combat maneuver it prefers to do it when the prey in
question is no longer fighting back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frost giants sometimes risk training these creatures. A few of them even
succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-remorhaz.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remorhazes are Huge Elemental Beasts, and Level 21 Elite Brutes with 480 HP. It
has low-light vision and projects an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Blistering Heat&lt;/strong&gt; that does
10 fire damage to any creature caught inside. It runs at speed 6 and burrows at
speed 4 with Tunneling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and grabs on a hit. After
grabbing a creature they can spend a minor action to try to &lt;strong&gt;Swallow&lt;/strong&gt; it (an
attack vs. Fortitude). The beast’s insides deal 10 physical and 10 fire damage
to swallowed victims at the start of its turn. The victim is considered
restrained, with line of sight and effect only to the remorhaz itself. It can
use only melee or close attacks (with penalties from the Restrained condition),
and if it manages to deal 30 damage the remorhaz will spit them out. Killing the
creature also allows the victim to escape, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an oversight here, I think, because the ability doesn’t list a size
limit for which creatures can be swallowed. I’d say Large or smaller is a good
value for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remorhaz can also &lt;strong&gt;Trample&lt;/strong&gt;, moving its speed, crossing enemy spaces, and
making a physical attack that damages and knocks prone against each enemy whose
space it moves through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That heated carapace can do more than project an aura, too. It can flare up in
an &lt;strong&gt;Immolating Carapace&lt;/strong&gt; attack (close burst 1 vs. Reflex; recharge 6) that
deals fire damage and inflicts ongoing fire damage that lasts while the targets
are adjacent to the beast. Yes, this stacks with the aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the remorhaz is bloodied, it can also use &lt;strong&gt;Enraged Heat&lt;/strong&gt; to deal
automatic fire damage to someone who hits it in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good tactic for them seems to be to bite and swallow a PC who can’t put up
much of a fight from the inside, and then run around trampling and roasting the
rest with Immolating Carapace to prevent them from surrounding the remorhaz. An
individual who’s only interested in a quick meal might even try to swallow a PC
and run away to digest them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remorhazes being used as attack beasts by giants will be more ready to fight a
battle to the end, and in that case they might wait to swallow a PC who falls to
0 HP. The others would need to kill the creature in order to heal their
buddy. Welcome to epic level!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 18: A frost giant acting as a beastmaster of
sorts, accompanied by a remorhaz and a rime hound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I had a bit of a hard time distinguishing between a remorhaz and
a behir in earlier editions. The distinction is clearer to me now, but only
because I spent some time studying their entries in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/remorhaz.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/remorhaz.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Phoelarch</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-phoelarch.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seem to remember phoelarches appearing in one of the late Monster Manuals for
3e. I don’t know if they appeared before that. Their 4e debut is here in the
MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Phoelarch is a fiery humanoid native to the Elemental Chaos. Their orange skin
and fiery hair makes them look kinda like a human-like version of the azer, or a
slightly differerent fire genasi. They’re typically nomadic and adventurous, and
so could be found wandering anywhere in the universe. But when you see a
phoelarch you’re seeing just half the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soul of every phoelarch is connected to that of a &lt;em&gt;phoera&lt;/em&gt;, a fire bird
that’s pretty much a mini-phoenix. Phoeras soar through the skies of the
Elemental Chaos, living their bird lives. Though smaller than phoenixes, they’re
still giant territorial birds of prey and have quite a temper, so they can end
up attacking passing adventurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, a phoelarch doesn’t have a lot to do with their phoera and
vice-versa. They have a vague sense of each others’ personality and emotions,
but each lives their own life, and has thoughts and concerns that are utterly
alien to the other. It’s quite possible for them to never meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when one member of the pair is killed, the connection instantly summons
the other one, which will arrive knowing what happened and will be
understandably very angry at the perpetrators. Since phoelarches are more
widespread, the most common scenario likely has the PCs fighting them first and
then the phoera, but I suppose it could happen the other way around. As long as
one member of the pair survives, the other will eventually return to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoeras are Medium Elemental Magical Beasts with the Fire keyword. The two
phoelarches we get here are tagged as Medium Natural Humanoids, but I really
think they should be Elemental as well and have the Fire keyword. As sapient
humanoids, a lot of their abilities come from training, so we get two stat
blocks for them. They still tend to use a lot of fire, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the individual stat blocks here are regulars, but they’re really “disguised”
elites when you think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phoelarch-mage&quot;&gt;Phoelarch Mage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoelarch mages love fire magic, and travel the world looking for adventuresome
mentors who can teach them using practical lessons instead of classroom
work. Some seek out their linked phoeras in order to gain a deeper understanding
of their link and of fire magic in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Phoelarch Mage is Level 12 Artillery with 93 HP. They have Resist 10 Fire,
Vulnerable 5 Cold, and project an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Phoenix Heat&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals 5
damage to any creatures caught inside. That means you should be careful with
their formation if they’re partnering up with flammable allies. Their ground
speed is 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mage’s basic attacks are a &lt;strong&gt;burning dagger&lt;/strong&gt; and a Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;phoenix
ray&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which deal fire damage. They also know a spell named &lt;strong&gt;Flames of
the Phoenix&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which is pretty much your typical fireball: area
effect, fire damage, plus ongoing fire damage. Presumably they also know plenty
of non-combat rituals, but those don’t appear in stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the mage drops to 0 HP their &lt;strong&gt;Rise from the Ashes&lt;/strong&gt; ability triggers and
they explode. This deals heavy fire damage (vs. Reflex) in a Close Burst 2. It
also creates a zone of fire that lasts until the end of the encounter and
damages anyone caught inside. Finally, when the mage’s next turn comes up, a
phoera appears within the zone and joins the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phoelarch-warrior&quot;&gt;Phoelarch Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoelarch warriors are usually wandering mercenaries that seek to get hired as
independent skirmishers and special forces. While their moral outlook is as
varied as that of any sapient, even a dastardly warrior will usually refuse to
work for slavers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Warrior is a Level 12 Skirmisher with 114 HP. They have the same
resistances and aura as the mage, and a Speed of 7. Their main attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;burning falchion&lt;/strong&gt; that deals fire damage and is a High-Crit weapon. They also
have a &lt;strong&gt;Burning Step&lt;/strong&gt; trait that deals automatic fire damage to anyone who
hits them with an opportunity attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the mage, the warrior also explodes when dead, creating a fiery zone and
being replaced by their phoera in the next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phoera&quot;&gt;Phoera&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoeras are level 12 Skirmishers with 114 HP. As magical beasts they’re sapient
and can talk, but their toughts are usually a bit alien to your typical humanoid
and even to their linked phoelarch. They have Resist 15 Fire and Vulnerable 5
Cold, and a damaging fire aura (2) similar to that of the phoelarch, but
larger. They run at speed 6 and fly at speed 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoeras fight with &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; that do physical and ongoing fire damage, and can
shoot &lt;strong&gt;feathers of flame&lt;/strong&gt; in a close blast 4 pattern. They can perform either
of those as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt; as well, flying their speed without
provoking opportunity attacks and making the attack at any point in the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they die, they explode and leave a fiery zone just like a phoelarch. If
their phoelarch is already dead, that’s the end of it. If not, it’d make sense
for the phoelarch to appear in this zone next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 12: a phoelarch warrior who fell in with a briar
witch dryad and a few snaketongue cultists. Do mind your positioning on this
one, as all of the phoelarch’s allies are very flammable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the phoelarch/phoera gimmick! Without it, they’d be just another “generic
fire guy” alongside azers, genasi and salamanders.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/06/phoelarch.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/06/phoelarch.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nordlond Bestiary Kickstarter Campaign</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit late to the promotion bandwagon for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;Nordlond Bestiary&lt;/a&gt;, since
there’s only a few days left in the project. But I’m still going to say it: go
back the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;Nordlond Bestiary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is already funded. If you back the project, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get your
reward, and you’ll be contributing to possibly making it &lt;em&gt;bigger&lt;/em&gt;. There’s a
chance it might make the first stretch goal, which means 16 extra pages full of
undead abominations for use in any GURPS campaign that needs monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the classic complaints of many new and veteran GURPS players is the lack
of a “proper monster book” for GURPS 4th Edition. Lots of books include a small
sample selection and tips on making more yourself, but there’s no official
“one-stop-shop” for ready-made critter stat blocks. And of course, this being
GURPS it’s kinda hard to make a truly generic monster book, since whether a
given monster is an impossible challenge or a mere speedbump depends on who your
PCs are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nordlond Bestiary is probably the closest we can get to that mythic book - a
chunky selection of creatures suitable for Dungeon Fantasy campaigns. DF has a
well-known starting point total and a known set of PC templates, you can easily
know how the monsters are callibrated. And it’s also the genre that’s more
likely to need a “monster book” anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book will be made for use with the DFRPG boxed set, but it’s also perfectly
usable with the GURPS core books if that’s what you have. And since you know
what sort of PC these monsters were made to fight, you can also adjust them for
your specific campaign more easily.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/02/nordlond-bestiary.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/02/nordlond-bestiary.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Ooze</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oozes have been in the game since the beginning, and as you can see in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/09/02/ooze.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt; the first 4e Monster Manual already featured a bunch of them. As I say
there, far more adventurers lost their lives to an ooze than to one of the
game’s titular dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the MM2 we get a few more oozes, some of which would go on to feature in
the Monster Vault. All of the oozes here have the Blind and Ooze keywords, which
make them immune to gaze attacks and particularly adept at squeezing through
small spaces. They also have BLindsight 10 and Tremorsense 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abolethic-skum&quot;&gt;Abolethic Skum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-ooze-skum.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw way back in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/01/04/aboleth.html&quot;&gt;Aboleth&lt;/a&gt; post, Aboleths can turn mortals into
servitors, a process which turns their skin into a layer of transparent
slime. Sometimes, though, this process goes awry and the victim’s form loses all
physical integrity. The resulting watery blobs full of organs are known as
“skum”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abolethic skums are barely sentient, but some memory of what they were remains
with them. This tangles up with residual fear and shame at what they have
become, so they tend to attack anyone who resembles their old form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skum are Level 18 Minion Brutes with the Aquatic keyword in addition to the
default ones. They emit a Psychic Dissonance aura (1) that inflicts Vulnerable 5
Psychic to every creature inside. They have Resist 20 Acid and crawl around at
Speed 2, but can swim at Speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; target Fortitude and do a flat 16 acid damage, which is in line
with Monster Vault math. And their &lt;strong&gt;Aqueous Form&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes them invisible
while in water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being described as failed experiments, a skum’s stats make it complement
its aboleth masters very well. If your PCs go into underwater Underdark
adventure (double the under for half the price!) make sure to place a psychic
aboleth in a room packed full of invisible skum. See how long it takes for your
PCs to figure out why they’re taking extra damage from the aboleth &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt;
dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;black-pudding&quot;&gt;Black Pudding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These also appear in the Monster Vault, so we covered them in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/09/02/ooze.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;. The MM2 version was their 4e debut, and it’s mostly identical (math
fixes aside). The only difference is that they lack the powerful &lt;strong&gt;melt&lt;/strong&gt; attack
and instead have a &lt;strong&gt;Mercurial Body&lt;/strong&gt; trait which allows them to ignore
difficult terrain and opportunity attacks when moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gray-ooze&quot;&gt;Gray Ooze&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray Oozes are another D&amp;amp;D classic. They’re about as runny as green slimes, but
more mobile, which means they have always been depicted as active
monsters. Their brand of slime is particularly good at dissolving bones, and
they feed on the resulting bone slurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they’re Level 2 Skirmishers with 43 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;stench&lt;/strong&gt; acts as
an aura (2) that inflicts a -2 attack penalty on creatues inside. They have 5
acid resistance, crawl with a Speed of 5, and climb with Speed 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is named &lt;strong&gt;Bone Melt&lt;/strong&gt;, targetting fortitude and dealing some
acid damage. Each hit also inflicts a cumulative -2 penalty to Fortitude, making
further hits likely. A successful save clears the entire penalty. They can also
shift 2 squares as a minor action, making them quite mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;green-slime&quot;&gt;Green Slime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another monster that appeared in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/09/02/ooze.html&quot;&gt;Monster Vault&lt;/a&gt;, the two versions are
more or less identical. The MV one is a bit simpler to use, though, so prefer
that one if you have the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oozes aren’t smart enough to understand the concept of alliances, but they’re
everywhere in the world of D&amp;amp;D. You don’t need any complex excuses to add an
ooze or three to any underground encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our example encounters for these entry are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 4: 2 green slimes and 2 gray oozes lounging around a lone ankheg’s lair.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: 2 black puddings and a darkmantle enveloper in accidental
cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: An aboleth overseer and two lashers with an entourage of 10
skum. This is that packed room I told you about.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/24/ooze.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/24/ooze.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Oni</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my post about &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/08/17/oni.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual oni&lt;/a&gt;, oni have been in D&amp;amp;D
since the beginning, but were only called by this name starting in 4e. Before,
they were called by the more generic name of “ogre mage”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different stories about oni in Japanese folklore. The entries
here in the MM2 are inspired by by some of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All oni in this entry are Natural Humanoids, and all but one are Large. They
have darkvision and a signature trait named &lt;strong&gt;Deceptive Veil&lt;/strong&gt; that allows them
to appear as any Medium or Large humanoid. Those trying to spot the disguise
need to win an opposed Insight test against the monster’s Bluff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oni-devourer&quot;&gt;Oni Devourer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-oni-devourer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Oni Devourer. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These oni are sorcerous tricksters. By day they take the shape of ascetics,
beggars and priests. By night they go out hunting for people to eat. Some
stories tell of a large group of oni devourers that took over an entire isolated
monastery, replacing all the monks and using the disguise to terrorize the
neighboring regions. Devourers can also be found in the service of more powerful
villains as advisors or “court magicians”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devourers are the only Medium oni in this entry, and are Level 7 Soldiers with
78 HP. An Oni Devourer likely approaches its target in disguise using its
&lt;strong&gt;Deceptive Veil&lt;/strong&gt; (which only lets them take Medium forms since they’re
Medium). Then it uses &lt;strong&gt;Hypnotic Glare&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Will) that pulls the
target 5 squares and dazes it (save ends). Once in melee range it’s going to use
&lt;strong&gt;Devour&lt;/strong&gt; to deal heavy damage and inflict a -5 penalty to the target’s saves,
and its basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack to damage and slow, preventing the victim from
escaping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open fight will likely see the oni in its natural form from the start, but
the general tactic will be the same. Despite not having a marking mechanic like
other Soldiers they end up being quite sticky with their daze/slow/save penalty
combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oni-overlord&quot;&gt;Oni Overlord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some stories oni aren’t subtle at all and instead lead gangs of monstrous
bandits that try to rob and devour any hapless protagonists they come
across. Oni Overlords are an attempt to translate those individuals to
D&amp;amp;D. They’re Level 12 Elite Brutes with the Leader keyword and 296 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oni Overlords lead through fear: their &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Leader&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) gives a
+5 damage bonus to all allies inside, but also deals 5 psychic damage to them
when they miss all targets with an attack. If you want to mitigate that downside
you should give them allies capable of making area attacks. Conversely, if an
ally damages an enemy, the overlord can use its reaction for a &lt;strong&gt;Violent
Reward&lt;/strong&gt; that gives that ally 5 temporary HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While closing to melee range, the overlord can use &lt;strong&gt;Overlord’s Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close
blast 5 vs. Fortitude; recharges when first bloodied) to deal necrotic and
poison damage to enemies, and also make them vulnerable to those two damage
types (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oni-thunderer&quot;&gt;Oni Thunderer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-oni-thunderer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Oni Thunderer. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oni Thunderers seem to be inspired by the myth of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.japan-talk.com/jt/new/raijin-and-fujin&quot;&gt;Raijin&lt;/a&gt;, the god of
thunder and storms, who according to the link looked kinda oni-ish and caused
trouble as often as he helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These oni are extremely strong but not divine. There’s usually nothing good
about them, either. They love a fight, and when they get into one they
complement their weapon attacks with thunder magic and teleportation. Their
weapon of choice seems to be a spiked chain, likely inspired by Raijin’s
drum-aura thing. I imagine they usually hang out with other rowdy epic
storm-based creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thunderers are Large Natural Humanoids, and Level 22 Skirmishers with 206
HP. They have dark vision, a ground speed of 8, and a teleport speed of 8
(meaning they can teleport at-will with a move action).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their oversized &lt;strong&gt;spiked chains&lt;/strong&gt; are Reach 3, do a mix of physical and thunder
damage, and pull the target adjacent to the oni on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their teleport speed already makes them hard to pin down, and they can use them
as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Thunderclap Portal&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge 4+). This lets them
teleport their speed and perform a special attack either before or after that
teleport. This is a close burst 2 that heavy thunder damage and pushes all
enemies in the area. An enemy who was grabbed by the oni’s chain takes even more
damage, though this ends the grab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hit by an attack, the thunderer can react with &lt;strong&gt;Chain Dance&lt;/strong&gt; and teleport
3 squares. Finally, they have the same Deceptive Veil power as all the other
oni, though they’re unlikely to use it often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a mix of encounters here illustrting the sort of monsters oni might see
as servants, equals, or masters depending on their relative power levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: 2 oni devourers, 1 oni night haunter, 1 troll. Your typical cannibal
giant gang.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 12: 1 oni overlord, 3 minotaur warriors, 2 scytheclaw drakes. These look
more like a bandit leader and his lieutenants, likely running a gang of humans
or other smaller humanoids.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 22: 2 death giants, 3 oni thunderers. Funny, I’d have expected storm
giants. But this does prevent the PCs from totally nerfing the encounter with
a single damage resistance power.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the variety of oni we’re getting here. A large body of legend demands
lots of different stat blocks covering different aspects of it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/22/oni.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/22/oni.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Nothic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nothics first appeared in the Miniatures Handbook for 3e, and make their 4e
debut in the MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothics are aberrant creatures that first arrived in the world aboard drifting
fragments of the Far Realm. Their minds are even more alien than those of slaads
to us poor mortals. Their huge eyes are capable of inflicting a variety of
afflictions, and they tend to be found in the service of other powerful
creatures. Nothics constantly cackle and cavort about, which their masters often
find amusing, but they also fight at their command, doing double duty as jesters
and bodyguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their masters aren’t necessarily aberrant! Nothics are often found in the
company of undead, for example. A few get adopted by cults of Vecna and receive
numerous blessings from the lich god, becoming even more dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothics are Medium Aberrant Humanoids. Those dinner plate eyes give them
Truesight out to 10 squares and Darkvision. They also act as the focus for a
variety of gaze attacks and psychic powers, which vary per stat block. Nothics
have a ground speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks in this entry range from the mid-Paragon to the early Epic
tiers. I believe the Neverwinter Campaign Setting, published much later, would
include a heroic-tier nothic as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nothic-cackler&quot;&gt;Nothic Cackler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-nothic-cackler.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cacklers are some of the most “jester-like” in behavior. They caper about even
during a battle, seemingly oblivious to the opposition even as they
fight. They’re level 15 Artillery with 116 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic melee attack is an anemic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; - it’s all about the mind
powers with them. They can choose between two at-will ranged attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first, &lt;strong&gt;Mind Rot&lt;/strong&gt; targets Will and does psychic damage. On a hit, it also
slides the target 6 squares and forces them to make a melee basic attack against
someone else (nothic’s choice). The other, &lt;strong&gt;Rotting Gaze&lt;/strong&gt;, targets Fortitude,
does necrotic damage, and inflicts a -2 penalty to all defenses (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactics are clear: rot the body, rot the mind, laugh, repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If surrounded, the cackler can use a &lt;strong&gt;Maddening Cackle&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3
vs. Will; enemies only; recharge 5+). This deals psychic damage, pushes 2
squares, and slides the hit targets 2 additional squares at the start of their
next turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nothic-mindblight&quot;&gt;Nothic Mindblight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behavior-wise, mindblights are the complete opposite of cacklers, appearing
sleepy and morose even while staring you to death. They’re level 19 Controllers
with 180 HP. They project an &lt;strong&gt;Eye Lure&lt;/strong&gt; aura (3) that slides enemies inside 2
squares at the start of the enemies’ turns. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are a little
stronger and also deal ongoing necrotic damage (save ends), but the eye powers
are still the main event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mindblight will likely open up with &lt;strong&gt;Mesmerizing Visage&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a
fireball-sized area attack that targets Will, does psychic damage, and inflicts
a -1 penalty to saves (save ends). The penalty worsens to -3 after the first
failed save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it will move on to its at-will powers, which deal no damage but have “save
ends” riders that capitalize on the Visage’s effect. &lt;strong&gt;Eye of Insanity&lt;/strong&gt; is a
Ranged 5 attack that targets will and dominates with an after-effect that dazes
the target for an additionall turn after they make their save. &lt;strong&gt;Necrotic Eye&lt;/strong&gt;
is a Close Blast 5 that targets Fortitude and inflicts 10 ongoing necrotic
damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nothic-eye-of-vecna&quot;&gt;Nothic Eye of Vecna&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-nothic-eye-of-vecna.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, Vecna likes this nothic sub-species and heaps blessings upon
them. They often hang around his cults. They’re Level 22 Lurkers with 162 HP,
and project a &lt;strong&gt;Soul Decay&lt;/strong&gt; aura (3) that allows allied undead inside to make
free melee basic attacks at the start of the nothic’s turn. So yeah, the best
place for this lurker to lurk is amid a crowd of undead melee bruisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Eye of Vecna is going to constantly emit pulses of &lt;strong&gt;Eye Rot&lt;/strong&gt; (minor
action), which targets the fortitude of every enemy within 10 squares and makes
the nothic invisible to them on a hit (save ends). This recharges when the
monster isn’t invisible to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After it does that, it skitters among the enemies who can’t see it using
&lt;strong&gt;Mobile Melee Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it to move its speed and make a basic claw
attack at any point during the move, drawing no opportunity attacks from the
target. That &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; is pretty nasty on its own as well, dealing necrotic
damage, immobilizing, and inflicting a -2 to all saving throws. &lt;strong&gt;Invisible
Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; gives it an additional effect against targets who can’t see the
nothic, opening the target up to an opportunity attack from another adjacent
monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the basic visual design of the nothic is quite striking, but their
mechanics don’t quite do it for me just from reading them. I guess they might
feel differently in play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encounters with nothics are also likely to involve the powerful villains they
serve. The book gives us three:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 14: A mind flayer infiltrator with an entourage of 2 nothic cacklers and
2 war trolls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 18: 2 aboleth lashers and their 2 pet mindblights in cahoots with a
death hag.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 21: A dark naga with an honor guard of 3 bodak reavers and an Eye of
Vecna pet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/19/nothic.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/19/nothic.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Vault 2: Neogi</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-neogi.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the Neogi first appeared as an element of 2e’s Spelljammer setting. In
4e, they make their debut here in the MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neogi are bizarre-looking spider-centipede people who originally hail from the
Far Realm. Their culture is a particularly cruel and pitiless variety of
imperialist capitalism. Ownership is all - the strong rule and own the
weak. They organize themselves in clans with slavery-based internal
hierarchies. A given neogi literally owns their immediate underlings and is in
turn a slave to its immediate superior. This goes up all the way to the Great
Old Master of the clan, who is no one’s slave. Neogi are a single-gendered
species without any concept of family. All of the clan’s eggs are carried and
gestated by the Great Old Master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neogi are renowned both as traders and slavers, following the same school of
commerce made famous during Earth’s Age of “Discovery”. If the other party is
weaker than you, rob and enslave them. If they’re equivalent or stronger,
negotiate and trade. They just love trading with similarly unsavory people like
devils, duergar, and drow. The only ones they avoid are the mind flayers, since
the entire neogi people was once enslaved by entities similar to flayers back in
the Far Realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, the MM2 doesn’t mention any of their nautical proclivities. I
guess this part of the Astral Sea wasn’t quite as fixed in the authors’ minds
back them. But since later descriptions would reveal you can pretty much
transplant all of Spelljammer directly into the Astral Sea, you can bet you have
Neogi trade/slave/warships roaming that plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neogi are Aberrant Magical Beasts. Most are Medium, but Masters are Large. Their
levels cover the first half of Paragon Tier, making them appropriate encounters
for the Underdark or Astral Sea. Like all monsters, their level can be adjusted
if you want to feature them earlier or later. They usually have climb speeds and
darkvision, and a degree of telepathy. They also speak Common and Deep
Speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Neogi are immune to the Dazed condition. Their attacks are usually some sort
of psychic power, though the exact effects vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neogi-slaver&quot;&gt;Neogi Slaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relatively “typical” individual, likely found as crew in an astral vessel or
as troops in raiding party. In either case, they’re likely to be accompanied by
plenty of non-neogi slaves. These are some of the few monsters in the book who
would make use of the “non-lethal takedown” rule, where you can decide someone
you took to 0 HP is not dead, just unconscious. After all, dead slaves are worth
nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slavers are Level 10 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 106 HP. They have a
ground speed of 8 and a climb speed of 6 with Spider Climb. Their basic melee
attack is a weak &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; with an ongoing poison damage rider. The first failed
save against this poison also slows the victim (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Charm Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Will. Instead of
dealing damage, it inflicts a -2 penalty on any attacks that don’t include the
slaver as a target (save ends). After the first failed save, the slaver
also becomes invisible to the target of the bolt!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their other attack is &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Shackle&lt;/strong&gt; (Recharge 5+), a Close Blast 3 that
targets Will, deals psychic damage, and dazes those it hits for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Thrall Goad&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action. This
allows all allies within 6 squares of the slaver to make a saving thrown with a
+5 bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neogi-spawn-swarm&quot;&gt;Neogi Spawn Swarm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neogi larvae are tiny and sub-sapient. Their only desire is to eat all nearby
available meat, living or not. They can be dangerous in large numbers, which is
what this stat block represents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swarm counts as a Medium Level 10 Brute with 131 HP. They have the standard
swarm resistance to melee and ranged attacks, and a vulnerability to close and
area attacks. Their ground and climb speeds are both 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Swarm Attack aura (1) deals automatic poison damage, and their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt;
are similar to that of the neogi slaver but deal more damage. When first
bloodied or when slain, the swarm lets out a collective &lt;strong&gt;psychic scream&lt;/strong&gt; that
attacls a close burst 1 and deals psychic damage with a Daze rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neogi-great-old-master&quot;&gt;Neogi Great Old Master&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Large individuals rule over entire clans, and carry all of the clan’s eggs
and larval broods in their immense abdomens. They’re Level 16 Controllers with
157 HP, a ground speed of 6, and a climb speed of 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Scythe Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that damages targets and knocks
them prone. Their main ranged attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Enslaving Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Will,
deals psychic damage and inflicts one of those progressively worsening
conditions. The immediate effect is that the target gets a -2 penalty to any
attacks that target the Master; after the first failed save, that worsens to a
Dominate effect; and after the second the domination lasts until the target’s
next extended rest. Yes, this does mean that an unlucky PC could find themselves
trying to avenge the Master even after it’s been killed by the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Master is first bloodied, its abdomen ruptures and releases a Larva
Burst. This works as a Close Burst 2 against Reflex that deals physical damage
and creates a zone of difficult terrain that lasts until the end of the
encounter. This could also be a good opportunity to introduce a Spawn Swarm to
the fight if the GM is feeling sadistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they can use a version of the Slaver’s Psychic Shackle that deals more
damage and has a wider area.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/19/neogi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/19/neogi.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Myconids</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-myconid.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids have been in the game since AD&amp;amp;D as one of its most famous “novelty
humanoids”. They make their 4e debut here in the MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids are sapient fungal humanoids who originated in the Feywild. The
fomorians did &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; to them in the distant past, and they still bear the
scars of that corruption. In our narrative present they can be found in deep
caves or the Underdark both in the world and in the Feywild. Their preferred
environment are underground mushroom forests that provide them with a complete
ecosystem to live in, but they also have an instinctive need to multiply and
spread and so can be found in less ideal conditions as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids communicate by releasing special spores laced with emotions and
sensations, which only other myconids can understand. Only one individual in
each of their colonies, known as the “Sovereign”, can communicate with outsiders
through telepathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mushroom-people aren’t evil, but their expansionist instinct, difficulty
with communication, and the fact that they live in the friggin’ &lt;em&gt;Underdark&lt;/em&gt;
means they tend to engage in conflict with anyone they come across. They often
end up enslaved by drow, fomorians, and shadar-kai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peaceful interaction with myconids is predictably hard - you have to reach the
sovereign, which means infiltrating the heart of their territory or letting
yourself be captured and hoping they take you there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids are Fey Humanoids with the Plant keyword. Sovereigns are Large,
everyone else is Medium. They have Tremorsense 10, which allows them to operate
well in total darkness. Their signature trait is &lt;strong&gt;Roots of the Colony&lt;/strong&gt;, a free
action that triggers when they’re hit by an attack and allows them to split half
the damage between themselves and a myconid ally within 5 squares. Given they’re
level 3-4, this is likely to be the party’s first encounter with something
resistant to focus fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;myconid-rotpriest&quot;&gt;Myconid Rotpriest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconid culture isn’t well-understood enough for people to know if they worship
something, but rotpriests kinda fulfill the “healer” role usually taken up by
clerics in other species. They do so in a much more self-sacrificing way,
though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rotpriests are Level 3 Brutes with the Leader keyword and 48 HP. They have a
speed of 5, and Regeneration 5 that can be temporarily disabled by radiant
damage. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;stipe staffs&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and can also release
&lt;strong&gt;decomposing sprays&lt;/strong&gt; to deal necrotic damage in a Close Burst 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have Roots of the Colony like every other myconid, and when another myconid
uses this ability to deal damage to them, rotpriests can use &lt;strong&gt;Sacrifice for the
Colony&lt;/strong&gt; to take all of the damage from the trigerring attack instead of just
half. The idea is that they then heal this using their regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they finally get killed, they release a &lt;strong&gt;Life Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that heals every
living creature in a Close Burst 1 for 10 HP. This includes both monsters and
PCs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;myconid-sovereign&quot;&gt;Myconid Sovereign&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each colony has one of these acting as its leader. As mentioned before,
sovereigns are the only myconids with any ability to communicate with
outsiders. They’re Level 4 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 58 HP. If
forced into a fight they can defend themselves with &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; and with a variety
of interesting spore bursts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default &lt;strong&gt;Spore Burst&lt;/strong&gt; is a close blast 3 that targets the Will of
nonplants and deals poison damage. There’s also &lt;strong&gt;Commanding Spores&lt;/strong&gt;, which
allows a plant ally within 5 squares to shift 1 square. Sounds like a waste of a
standard action, but it can set up some interesting flanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Sovereign should stay a bit away from the main scrum, spraying it with its
spore pesticides and helping keep the PCs surrounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;myconid-guard&quot;&gt;Myconid Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it’s the last monster in the entry, guards are likely to be the most
numerous foes the party meets. They’re the rank and file of the colony’s
protectors. Guards are Level 4 Soldiers with 56 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;spiny strikes&lt;/strong&gt; from their fists, and can release
&lt;strong&gt;pacification spores&lt;/strong&gt; in a close burst 1 that target enemies’ Wills, do poison
damage, and prevent those hit from taking standard actions during their next
turns. Fortunately, this is only an encounter power. Roots of the Colony is the
last trick on their arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front-liners are going to have a bit of a bad time facing down myconid guards,
since the guards can stagger their spore releases to keep the PCs from attacking
for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids can live in any place that provides good conditions to mundane fungi,
such as damp caverns, surface forests, and so on. Encounters with them can
involve any wildlife that also lives in these places, either as “third parties”
or perhaps as pets if the wildlife is also fungal. They can also be found
alongside the several people who enslave their colonies, though in that case you
might need to perform some level adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are an all-myconid party that has just ran into a
deathjump spider (level 3); a pair of myconid guards minding an arbalester for
their bosses near a patch of green slime (level 4); and a geonid accompanied by
a pair of rust monsters and another of rotpriests (level 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these mushroom people, and I like making then relatively friendly once
the PCs manage to breach the communications gap.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/myconid.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/myconid.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Marut</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-marut.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth edition Maruts debuted in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/07/03/marut.html&quot;&gt;first Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;, as enigmatic
mercenaries from the Astral Sea that demanded future favors as payment for their
services and kept detailed ledgers of these in their astral fortresses. Here we
get a bit more lore about them, and three new stat blocks to go with the two
from the first MM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM2 bits of lore seem to have been written by a different author from the
first, and this second author seems to have time-traveled from 3e or 2e. It
talks a lot about Maruts being interested in “the upholding of oaths and
contracts” in the abstract, which doesn’t really match the first book. Yes,
they’re very interested in this stuff, but only when the oaths made &lt;em&gt;by them&lt;/em&gt; or
&lt;em&gt;to them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also another bit that says they consider themselves to be “astral
spirits of the air”, and despite the convoluted justification accompanying this
I don’t think the Astral Sea is a place with strong elemental associations
either way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more interesting bit is the one that says Maruts aren’t an unified block -
they’re divided into groups called “cadres” that hold slighty different
philosophies. Each cadre has their own fortress and interacts with other
sapients in more or less the same way, but I guess they differ in what they’re
stockpiling those favors for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some cadres have started calling in a few of their favors and demanding periods
of indentured servitude from people. Maruts don’t mistreat their servants, but
they’re still demanding and humorless bosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maruts in this entry are Medium Immortal Humanoids. They have Truesight out
to 10 squares, a ground speed of 8, and flight and teleport speeds of 4. They’re
immune to sleep and have Resist Thunder 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the stat blocks in this entry are described as “hunting down those who
oppose marut law”, which again doesn’t quite make sense. Pretty much every Marut
will hunt and fight someone who backed out of a deal with them, so instead of
repeating this I’ll speculate about what someone might hire these new varieties
for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marut-castigator&quot;&gt;Marut Castigator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castigators make good bounty hunters, since they’re good at preventing their
target from running away. They’re Level 21 Skirmishers with 146 HP and all
standard traits. They wield a double sword in combat, and have access to thunder
and lightning-themed magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;double sword&lt;/strong&gt; attack can deal physical or lightning damage, at
the marut’s discretion. They can also make &lt;strong&gt;Double Attacks&lt;/strong&gt; with it, but not
all the time (recharge 4+).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prevent someone from running, they can use the &lt;strong&gt;Punisher’s Lash&lt;/strong&gt;, a Reach 2
vs. Reflex spell that deals weak lightning damage, slows, and prevents the
target from teleporting for a turn. If the target still tries to run, they can
give chase with a &lt;strong&gt;Thunderbolt Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to teleport 4
squares and make a basic attack with bonus damage afterwards. This recharges
when they hit with the two strikes from a double attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marut-prosecutor&quot;&gt;Marut Prosecutor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objection! Prosecutors are probably pretty good at that very role during an
actual trial, with their epic levels of Insight and Intimidate. They can also
use magic to infuse their words with the leaden weight of the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors are Level 21 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 147 HP. They
can punch people with &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; that do bonus thunder damage and slow (save
ends), but their judicial magic is their greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action they can issue a &lt;strong&gt;Dictum&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that
does no damage and immobilizes (save ends). They can also use a minor action to
mark someone with a &lt;strong&gt;Sigil of Indictment&lt;/strong&gt;  (ranged 10 vs. Will), which also
does no damage but forces the marked victim to grant combat advantage to the
prosecutor and take 5 extra psychic damage from all attacks directed at it. This
lasts for a turn and can be sustained, but only one target can bear the Sigil at
a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the prosecutor can take a bit more time and spend a standard action to
harangue someone with a &lt;strong&gt;Biting Testimony&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 10, targets one enemy,
vs. Will). This deals psychic damage, and inflicts a -2 penalty on all of the
target’s attacks, skill checks, and ability checks (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means prosecutors call the shots during a fight, marking someone
with the Sigil and having their allies focus fire on the victim, which they’ll
try to immobilize with Dictums. Dictums can also be used to prevent defenders
from helping a focused squishy. “Close Burst X; targets one enemy” is just a
terse way of saying that power is a ranged attack that doesn’t draw OAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marut-executioner&quot;&gt;Marut Executioner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An executioner is who you call when you need an obstacle removed. When they’re
not doing that, they’re out collecting debts owed to their cadre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executioners are Level 22 Brutes with 205 HP. They wield &lt;strong&gt;Double Axes&lt;/strong&gt; that
does bonus thunder damage, knocks prone on a critical, and can be used in
several other maneuvers. &lt;strong&gt;Slayer’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) allows them to attack
everyone in a Close Burst 1; &lt;strong&gt;Warranted Stroke&lt;/strong&gt; targets a bloodied enemy, does
a ton of damage, always knocks prone, and gives the executioner 1 action point
if it drops the target to 0 HP or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also issue an &lt;strong&gt;Execution Call&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter, a Close Blast 5
that targets enemies’ Fortitude, does thunder damage, and pulls them adjacent to
the executioner. A miss here still does half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the mechanics of these new Maruts, but I dislike the throwback to 3e lore
here. Law is not a universal cosmic principle in 4e!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters have marut mercenary squads accompanying a djinn (level
21) or a trio of rakshasa knights (level 23).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/marut.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/marut.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
