<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 03:12:06 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 03:12:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Demogorgon (Part 2)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click [here][1] to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/06/11/demogorgon.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, this time we’ll be looking at Demogorgon’s
Exarchs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Exarch” is the term D&amp;amp;D 4 uses for the “lieutenants” of a god or equivalent
entity. They might preside over a narrower slice of their master’s portfolio, or
simply help run their operations in the world and other planes. Though
subordinate to someone else, exarchs are in no way weak: in the god-ranking
system used in previous editions, all of them would have ranked as anything from
demigods to intermediate deities themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orcus, which we looked at in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/26/ettin.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual let’s Read&lt;/a&gt;, had one exarch:
Dorensain, the King of Ghouls. Demogorgon has two, described below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kazuul&quot;&gt;Kazuul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazuul used to be a human champion of Erathis a long time ago, and in her
service he carved many a swath of order through savage lands. I guess that in
the end something convinced him that this “carving a swath” business didn’t make
him any different from the “savages” he claimed to oppose, and so he decided to
embrace that and pledge himself to Demogorgon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demon lord gave him a gift of size and strength, making him double in size
and become deformed by his over-developed demonic musculature. Kazuul now fights
in the name of Hethradiah, the “brutal but cunning” head, driving a horde of
demons before him to raid places in the Abyss and elsewhere in the multiverse. I
guess Kazuul is a big inspiration to those shrieking cultists we saw in the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/06/11/demogorgon.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a former human, Kazuul fights with weapons. Being a former &lt;em&gt;adventurer&lt;/em&gt;,
he’s always on the lookout for better weapons. If he notices one of his
opponents is wielding something particularly sweet (say, a level 28+ magical
weapon), he will engage that opponent and ignore everyone else until he’s taken
the weapon for himself. Otherwise, he will just focus on killing whoever is
closest and repeating that until there is no one else to kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obsession with magic weapons stems in part from the fact that Kazuul used
to own a legendary sword named Gorgorin the Shatterer. He lost it in a battle
against Hainard, one of Pelor’s exarchs. He’s still sore about that, and looking
for a way to either get his sword back or to find a suitably awesome
replacement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazuul’s current weapons are quite awesome already: there’s The Tooth of Grom, a
sword forged from the tooth of a fire titan lord, and The World Splitter, an axe
taken from Clangeddin Silverbeard, one of Moradin’s Exarchs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an ancient prophecy which proclaims that when Kazuul recovers Gorgorin,
he will use it to slay Demogorgon and then displace Yeenoghu as the lord of
gnolls. This prophecy has caused lots of infighting amongst demons, and there
have been several failed attempts by all factions involved to find the blade’s
current hiding place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kazuul is a Large Elemental Humanoid with the Demon tag, making him an official
demon. He’s a Level 28 Elite Soldier with 528 HP. He has Darkvision and demonic
Variable Resistance 10, switchable 3x/encounter. He has ground and fly speeds of
5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has two basic attacks with his sweet magic weapons: the &lt;strong&gt;Tooth of Grom&lt;/strong&gt;
(Reach 2 vs. AC) does physical damage and forces the target to make a melee
basic attack against a target of Kazuul’s choice on a hit; the &lt;strong&gt;World
Splitter&lt;/strong&gt; (reach 2 vs. AC) also does physical damage and inflicts a -4 AC
penalty (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of Kazuul&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to attack with both weapons
in a single standard action. Oh, and &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to make
opportunity attacks against any enemy he can reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If his enemies are beyond the reach of his blades, Kazuul can attack with
&lt;strong&gt;Abyssal Flames&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 3 within 20 vs. Reflex) at will, doing fire
damage on a hit. He also has a couple of handy spells for use when he gets
closer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Word of Doom&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Will; encounter) does heavy physical damage
and allows Kazuul to crit against the targets on a natural roll of 15-20 (save
ends). This is scarier than it might sound for someone used to 3.x! In Fourth
Edition, criticals happen only on a natural 20. Only a handful of powers in the
entire game increase that range. Word of Doom is the only one I can think of
that widens it this much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vortex of Blades&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Reflex; enemies only; encounter) does
double the damage of a basic attack and stuns (save ends). Simple, but still
scary: stun (save ends) is a pretty serious condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thrarak&quot;&gt;Thrarak&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demogorgon-thrarak.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Chippy. Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrarak’s origins are closely tied to the mythological origns for &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/26/ettin.html&quot;&gt;ettins&lt;/a&gt;
that I wrote about during the first Monster Manual/Vault Let’s Read. It starts
with Demogorgon fighting the god Amoth, who split his head in two. Before that
wound had even healed, the earth primordial Storralk ambushed him and tried to
take him down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the linked post says, Demogorgon defeated the would-be usurper handily, and
bound his broken but still-living form under his throne. It was Dagon who gave
him the idea for a bit of extra cruel punishment: using a ritual provided by
Dagon, Demogorgon caused the first Ettins to be born from Storralk’s spilled
blood, and to scatter through the world. Each one contains a small fraction of
Storralk’s essence, so whenever an ettin feels pain, Storralk’s body feels it as
well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those first ettins chose to stay at Demogorgon’s side, and to seek his
favor by alternatively healing and cutting Storralk’s flesh. This eventually got
his attention and Demogorgon made her one of his exarchs: Thrarak, the Flayed
Maiden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrarak is specifically the Exarch of Ameul, the cunning head. She acts as
Demogorgon’s emissary of vengeance, going after mortals and other entities that
have angered the Prince of Demons or those who have the potential to become
threats in the future. An expert torturer, she fights using twin lashes and
yelling streams of maddening lore that’s dangerous to hear. She prefers to focus
on one opponent at a time, which will either be the target of her master’s ire
or the closest available enemy. Once she chooses a target she will ignore any
other enemies to focus on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legend has it that if Thrarak is slain and her heart burned upon Demogorgon’s
throne, Storralk will finally break free of his prison. Freeing him could be an
important step in defeating Demogorgon himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrarak is a Large Elemental Humanoid (giant) and a Level 26 Elite Brute with
596 HP. She has all the traits common to all Ettins: trained Perception,
darkvision, ground speed 8, and the Dual Brain and Double Actions traits
described in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/26/ettin.html&quot;&gt;original ettin post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her basic melee attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Lash of Ruin&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach 3 vs. AC) which does
physical damage, knocks prone, and dazes for a turn on a hit. She can sometimes
increase her rythm and perform a &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (close burst 3
vs. AC; recharge 5-6), dealing physical damage and dazing (save ends) all she
hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter she can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Howl of Madness&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Blast 5
vs. Will), which does psychic damage, slides the targets 3 squares, and forces
them to make a melee basic attack against a target of Thrarak’s choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those ettin traits I linked to are quite important to all of this: Thrarak has
two full turns per round and some resistance to restrictive conditions. She can
do a lot, which makes her dangerous to those enemies she’s focusing on. She
should be put in charge of a monster team who can keep the remaining PCs off her
back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have one encounter for each Exarch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 25: Thrarak, 1 abyssal rotfiend, and 2 nycademons.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 27: Kazuul, 1 marilith, and 1 balor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels appropriate to add a whole bunch of minions to either encounter, if you
think they’re not dangerous enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I like these two as villains more than I like Dorensain, Orcus’
exarch. Mechanically, Thrarak is just an epic ettin, but she has an interesting
backstory tied to her people’s mythological origins. Kazuul’s magic weapon
obsession is also interesting, and the Gorgorin lore has a lot of potential as
an adventure hook.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/14/demogorgon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/14/demogorgon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Popcorn Initiative in GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/pop-corn.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS uses a fairly traditional initiative system to determine who goes first in
combat. Like all such systems, it works well for “real-time” gaming, but it
tends to get in the way of good “flow” for a Play-by-Post or other asynchronous
game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past I tried to solve that by having players declare 3-5 turns’ worth of
actions in advance and resolving those on my side, but that ended up being a lot
of work and after a while I burned out on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at about this time that I first read Lancer, and noticed it used an
interesting initiative system. One of the PCs always acts first in a turn,
followed by an enemy. We alternate that way until all people on one side have
acted, and then the remaining combatants on the other side act one after the
other. The players themselves decide who acts during each “player activation”,
and the GM decides who acts during each enemy activation. The order in which
characters act can therefore vary from turn to turn, but the order of
&lt;em&gt;activations&lt;/em&gt; always remains the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d later find out this model was known as “Popcorn Initiative”. It worked well
for me in the couple of sessions of real-time Lancer I ran, and I’d get a lot
more experience with it when I joined a forum game of Zeitgeist using D&amp;amp;D 4th
Edition rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popcorn Initiative works extremely well in that game. Post flow during combat is
pretty much uninterrupted as long as there’s anyone available to post. We get
through a whole combat round in a single day if everyone is on point, a
formidable pace for an asynchronous game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked so well, it made me think I’d only run an async GURPS game if I could
use popcorn initiative in it. And it turns out adding popcorn initiative to
GURPS is not hard at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-rule&quot;&gt;The Rule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of using Basic Speed values to determine turn order, use the system
described at the start of this post, and repeated here for ease of reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A PC always goes first, followed by an enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The two sides then alternate taking their turns until all members of one side
have finished.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The remaining combatants then take their turns one after the other.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Repeat the above procedure for each 1-second round in the combat.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Players decide which PC acts on each player turn. The GM decides who acts on
each enemy turn. The order doesn’t have to remain constant from second to
second.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traits and maneuvers that give extra actions or extra attacks all affect the
character’s &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; turn, as normal. A character’s defenses “reset” at the start
of their turn as usual. Surprise still works the same, and limits your actions
in the same way. All this rule change is how to determine the order in which
turns happen in a 1-second round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the battle involves one or more characters with Enhanced Time Sense, then
all of them get to go before the less enhanced combatants, using the rules above
among themselves. It effectively splits the second into two “sub-rounds”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a high Speed here is still useful because it gives you more Dodge and
more Move. Changes to Basic Speed cost the same as under the standard rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;popcorn-examples&quot;&gt;Popcorn Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 1&lt;/strong&gt;: A party of four fantasy adventurers fights a group of 6 orcs. The
heavily armored warrior PC goes first and positions himself to protect his
squishier buddies. An orc goes next, then a PC, and so on until all PCs have
acted. The final two orcs act one after the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Two of the orcs in the battle above attack the warrior, who
blocks once and parries once. This leaves him with penalties for further
defenses. If he is not the first to act next round, the penalties will stay with
him until he does take his turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 3&lt;/strong&gt;: The same four adventurers meet a Giant Enemy Crab who has Extra
Attack 1. Again one of the PCs goes first. The crab goes next, and he can make 2
attacks during his turn as in the normal rules. Then the remaining PCs act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 4&lt;/strong&gt;: A group of 6 WW2 British Commandos ambushes a patrol squad of 8
Nazi soldiers. The Nazis are surprised and are considered Mentally Stunned as
per the standard rules. Though the GM gets to choose the order in which the
enemy soldiers act, all they can do on their turns is attempt to recover from
the stun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example 5&lt;/strong&gt;: A 6-person squad of the Solar Patrol runs into a pack of three
homicidal robots while exploring a ghost spaceship! All of the robots have
Enhanced Time Sense, and so does one of the PCs who is a robot themselves. So
the PC robot acts first, then the three enemy robots, and then the rest of the
PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is definitely a system I want to try out when I next GM an async GURPS
game. I tried to change the standard rules as little as possible. Lancer does a
few more things, like giving certain powerful enemies multiple activations per
round, but I want to experiment with this base version before I try doing that
in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/12/popcorn-initiative.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/12/popcorn-initiative.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Demogorgon (Part 1)</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demogorgon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Jesper Ejsing. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got to the Big Cheese of this book quite early, for his name starts with D:
it’s Demogorgon! He’s been in the game since the days of AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition. The
name became quite famous when Stranger Things aired, though I don’t think it
refers to the same creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry is like the Orcus entry in the MM1: It includes not only the stats
for the titular demon lord but also its associates, aspects, exarchs, and even
cultists. I’m going to go through them in reverse order, starting with the
cultists and moving up the levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demogorgon is a demon lord’s demon lord. His credo is quite simple: through
strength, cruelty and slaughter the strong prosper and the weak die. Be strong,
be cruel, and slaughter the weak. That doesn’t mean he’s stupid, though! Each
head has its own personality and highly developed intellect: Aameul is cunning
but brutal and Hethradiah brutal but cunning. They hate each other and argue a
lot but generally end up working towards compatible goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demogorgon also has another business partner who is not himself, which makes him
a bit unique among demon lords: Dagon, a Demon Lord inspired by the fishy entity
of Lovecraftian fame. A keeper of secrets and cosmic mysteries, he shares these
secrets with Demogorgon, but only whispers a given secret to one of the
heads. This keeps their mutual hatred and jealousy going strong, and furthers
Dagon’s own goals. Their servants and cults can be found cooperating some times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll eventually discuss the big bosses in more detail, but for now let’s begin
by looking at their cults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cults-of-demogorgon&quot;&gt;Cults of Demogorgon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-demogorgon-cultists.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demogorgon’s cults gain prominence when war or other wide-ranging disasters
ravage the land, as people turn to him in a desperate attempt to survive and end
up becoming murderous marauders themselves. I imagine this tends to prolong the
problem that caused the cult to rise in the first place. These cultists wander
around like berserking pirates, pillaging and destroying everything in their
path. What makes them different from, say, gnolls? Well, they’re more interested
in taking your stuff than in eating you, and unlike gnolls or orcs they’re a
very diverse crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members include individuals from any of the “civilized” species as well as
troglodytes, kuo-toa and other aggressive humanoids. Note that none of them
“naturally” worship Demogorgon: even troglodytes and kuo-toa typically venerate
other deities. This means that every cultist of Demogorgon is a heretic to their
own people. A lof of them were probably press-ganged into the cult during one of
those raids I mentioned in the previous paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also some cultists who go deeper into the demon lord’s mysticism,
believing that like their boss they are of two minds: a civilized mind who acts
as a shackle to a an instinctive, destructive second self. Some try to explore
this duality, while others try to cast of these shackles entirely, worshipping
only Hethradiah, the most aggressive of the two heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever their individual views, these cultists are all Chaotic Evil by any
reasonable definition of the alignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cults-of-dagon&quot;&gt;Cults of Dagon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dagon has his own cults too, and these are as Innsmouthy as you’d expect. His
temples are undewater, though they include air-filled rooms to accommodate
visiting terrestrial worshippers. These tend to congregate in coastal
communities, and to sacrifice sapients to their master. Dagon’s demands grow
with time, forcing his cultists to perform ever greater sacrifices in order to
avoid being swallowed by tidal waves or other disasters sent by their overlord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His worshippers also frequently include wizards and sages willing to bargain
with him for some of those cosmic secrets. These tend to rise to the position of
cult leaders. The most powerful among them might be able to visit Dagon
personally in his doubly-abyssal domains, and barter legendary artifacts for the
lore they seek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, Vecna hates Dagon and their cults fight a lot. How did you guess?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get quite a few cultist stat blocks here, all human. You can easily combine
them with standard stat blocks from other humanoid species to get the diversity
hinted at in the lore, or add the signature traits of those humanoids to the
Demogorgon-flavored stat blocks from this entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abyssal-marauder&quot;&gt;Abyssal Marauder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abyssal marauders roam the land in loose warbands, and the sea in rickety
warships they barely know how to sail. When they see a village or ship, they
attack, kill everyone, take what they can and burn what they can’t. In doing
this they honor their demonic overlord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some pirate captains or land-bound warlords manage to hire bands of abyssal
marauders to bolster their ranks for big raids, paying them mostly with the
promise of plentiful loot and chances to kill people. Unless they can keep
providing that loot between battles, though, it’s very hard to keep the
marauders in line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marauders are Level 6 Skirmishers with 69 HP and a speed of 6. Their piecemeal
protections are equivalent to leather armor, and they carry a long spear and a
pair of throwing axes to battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; (reach 2 vs. AC) and the &lt;strong&gt;throwing axes&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 5/10
vs. AC) count as basic attacks, and both allow the marauder to shift 1 square on
a hit. They’ll usually open the fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Howling Charge&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows
them to throw an axe at someone and immediately charge them with the spear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bloodied, marauders are taken over by a &lt;strong&gt;Death Fury&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them
to make two basic melee attacks per standard action at a -2 penalty to each. It
also forbids them from using any of their other attacks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reach weapons and plentiful shifting make marauders work well when paired with a
“wall” of sturdier allies, like the shrieking cultists we’ll see below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;berserker-prelate-of-demogorgon&quot;&gt;Berserker Prelate of Demogorgon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prelates are priest-types, preaching the credo of Demogorgon to their fellow
cultists as their leader or (in the book’s words) their “spiritual pet”. Unlike
the cultist priests of other demon lords, berserker prelates lead from the front
and join the fight alongside their flock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prelates are Level 8 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 86 HP. Their speed
is 5, they wear hide, and carry a big club into battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; is their basic melee attack, and allows them to push the
target 1 square on a hit. At range they fling &lt;strong&gt;Abyssal Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Will) that do physical damage and slide the target 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their leadery skill is &lt;strong&gt;Bloodletter’s Call&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 3). Against enemies,
this is an attack vs. Will that does psychic damage and dazes for a turn. On
allies, it instead acts as a buff giving them +2 to attack for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name might imply, berserker prelates are gripped by the same &lt;strong&gt;Death
Fury&lt;/strong&gt; as their marauder buddies when bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shrieking-cultist-of-demogorgon&quot;&gt;Shrieking Cultist of Demogorgon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These psychos have given up on any semblance of restraint and rationality,
seeking to emulate Hethradiah, the most violent of Demogorgon’s heads. When a
lot of them gather, people who are themselves on the path to madness might
discern the demonic hymn hidden in their collective shrieking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cultists are Level 7 Brutes with 94 HP. They wear mail, so their speed
is 5. They wield a &lt;strong&gt;greataxe&lt;/strong&gt; and carry a brace of &lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt;, which are
basic attacks doing heavy damage as expected of a Brute. Once per encounter they
can intensify their incoherent screaming into a &lt;strong&gt;Howl of Fury&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3
vs. Will) that does psychic damage and immobilizes the targets for a turn on a
hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also make their fury &lt;em&gt;solid&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;Death Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 1
vs. AC; encounter), which does physical damage and creates a zone of horrible
noise that moves with the cultist, in effect working like an aura 1. Anyone
caught inside takes 5 physical damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shrieking Cultists lack the &lt;strong&gt;Death Fury&lt;/strong&gt; trait from their other two
correligionists: for all practical purposes, they’re &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; in this state
already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;doom-flayer&quot;&gt;Doom Flayer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doom Flayers are wizards who worship Dagon to gain access to his secrets,
offering sacrifices to him and helping further his plots. They will likely tell
you they are perfectly rational and can stop the demon worship any time they
want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re Level 8 Artillery with 65 HP, wielding a &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; for emergencies and
otherwise using a large collection of Dagon-themed spells to fight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Force Lash&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Reflex) does force damage and slows the target for
a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grasping Tentacles&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Fortitude; recharge 5-6) does physical
damage and immobilizes (save ends). Until the target saves, any enemy starting
its turn adjacent to the target is slowed (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doom Foretold&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10; minor; encounter) auto-hits and makes the target
grant combat advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Churning Vortex&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within 10 vs. Reflex; encounter) does physical
damage, slides 1 square, and knocks the targets prone on a hit. It does half
damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The encounter powers work as a good fight-opener, and you should use them that
way or you might miss the chance to do so if the party decides to focus fire on
the flayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry has a bunch of sample encounters but only two are cultist-themed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: 1 abyssal marauder, 2 shrieking cultists, 1 berserker prelate, and 1
tiefling darkblade. Remember what I said about using other stat blocks as
cultists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: 1 doom flayer, 2 troglodyte thrashers, 2 abyssal marauders, 1 gnaw
demon. And here’s that Dagon/Demogorgon partnership at work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D has a lot of hordes of murderous raiding cultists, and making them different
from each other can be a tough job for a writer. I feel they succeeded here,
though. Demogorgon’s cultists are the only ones with a diverse membership by the
book, and the Death Fury trait makes them look properly “two-faced”, going from
canny fighters to frothing nutjobs as the fight progresses.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/11/demogorgon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/11/demogorgon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Darkmantle</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-darkmantle.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darkmantles feel like a very AD&amp;amp;D kind of monster, but I can’t find mention of
them in the Monster Manuals for those editions. Either they appeared in a
supplement, or they’re actually introduced in 3.x.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The darkmantle is a creature native to the Shadowfell, which predictably means
it likes hanging out in dark places such as caves and underground ruins. Being
both pointy and membranous, they hunt by hanging from the ceiling disguised as
stalactites and dropping on unsuspecting prey from above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darkmantles have animal intellect, and are about as smart as dogs. As such,
they’re often tamed by shadow- and underground-themed humanoids to act as
guards and/or living traps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s only one stat block here, so we’ll get right to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;darkmantle-enveloper&quot;&gt;Darkmantle Enveloper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is described as a Large Shadow Magical Beast, though I think it should be
labeled a Beast instead. Beasts “look and behave like animals”, and magical
beasts “look like animals and behave like people”. Well, the label is just
descriptive, so it makes no difference in the stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Darkmantle Enveloper is a Level 8 Lurker with 76 HP. It has both Blindsight
8 from echolocation, and Darkvision. It emits a &lt;strong&gt;Shadowy Field&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that
reduces bright light to dim light, which I guess it only activates once its
presence is known. It has ground and climb speeds of 2, and a fly speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Lash&lt;/strong&gt; that does regular physical damage, but
the main event is &lt;strong&gt;Engulf&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Reflex), which does the same damage
and grabs the target. The target is considered blinded until the grab ends, and
the creature can spend a minor action to sustain it and deal an automatic 5
damage to the target. Only one victim can be engulfed at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the victim’s buddies try to help them, the darkmantle can use a &lt;strong&gt;Shadowcry&lt;/strong&gt;
(close burst 3 vs. Fortitude; minor action; encounter) to keep them at bay. This
does light thunder damage and dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone manages to damage the darkmantle, it can react with a
&lt;strong&gt;Shadowjump&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5-6), which allows it to teleport 6 squares to a space
in darkness or dim light. The creature arrives invisible and with its aura
turned off, both of which last for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One small mechanical issue: since Engulf is not a basic attack, it can’t be used
as part of a charge. This could be interpreted to say that the darkmantle can’t
drop from the ceiling and use Engulf, but that’s clearly not the intention
here. I’d say the attack &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be used as part of a “drop charge”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 6, and feature a pair of darkmantles acting as
guards for a trio of duergar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eh… it’s another underground ambusher that disguises itself as a rock
formation. The most a darkmantle has ever interested me is when it was part of a
joke about gygaxian deathtrap dungeons (“the stalactites are darkmantles; the
stalagmites ropers…”).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/07/darkmantle.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/07/darkmantle.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Cyclops</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-cyclops.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Chippy. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another one of those entries that gives us more stat blocks for monsters
introduced in the first Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already covered the bulk of cyclops lore in the corresponding &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/09/03/cyclops.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual
post&lt;/a&gt;, so I’ll going to say it’s super cool and ask you to read the original
post again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get some specific lore for the two new variants: Cyclops Crushers are
employed as slave minders, directing their crushing towards any who step out of
line. Feyblades are pampered bodyguards who rarely engaged in manual labor, and
like to lord their superior status over their less important colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/09/03/cyclops.html&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt; also contains the traits for cyclopes, but I’ll summarize
them again for convenience: they’re Large Fey Humanoids, trained in perception,
and have Truesight, which lets them see invisible creatures and objects. They
all also have some sort of Evil Eye ability that varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cyclops-crusher&quot;&gt;Cyclops Crusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one appears in the Monster Vault, so it’s also covered in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/09/03/cyclops.html&quot;&gt;original
post&lt;/a&gt;. Its MM2 stat block is identical as far as abilities go, but suffers
from all the math bugs common at the time of publication. Go with the Monster
Vault stat block and you won’t be missing anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cyclops-feyblade&quot;&gt;Cyclops Feyblade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first cyclops we haven’t already seen in our Let’s Reads is a Level 21
Soldier with 200 HP, which means it’s significantly stronger than all the other
cyclopes we’ve seen so far. It wears mail and fights with a longsword. Its speed
is 8. It’s more or less equivalent to a simplified PC swordmage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its greater level the feyblade is actually very mechanically simple. The
&lt;strong&gt;Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; is its most basic and best attack, doing physical damage with no
riders. The &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; is a Ranged 20 minor action that marks a target
automatically, lasting until the end of the encounter or until the feyblade
marks someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cyclops earns its title because it knows &lt;strong&gt;Wildstep&lt;/strong&gt;, an immediate
interrupt that triggers when the marked victim ignores the mark. The feyblade
can then teleport 10 squares to be adjacent to the victim and make an attack to
it that deals sligthly less damage than the basic sword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all cyclopes are slaves to the fomorians, but the MM2 seems to want to
emphasize their “natural” position as someone else’s goons and mentions they can
also be found serving firbolg and drow. This would eventually be elaborated into
a code of honor that prevents oaths of servitude from being broken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 13: 2 crushers, 2 eladrin bladesingers and 1
firbolg moon seer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyclopes are cool, and more of them means more choice for a fey paragon campaign
versus the Fomorians. So I like these ones.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/06/cyclops.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/06/cyclops.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Couatl</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-couatl.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Eva Widermann. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couatls are inspired by Aztec mythology and have been in the game since at least
AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition. They were given a significant role in the lore of Eberron, and
I guess this entry brings that to their generic depiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couatls are sapient winged serpents widely known for their great virtue, wisdom
and power. They have opposed demons and other servants of evil since ancient
times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is true, but it’s not the whole truth. It’s less widely known that
couatl righteousness can end up crossing the line into self-righteousness. Each
individual tends to have specific plans that they pursue with single-minded
dedication, and being convinced of their own rectitude they tend to not see
people who get in the way of those plans with good eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those plans are never actually evil, of course: they’re stuff like protecting a
village or other region, pushing a mortal along a destined path, sealing a
planar breach, or preventing one from opening in the first place. Still, it’s
very possible for a bunch of well-meaning PCs ignorant of the wider picture to
get in the way of a couatl’s plans and draw the creature’s wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancient legends say that couatls were born of the world’s first light, and that
they fought alongside the gods during the Dawn War. They were supposedly
responsible for binding a great number of powerful and dangerous creatures in
the world or in other planes, and a lot of those mysterious plans have something
to do with keeping those creatures bound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couatls have the innate ability to travel from any plane to the Astral Sea in 10
minutes, arriving at a random location or at a teleporation circle they
know. They can likely also use standard rituals to travel from the Sea to
elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Eberron, if I’m not mistaken, couatls are the ones responsible for binding
the demonic Lords of Dust in the distant past, and their magic have a lot to do
with the deepest secrets of the Silver Flame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couatls are Large Immortal Magical Beasts with the Reptile keyword. They have a
ground speed of 6 and a flight speed of 8 with Hover. And they also have two
signature traits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radiant Absorption&lt;/strong&gt; makes it so that when a couatl takes radiant damage, its
own attacks deal 5 extra radiant damage until the end of its next turn. &lt;strong&gt;Twist
Free&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to roll saves against the immobilized and restrained
conditions both at the start and end of their turns. This applies even when the
conditions would end after a set time instead of being (save ends): in that
case, the start-of-turn save could terminate the condition early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two stat blocks we get here are Unaligned, which I guess is what you get
when you combine “opposes evil” with “is a smug snake”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;couatl-cloud-serpent&quot;&gt;Couatl Cloud Serpent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud Serpents are Level 18 Artillery with 135 HP and all standard couatl
traits. They prefer to fight by shooting lasers and lightning from above (and
far away).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This most often takes the form of a &lt;strong&gt;Sky Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 20 vs. Reflex) which
deals lightning and radiant damage. If the opposition clusters together they’ll
use &lt;strong&gt;Snaking Arcs&lt;/strong&gt; (Area Burst 3 within 20 vs. Reflex), which is a little
weaker but covers an area. It recharges once they’re first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy manages to get close to them they can use a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which
is a bit weak but deals ongoing poison and radiant damage (save ends). Even
their venom is shiny! They can also push the interloper away with &lt;strong&gt;Hurtling
Coils&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach 2 vs. Fortitude, minor action 1/round), a non-damaging attack
that pushes targets 2 squares and knocks them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;couatl-star-serpent&quot;&gt;Couatl Star Serpent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star Serpents are Level 15 Elite Controllers with 286 HP. They’re a lot more
fond of melee combat than their cloud serpent cousins, and love to use
constricting attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is the same as the cloud serpent’s. The venom does a little less
ongoing damage, but also slows (save ends all). Their &lt;strong&gt;Righteous Coils&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach
2 vs. Fortitude; minor action 1/round) do a bit of damage and grab. Grabbed
targets grant combat advantage to the star serpent, and it can move them without
needing to make Strength tests like the standard grapple rules say. There’s no
state limit to the number of grabbed victims; conceivably, the whole party could
be wrapped in the serpent’s coils. The escape DC is 27.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The couatl can &lt;strong&gt;Constrict&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fortitude; minor action 1/round) a grabbed
target, dealing decent physical damage and dazing them for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The star serpent also has two magic encounter powers: &lt;strong&gt;Purifying Scream&lt;/strong&gt;
(close burst 5 vs. Will) does psychic damage and also stuns the target for a
turn if it’s taking ongoing fire, poison or radiant damage. &lt;strong&gt;Couatl Radiance&lt;/strong&gt;
grants the creature the insubstantial and phasing traits and allows it to shift
8 squares. The goal here is to pass through as many allies and enemies as
possible: every ally the couatl passes through regains 15 HP and can spend a
healing surge; every enemy suffers an attack vs. Will that, on a hit, deals both
immediate and ongoing fire and radiant damage. This nicely sets them up for a
Purifying Scream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couatls can be found hanging out with other creatures that share a similar
desire to oppose or guard against evil. They might also engage in a bit of smug
snake realpolitik and work alongside shadier allies with the goal of thwarting a
worse evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book gives us two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 14: a star serpen, 3 deva knights-errant, and 1 phoelarch warrior.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 20: 2 cloud serpents, 2 marut executioners, 1 marut prosecutor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like couatls! This more ambiguous portrayal of them gives me plenty of hooks
to hang plots from, which I can’t say was something the purely Lawful Good
version did.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/06/couatl.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/06/couatl.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Colossus</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-colossus.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Brian Valenzuela. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw back in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/08/23/colossus.html&quot;&gt;Colossus entry for the Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;, colossi are at
the top of the tech tree for traditional constructs, and only gods and
near-divine spellcasters have the power to create them. They’re the kind of
thing that was used as a weapon in the Dawn War. Well, here we learn that the
gods weren’t the only side of that war that could make colossi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the post linked above, I made a reference to the giant monsters from the
Shadow of the Colossus game. The primordial colossus we’re looking at here fits
them much better than the godforged variant from the first Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most primordial colossi were created at the time of the Dawn War, and being as
ageless as their creators they still exist today. Some roam the planes seeking
to fulfill the orders of their long-gone masters, but others lie dormant looking
for all the world like shattered ruins or broken parts of the landscape. When
someone approaches them, they rise and smash the intruder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magic that goes into a primordial colossus is a little wilder and less
controlled than the one that goes into the god-forged variant. The principles
behind it are such that a primordial colossus might be created &lt;em&gt;by accident&lt;/em&gt;
in any event that causes the release of a massive amount of elemental
energy. This includes the awakening or destruction of a mighty elemental
being. It’s also possible for an epic spellcaster to acquire and perform the
ritual to create one of these constructs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again we get a single stat block here, so let’s get right to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;primordial-colossus&quot;&gt;Primordial Colossus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This baby is a Huge Elemental Animate with the Construct keyword, and a Level 29
Elite Brute with 640 HP. It’s immune to disease, fear, poison and sleep, and has
a Variable Elemental Resistance 15 switchable 3 times per encounter. Its ground
speed is 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primordial colossi really lean into that mechanic for composite energy
damage. They have an &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Presence&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that deals 15 damage of the
“acid, cold, fire, lightning, and thunder” type to anyone caught inside. You
need resistance to all five types in order to not take full damage from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; do physical damage, but they likely prefer to use a
&lt;strong&gt;Colossal Slam&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (close blast 3 vs. AC), which does the same damage
over an area and triggers a secondary attack vs. Fortitude that does a bit of
extra five-type elemental damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy moves adjacent to the colossus, it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Reactive Kick&lt;/strong&gt; as
a reaction, targetting Fortitude, doing a good bit of five-type damage, pushing
the target 4 squares and knocking it prone. This recharges once the colossus is
first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying away does you no good, since it can throw &lt;strong&gt;Primordial Stones&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged
20 vs. Reflex) that do only a bit less damage than the slam and have a secondary
area attack (Close Burst 5 vs. Fortitude) which does that sweet five-type
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two sample encounters have primordial colossi guarding ancient ruins
alongside other similarly powerful apotropaics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 26: 1 primordial colossus, 2 great flameskulls, 1 slaughterstone
hammerer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 27: 1 primordial colossus, 1 primordial naga.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe an epic adventure centered on Far Realm opposition could have some
horrible aberrant secret guarded by both godforged and primordial colossi -
something so terrible the gods and primordials actually joined forces to
protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, I find those Big Balls of Elemental Damage in the colossus’ stat
block to be a lot of fun. It’s so hard to resist you’d get the same result by
just using straight physical damage, but describing it this way reinforces the
elemental nature of the creature… and you get to see the look on your players’
faces as you announce they took acid, cold, fire lightning and thunder damage.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/colossus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/colossus.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Cockatrice</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-cockatrice.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Brian Valenzuela. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know both cockatrices and basilisks are based on the same vague lump
of medieval folklore about an animal that can turn you to stone. The exact name,
description and proportion of snake/lizard/chicken traits this animal has varies
in each specific story. D&amp;amp;D, of course, turned each possible name for the same
thing into a totally different monster. They’ve been in the game since at least
the days of BECMI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cockatrices are bird-like monsters whose bite can turn a victim to stone. Unlike
a lot of other deadly creatures, though, they don’t actually seem to be
predators. Their petrification powers are a defense mechanism, which they will
use while trying to run away from whatever enemy threatens them. So yeah, you
could say cockatrices are a bit chicken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, cockatrice lairs tend to have the little statue gardens common to
petrifying monsters, all likely made from predators who thought they could
handle it or from innocent creatures who had no idea whose lawn they were
stepping on. I imagine careful adventurers can just avoid the area entirely if
they see the statues, though there are reasons they would seek it out instead:
the freshly plucked feathers of a cockatrice can be used to brew a potion that
undoes petrification if applied within 24 hours. A single dose requires a whole
cockatrice’s worth of feathers, which in turn likely requires killing the beast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cockatrices are themselves immune to petrification, which makes them good pets
for medusas. The book also says other reptilians, like lizardfolk and yuan-ti,
also make use of them. They’re definitely easier to handle than a basilisk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only get a single stat block here, so let’s get right to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cockatrice&quot;&gt;Cockatrice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Small Natural Beast and a Level 5 Skirmisher with 63 HP and low-light
vision. It’s immune to petrification as discussed earlier, and has a ground
speed of 4 and a flight speed of 6 (clumsy). As a reminder, the Clumsy keyword
means the creature has a -4 to attacks when using that movement mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cockatrice’s basic attack is its &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which is kinda weak but triggers
a secondary attack vs. Fortitude. A hit there does no damage and slows the
victim (save ends). This worsens to Immobilized on the first failed save, and to
“permanent until cured” petrification on the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy moves adjacent to the cockatrice it can use &lt;strong&gt;Buffeting Wings&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 4-6) as an interrupt, which allows it to bite the triggering enemy and
shift 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given their low level, cockatrices are likely to be the first petrifying
monsters a party encounters. They’re simple, but their main attack is scary
enough to make up for that. They could be made into higher-level threats if, in
addition to leveling them up, you made them more mobile and gave them an extra
special attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 5: 2 cockatrices and a trio of lizardfolk using
them as attack animals.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/cockatrice.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/cockatrice.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Chaos Shard</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-chaos-shard.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any edition of D&amp;amp;D it’s easy to get obsessed with its fiend taxonomy, but
there are always some creatures that end up slipping through its cracks. Take
chaos shards, for example. They form spontaneously at the edges of the terrible
maelstrom that exists at the border between the Elemental Chaos and the Abyss,
when the energies of those two planes clash in a particular way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These crystalline entities are sapient, violent, and cruel. Since they don’t
have any biological needs to distract them, they’re quite content with roaming
around and blasting everything they see with elemental energies. I imagine they
give preference to targets that can scream and suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having themes tied to the Abyss, being Chaotic Evil, and even having
variable elemental resistance, these things are not demons. They do have some
sort of metaphysical connection to the Shard of Pure Evil at the bottom of the
Abyss, though. Legend has it that the most powerful chaos shards are splinters
of that legendary blight upon the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some wizards trap chaos shards for use as power sources, which I bet is not at
all dangerous or likely to result in death and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a handful of stat blocks for shards covering from the mid-Heroic to the
mid-Paragon tiers. All are Medium Elemental Magical Beasts. They have
Darkvision, immunities to disease and poison, and a variable elemental
resistance similar to that of demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re all Artillery monsters, and their movement is fairly slow, though they
do fly. Most are strongly aspected towards a specific element, and have damaging
auras that get a bit stronger if their enemies are suffering from some condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;storm-shard&quot;&gt;Storm Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 4 Artillery shard has 44 HP and aspected towards lightning and
thunder. Its ground and fly speeds are 3, and it projects a &lt;strong&gt;Static Storm&lt;/strong&gt;
aura (2) that deals 3 lightning and thunder damage to those enemies caught
inside. This rises to 5 if the enemy is immobilized. They have the standard
senses and immunities, and their variable resistance is 5 and can be switched
once per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fire &lt;strong&gt;Shock Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fortitude) that do some lightning damage and
“strongly incentivize” the target to move: if they don’t end their next turn at
least 4 squares away from their current position, they take lightning damage
roughly equal to triple that of the initial attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If forced into melee, the shard attacks with &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fortitude)
which deal thunder damage and knock the target prone if it’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When killed, storm shards explode! This &lt;strong&gt;Storm Shatter&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 3
vs. Fortitude) attack deals lightning and thunder damage, pushes the targets 3
squares, and deafens them (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note on damage types: the expression “lightning and thunder damage” above
denotes an attack with a single damage roll that is of both types at
once. Targets use the smallest of their relevant elemental resistances against
this damage. In this specific example, someone with Lightning Resistance 10 and
Thunder Resistance 5 would subtract only 5 from the rolled damage. Someone that
resists only one of the component types takes full damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;death-shard&quot;&gt;Death Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aspected towards necrotic energies, Death Shards are Level 8 Artillery with 71
HP. It has all the standard traits including Variable Resistance 5
(1/encounter), and also Necrotic Resistance 10. Its speed is 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thing projects a &lt;strong&gt;Death Shadow&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that deals necrotic damage to
enemies caught inside, which increases if the enemies are slowed. It fires
&lt;strong&gt;Death Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that deal necrotic damage and slow
(save ends). In melee, it cuts you with a &lt;strong&gt;Razor Shard&lt;/strong&gt;, a regular basic
attack dealing physical damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit less volatile than the Storm Shard, but still dangerous: when hit by
a critical, it reacts with a &lt;strong&gt;Critical Fracture&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2
vs. Fortitude), which deals necrotic damage and weakens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the death shard resists damage (i.e, if it’s hit with something covered by
its resistances), all of its attacks deal extra damage until the end of its next
turn. This trait is named &lt;strong&gt;Life to Death&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flame-shard&quot;&gt;Flame Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Level 12 Artillery monsters have an even 100 HP and are a bit more literal
about this whole artillery business than most of their compatriots. Their speed
is 4 and their variable resistance 10 (switchable twice per encounter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flame shard’s main ranged attack is &lt;strong&gt;Flame Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 2 within 10
vs. Reflex) which is basically like an at-will fireball, though its damage is
rather low. In melee it stabs people with a &lt;strong&gt;Burning Shard&lt;/strong&gt; that does fire
damage, and it projects a &lt;strong&gt;Heat Wave&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that deals fire damage and
inflicts a -2 penalty against ongoing fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When killed they explode in a final attack that’s much like a Flame Burst
centered on themselves, and which also does ongoing fire damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prismatic-shard&quot;&gt;Prismatic Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living proof that “Radiant” doesn’t always mean “Good”… it can also mean “evil
disco ball”! These are Level 16 Artillery monsters with 123 HP. To the standard
list of shard immunities they add an immunity to &lt;em&gt;radiant damage&lt;/em&gt;, making the
party’s divine characters very sad. Their variable resistance is 10 and can be
switched four times per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their aura (2) is named &lt;strong&gt;Prismatic Corona&lt;/strong&gt;. It does radiant damage and
inflicts a -2 penalty to all saving throws during made during the affected
enemy’s turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Prismatic Shard’s attacks do radiant damage. The melee &lt;strong&gt;Prism
Flare&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex) has nothing else going on for it. The &lt;strong&gt;Iridescent Bolt&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 20 vs. Will) also blinds for a turn. Its &lt;strong&gt;Flashing Colors&lt;/strong&gt; (close
burst 3 vs. Will; minor action) do no damage but daze (save ends). And the
&lt;strong&gt;Prismatic Shatter&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Will) attack it uses when it dies also
blinds (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, chaos shards don’t have frail organic bodies to worry about,
so they can live solely for the fun of seeing people explode from their
elemental blasts. They hang out with creatures who are equally appreciative of
this highly refined form of entertainment, including slaads, demons, and certain
types of Internet troll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also be summoned and controlled through elemental magic, which makes
them popular with certain spellcasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: 2 death shards, a bloodseep demon, and 2 evistros.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 17: 1 prismatic shard, 3 blue slaads, and 1 green slaad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaos shards fulfill the important mechanical niche of providing artillery
support for demons and slaads, since these monster types are all about melee and
tend to lack ranged firepower. They also further confuse the taxonomy of “things
from the Abyss”, something which I’m finding more and more interesting as I
progress through these monster books.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/01/chaos-shard.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/01/chaos-shard.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Vault 2: Centipede</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-centipede.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monstrous centipedes have been in the game since the beginning, and are based on
real-world animals. Let’s see what 4e makes of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only recently realized D&amp;amp;D centipedes aren’t as fantastical as I always
thought. There are thousands of real-world centipede species, and the ones I was
familiar with were pretty small and generally not dangerous to people. However,
some species can reach up to 30cm (a foot!) in length, and have a poisonous bite
that might cause fever and chills in people. It’s possible for someone to be
allergic to centipede venom, and in that case their bite can cause anaphylatic
shock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the only fantastical thing about the D&amp;amp;D centipede in early editions of the
game was the fact that its venom was always save-or-die. Its size was realistic,
and so was its venom in later editions when it became less deadly. Of course,
the game also had truly giant centipedes which were entirely fantastical, and
this remains true here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centipedes can be found in woodlands, caves, and lots of other
environments. They’re ferocious predators and aggressive enough to attack much
larger creatures if they feel threatened. The larger specimens are of a scale
large enough to see humanoids as potential prey, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all this aggressiveness, it seems lots of sapient creatures are able to
keep them as pets and guard animals. I suspect magic might be
involved. Centipedes are particularly popular pets for Torog worshippers, who
consider them sacred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centipedes are Natural Beasts of varying size. The game gives them Darkvision,
though it might be more accurate to give them blindsight instead. The authors
didn’t consider a single foot-long centipede to be a worthy threat, so we get
stats for a swarm of them and for a giant specimen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centipede-swarm&quot;&gt;Centipede Swarm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Medium swarm is a Level 2 Brute with 44 HP. It has ground and climb speeds
of 6, with Spider Climb (which allows them to cling to ceilings). It has all
standard swarm traits, taking half damage from melee and ranged attacks, and 10
extra damage from close and area attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) deals 3 automatic damage to each enemy caught
inside, +2 per centipede swarm adjacent to the enemy. This is deceptively
dangerous, particularly if you assume multiple swarm auras stack! An enemy
adjacent to a single swarm will take 5 damage at the start of their turn. An
enemy adjacent to 2 of them would take 14, or 7 if the auras don’t stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The swarm’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex), which deals a
little bit of physical damage, which increases by 1 with each adjacent centipede
swarm. A hit also deals ongoing 5 poison damage (save ends). If the enemy is
already taking ongoing poison damage, they’re weakened (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the swarm is hit by an area or close attack, their &lt;strong&gt;Survival Instinct&lt;/strong&gt;
causes them to shift 3 squares as a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting monster: despite being a brute, its attack is kinda weak. Most of
the damage comes from the swarm aura, particularly if you assume multiple
centipede swarm auras stack. You’ll never encounter just one swarm either -
there should be at least two in the group to enjoy those cool exponential
bonuses. More than two might be pushing a bit, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centipede-scuttler&quot;&gt;Centipede Scuttler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proper giant, this is a single Medium individual. It’s a Level 4 Skirmisher
with 51 HP and both ground and climb speeds of 8. Can’t run away from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; targets AC and does a little more damage than the swarm’s, but has
the same riders. Against a weakened creature (which likely got that way from its
venom) it can &lt;strong&gt;Feed&lt;/strong&gt;, dealing roughly triple the damage of a basic bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an at-will move action, the Scuttler can, well, &lt;strong&gt;Scuttle&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it
to shift 4 squares. When it shifts into an ally’s space while scuttling, that
space doesn’t count as one of the 4 squares. Be sure to give it lots of
buddies when building the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 4: 1 ankheg, 2 bloodthorn vines, and 2 centipede swarms. What rotten
luck that all of them would be hanging out next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 5: 2 scuttlers, 1 gnoll huntmaster, 2 gnoll marauders. So they keep more
than hyenas as pets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the old save-or-die centipedes and these feel properly scary as well,
while also being distinct from all the other giant creepy crawlies.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/30/centipede.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/30/centipede.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
