<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 18:23:42 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 18:23:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Bitterstrike</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-bitterstrike.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This our first example of a “concrete” dragon, where they take the generic
information from the Monster Manuals and use it to make a specific atypical
individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, a young white dragon came to the Nentir Vale. Making her lair
inside the nothern Winterbole forest, she frequently flew out to hunt and to
break things for fun, and eventually came to see the Vale as her own personal
buffet and playground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lasted until the Tigerclaw barbarians who also lived in Winterbole decided
to stand up to her. Their chief was the great hero Fangstrike, who dueled the
dragon and manage to bury his war pick in her left eye. Wounded and humiliated,
the dragon flew away and spent the next thirty years sulking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience made her a cautious and vindictive. About nine months after
Fangstrike died of old age, she came back to wreak havoc on the tribe, killing
the chief’s surviving family and threatening the rest of the tribe with
destruction unless they paid her an annual tribute of treasure and a high-status
hostage. This how she came to be known by her current name of Bitterstrike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitterstrike made the same ultimatum to every other group of sapients who made
Winterbole their home: the Frost Witches, the Winterbole Treants, and the satyrs
who made the evergreen forest their home. Pay tribute and send hostages, or die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, Bitterstrike considers herself queen of Winterbole, and those annual
hostages make up her court. She uses them as agents and servants, and has them
keep an ear out for rumors and news from their original communities. If any of
these news sounds like an insult or threat to her, Bitterstrike becomes obsessed
with taking revenge on the offender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually this takes the form of a direct strike by the dragon, but Bitterstrike
is cautious enough to gather a posse of her vassals if she feels a solo attack
doesn’t have good odds. Whether alone or at the head of a posse, Bitterstrike
takes great pleasure in revenge and in the acquisition of more loot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the dragon queen is nowhere near the genius she thinks she is, and her
“vassals” view her more as a pawn than as a queen. Every single faction under
her control manipulates her into advancing their own goals by telling her false
information, and the Satyrs are in the habit of replacing the magic items in her
hoard with cheap mundane copies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs can come into conflict with Bitterstrike by trespassing into her hunting
grounds or offending her directly. It might also happen that they piss off one
of her “vassal” factions and they plant a few convenient rumors to sic her on
the party. Depending on how powerful the party is, she might bring in a few
elite vassals along for support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have stats for Bitterstrike herself and for the typical vassals or pets that
might accompany her. A lot of these are based on other existing factions we’ll
look at later, so you get a preview of what they can do right here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the vassals have Resist Cold 5 and Ice Walk, both necessary for survival
when hanging around Bitterstrike. All vassals and the dragon herself also have a
custom encounter power named &lt;strong&gt;Bitter Vengeance&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when an enemy
within 5 squares hits them with an attack. As a free action, they deal 10
automatic cold damage to the enemy and push them 2 squares. Bitterstrike’s
vengeance is more forceful and yeets the offender 7 squares instead. This makes
them all perfect to fight on maps that include hazardous cold-based terrain like
bodies of icy water or snow-covered pits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bitterstrike&quot;&gt;Bitterstrike&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Wyrm of Winterbole is a Level 10 Solo Brute with 520 HP, Resist Cold
10, a ground speed of 6 with Ice Walk, and a flight speed of 6. She’s actually
the first MM3/MV-compatible adult white dragon we ran across in our readings, as
the MV only contained Young and Elder examples. Though she only has one eye,
that doesn’t affect her stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a white dragon, she has an &lt;strong&gt;Action Recovery&lt;/strong&gt; trait that automatically ends
any dazing, stunning, or dominating effects on her when her turn ends, and
&lt;strong&gt;Instinctive Rampage&lt;/strong&gt; that gives her a free action at her initiative + 10
where she can move her speed, go through enemy spaces, and use a claw attack on
any enemy whose space she moves through. She gains Resist 5 to all damage during
this action, to better tank opportunity attacks. She also has a &lt;strong&gt;Savage Blood&lt;/strong&gt;
trait that makes her crit on a roll of 17-20 while bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitterstrike’s Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; deals cold damage, half on a miss. Her Reach 2
&lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; can attack two different creatures with one action. Her &lt;strong&gt;Breath
Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a Close Blast 5 that deals cold damage and slows (save
ends). On a miss it deals half damage and slows for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a flanking enemy hits Bitterstrike she can react with a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Slap&lt;/strong&gt; to
damage and push them 5 squares. The first time she’s bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied
Breath&lt;/strong&gt; allows her to recharge and immediately use her breath weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitterstrike has Int 10, Wis 15, Cha 10. Every single one of her vassals listed
below has higher mental stats than her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;treant-vassal&quot;&gt;Treant Vassal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Winterbole treant, patterned after a coniferous tree, serving as one of
Bitterstrike’s vassals. It’s a Large Fey Magical Beast (plant) and a Level 8
Elite Soldier with 182 HP and a speed of 8 with Forest and Ice walk. It has
Threatening Reach 2, and a &lt;strong&gt;Wooden Body&lt;/strong&gt; trait that makes it take ongoing 5
fire damage (save ends) whenever it takes fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The treant’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt; and it can &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. It can
also use a &lt;strong&gt;Bitterwind Blast&lt;/strong&gt; that’s like a smaller version of Bitterstrike’s
breath weapon. It recharges when the creature is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an Essentials-style soldier, the Treant doesn’t mess with marks and can
instead use &lt;strong&gt;Pounding Branches&lt;/strong&gt; to attack any enemy in reach that makes an
attack that doesn’t target it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;satyr-vassal&quot;&gt;Satyr Vassal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This satyr is a Medium Fey Humanoid and Level 8 Elite Artillery with 136
HP and a speed of 6 with Ice Walk. As a bard-type, it’s surrounded by an aura
(5) of &lt;strong&gt;Cold Wind Song&lt;/strong&gt; that gives it +5 to defenses against attacks
originating from &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; the aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The satyr wants to stay really far away from its enemies, so it uses a Range 20
&lt;strong&gt;North Wind Bow&lt;/strong&gt; to attack. A hit deals cold damage and pushes the target 3
squares. Once per encounter it can pull a Hanzo and fire a &lt;strong&gt;Diving Dragon
Shot&lt;/strong&gt; that hits an Area Burst 2 within 20 squares. This deals cold damage, half
on a miss, and creates a zone that deals cold damage to any who end their turn
inside until the end of the encounter. If forced into melee, it can use its
horns to &lt;strong&gt;Gore&lt;/strong&gt;, damaging the target and knocking it prone, which should allow
for a quick escape to safer ranges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-vassal&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Vassal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This barbarian from the Tigerclaw tribe is a shifter who’s pretty much always in
“shifted” mode. He’s a Level 8 Elite Skirmisher with 178 HP and Speed 6. His
&lt;strong&gt;Charging Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives him a 1d6 damage bonus on charge attacks and
allows him to use its normal actions after charging. Usually a character can
only use free actions after charging on their turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The barbarian fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Light Pick&lt;/strong&gt; and can use it to make &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attacks&lt;/strong&gt;. Once per encounter he can make a special attack named
&lt;strong&gt;Bitterstrike’s Slash&lt;/strong&gt; which deals heavy cold damage and ongoing cold damage
(save ends) on a hit. On a miss it slows and still inflicts the ongoing damage
(save ends). If an enemy ends their move flanking the vassal, he can use &lt;strong&gt;Wild
Instinct&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 1 square or move its speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frost-witch-vassal&quot;&gt;Frost Witch Vassal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This elf sent by the Frost Witches is the smartest vassal in the bunch. She’s a
Level 10 Elite Controller with 204 HP and Speed 6. She emits a &lt;strong&gt;Chill Aura&lt;/strong&gt;
(1) that slows enemies caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The witch fights in melee with a &lt;strong&gt;Frost Touch&lt;/strong&gt; that deals cold damage and
slides 2 squares, and at range with an &lt;strong&gt;Icicle Shard&lt;/strong&gt; that deals cold damage
and immobilizes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her big finisher is a &lt;strong&gt;Hailstone Hex&lt;/strong&gt; that deals cold and psychic damage. It
also forces the target to grant combat advantage and inflicts ongoing cold
damage (save ends both). While this effect persists, enemies of the witch that
start their turn adjacent to the victim suffer 5 cold damage. In other words,
it’s a miniature hailstone cloud following the victim around!  This recharges
when the witch is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wild-coldscale-drake&quot;&gt;Wild Coldscale Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is more of a pet than a vassal, as it’s a Medium Natural Beast and not
sapient. You can use these to fill out a vassal encounter. It’s a Level 8 Lurker
with 70 HP and Speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coldscale drakes have &lt;strong&gt;Snow Camouflage&lt;/strong&gt; that gives them partial concealment in
any icy terrain, and deal an extra 4d6 damage to any target that cannot see
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They need that boost because their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is a little weak without
it. Fortunately they can use their &lt;strong&gt;Snow Stalker&lt;/strong&gt; ability when on icy terrain
or within 10 squares of a white dragon to become invisible until after they make
their next attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitterstrike is a dangerous solo boss fight for a level 6 or 7 party. When
facing more powerful PCs she will bring enough elite vassals and coldscale
drakes to keep that level advantage. Most encounters against her should happen
in the Winterbole region, which will give her and her vassals a big terrain
advantage. Anyone level 5 or lower is seriously risking their lives by going too
deep into the Winterbole forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, I like the dynamic of a somewhat stupid “queen” constantly
manipulated by her much smarter vassals.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/12/01/bitterstrike.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/12/01/bitterstrike.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Barrowhaunts</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-barrowhaunts.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an entirely original setting-specific entry. Now this is what I’m here
for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gray Downs is a region of dreary fog-shrouded hills in the center-north of
the Nentir Vale. It contains a great number of burial mounds built by ancient
humans who lived here centuries before the arrival of the Nerathi. These hill
clans are extinct, but their ruins remain as witnesses of their existence. The
greatest of these mounds is the Sword Barrow, which sits prominently at the
center of the Downs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sword Barrow is exactly the sort of place that would be considered a prime
delving spot: it reaches deep underground, its layout is complex, and it’s
filled with traps and treasure belonging to the forgotten king or warlord that
rests at its bottom. It’s also already “taken”. If you get too close to it, the
Barrowhaunts will shank you for trying to move into their territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Barrowhaunts are a group of undead revenants who used to be an adventuring
party in life.  They are themselves quite ancient, and no one knows why they
became undead. The leading rumor is that they delved the Sword Barrow and
attracted the ire of the warlord buried inside, whose spirit called out to the
hill clans and told them to come take their revenge. They answered the call, and
the Barrowhaunts preferred to slaughter them all rather than relinquish their
loot. So yeah, according to this story they’re responsible for the final
extinction of the hill clans. One of the hillfolk elders laid a dying curse upon
the adventurers, binding them to the land for all eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This didn’t have any obvious immediate effect, but the adventuring party did
become more and more obsessed with the region as time went by. They kept coming
back for more treasure, and attempted many delves into the Sword
Barrow. Eventually their greed surpassed their skill. After the ensuing TPK,
they got back up, now fully under the effects of the curse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As undead, the Barrowhaunts effectively became eternal guardians of the Grey
Downs barrows, but they frame this duty in terms of their original greedy
mentality. They spend their existence delving the barrows and moving loot around
to protect it from “rivals” and “claim-jumpers”, which means anyone wandering
through their claimed territory. They savagely attack any intruders and add
their loot to the pile. Somewhere in the Downs is a big stash of all the
treasure they’ve gathered over the ages, but no one has been able to find it and
live to tell the tale yet. It might be inside the Sword Barrow, it might be
somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Barrowhaunts are aided in their duty by the spirits of the creatures and
people they’ve killed over the ages. Many of these are hillfolk, but there are
also newer ghosts. None of them want to see the Barrowhaunts’ curse end, so they
fight hard to keep them from being destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Barrowhaunts are all specific individuals! They share in common a set of
generic undead traits: immune to fear and disease, resist 10 necrotic,
vulnerable 5 radiant, Darkvision. All of their other traits come from training
or from their respective racial powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lingering spirits that accompany them are Shadow Humanoids and Beasts with
undead traits. They’re all minions but they have high damage resistance, making
them a lot more stubborn than most minions. Let’s look at them first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lingering-warrior-spirit&quot;&gt;Lingering Warrior Spirit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A humanoid spirit and a Level 7 Minion Soldier. It has immunity to disease and
fear, and Resist 15 to all damage except radiant. Their &lt;strong&gt;Phantom Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; deal
a bit of damage and immobilize for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That damage resistance at level 7 means that fighting these things pretty much
requires someone who can deal radiant damage on demand, like a cleric, paladin
or even a star warlock with the right powers. A PC striker might be able to
brute-force them, but not consistently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lingering-monster-spirit&quot;&gt;Lingering Monster Spirit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ghost of a non-humanoid monster. It’s a Large Level 9 Minion Brute, with a
ground speed of 8 and a climb speed of 6. It attacks with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Savage
Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; that do good damage for a minion. The thing that makes it special is
Resist 20 to all non-radiant damage, which means they’re almost impossible to
brute-force. Bring a cleric!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uthelyn-the-mad&quot;&gt;Uthelyn the Mad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the Barrowhaunts’ half-elf rogue. She’s a Level 8 Skirmisher with 86
HP. Her &lt;strong&gt;Maniacal Laughter&lt;/strong&gt; acts like an aura (1) that inflicts a -2 attack
penalty on enemies inside. She wields a &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; and can do &lt;strong&gt;Mad
Slashes&lt;/strong&gt; with it, which let her shift 2 squares before and after the attack as
an effect, and deal bonus necrotic damage against targets that grant combat
advantage to Uthelyn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter she can react to an effect that would immobilize, slow, or
restrain her with a &lt;strong&gt;Ghostly Escape&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets her end the effect and gain
insubstantial and phasing for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adrian-iceheart-reginold&quot;&gt;Adrian “Iceheart” Reginold&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was their human wizard, specializing in cold spells. He’s a Level 8
Controller with 86 HP, and is also resistant to cold and vulnerable to fire in
addition to all the standard traits mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adrian uses a &lt;strong&gt;Frost Staff&lt;/strong&gt; that does cold damage in melee, and shoots tricky
&lt;strong&gt;Ice Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; that do “cold and necrotic” damage and slow for a turn. As a
reminder dual-typed damage uses the target’s smaller resistance value, so if a
PC is only resistant to cold they’re going to take full damage from the
bolts. The wizard can also cast &lt;strong&gt;Deep Freeze&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3 vs. Fortitude,
recharge 5+) to deal cold damage and restrain for a turn, and &lt;strong&gt;Vortex of Ice&lt;/strong&gt;
(area burst 1 within 10, encounter) to deal heavy cold damage, slide 3 squares,
and knock prone. A miss here deals half damage and slides 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;joplin-the-sly&quot;&gt;Joplin the Sly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party’s second rogue, this one a halfling. She’s a level 8 Lurker with 68
HP. Joplin gets the halfling’s &lt;strong&gt;Nimble Reaction&lt;/strong&gt; trait, gaining +2 AC
vs. opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Vanishing Strike&lt;/strong&gt; with a short sword, which makes her
invisible to the target for a turn on a hit, and deals increased damage when she
has combat advantage. Once per encounter, when someone hits or misses her with a
melee attack, she can use &lt;strong&gt;Swift Rebuke&lt;/strong&gt; as an &lt;em&gt;interrupt&lt;/em&gt;, making a free
Vanishing Strike against the enemy with combat advantage. Since this is an
interrupt, it can turn a hit into a miss with the full concealment bonus for
being invisible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;boldos-grimehammer&quot;&gt;Boldos Grimehammer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party’s dwarf fighter is a Level 9 Brute with 122 HP. He gets the same
resistance to forced movement and knockdowns given to PC dwarves, and fights
with a battleaxe and shield. The &lt;strong&gt;axe&lt;/strong&gt; can be used for basic strikes or for
&lt;strong&gt;Mighty Swings&lt;/strong&gt; that deal a little less damage and either push the target 1
square or knock it prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Boldos is hit by an attack that would push, pull, or slide him, he can
respond with the &lt;strong&gt;Soldier of Fortune&lt;/strong&gt; interrupt, which gives him a free basic
attack with a +5 damage bonus against the triggering enemy. He always hits you
back before you push him, and since he’s a dwarf he might end up staying put
anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cassian-dcherevan&quot;&gt;Cassian d’Cherevan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party leader, this human warlord was probably some sort of noble in
life. He’s a Level 9 Elite Soldier with the Leader keyword and 192 HP. He’s
armored in plate and uses a &lt;strong&gt;greatsword&lt;/strong&gt; to fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an elite, he can make &lt;strong&gt;Double Attacks&lt;/strong&gt; with the sword, and once per
encounter he can make a &lt;strong&gt;Call to War&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets him attack once and allow
every ally within 5 squares to shift up to 2 squares and make a basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can use his &lt;strong&gt;Bolstering Presence&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) to give
every ally within 3 squares a +5 damage bonus for a turn. And if an adjacent
enemy makes an attack that doesn’t target him, Cassian can use &lt;strong&gt;Relentless
Assault&lt;/strong&gt; to automatically deal 12 damage to that enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the Barrowhaunts, because they’re a very specific group tied to a
specific spot on the map. They have a history, and a concrete reason for doing
what they do. This is the sort of entry you can write when you don’t have to be
as generic as possible. I also really like that they’re a party of murderhobos,
a kind of dark mirror held up to the PCs, saying “take care or you’ll end up
like them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically they’re all set up to work like a typical adventuring party. Each
member models a specific PC class or role, and their teamwork will take up a
very smilar form. Any fight against the PCs is going to happen in the Gray
Downs, an area full of obscuring mist and hilly, boulder-strewn terrain. The
Barrowhaunts have been there for centuries, are intimately familiar with it, and
will definitely set up traps and ambushes when attacking intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/29/barrowhaunts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/29/barrowhaunts.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Abyssal Plague Demon</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-abyssal-plague-demons-01.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a big deal about how there were few “newer and weirder” monsters in this
book, and now it turns out that the very first entry is one of those. Abyssal
Plague Demons are a monster new to 4e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite devoting a lot of text to the lore for abyssal plague demons, the entry
is irritatingly vague. That’s because these monsters are actually the main
featured threats of a series of novels published between 2010 and 2012. MV:TNV
was published in 2011, right in the middle of the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Abyssal Plague novels were planned as a big multimedia, multi-world metaplot
event. The novels would take place across multiple published settings, with the
main action taking place in the implied one, and side stories taking place in
Dark Sun and the Forgotten Realms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entry here is very vague and avoids naming names, probably out of a fear of
spoiling the event’s plot. There’s a demon lord who escaped into our universe
from another one he destroyed. He was stopped by “the heroes of the age” and
imprisoned, but recently one of his exarchs managed to escape and it “found a
vessel in the world”. This entity is responsible for spreading the Abyssal
Plague, a disease that covers its victim’s bodies in growths of alien crystal
and either kills them or transforms them into Abyssal Plague Demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a decade of hindsight, I can give you those spoilers: the “demon lord” is
actually Tharizdun and the thing that came from a another universe that was
destroyed by demons is the Shard of Evil that he used to make the Abyss. In the
novels, one of his worshipers manages to pierce the walls of Tharizdun’s prison
with a shard of the Living Gate (an entity described in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/10/15/shardmind.html&quot;&gt;Shardmind&lt;/a&gt; post
for the MM3), freeing one of his exarchs. This exarch is an entity known as the
Voidharrow and it is the thing responsible for spreading the Abyssal Plague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entry presents the Plague as a rising threat that only recently began to
spread, but doesn’t make an effort to connect it to other plot hooks in MV:TNV
or to the wider cosmic stuff at its root. I guess you’re supposed to read the
novels to find out about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-abyssal-plague-demons-02.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abyssal Plague Demons are creatures mutated by the plague. Some used to be
animals, some used to be humanoids. Aside from a general “demonic” look, they
have a common aesthetic element: red crystal, flecked with gold and silver. This
is present as either visible veins of liquid crystal, or as solid plates of the
stuff that might act as armor or weaponry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stat-wise, they’re demons: Elemental Beasts or Elemental Humanoids with the
Demon keyword, Darkvision and Variable Resistance (5, switchable twice per
encounter). All of them are also carriers of the Abyssal Plague, which they can
spread via bites or via their natural crystal weaponry. They’re all mid-Heroic
tier, making them appropriate for encounters in the middle world as your home
grounds start to suffer from the Plague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Abyssal Plague is a Level 8 Disease that follows the standard rules for
this. At the end of any fight where you’re exposed to it, you make a saving
throw. If you fail, you contract the disease at Stage 1. At the end of every
extended rest, you make an Endurance test. If you beat the disease’s Maintain DC
of 12, you stay as you are. If you beat its Improve DC of 16 your stage
decreases by 1 (Stage 0 means you’re cured). If you beat neither you progress to
the next stage. Effects from each stage are cumulative. If you reach Stage 3,
natural recovery is no longer possible and only a Remove Affliction ritual might
save you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stage 1 is usually just a nuisance. In this case, 10% of your body is covered in
alien growths and you lose a healing surge. Stage 2 is a major hindrance: here,
it means a -2 to AC, Fortitude and Reflex plus a permanent Slowed condition as
50% of your body is taken over by growths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stage 3 is often incapacitating or fatal. Unlike most other diseases, Abyssal
Plague still makes you roll Endurance daily when you’re here, but the roll is
not for recovery. If your total roll fails to beat a DC of 12, you die. If you
roll between 12 and 23, you live another day in incredible pain. If you roll a
24 or more, you turn into an Abyssal Plague Demon. So yeah, this plague kills
the weak and turns the strong into demons. You need to apply Remove Affliction
before either happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, multiple exposures during a fight still mean you only roll the save
once, and if you’ve already contracted the disease further exposures do nothing
to worsen your condition. So if your PC is tough and your party is on a
tight time-table, you can gamble that you’ll be able to recover naturally from
Stage 1. Remove Affliction is a big resource drain if you don’t have time for a
long rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plague-demon-chaos-hound&quot;&gt;Plague Demon Chaos Hound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Medium Beast demon, this quadruped is a Level 5 Minion Skirmisher with Speed 8
and darkvision. Its &lt;strong&gt;Pack Attack&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives it a small damage boost for each
other plague demon that’s adjacent to their target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their sole attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that allows them to shift 1 square on a hit and
exposes the target to Abyssal Plague. As a minion, it lacks Variable Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plague-demon-chaos-footsoldier&quot;&gt;Plague Demon Chaos Footsoldier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Medium Humanoid with Speed 6. It’s a Level 5 Minion Soldier without Variable
Resistance. Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Grabbing Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does light damage and
grabs on a hit. Once it has a grabbed victim, the footsoldier can &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; for a
bit more damage and exposure to the Plague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plague-demon-chaos-beast&quot;&gt;Plague Demon Chaos Beast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The non-minion version of the Chaos Hound is a Level 6 Skirmisher with Speed 8
and 76 HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;Chaotic Growl&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (1) that inflicts a -2 attack
penalty to enemies inside. Its basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; damages and exposes to the Plague,
while its &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; allow it to shift 1 square on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plague-demon-chaos-bender&quot;&gt;Plague Demon Chaos Bender&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Large Beast demon, this Level 6 Controller has 72 HP and some reality-warping
powers. It projects a &lt;strong&gt;Chaotic Field&lt;/strong&gt; as an aura (2) that allows the demon to
shift 2 squares if any enemy ends their turn inside. Its basic attack is a
plague-infected &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, and it can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Flurry of Claws&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks
a Close Burst 1, slows, and inflicts ongoing physical damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plague-demon-chaos-knight&quot;&gt;Plague Demon Chaos Knight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sapient Medium Humanoid is a Level 6 Soldier with 78 HP. It projects an
aura of &lt;strong&gt;Crimson Retribution&lt;/strong&gt; (1) that automatically deals 5 damage to anyone
inside who makes an attack that doesn’t target the chaos knight. Its &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt;
damage and knock prone on a hit, and its extruded &lt;strong&gt;Crystal Blade&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
4+) deals heavy damage and exposes to the Plague. Since it’s a recharge power,
I’m guessing the blade shatters when used as a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plague-demon-chaos-vanguard&quot;&gt;Plague Demon Chaos Vanguard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sapient Large Humanoid is a Level 9 Soldier with speed 6 and 100 HP. It’s a
powered-up version of the Knight, with nearly identical traits. Its aura is
wider and deals 10 damage instead of 5; its &lt;strong&gt;slam&lt;/strong&gt; pushes 2 squares instead of
knocking prone; and its &lt;strong&gt;Sweeping Crystal Blade&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) is a Close
Burst 3 attack instead of a single-target melee power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would you believe that I even forgot these things were here? The combination of
epic-sounding but vague lore and mid-Heroic mechanics smells very metaplotty to
me, particularly after I learned about these novels. This is the outer edge of
the plot and you’re not allowed to dig deeper, that’s what the novel heroes
do. I don’t know if they ever released a book that allowed the PCs to be more
central in eliminating the Plague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanics are functional, but pretty simplistic since the demons’ main
gimmick is being carriers for the Abyssal Plague. There’s tons of more
interesting opposition in MV:TNV. So, overall, my inclination is to give these
monsters a pass. The next entries are better, I promise!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/27/abyssal-plague-demon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/27/abyssal-plague-demon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-cover.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full name of this book is &lt;strong&gt;Monster Vault: Threats to the Nentir Vale&lt;/strong&gt;. It
was published in 2011 for Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons 4e, and as far as I know it’s the
last “proper” monster book for that edition. It would still get a few more
player-focused books over the rest of 2011 and 2012, but after that Wizards of
the Coast would begin focusing all of its efforts on 5th Edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really love Threats to the Nentir Vale, and I’ve been looking forward to
“Let’s Read”-ing it since I started writing the first Monster Manual/Monster
Vault post, in the far-off past of 2019, before the Plague Years. It’s as much a
setting book as a list of creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threats to the Nentir Vale sits at a point in the “generic to specific” scale I
hadn’t seen before. Monster Manuals are the most generic, presenting monsters
for any setting and campaign. Adventures with custom enemies are the most
specific, presenting creatures built to support a single scenario. This Monster
Vault is just a step more general than that, with monsters built to fit a
single region. You can run multiple campaigns there, and this book will make
sure the opposition you face always has that cool regional flavor. It does
include a few more general entries, but even then it tries to tie them to the
Vale in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-brief-history-of-the-nentir-vale&quot;&gt;A Brief History of the Nentir Vale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get into the monsters, we get another summary of the Vale at the start
of the book. This is a bit more detailed than the one in the DMG and it focuses
on what threats live in many of its sub regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, the Nentir Vale bears some resemblance to &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/09/03/one-post-skyrim.html&quot;&gt;Skyrim&lt;/a&gt; in
its physical characteristics. It’s a roughly rectangular region delimited by
mountain ranges and containing plains, forests, hills and marshes within its
borders. Its northernmost areas are frosty, and most of the rest is in the
colder end of temperate with well-defined seasons. Unlike Skyrim it does not
border the sea, and at 150km x 225km it’s also smaller than Skyrim’s “real”
size&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Vale is crisscrossed by a small network of rivers that join
together to form the Nentir River, which flows southwest and out of the map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the rest of 4e’s implied setting, the Vale is a layer cake of ruins from
ancient fallen empires. The most recent one was the majority human empire of
Nerath, whose settlers arrived here from the south 300 years before our
narrative present. The Nerathi settled the valley and lived in relative peace
for 200 years. Right about then, an enormous orcish army led by Clan Bloodspear
invaded from the neighboring region Stonemarch, crossing over the mountains. The
local military was unable to stand up to them, and Nerath was too busy dealing
with its own multiple crises to send reinforcements. The Bloodspear wrecked the
valley’s infrastructure and razed many of its settlements until internal
conflicts caused them to retreat back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest communities of the time managed to survive in an extremely
diminished state, and it’s been only a few years since they managed to
re-establish contact with each other. Travel between them is extremely
dangerous, and not just because of hostile fauna. The ruins of Nerath and at
least three other ancient empires still cast their shadows over the Vale. No
less than three dragons count parts of it as their territory, sharing space with
hostile sapient communities that filled the void left by the Nerathi. Foreign
conquerors are starting to set their sights here as well, including the
Bloodspear Clan.. Even within our nominal points of light, internal threats are
rising in power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroes of the Vale have their work cut out for them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-to-the-monsters&quot;&gt;Introduction to the Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a late-edition book, the monster math here is entirely in sync with the
latest advances from the Monster Manual 3 and the Monster Vault. The Nentir Vale
started out as a setting meant for Heroic-tier characters, which would be
expected to leave it behind when they hit the Paragon levels. However, this book
includes monsters ranging up to the late Paragon tier, doubling the region’s
potential “lifespan” as a campaign setting. Of course GMs could have done this
on their own already, but it’s neat to see it done in a book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also helps that the monsters are set up in such a way as to allow a &lt;em&gt;sandbox&lt;/em&gt;
campaign in the Vale, which makes this a setting very in keeping with the spirit
of old D&amp;amp;D. If your players arrive at one of the locations described here,
you’ll know who lives there and how powerful they are. Carefree players might
run into things they can’t handle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few weird new monsters here - most of them are specific groups or
individuals belonging to fairly “basic” species covered in the first Monster
Vault, but with added twists that make them unique denizens of the Nentir
Vale. Each monster gets more room for lore than was possible in the MM3 and on
the MV, and that extra space is used to detail their unique circumstances and to
tie them to specific regions within the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Skyrim is around 500km x 600km, according as I found out &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/25/wir-tnv-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/25/wir-tnv-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What's Next for Octopus Carnival</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh hey, turns out I’ve posted the last entry in my Monster Manual 3 Let’s Read!
It’s officially finished! Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not done reading monster books yet, though. Next up on my list is &lt;strong&gt;Monster
Vault: Threats to the Nentir Vale&lt;/strong&gt;, the last “proper” monster book for D&amp;amp;D 4th
Edition. I really like it, and I hope you do to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one’s going to be a bit different from the other projects. Entries for
those were posted first to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.rpg.net&quot;&gt;RPG.net forum&lt;/a&gt;, and then here after a
delay. Since I was, er, less than optimally organized in updating this blog,
some times that delay was considerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten better about updating both the forum and the blog, though, and now
that the MM3 reading is finished, the Threats one will be posted in sync between
the two starting a couple of days from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll also keep posting about other subjects, though those posts might be a
little more spaced out since I don’t have a buffer of them. I’ll write as the
muse strikes, as always.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/24/whats-next.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/24/whats-next.html</guid>
        
        <category>meta</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Yuan-ti</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a situation that’s familiar to us by now, Yuan-ti would get a revamp and a
lore infusion in the upcoming Monster Vault (and you can see how that looks like
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/27/yuan-ti.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and this entry presents stat blocks that complement the ones that
would come out in the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore section of this page lacks the nifty creation myth from the MV entry,
sticking to a more generic “perfidious infiltrators” profile for the yuan-ti. It
does add a new bit, however: the snake god Zehir doesn’t just want to see his
favorite people thrive in the world. His true goal is to become the supreme
authority in the cosmos. Zehir is convinced that the universe can only withstand
the return of the primordials if it’s led by the strong hand of a single
absolute ruler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this means we have at least two authoritarian assholes in our current
pantheon: Asmodeus and Zehir. Big Z’s goals are not widely known in the world -
only his most powerful and trusted servants are privy to this mystery. There are
other gods who are aware of this but they’re content to merely keep an eye on
the snake god as long as his machinations continue to hurt their enemies. Things
might get more heated should Zehir explicitly turn against his fellow deities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yuan-ti are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Reptile keyword. They have a
ground speed of 7, and 5/tier poison resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the MM1 and Monster Vault gave us heroic and paragon stat blocks for
snaketongue cultists and yuan-ti, the MM3 gives a bunch of high-epic stat blocks
that apparently represent those individuals who are closest to Zehir and
actively working towards his goal of complete world domination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty here for all sorts of all-yuan-ti encounters, but they also
employ various sapient humanoid cultists, and make pets or allies of any
creature who is even remotely similar to a snake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The individual stat blocks are relatively simple, making me think PCs are
supposed to face them in large numbers. It would certainly be possible to
downscale them to lower levels without changing much else about their stat
blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coil-of-zehir&quot;&gt;Coil of Zehir&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Large yuan-ti who’s almost completely snaky, its arms almost vestigial. It’s a
Level 26 Controller with 235 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coil’s basic attack is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that does light physical damage,
pulls the target 2 squares, and grabs it on a hit. The Coil can only have one
victim grabbed at a time, and it can hit them with &lt;strong&gt;Crushing Coils&lt;/strong&gt; for an
automatic 40 damage that also dazes them for a turn. As a minor action, it can
use a Close Burst 3 &lt;strong&gt;Tail Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; that does no damage and knocks targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coil wants to grab hold of someone and squeeze them to death, using tail
sweeps to keep would-be rescuers away. Dazed victims can still try to get away
(Athletics DC 38 or Acrobatics DC 39), but their other options are sharply
limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yuan-ti-abomination-berserker&quot;&gt;Yuan-ti Abomination Berserker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abominations are those ‘snakier’ yuan-ti with humanoid torsos but the lower
body of a giant snake. Another Large variant, Berserkers know how to fight and
know they shouldn’t attack other yuan-ti or cultists. That’s about it. The
others treat them nicely to avoid accidents, and then point them at whoever they
want dead. Berserkers are Level 27 Brutes with 293 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures fight with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; that do heavy physical
damage. Every so often they’ll spin and do a &lt;strong&gt;Roundhouse Slam&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+),
making a basic attack against every adjacent enemy. If you hit them while
they’re bloodied, they can make a free slam against you as a reaction. Simple
but effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yuan-ti-malison-guard&quot;&gt;Yuan-ti Malison Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-yuan-ti-guard.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malisons are the more humanoid yuan-ti, still covered in scales and with snake
heads, but otherwise humanoid. This is an elite front-line fighter who serves
Zehir proudly despite the shame of having legs. It’s a Level 27 Soldier (Leader)
with 242 HP. It knows how to fight in formation and its &lt;strong&gt;Overlapping Scales&lt;/strong&gt;
aura (1) gives a +2 bonus to AC to all allies inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guards fight with &lt;strong&gt;scimitars&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;longbows&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which deal decent
damage and inflict ongoing poison damage (save ends). The scimitar marks for a
turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures want to be in a tight formation with either other melee allies,
or with an artillery detachment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yuan-ti-abomination-spitter&quot;&gt;Yuan-ti Abomination Spitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An abomination with well-developed venom glands that produce a “blessed” venom
far deadlier than that of a mundane snake. It’s Level 27 Artillery with 186
HP. It can &lt;strong&gt;Spit Venom&lt;/strong&gt; out to Range 20, dealing immediate and ongoing poison
damage on a hit. It can also &lt;strong&gt;Spray Venom&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) on a close burst 5,
dealing poison damage and dazing (save ends). If someone closes to melee, it can
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; to deal physical damage and inflict ongoing poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an attack hits the spitter, it can flare its &lt;strong&gt;Cobra Hood&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to
gain +4 to AC for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yuan-ti-malison-blessed&quot;&gt;Yuan-ti Malison Blessed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An epic priest of Zehir, receiving blessings directly from the deity. It’s a
Level 28 Controller (Leader) with 250 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the blessed’s controllery effects are passive and always on. It projects
an aura (3) of &lt;strong&gt;Zehir’s Favor&lt;/strong&gt; that allows allies inside to reroll failed
recharge rolls. It also projects an aura (5) of &lt;strong&gt;Zehir’s Agony&lt;/strong&gt; that deals 15
poison damage to any enemy starting their turn inside. While bloodied, the
blessed can &lt;strong&gt;Slither Away&lt;/strong&gt;, gaining a +2 bonus to speed and a +5 to all
defenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blessed’s active actions are few, but powerful. It fights with a
&lt;strong&gt;scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; whose strikes damage, strip poison resistance, and inflict a -2
penalty to saves vs. poison effects (save ends both). And yes, about 90% of all
attacks described in this MM3 entry are poison effects. Including this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blessed can also use &lt;strong&gt;Zehir’s Command&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action, allowing two
allies within 5 squares to either make a basic attack or shift their speed as a
free action. If an enemy within 5 squares shifts, the blessed can use &lt;strong&gt;Shifting
Feet&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to slide them 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these creatures are technically regulars, they have the action efficiency
you’d expect from an elite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yuan-ti-malison-assassin&quot;&gt;Yuan-ti Malison Assassin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-yuan-ti-assassin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one has a sword and it very much wants to stab you with it so you can
sample the many substances it put on the blade. It’s sent after people who anger
Zehir directly. It’s a Level 28 Lurker with 194 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assassin’s basic &lt;strong&gt;Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; deals very light damage and blinds for a turn
on a hit. A victim who cannot see the assassin for any reason is subject to a
&lt;strong&gt;Death Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that deals standard physical damage, inflicts ongoing 15 poison
damage, and imposes a -2 penalty to saves (save ends both). After the first
failed save, the damage worsens by 5 and the save penalty by 1. Someone also
targetted by the Blessed could be looking at a total -5 save penalty here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a ranged or melee attack hits the assassin it can use &lt;strong&gt;Shield of Zehir&lt;/strong&gt; to
make sure a blind victim adjacent to it also suffers the attack’s damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yuan-ti-malison-stalker&quot;&gt;Yuan-ti Malison Stalker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relentless pursuer sent after victims who steal from Zehir’s temples or commit
other crimes against the yuan-ti people. They’re Level 28 Skirmishers wtih 254
HP. They’re more or less equivalen to PC avengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalkers use &lt;strong&gt;greataxes&lt;/strong&gt; and have 5e advantage on their attacks if the target
is the only creature adjacent to them. They can also teleport 3 squares as a
minor action, which means they can move up to 13 squares a turn without spending
their standard action, and they can charge someone from 20 squares away. It’s
impossible to outrun a stalker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;molt-of-zehir&quot;&gt;Molt of Zehir&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally a person-shaped bag of snakes, made from the cast-off skin of a
yuan-ti. This apparently &lt;em&gt;just happens&lt;/em&gt; when an epic yuan-ti molts, it’s not a
conscious ritual or anything. The snakes just appear from somewhere and crawl
inside the skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molts are Level 26 Minion Skirmishers. They have a basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; attack and
when they die the dispersing &lt;strong&gt;Horde of Snakes&lt;/strong&gt; acts as a Close Burst 1 attack
that damages and inflicts ongoing poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not overly fond of classic yuan-ti lore these days, because it has too
strong a whiff of “yellow peril” about it. I’d probably come up with something
different for them if I had to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, these creatures are kind of interesting, though each one is very
simple. Mechanically, I think you can knock 10 or even 20 levels off them if you
don’t want your PCs to wait until the campaign’s endgame to fight the snek
people.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/23/yuan-ti.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/23/yuan-ti.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shadowrun: Goncharov</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently read about a fun Tumblr meme. It’s about Goncharov, a 1973 Martin
Scorcese movie that never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It began when someone posted a picture of these bootleg boots they bought
somewhere. The brand label had one of those word salads copied from somewhere
and edited by someone not too familiar with the target language. In this case,
it was copied from a poster for Gomorrah, a real movie. And it read “Martin
Scorcese presents Goncharov”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tumblr &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tumblr.com/hussyknee/701454778540146688/im-so-confused-rn-can-you-explain-the-goncharov&quot;&gt;kinda ran with it&lt;/a&gt;, so now you have a lot of people making things up about
the movie and fabricating screenshots, posters, bits of soundtrack, talking
about all of this as if it was a real cinematic masterpiece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone in a Discord server I frequent suggested Goncharov should become a
standard name for someone who doesn’t exist, the opposite of John Doe. And this
got me thinking about Shadowrun again. Here are two uses for the name Goncharov
in a Shadowrun-like setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mundane&quot;&gt;The Mundane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Shadowrun, “Mr. Johnson” is shadowrunner slang for a person who hires
shadowrunners. The stereotypical Mr. Johnson is a shady fuck in a suit who talks
in vague businesslike terms&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but it can be anyone who is willing to be the
“client” for a runner group. That’s an established part of the game already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how about we say Goncharov is the “reverse” term? Goncharov is Johnson code
for shadowrunners! Sure “shadowrunners” is canon and also works well, but you
can’t really write “shadowrunner payoff” in your official corporate ledger, can
you? So instead you write “payment to Goncharov for services rendered”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just like no self-respecting mysterious client calls themselves Mr. Johnson,
no self-respecting runner calls themselves Goncharov. Someone who takes that as
their handle or even as an alias is telling the whole world they’re a clueless
poser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little bit of culture works well in the Shadowrun setting itself, and on
any other setting that has stylish urban mercenaries as characters, including a
lot of GURPS Action or GURPS Cyberpunk campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numinous&quot;&gt;The Numinous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go a bit further, shall we? Here’s a mystical explanation that’s a bit
more mystical than even Shadowrun’s default setting allows for&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and is a bit
closer to Exalted’s take on spirits and magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goncharov is the Small God of Shadowrunners. He started out as an abstraction,
as above, but at some point became a real part of shadowrunning culture. Either
an existing spirit took on the mantle, or folk belief made him real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real&lt;/em&gt; runners, those who are more than amoral assholes doing horrible things
for money, they have an understanding with Goncharov. They never forget the
corps and the big syndicates are the enemy even when circumstances force them to
work for these groups. They never sell out. They know who their community and
friends are, and they look out for them. And after every successful job, they
give Goncharov his cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goncharov looks like a fit but somewhat scuffed up man in a nice but somewhat
scuffed up suit. The details vary, but he never looks overly fancy or
arrogant. In other words, he might look like John Wick after a fight or three,
but never like the Continental Hotel guy - that’s the god of Mr. Johnsons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magicians can take Goncharov as a mentor spirit. He provides bonuses to combat
spells and Spirits of Man, whatever form those bonuses take in your edition of
choice. Non-magicians can also have “an understanding” with him for a slightly
cheaper price. This gives them access to the Goncharov’s Cut rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goncharovs-cut&quot;&gt;Goncharov’s Cut&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have an understanding with the god of Shadowrunners, and keep to his
code, can gain extra Karma for giving him his cut. This includes magicians who
take him as a mentor spirit, or any character who spends points to buy a
slightly cheaper Edge representing the covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the Karma for Cash rule in your game, such characters gain an
extra point of Karma when using the rule, if they would already gain at least
one point normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s not a general campaign rule, such characters still gain access to it,
becoming able to exchange money for a single point of Karma after every run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases the money goes to support and improve the runner’s community, or
to help out fellow shadowrunners in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-gurps&quot;&gt;In GURPS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a GURPS Action or Cyberpunk campaign with supernatural elements, The
Understanding is a -10-point Code of Honor, since it’s informal but applies to
interactions with people who are not your peers. Give Goncharov his cut and use
it to support your community and fellow runners; hunt down and punish any who
betray them&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; never sell out; even if you need to do a job for a corp or a
crime syndicate, never forget they’re the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code can work as a “pact” limitation for supernatural or cinematic traits
related to being stealthy, discreet, or good at combat (yes, even Gunslinger or
a talent like Smooth Operator). It would provide a 10% discount on their price,
as normal, and would make these abilities unavailable until atonement if the PC
breaks the attached code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monetary value of Goncharov’s cut is 10% of any earnings from
“shadowrun”-like missions. GMs and players who don’t want to bother with
accounting can just remove it from the PC when it’s given, and assume it gets
spent properly. In games where more detailed tracking is important, the PC
doesn’t need to spend the money immediately, just set it aside for use when
necessary. Using it for personal benefit after it’s been set aside is a
violation of the Code, though. If the protected community has its own
organization stats, the player might want to consider transferring this money
from the PC to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the code might also lead to acquiring traits such as positive
reputation among your community or fellow runners, or Enemies in the form of
traitorous villains and amoral mercenaries who think you’re weak for having a
conscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atonement from breaking the code usually takes the form of a dangerous mission
to aid an oppressed community or fellow runner in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And who betrays you at the end. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though I understand it was kinda moving in this direction in its latest
editions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, you are totally following the code if you track Clockwork down and
shoot him in the head after telling him “Goncharov says hi”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/22/goncharov.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/22/goncharov.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Yeti</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-yeti.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yetis are inspired by real world folklore and I’m sure they showed up in a
previous edition of D&amp;amp;D before. This seems to be their 4e debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D yeti are borderline-sapient predators adapted to live in permafrost covered
mountains. While they usually feed on other mountain-dwelling animals, they’re
more than powerful and ferocious enough to attack people, and so everyone who
lives near their habitat knows they exist. Learning how to recognize signs of
yeti presence and avoid the creatures is probably a standard part of mountain
survival training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yetis have a well-developed sense of smell and can track prey across great
distances. They hate the smell of rotting flesh, however, so leaving decomposed
animal carcasses around an area can serve to keep them away. Herders also know
to pay attention to their animals: if they grow too agitated for no apparent
reason, it might be because they’ve sensed an approaching yeti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A yeti relies on its powerful muscles, sharp claws, and magic-enhanced howls to
kill its prey. They don’t really have any sort of technology or a complex
society, but they live in bands and work very well together. They’re smart
enough to avoid large, well-armed expeditions, but they’ll be on top of any
isolated stragglers before you can say “Look out, a yeti!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeti are Medium Natural Beasts with Speed 6, Ice Walk, Resist 5 Cold and
Low-Light Vision. Their signature encounter power is their &lt;strong&gt;Fearsome Howl&lt;/strong&gt;, a
Close Blast 4 vs. Will that deals psychic damage and pushes 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the entries here have &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; as their basic attacks. These don’t have
any riders and are always underpowered for their level, which means they’ll use
their other attacks as much as possible. Their other attacks also tend to have
low-ish damage, but have interesting riders. They have an Int between 9 and 11
while still counting as Beasts, which is why I said “borderline sapient” above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeti encounters will most often be against an all-yeti group, as they don’t
really ally with anyone or keep pets. For variety, you can add other
opportunistic predators, or maybe a wild cold elemental or two. Also, these
encounters are all pretty much guaranteed to take place in treacherous frozen
mountain paths full of ice-based difficult terrain and hazards like tall cliffs
and snow-covered sinkholes. Every yeti has at least one forced-movement power
available to it (Fearsome Howl), so they’re likely to be more dangerous than
their stats alone indicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yeti-hunter&quot;&gt;Yeti Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your typical roaming yeti, whose howls can be heard from miles away but don’t
really give away their position because of the way sound echoes in the
mountains. It’s a level 3 Soldier with 49 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hunter’s claw attack will probably only feature as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Twin Claw
Grab&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets it make two attacks and grab the target if both hit. It
doesn’t have any special abilities to exploit a grab, but the basic rules still
apply. Its marking abilities are a ranged &lt;strong&gt;How of Challenge&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
psychic damage and marks for a turn, and a close burst &lt;strong&gt;Call for Blood&lt;/strong&gt; that
deals more psychic damage and marks everyone it hits (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yeti-howler&quot;&gt;Yeti Howler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A yeti whose magic howls are more powerful than usual. Some stories say they’re
the embodiment of angry ghosts, howling against the injustice of their premature
deaths. They’re Level 4 Controllers with 58 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The howler’s &lt;strong&gt;Chilling Wail&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (3) that deals 5 psychic damage
and imposes a -2 defense penalty for a turn against any enemy who ends their
turn inside. This actually brings its melee damage up to par, with a little
extra aimed at the other PCs inside the aura. If you try to stay away from it,
the howler will bombard you with &lt;strong&gt;Hurled Boulders&lt;/strong&gt; that work like ranged area
attacks dealing physical damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to their Fearsome Howl, howlers can also emit a &lt;strong&gt;Piercing Shriek&lt;/strong&gt;
once per encounter. This ranged attack deals thunder damage, and if the target
ends their next turn within 5 squares of the yeti they take another 5 thunder
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yeti-rampager&quot;&gt;Yeti Rampager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is angrier than usual, with a more mobile fighting style. It’s a Level
5 Skirmisher with 67 HP. They have a Speed of 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rampagers love to charge, so they’ll try to make space for those charges as
often as possible. They’ll pick a target and use their &lt;strong&gt;Battle Howl&lt;/strong&gt; against
it, a ranged attack that deals psychic damage and lets them charge as a free
action on a hit. They can also just charge normally instead, if they’re not
confident of hitting the target with the howl. In either case their &lt;strong&gt;Furious
Charger&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them +5 bonus damage on charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they’re surrounded by melee PCs, howlers can use Furious Howl or &lt;strong&gt;Trample&lt;/strong&gt;
to get away. That last ability lets them shift their speed and make a melee
attack that damages and knocks prone on a hit against any enemies whose spaces
they move through during the shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeti are interesting mechanically, but they require a bit more thought on the
part of the GM to ensure they’re dealing level appropriate damage. None of them
are the type to stand still and spam basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, I don’t see much wrong with their lore. They’re described as
dangerous predators, and the word “savage” doesn’t appear even once in this
entry. The biggest criticism I can make is that yetis are so iconic outside D&amp;amp;D
that facing one feels kinda “mundane” when compared to some of the other
monsters available. That’s just a personal taste thing, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wouldn’t be hard to use these stat blocks for a sapient and friendlier yeti
if that’s how you want them to be in your campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/21/yeti.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/21/yeti.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Xivort</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-xivort.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure xivorts appeared in a previous edition, but here they get some new
4e-specific lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xivorts are a tragic threat. They are descended from gnomes enslaved by
fomorians and subjected to all sorts of tortures and experiments. Their long
captivity in the Feydark caused them to mutate into their present cave-adapted
state, which was further exacerbated when most of them were freed from their
captors by a cabal of night hags and brought to the Shadowfell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hags were only interested in liberating the xivorts as a way to deal a blow
to their fomorian masters, so they just left the former gnomes to their own
devices in the Shadowfell. These newly freed xivorts had only known torment and
suffering all their lives, so they set about dealing that to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual I’m not fond of painting a whole sapient species with such a broad
negative brush, so I want to say xivorts are just people and you can find whole
communities of non-evil individuals out there. The ones you end up fighting
might still fit the description here, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For good or ill, xivorts tend to associate with dark ones and gnomes. They have
a particular distrust of larger people, an echo of the hatred they hold for
fomorians. Goliaths and half-orcs tend to be priority targets in combat
encounters because of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xivorts are Small Fey Humanoids with a Speed of 5 and Darkvison. Their signature
ability is &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Step&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers whenever an adjacent enemy hits
them. It allows the xivort to teleport 2 squares to another space adjacent to
the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the entries here are level 1 or 2, which makes me think they’re meant to
be novel kobold and goblin replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xivort-slasher&quot;&gt;Xivort Slasher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a “slasher” in the horror movie sense. It fights because it likes to
inflict pain. As a Level 1 Skirmisher with 26 HP, it’s not a big threat to a
trained adventurer, but from the point of view of a non-combatant it could look
like an unstoppable killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slasher fights with a &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and throws &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; at
range. Besides the standard Shadow Step it has &lt;strong&gt;Cunning Step&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it
to shift 1 square when an enemy adjacent to it is hit by an attack. This doesn’t
have to be one of the slasher’s own attacks, it can be anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If several slashers gang up on a single enemy, that enemy will soon find
themselves surrounded by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xivort-darter&quot;&gt;Xivort Darter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one fights using concealable thrown darts, a tradition dating back to the
xivort’s time as Fomorian captives. It’s Level 1 Artillery with 22 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the xivort’s &lt;strong&gt;Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; and its &lt;strong&gt;Darts&lt;/strong&gt; are a bit weak, but it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Dart Volley&lt;/strong&gt; to make two ranged attacks in the same action. Once per
encounter it can throw its special &lt;strong&gt;Dream Venom Dart&lt;/strong&gt;, which does the same
damage as a basic one and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the darter’s ranged attacks target &lt;em&gt;Reflex&lt;/em&gt;, not AC, making it
particularly effective against heavily armored defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of the usual Shadow Step, the darter has &lt;strong&gt;Darter’s Step&lt;/strong&gt;, which
works the same but doesn’t restrict its teleport destination. It’s meant to let
them get away from melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xivort-net-caster&quot;&gt;Xivort Net Caster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is trained to bring larger foes down so they’re easier to kill. It’s a
Level 1 Controller with 26 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The net caster can use a non-damaging &lt;strong&gt;net&lt;/strong&gt; as a ranged area attack to
restrain everyone it hits (save ends). If someone escapes the net it can throw a
pair of non-damaging &lt;strong&gt;bolas&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to knock them prone and prevent
them from getting up for a turn. Then it moves in with its &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt;,
which deals bonus damage against prone, immobilized, restrained or sloweed
enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the status effects the net caster inflict make the target grant combat
advantage, so they go really well with monsters that can exploit that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xivort-shadow-caller&quot;&gt;Xivort Shadow Caller&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spellcaster using the ‘mysteeeerious’ Shadow source, who apparently traded
part of their soul to the Shadowfell itself in exchange for power. It’s Level 2
Artillery with the Leader keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadow callers user &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, but like most artillery they want to
stay further away and use their ranged spells. &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Phantoms&lt;/strong&gt; is their
basic ranged attack, dealing psychic damage and making the target grant combat
advantage for a turn. This has an extra +1 to hit for every creature adjacent to
the target, be it ally or enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deathmark Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) deals necrotic damage and lets an ally of the
caster make a free melee basic attack against the target. And &lt;strong&gt;Shadow
Strangler&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a “pseudo-summon” that immobilizes and inflicts
ongoing 5 necrotic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as low-level enemies go, they’re… okay I guess? Fighting these guys
instead of kobolds is a nice change of pace, but I’ll confess I lose a bit of
enthusiasm for them when I realize they’re another attempt to hype up the Shadow
power source.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/20/xivort.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/20/xivort.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Wilden</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-wilden.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe wilden are new to 4e, first appearing in the Player’s Handbook 3 as an
option for PCs. This is their corresponding Monster Manual entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden are the middle world’s immune response to the Far Realm. They appeared
very recently, emerging from the Feywild’s deepest and most untouched natural
environments. Theoretically, that’s a reaction to an upsurge in Far Realm
activity in the world, and it’s worrying that the signs of that haven’t been
noticed by anyone else yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not even the wilden themselves have a clear idea of what caused them to
emerge. The setting’s youngest sapient people by far, they have an instinctual
drive to protect nature and oppose aberrant creatures, but they have yet to form
a unified culture and traditions of their own. Most individuals turn to other
creatures around them for examples. For many, those come from more established
fey peoples like elves, eladrin, and gnomes. Others turn to the beasts of the
wild, or to more zealous spirits like dryads and treants, and end up much
fiercer and much less sociable. Some even fall in with evil fey like fomorians,
ending up as villainous as them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden are Medium Fey Humanoids with a speed of 6 and low-light vision. As PCs,
their gimmick is that they may assume one of three &lt;em&gt;aspects&lt;/em&gt; after an extended
rest, each of which changes their appearance a bit and gives them a different
racial power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the three stat blocks in this entry belongs to a single aspect and
carries that aspect’s related power, in a version stronger than what’s available
to PCs. They’re Unaligned and may represent allies, neutrals, or hostiles as
your story requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re all in the low-heroic range, which means you can find NPC wilden in the
same areas where you’d find NPC elves and gnomes. They often use wolves, spiders
and drakes as pets, and there are many such creatures that would be
level-appropriate for a wilden encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wilden-destroyer&quot;&gt;Wilden Destroyer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wildens who adopt the aspect of the Destroyer are usually the designated
warriors of their communities. They wield large carved wooden clubs, and every
time they survive a battle they add a new carving to their weapons to celebrate
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Destroyers are Level 2 Soldiers with 39 HP. Their carved &lt;strong&gt;greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt; damage
and mark for a turn on a hit, and they can throw &lt;strong&gt;handaxes&lt;/strong&gt; as basic ranged
attacks. If an enemy marked by the destroyer tries to ignore the mark, the
destroyer gains a +4 bonus to attack and damage that enemy during their next
turn. If a bloodied enemy attacks the destroyer or one of the destroyer’s
adjacent allies, it can use the &lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the Destroyer&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power to
attack that enemy as a reaction. If this hits, the enemy becomes stunned for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC Wildens in Destroyer aspect can use that power too, though for them it dazes
instead of stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wilden-hunter&quot;&gt;Wilden Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden who adopt the Hunter aspect fulfill that role in their community, and
also make for excellent scouts. They are Level 2 Lurkers with 33 HP. They fight
with &lt;strong&gt;shortswords&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;longbows&lt;/strong&gt; that just make basic attacks. All their
interesting stuff is in their passive traits and their racial power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The passives are familiar to us by now: &lt;strong&gt;Camouflage&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make
Stealth checks with only partial cover and concealment; &lt;strong&gt;Sniper&lt;/strong&gt; lets them
stay hidden when they miss with a ranged attack from hiding; and &lt;strong&gt;Hidden Shot&lt;/strong&gt;
lets them deal extra damage when they attack from hiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their encounter power is &lt;strong&gt;Pursuit of the Hunter&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when an enemy
ends their movement within 2 squares of the hunter. The hunter can react by
shifting 3 squares, and for their next turn they will deal 5 extra damage with
their attacks against that enemy, and will also ignore partial cover and
concealment against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC Wilden in the Hunter aspect get a similar Pursuit power, except it deals 1d6
extra damage instead of the fixed 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wilden-ancient&quot;&gt;Wilden Ancient&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilden who adopt the aspect of the Ancients are their community’s shamans and
guides. They’re called “Ancients” because their magic lets them cast their minds
to the collective history of the Feywild and the world. When they go into these
trances, their whole community stops to take care of them and await their
awakening, which might bring important insights or prophecies with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ancient depicted here is Level 4 Artillery with 45 HP and the Leader
tag. It’s a primal spellcaster who fights with a &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; and with several
combat spells. Their spear attacks are very weak but allow an ally adjacent to
the target to make a free melee basic attack at +4 to hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their combat spells have varied effects: &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Vine&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic ranged
attack that deals physical damage and pulls 2 squares; &lt;strong&gt;Rumbling Earth&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) is a ranged area attack that damages and immobilizes (save ends);
and &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a ranged area attack that does heavy
lightning damage, half on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per round as a minor action they can impart the &lt;strong&gt;Wisdom of the Ancients&lt;/strong&gt;,
granting them a +2 attack bonus for their next turn. And then they hit an enemy
with an area attack, they can use their &lt;strong&gt;Voyage of the Ancients&lt;/strong&gt; encounter
power to teleport 3 squares and make one of the enemies they just hit grant
combat advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their many controllery effects, it makes sense for Ancients to be
artillery. They want to stay safe behind a wall of bodyguards and bombard their
enemies, not mix it up in melee like a controller might want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gotta say it feels a bit odd to find a low-heroic entry right after the
high-epic Weavers, but that’s just a product of the book being in alphabetic
order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wildens are serviceable enough as low-heroic enemies, about in line with what I
expect from an entry dedicated to a creature that’s also a PC option.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/18/wilden.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/18/wilden.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
