<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 13:26:12 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 13:26:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Vampiric Mist</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-twig-blight.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vampiric Mists originally appeared back in AD&amp;amp;D 1e, in Dungeon Magazine 17. This
is their 4e debut, with lore appropriate to the Nentir Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancient legends tell that the Witchlight Fens mark the spot where a demon lord
was slain at the dawn of time - the region became a swamp when its corpse fell
there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In slightly-less-ancient times, a lich whose name has been lost to history
established a lair in the Fens with the goal of finding the remains of this
demon lord and reanimating them as super-powerful undead creature. Accompanying
the lich was a coven of nine vampire lords, its loyal retainers. These vampires
were tasked with hiding and guarding the lich’s soul vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time after that, one of the lich’s enemies, a powerful hag, came to the
fens in search of its soul vessel. She had created a custom ritual to destroy
the vampires, and she enacted it there, but it didn’t have the desired
effect. Her magic succeeded at destroying the bodies of the vampires, but their
essence remained and coalesced to form a new, more dangerous
creature. The hag left without finding the artifact, which remains in the Fens
protected by its gaseous guardian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a deserted clearing in the Fens that contains a single slab of stone in
its middle. That is the territory of the monster known as the Crimson Deathmist,
who endlessly roams it looking for new victims. It prefers the blood of elves
and other fey, but it will kill anyone it can reach. It has been a very long
time since anyone who encountered it has lived to tell the tale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stone slab conceals the entrance to a catacomb complex where the lich’s soul
vessel is hidden. The fate of the lich itself is unknown. Maybe it’s still in
the Fens somewhere, or maybe something peculiar happened to it to take it out of
the picture without destroying its vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all vampiric mists have such an epic origin. A more common and less powerful
variety appears when a vampire who is forced into mist form has its resting
place destroyed before it can get there. To avoid permanent destruction, the
vampire will sometimes shed its physical form by an act of will, becoming a
vampiric mist. This causes it to lost most of its intellect and memories, and to
become a creature of hunger and instinct. They’re still smart enough to team up
with other evil or predatory swamp dwellers like hags, vine horrors, and outcast
lizardfolk. There’s always the danger the mist will turn on these allies if they
have blood and victims become scarce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get several varieties of vampiric mist here, which I guess come from
different types of vampire, or vampires who met different ends. One of those is
the late-Paragon Crimson Deathmist, but others hover hungrily around the late
Heroic and early Paragon tiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of them have Darkvision, immunity to disease, 10 Resistance to necrotic and
poison damage, and 5 vulnerability to radiant damage. Their ground speed is 0,
but their flight speed is a 5 with an altitude limit of 2. That means they never
land, but also can’t fly beyond melee reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these creatures have the &lt;strong&gt;Mist Form&lt;/strong&gt; trait, which lets them move
through openings of any size and occupy the same space as other creatures. They
also count as &lt;strong&gt;Insubstantial&lt;/strong&gt;, taking half damage from everything but fire,
force, or radiant damage. Fire or radiant damage additionally makes them lose
this trait for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesser mists have an aura (1) named &lt;strong&gt;Siphoning Presence&lt;/strong&gt; that prevent enemies
inside from spending healing surges, and deal 5/tier necrotic damage to enemies
who end their turns inside. When the aura deals damage, the mist recovers 5
HP. Being inside the mist does count as being inside its aura. They are Medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vampiric-mist&quot;&gt;Vampiric Mist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our basic model is a Level 9 Skirmisher with 85 HP and all the standard traits
listed above. It can shift its speed as a move action using the &lt;strong&gt;Shifting
Mists&lt;/strong&gt; ability, which ensures it will never move normally. Its basic attack is
a contact &lt;strong&gt;Life Drain&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude, deals necrotic damage, and
makes the target vulnerable to necrotic damage for a turn. It can also spread a
&lt;strong&gt;Wave of Lethargy&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that attacks a Close Burst 2, deals a bit of
psychic and necrotic damage, and slows for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thing is almost impossible to pin down. With multiple mists in the same
encounter, some can “prime” targets by hitting them with Life Drain to make them
take increased damage from a Wave of Lethargy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vampiric-mist-corruptor&quot;&gt;Vampiric Mist Corruptor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess this is what you get from a more traditional D&amp;amp;D vampire who was capable
of using a dominating gaze and really leaned on this ability. Corruptors are
Level 11 Controllers with 100 HP and all standard traits described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the fight starts they’ll try to hit someone with their &lt;strong&gt;Corrupting
Gaze&lt;/strong&gt;, which dominates (save ends) on a hit and deals necrotic and psychic
damage as an aftereffect. This recharges whenever the creature doesn’t have a
dominated victim!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dominating a PC, it will attack the others with its &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals
necrotic damage and slides 2 squares on a hit. Perfect for dragging other PCs
closer to the dominated one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the mist is first bloodied, it will let loose a &lt;strong&gt;Deathly Howl&lt;/strong&gt; that hits
a Close Burst 5, pushes 3 squares on a hit and forbids targets from spending
healing surges (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t add more than one or two of these to an encounter group. It’s no fun for
anyone if the whole party ends up dominated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chillborn-vampiric-mist&quot;&gt;Chillborn Vampiric Mist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cold-themed mist. It’s a Level 9 Soldier with 85 HP and all standard
traits described above. All of its attacks do cold and necrotic damage. There’s
a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that slows for a turn and the &lt;strong&gt;Grasp of the Cold Grave&lt;/strong&gt; that
immobilizes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mists lack marking capabilities, but their attacks are still very good at
making movement difficult for PCs. It could easily be reskinned into some other
frost-themed ghost without any changes to its stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crimson-deathmist&quot;&gt;Crimson Deathmist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legendary Crimson Deathmist is a Huge entity, and a Level 19 Elite Soldier
with 328 HP. It’s faster with a flight speed of 6 and an altitude limit of 3. It
is however slightly more vulnerable to radiant damage (10 instead of 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This monster has all the standard traits, but its Siphoning Presence is renamed
to &lt;strong&gt;Impending Doom&lt;/strong&gt; and upgraded. I has a radius of 2 instead of 1, and
restores 10 HP to the mist instead of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deathmist can pull enemies 4 squares closer with its &lt;strong&gt;Hypnotic Lure&lt;/strong&gt;
(at-will, minor action), and then &lt;strong&gt;Demand Obedience&lt;/strong&gt; from them. This is a
melee attack that can target two creatures at the same time. It deals psychic
and necrotic damage, with an additional 10 damage the next turn if the targets
attack anyone other than the Deathmist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Deathly Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic and poison damage
and also slows for a turn. It can also release a &lt;strong&gt;Terror Wave&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
psychic damage in a Close Burst 2 and immobilizes for a turn. That last one
recharges when it’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mists’ mechanics are cool, but what really drew my attention was the story
about the lich. A lich whose name is unknown, who lived in ancestral times, who
was interested in undead demon lords, and who is no longer around? That could be
Vecna, whose deeds in this place let him ascend. And instead of a typical soul
vessel you’d find his Eye at the bottom of this catacomb dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that doesn’t appeal, you’ll notice that any party capable of defeating the
Crimson Deathmist guarding the entrance is at about the right level to tackle
the Tomb of Horrors… You’d need to change that clearing a bit to include the
three entrances, but otherwise it’s as good a place to put it as any.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/04/vampiric-mist.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/04/vampiric-mist.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Twig Blight</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-twig-blight.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D Third Edition made many attempts to create new monsters that would grow
popular enough to become iconic, and I think these little critters were one of
their greatest successes even though they weren’t an intentional attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They first appeared as custom opposition in The Sunless Citadel, the very first
official module for Third Edition. They had a very specific origin tied to the
overall story arc of that campaign. That origin is mentioned in version, but we
also see some lore that talks about them in the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig blights look like large woody shrubs or small trees with interlocking
branches. They can change shape somewhat to blend in with the surrounding
vegetation, and they can also uproot and twist themselves into roughly humanoid
shapes in order to hunt or migrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blights need fresh blood to reproduce and grow, using their roots to absorb it
from the soil or directly from corpses. New seedlings sprout from their root
systems, as many as a dozen at a time. They’re very fragile early on, but mature
quickly and after a few days are big enough to start ambushing small creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first blights originated from the Gulthias Tree, which grew from the stake
used to slay ancient vampire who went by that name. Some people speculate that
repeating the process to create a similar tree could create new varieties of
twig blight, though of course few are unbalanced or evil enough to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Vale-specific story is about a lonely pig farmer named Fellis, who was the
first to discover these creatures in the Vale. A strange new bush appeared
overnight in his slaughter shed, and soon it began sprouting seedlings. Fellis
loved the little scamps, giving them names and playing them tunes on his
flute. His neighbors were very worried about all of this weirdness, but still
regularly went there to trade for pig meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that winter, however, severe snow storms tore through the region and made
regular travel impossible until the thaw. When Fellis’ neighbors managed to get
to his farm again, they saw that the man, his family, his pigs, and even the cat
had all been killed. All that was left was a number of pulsating bushes
sprouting from their corpses. Several nearby villages banded together to burn
out the infestation, but a few individuals managed to escape into the
surrounding woods. So now we can add “twig blight infestation” to the list of
everyday disasters that can fall upon the people of the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig blights can survive from normal soil nutrients and sunlight like mundane
plants, but they vastly prefer to have access to a blood supply. Their numbers
increase rapidly when they can find a big source like a slaughterhouse or
battlefield, though even a single corpse is enough to let their reproduction
cycle continue. When their current blood supply runs dry, they’ll uproot
themselves to look for more. If can’t find a new victim or supply quickly,
they’ll take root again and wait in ambush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig blights can even be found in dungeons, ruins, caves, and other places never
touched by the sun. Without access to light, they become even more bloodthirsty
than usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some powerful creatures try to make use of twig blights as unguided boundary
guardians by seeding them along that boundary. However, the creatures are fickle
and as likely to follow the wind to nearby settlements as they are to stay in
place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig Blights are monsters. They have some intelligence and can even speak Elven,
but they only use that to set up smarter ambushes. They only see other
creatures, sapient or not, as food sources, and only interact with them through
violence. You might be able to keep them contained for a while if you supply
them with enough blood, like Fellis did, but their reproductive cycle will
ensure their population quickly outstrips the supply, at which point they’ll
begin hunting for live prey (which means &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twig Blights are Small Fey Humanoids with the Plant tag. They have ground and
climb Speeds of 5 with Forest Walk, and Darkvision. They have Resist Poison 5
and the non-minions have Vulnerable to Fire 5. Their signature trait is
&lt;strong&gt;Rooted&lt;/strong&gt;, which reduces forced movement from pulls, pushes, or slides by 3
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like their original 3e incarnation, they’re early Heroic opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight-seedling&quot;&gt;Twig Blight Seedling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A seedling who just grew big enough to hunt. It’s a Level 1 Minion
Skirmisher. Their &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack lets them shift 2 squares before making the
roll, deals poison damage, and has a small damage bonus when the target is
granting them combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their tactics are simple: surround and kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight&quot;&gt;Twig Blight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic model is a Level 2 Lurker with 28 HP. It can turn &lt;strong&gt;invisible&lt;/strong&gt; for
a turn with a standard action, and surprise opponents with &lt;strong&gt;Blighted Claw&lt;/strong&gt;
attacks that do heavy poison damage and weaken (save ends). Even a miss still
does half damage and weakens for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the blight can’t become invisible, it can still attack with basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;
attacks that do a typical amount of poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight-swampvine&quot;&gt;Twig Blight Swampvine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new variant! It could be that classic blights adapted themselves to a
swampy environment… or it could be that someone out there did prove the
stake-tree theorem. They’re particularly common in the Witchlight Fens along the
Nentir River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swampvines are Level 3 Soldiers with 42 HP. They’ll use their minor actions to
pull targets close using a &lt;strong&gt;Swamp Vine&lt;/strong&gt;, which also grabs them (escape DC
13). If a grabbed target attacks someone other than the swampvine, they take an
automatic 5 poison damage. They can also make basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks that do
poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twig-blight-swarm&quot;&gt;Twig Blight Swarm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big bunch of classic twig blights that decided to stop being subtle. It’s a
Large Swarm made up of Small creatures, and a Level 5 Brute with 74 HP. It’s
Swarm Attack aura deals 3 damage to those inside, and while it looses its
specific vulnerability to fire it’s still vulnerable to close and area attacks
like any other swarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its version of &lt;strong&gt;Rooted&lt;/strong&gt; makes it completely immune to being pushed, pulled, or
slid, and its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Claws&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack deals poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are lots of people who will be happy to have official 4e stats
for Twig Blights. Their explicitly unnatural origin and their monstrous
disposition tends to make them better “guilt-free” low-level opponents than your
usual selection of humanoids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incarnation of them is also quite tricky for low-level PCs to handle, since
a lot of their early powers rely on forced movement for their more interesting
effects.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/02/twig-blight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/02/twig-blight.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Treants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treants appear in the MM1 in a generic form. Here we see not one but two
specific treant factions present in the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the hillfolk, before the Tigerclaw, before even the elves, the Nentir
Vale was covered by a single, vast forest. And in this forest, the treants
ruled. They feared no one, not even the mighty dragons, for the entire region
was under the protection of Malorunth the Eternal Ash, a gigantic tree who as
also a powerful archfey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One spring evening, however, Malorunth died under mysterious circumstances. The
once vigorous tree was now entirely petrified, leaves falling from its brittle
branches in droves. With Malorunth dead, its blessing left the Vale, and the
dragons who coveted it were quick to capitalize on the opportunity, arriving in
large numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle that followed between treant and dragon was called the War of Endless
Branches, and it’s because of this war that the Nentir Vale looks like it does
today. Draconic magic and breath weapons cut a swathe of devastation across the
center of the region that created the large open area there, and separated
Winterbole Forest to the north from Harken Forest to the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragons would go on to win the war and move into the “cleared” area. They
were powerful, but what really brought them victory was the growing distrust and
suspicion among the treants themselves, which caused them to stop working
together and turn on each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, the deciduous treants began to think their coniferous relatives had
something to do with the death of Malorunth, and this suspicion festered enough
that they began voicing it aloud for everyone to hear. Arguments turned to
fights, and soon the treants were more concerned with their brand new civil war
than with keeping the dragons out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This civil war caused the conifers to migrate north to Winterbole forest, where
they would eventually begin venerating the archfey of winter known as the Prince
of Frost. The deciduous treants stayed in Harken Forest, paying homage to the
petrified corpse of Malorunth, which still stands today. They believe the
Eternal Ash will be brought back to life if its murder can be avenged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war technically still rages, but it does so at a treant’s pace. There’s a
battle every century or two, when one of the group manages to organize a Great
March to attack the other’s territory. The fact that they must cross the entire
Vale to do so makes these marches even harder to organize, and slower to
happen. The last one was two hundred years ago, when Harken attacked
Winterbole. The next one will probably be a Winterbole attack, but sometimes it
happens that the same side will launch two attacks in a row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the last battle in this war is older than the fall of Nerath, and there
probably are no surviving Nerathi records of it. Maybe there are a few very old
elves and eladrin who remember it. And maybe the Frost Witches or Harken’s Heart
druids might know, since they live in those forests. But almost no one else has
any idea that a new Great March might be in their future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;winterbole-treants&quot;&gt;Winterbole Treants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-treants-winterbole.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These conifer creatures consider fleshy humanoids to be annoying pests and
parasites, and try to keep their territory free of them. This is made more
difficult by the fact that their slice of Winterbole Forest has a lot of
Arkhosian ruins and Shadowfell crossings in it, so delvers and explorers often
seek those out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have an alliance with Bitterstrike, whom we already met. The dragon
believes the treants to be her vassals, and they put up with this delusion as
long as she holds up her end of the bargain and assists them in the next Great
March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all treants, they are Fey Magical Beasts with the Plant and Treant tags. In
addition to low-light vision, they have both Forest Walk and Ice Walk, ignoring
difficult terrain with either or both of these themes. Needless to say this type
of terrain is plentiful in their home ground. They also have Resist Cold 10 -
even the minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winterbole-sapling&quot;&gt;Winterbole Sapling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Medium saplings are energetic and aggressive, and often team up with
Winterbole-aligned Wood Woads in raids against the Tigerclaw and other
trespassers. They’re Level 11 Minion Soldiers with a Speed of 6. Their &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt;
deal a bit of damage and immobilize for a turn, and their &lt;strong&gt;Numbing Branches&lt;/strong&gt;
aura (1) deals 3 damage to immobilized enemies that start their turns inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes for enemies who likes to mob and surround a single target. If even
one of them hits, all of their auras will deal damage that round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winterbole-rimeneedle&quot;&gt;Winterbole Rimeneedle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rimeneedles are the most intelligent of the “lesser” conifers, and tend to act
as scouts. They’re Large, and Level 12 Skirmishers with 122 HP. It has a Speed
of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rimeneedles are probably going to start the fight with &lt;strong&gt;Winter’s Step&lt;/strong&gt;, a move
action encounter power that lets them teleport 5 squares and make a Close Burst
2 attack on arrival. This deals cold damage, half on a miss. It probably
involves forcefully ejecting those rime needles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is a move action, the treant can immediately follow it up with a
basic &lt;strong&gt;slam&lt;/strong&gt; or with &lt;strong&gt;Tree Stomp&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets it shift its speed and move
through enemy spaces while doing so. The rimeneedle can make one slam attack
against an enemy along this path, and will additionally knock the enemy prone if
it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately as a non-minion treant, it has the &lt;strong&gt;Wooden Body&lt;/strong&gt; weakness, which
causes it to ignite and take ongoing 5 fire damage (save ends) from any attack
that deals fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winterbole-frostbeard&quot;&gt;Winterbole Frostbeard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaders of the Winterbole treants are the venerable Frostbeards, who can
command the winter. They’re rare and seldom seen by others, but they’re out
there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forstbeards are Level 16 Elite Controllers with the Leader tag and 308 HP. Their
size is Huge, their speed is 8, and they’re immune to being knocked prone. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Deep Roots&lt;/strong&gt; reduce any forced movement inflicted on them by 2 (which can
negate the movement entirely), and when they spend their action point every ally
within 10 squares can make a free basic melee attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their opening move is likely a &lt;strong&gt;Howling Blizzard&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that
deals heavy cold and thunder damage in an Area Burst 2 within 10 squares, and
knocks prone on a hit. The blizzard lingers as a zone that deals 10 cold damage
to people who end their turns inside. The frostbeard can move the zone up to 5
squares with a move action, and sustain it with a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the zone is in the battlefield, the frostbeard will likely wade inside it
and begin hitting people with &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt;, which it can make as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. If things begin to look dicey, it can call upon the &lt;strong&gt;Spirits of the
Forest&lt;/strong&gt; (move action, recharge 6+) to teleport itself and up to 3 nearby allies
up to 5 squares, granting them +2 to all defenses for a turn on arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess their main weakness, aside from the usual Wooden Body, is that they have
three different things they can do with their move action: move the blizzard,
use Spirits of the Forest, or make normal moves. If they’re doing one of them,
they can’t do the others unless they give up their standard action. Therefore,
it’s possible to play “keep-away” with them to make them fight at less than
optimal strength. If you stay rooted to one spot, though, they’ll fight you with
slams while pulling the blizzard to sit on top of themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;harken-treants&quot;&gt;Harken Treants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-treants-harken.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deciduous treants of the Harken forest are quite standard as far as rules
go. They use the standard stat blocks for the Treant and Bramblewood Treant from
the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/06/treant.html&quot;&gt;Monster Vault&lt;/a&gt;. They do often work alongside wood woads, so we have a
couple of stat blocks for those in addition to the (by now slightly outdated)
basic stats from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their leader is the most exceptional thing about them: Mysteriphal is the oldest
living creature in the entire Vale. He was there when Malorunth fell, and swore
to forever protect his petrified husk. As mentioned above, Mysteriphal believes
Malorunth will return to life once his murder is avenged. In our narrative
present he’s a huge fire-and-curse scarred thing, any hints of his former
kindness and nobility long gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wood-woad-druid&quot;&gt;Wood Woad Druid&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess the existence of these guys explains why the Harken treants wouldn’t be
allied with the Harken’s Heart druids. They’re Level 14 Skirmishers with the
Leader tag and 145 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The druid only has a speed of 5 and no Forest Walk, but it’s immune to the
Immobilized, Restrained, and Slowed conditions. It will likely try to approach a
squishy PC and use &lt;strong&gt;Polymorph Into Plant&lt;/strong&gt; on them. This targets Fortitude, and
does what it says on the tin. It lasts for a turn or until the druid drops to 0
HP, whatever comes first. The polymorphed target is considered stunned, and
gains Vulnerable 15 to fire. This recharges whenever the druid misses with it,
so he can keep trying until it sticks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the polymorph attack doesn’t look like an attractive option, the druid can
hit people with his &lt;strong&gt;cudgel&lt;/strong&gt;, using either basic attacks or a &lt;strong&gt;darting
strike&lt;/strong&gt; that lets him shift 2 squares before or after the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His leaderly options include &lt;strong&gt;Earthen Stride&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will, move action), which
lets the druid and an adjacent ally shift 2 squares; and &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Boon&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor, encounter) which gives a plant ally 25 temporary HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wood-woad-juggernaut&quot;&gt;Wood Woad Juggernaut&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 15 Brute is Large instead of Medium. He has 160 HP and fights mostly
with his powerful &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt;. He will charge if at all possible, since he has
Resist All 15 while charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once his preferred opponent is within his melee reach of 2, the juggernaut will
try to tag them with &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Reign&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a more damaging strike
that also inflicts ongoing 10 damage (save ends), and heals the juggernaut for
the same amount whenever the target takes this ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mysteriphal&quot;&gt;Mysteriphal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leader of the Harken treants is a Huge specimen, and a Level 20 Solo
Controller with 768 HP. This probably makes him the most powerful individual in
the whole Vale. Everything about him hints at his tremendous age, from his
scarred look to his stats. He ponderously drags himself at a speed of 4 without
Forest Walk, but is immune to poison since he has had time to build a tolerance
to all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an &lt;strong&gt;Ancient Entity&lt;/strong&gt;, Mysteriphal automatically downgrades the Dominated and
Stunned conditions to Dazed. His long fighting experience gives him
&lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach 3&lt;/strong&gt;, but he’s even more flammable than a typical treant. He
takes ongoing 10 damage (save ends) when he takes fire damage, but while on fire
his melee attacks also deal an extra 10 fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mysteriphal’s powerful Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; damage and push the target 1 square,
and he can make &lt;em&gt;four&lt;/em&gt; of them with a single standard action. If someone in
reach deals fire damage to him, he can make a free slam against the offender as
a reaction (which will already benefit from that bonus fire damage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also has several other tricks he can surprise his opponents with. Instead of
slamming he can use a &lt;strong&gt;Reverberating Word&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks all nonplants in a
Close Burst 3, deals heavy thunder damage, and dazes for a turn. This is perfect
for use with an action point, since it lets him do &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; and still punch his
enemies. It also recharges when Mysteriphal is first bloodied, so that second
solo action point also has an easy pre-defined use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can use a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Root Grab&lt;/strong&gt; to grab a target (DC 25)
and pull them up to 2 squares. He can have up to four different creatures
grabbed this way. This doesn’t deal damage… unless Mysteriphal is on fire,
when it benefits from the bonus. And if you think you’re safe by putting some
difficult terrain between Mysteriphal and yourself, the wily old treant can
&lt;strong&gt;Teleport&lt;/strong&gt; 4 squares as a move action (recharge 4+) and reach you anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs fighting Mysteriphal might want to consider &lt;em&gt;avoiding&lt;/em&gt; fire attacks. While
they’re still effective, they also make him much more dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a tragic story all around. Probably only the treants themselves remember
why they’re fighting, and barely anyone else would remember they’re fighting at
all due to the long quiet periods between Great Marches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth about Malorunth’s death is a mystery literally older than mortal
civilization, making it almost impossible to solve. And even if our nearly-Epic
PCs manage it, it’s probably still not enough to get the treants to end their
war. It might have started over this murder mystery, but after millenia of
conflict both sides have plenty of reason to keep hating each other.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/31/treants.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/31/treants.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Tigerclaw Barbarians</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-tigerclaw.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve heard about these people in several previous entries, and now is the time
to take a more detailed look at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tigerclaw people claim direct descent from the Hunter of Winter, a powerful
primal spirit in the shape of a sabertooth tiger who roamed the world when it
was young. Their stories tell of Hota Swiftstripe, one of their first
chieftains, who ran into the Hunter while he was tracking a bear near a
glacier. The spirit lashed out with a claw and took out one of Hota’s eyes
before he could even blink, but the chieftain proceeded to lure it to a frozen
lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tiger’s great weight cracked the ice and caused it to fall in, but Hota fell
compassion for such a great hunter and reached out with his spear to help the
beast get out. The Hunter of Winter told Hota that from that moment on they were
brothers, since Hota bore the Hunter’s mark and had saved its life. Hota himself
would be blessed with the blood of the tiger, and so would all his
descendants. When Hota returned to his tribe, he was no longer a human, but one
of the first razorclaw shifters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of Hota’s descendants were shifters as well, so today the Tigerclaw are
divided into two sub-groups. The Tigerbloods who occupy important roles such as
chieftain, shaman, and several types of elite warrior; and the Tamed,
non-shifters who work as gatherers, artisans and rank-and-file warriors. These
are not quite castes despite being called such by the book: there is a way for
one of the Tamed to become a Tigerblood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a Tamed has proven themselves worthy, the tribe’s chieftain invokes a rite
of initiation where the candidate must hunt and attempt to subdue a sabertooth
tiger. They must not &lt;em&gt;kill&lt;/em&gt; it - this is seen as a grave offense punishable by
death. Those who succeed are elevated to Tigerblood status. While they do not
become shifters themselves, they’re paired with a Tigerblood shifter so that
their children are born shifters. There doesn’t seem to be any gender-based role
division within the Tigerclaw, or at least the book doesn’t mention any. The
important one is the Tigerblood/Tamed distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tigerclaw used to live all around the Vale, but were driven north when
Nerath began to encroach on their territory. Chief Scargash’s tribe lives in
Winterbole Forest in our present, and has been there for 70 years after
returning from the frozen wastes north of the forest. Presumably there are other
tribes who still live up there. The book says they sometimes kidnap worthy
outsiders as mates to keep their numbers up, or adopt orphans from other
communities for the same reason. The first alternative is a horrible cliche, so
I’d suggest focusing more on the second and saying they also take in willing and
worthy adult outsiders instead of kidnapping them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the Tigerclaw are usually distrustful of outsiders. They remember
Nerath and the empires that came before, all of whom tried to impose their ways
on their people only to eventually crumble to dust while the Tigerclaw
endured. They consider all “creatures” outside their tribe to be hunters
competing for territory, whether those creatures are monsters or people. These
“competitors” can be negotiated and traded with, but never fully trusted. And if
they threaten the tribe, the Tigerclaw think no more of raiding a human or elven
settlement than they would of cleaning out a nest of snakes or culling an uppity
wolf pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their society also has its own criminals and outlaws, too. Tribe members who
slay their kin or steal from the tribe are either put to death or exiled,
depending on the severity of the crime. Those who are exiled are known as the
Riven. Most of them are quite evil and resort to worship of evil spirits or
demons to survive when cut off from the tribe. While some live as lone hunters,
others band together in marauder groups who make a living raiding both their
former kin and the outsider communities found south of Winterbole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest of these groups is led by a shaman named Shadowfang, who was exiled
for worshipping a giant demon lord named Kostchtie. They are based west of the
Winter River and frequently go south to raid villages and towns. The Lord Warden
of Fallcrest has a standing bounty on Shadowfang’s head. The book doesn’t
mention whether the people of the Vale distinguish between Riven and standard
Tigerclaw, so you can vary your answer there depending on what sort of story you
want to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their biggest internal conflict right now comes from the fact that Chief
Scargash and his shamans are making a serious attempt at opening diplomatic
channels to the other sapient inhabitants of Winterbole: the Frost Witches, the
Treants, and Bitterstrike. This appears to be working, but it has the more
traditionalist of the Tigerblood worried because they fear this will make the
Hunter of Winter see them as “soft” and withdraw its gifts. In other words,
they’re like fighting and know successful diplomacy will leave them with less
excuses to pick fights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already saw how Bitterstrike and the Frost Witches see these attempts, and
we’ll look at the treants in a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get several stat blocks for Tigerclaw warriors here, spanning most of the
Heroic tier. I’ll look at them in order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks are either humans or shifters. Shifters get low-light vision and
might have transformation-related abilities that kick in while they’re bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-hordling&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Hordling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likely a Tamed warrior of no particular distinction, this human is a Level 3
Minion Skirmisher. They attack with a battleaxe that crits on a 18-20, though
the damage increase from the critical is not spectacular since this is still a
minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-brave&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Brave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This human is a skilled warrior, which means they might one day undergo the
Tigerblood initiation ritual. They’re a Level 3 Soldier with 49 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Braves fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Broadsword&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and throw  &lt;strong&gt;Sabertooth Spears&lt;/strong&gt; at
range (they carry 2). The sword makes basic attacks that mark for a turn on a
hit. The spear targets Reflex and immobilizes for a turn on a hit. On a miss it
deals half damage and slows for a turn. This is not an at-will attack: it
recharges when the brave is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a marked enemy adjacent to the brave shifts, they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Sabertooth
Jab&lt;/strong&gt; to make a free sword attack against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-scout&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Scout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a shifter, which means they’re definitely a Tigerblood. They’re also a
Level 4 Skirmisher with 55 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scout is an &lt;strong&gt;Adept Charger&lt;/strong&gt;, which means they’re not limited to taking
only free actions after a charge. Their &lt;strong&gt;Razorclaw Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; power gives them a
+2 bonus to Speed and a +4 to defenses against opportunity attacks while
bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouts fight with paired &lt;strong&gt;Light Picks&lt;/strong&gt;, meant to invoke the image of a
sabertooth tiger’s fangs. They do an extra die of damage if used on a charge,
and can use a power named &lt;strong&gt;Sabertooth Strike&lt;/strong&gt; to attack two different targets
at once. This recharges as long as at least one of the attacks misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy ends its movement in a square where it flanks the scout, the scout
can use &lt;strong&gt;Wild Instinct&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to shift 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-fang-wielder&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Fang-Wielder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shifter is a Level 5 Brute with 77 HP. They use a &lt;strong&gt;heavy war pick&lt;/strong&gt;, whose
attacks to extra damage while they’re bloodied. It can also be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Fang
of the Sabertooth&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge 5+), which does heavy damage, knocks
prone, and on a critical hit inflicts 5 ongoing damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Fang-Wielder first becomes bloodied, they use a reaction named
&lt;strong&gt;Winter’s Rage&lt;/strong&gt;, which is an attack on a Close Burst 1 that damages and knocks
prone on a hit, does half damage on a miss, and pushes 1 square as an effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fang-Wielders want to charge right in and actually like getting surrounded by
melee PCs, because all of their best traits kick in when they’re bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tigerclaw-shaman&quot;&gt;Tigerclaw Shaman&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These shifters act as spiritual advisors and general spellcasters for the
Tigerclaw. They’re Level 5 Controllers with 52 HP. In combat they use a
&lt;strong&gt;Longspear&lt;/strong&gt; and some mind-affecting magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes the &lt;strong&gt;Phantom Fangs&lt;/strong&gt; at-will spell, which on a hit does psychic
damage and immobilizes for a turn, and on a miss slows for a turn. It also
includes the &lt;strong&gt;Concussive Roar&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, a minor action that attacks a
Close Blast 3 and on a hit pushes targets 3 squares and immobilizes them. On a
miss it pushes 1 square instead, but in either case it does no damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sabertooth-tiger&quot;&gt;Sabertooth Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, as implied in the lore the Tigerclaw make use of sabertooth tigers as
pets. Tigerblood candidates have to tame a wild tiger as part of their
initiation, and I imagine they also breed and raise tigers to accompany
hereditary Tigerbloods. An encounter involving Tigerclaw members is also likely
to involve these beasties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabertooth Tigers are Large Natural Beasts with the Mount keyword and Level 6
Soldiers with 72 HP. They have a ground speed of 8 and a climb speed of 4. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Charging Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; trait works like the scout’s Adept Charger, letting them
make any type of action after a charge. And their &lt;strong&gt;Tiger Charge&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives a
+2 damage bonus to the charge attacks of their rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do extra damage on a charge, and grab on a hit (escape DC
15). If the tiger has a grabbed victim, it can only bite that victim. It can
also use &lt;strong&gt;Puncturing Fangs&lt;/strong&gt; against them. This hits automatically, does some
physical damage, and inflicts ongoing 5 damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tigers are higher level than most of the humanoids in this entry, but this is
not a problem because ever since the Monster Vault mount monsters no longer have
to be of equal or lower level than their riders. You can safely drop this
restriction from all older monsters as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tigers want to charge in, grab someone, and keep using Puncturing Fangs on
them, preferrably while their rider attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scargash-tigerclaw-chief&quot;&gt;Scargash, Tigerclaw Chief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scargash seems to be a fairly typical Tigerclaw chief as far as stats go. You
could use the same stats for chiefs of other tribes if any appear in your
game. He’s a shifter, of course, and a Level 6 Elite Brute with the Leader tag
and 176 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scargash gains a +2 bonus to all of his defenses while bloodied, and his
leadership style expresses itself as an aura (5) named &lt;strong&gt;Encircle the Prey&lt;/strong&gt;,
which grants allies +2 to damage on attacks against targets they are flanking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His &lt;strong&gt;War Pick&lt;/strong&gt; inflicts ongoing damage on a hit and can be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. If both of those attacks hit the target also suffers a -2 penalty to
all defenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His encounter power is a &lt;strong&gt;Staggering Swipe&lt;/strong&gt; that damages the target and does
half damage on a miss. As an &lt;em&gt;effect&lt;/em&gt;, it also slides the target 3 squares to a
space adjacent to one or more other enemies. Those enemies take an automatic 10
damage and fall prone as the flung target bowls into them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;primal-sabertooth-tiger&quot;&gt;Primal Sabertooth Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of majestic mount a Tigerclaw chief would ride into battle. They could
be extraordinary mundane specimens, but are likely somehow blessed by the Hunter
in Winter either naturally or via Tigerclaw rituals. Primal sabertooths are Huge
Natural Beasts with the Mount keyword and Level 8 Elite Soldiers with 178 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have the same Charging Pounce trait as their smaller relatives, and also
have Threatening Reach 2. Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that damages
and inflicts 5 ongoing damage. If the target was already taking ongoing damage,
this inflicts 10 ongoing damage instead. This means that a second claw attack on
the same target will worsen their ongoing damage, or that a first attack will
already inflict the worse condition if the target was taking ongoing 5 damage
from another source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primal tiger’s &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; is a minor action. It does light damage and grabs
with escape DC 20. The tiger can pull the victim along when it moves without
provoking opportunity attacks from the victim. Only one victim may be grabbed at
a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Go For the Kill&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which targets Reflex,
deals heavy damage, knocks prone, and gives the tiger 5 temporary HP if the
attack bloodies the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the tiger hits 0 HP, it can shift its speed and use Go For The Kill one
last time. If this reduces the target to 0 HP, the tiger heals back to 20 HP
instead of dying. This ability, called &lt;strong&gt;Fierce Spirit&lt;/strong&gt;, is an encounter power,
so the tiger can’t use it again in the same fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book uses the word “barbarian” a lot, but I’ve avoided doing it here. I
suppose they’re barbarians in the D&amp;amp;D class sense, but I wouldn’t want to use
the rest of that word’s baggage with them. And if I included the Tigerclaw in a
game, I’d definitely remove the bit where they raid other communities for
“worthy mates”. It’s still a bad trope no matter how you look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Removing that shitty trope leaves you with a fairly complex people as far as D&amp;amp;D
cultures go. They’re not likely to be very friendly to outsider PCs, but they
have good reasons for their suspicion. Outsiders can still interact with them in
peaceful ways with a bit of work, and they would make a good origin culture for
martial or primal PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Bitterstrike decides to go a-conquering, she’ll want to force Scargash’s
tribe to act as her front-line troops. I imagine their traditionalists will
welcome this since it will mean an end to diplomacy followed by lots of battles,
but most of the tribe would resent serving under the dragon and/or being
manipulated by Frost Witches who would surely be the secret instigators of the
whole thing. They’re the first troops you fight, but they’re also the weak link
you work in order to dismantle the Army of Winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowfang’s bunch makes for a much less ambiguous enemy faction, but PCs who
like to go for the diplomatic solution would still have plenty to do in a
scenario where the people of Winterhaven and Fallcrest had trouble telling them
apart from other Tigerclaw and directed their enmity at all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/25/tigerclaw-barbarians.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/25/tigerclaw-barbarians.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Shadowmire</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-shadowmire.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s our third dragon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The black dragon Shadowmire has made the Witchlight Fens his home for over two
hundred years. He’s the more active and aggressive of the Vale’s current
draconic inhabitants, and I guess also the one most like a typical dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowmire claims the entire extent of the Witchlight Fens as his dominion,
but though his personal power is terrifying, his power &lt;em&gt;base&lt;/em&gt; is not quite up to
the task of controlling all of that territory. The dragon rules many of the
lizardfolk tribes who live on the area as a terrifying overlord, and while
they’re not always capable of preventing others from encroaching into the fens,
Shadowmire uses them to punish any groups foolish enough to do so. He likes to
brag that the fall of Kalton Manor was his greatest victory, though he was not
the sole factor involved in that tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s main goal is to turn his claims into reality, and to grow ever
wealthier and more powerful in the process. He patrols the Fens to make its
inhabitants fear him, and can sometimes be seen flying over the Nentir River
where it passes by the swamp. He can also move more stealthily, even swimming
silently where the water is deep enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowmire’s lair is under the Cairnwater river, accessible through an
underwater entrance at the river bed. Its true location is known only to the
dragon himself, but there’s much speculation about it and the treasures it
contains. Shadowmire is entirely aware of this and keeps a number of fake lairs
throughout the fens, which he uses to misdirect his enemies and lure greedy
adventurers to their doom. The dragon increases his hoard by looting those
greedy adventurers, and by raiding trade boats that pass through the Nentir
river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since he’s lived in the Fens for so long, Shadowmire knows practically every one
of its secrets, and a good deal about the story of the Vale besides. He also
makes some effort to remain aware of the Vale’s current affairs through his
network of spies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every inhabitant of the Fens serves the dragon, and some even try to oppose
him. I imagine there might be a hag coven or two who have objections to his
rule, but the group the book calls out as the most persistent torn on
Shadowmire’s side are the Daggerburg Goblins! They regularly venture into the
fens and clash with Shadowmire’s lizardfolk servants. I imagine they might be in
a true pickle if the dragon decides to retaliate personally, but he doesn’t like
leaving the Fens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowmire’s stats make me think all three dragons were written by different
authors, because he’s Huge and a Level 19 Solo Lurker with 712 HP. This makes
him the most powerful dragon in the book, even stronger than slumbering
Calastryx. I guess this is balanced by the fact that he has the weakest army, as
his lizarfolk aren’t very organized and can’t operate very well outside the
swamp. This limits how far he can expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having a level comparable to that of a “stock” Elder Black Dragon,
Shadowmire has a slightly less varied repertoire of attacks. His passive traits
are all work the same, as do his &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied
Breath&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bite and Breath Weapon do less damage than the ones from the base elder
dragon. The difference here is that the Threats writers considered the added
ongoing acid damage from both the bite and the breath to be part of the damage
formula, while the Monster Vault writers added them on top of that. Both bite
and breath do half damage on a miss, too, so a fight against Shadowmire is a
grueling battle of attrition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowmire’s &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks do the same damage as a base elder dragon’s, and
pull the target 2 squares. His &lt;strong&gt;Tail Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; works the same but does more base
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally we get to the star of the show, his custom ability: &lt;strong&gt;Swamp
Simulacrum&lt;/strong&gt;. When used, this makes Shadowmire turn invisible for a turn and
summons 2 identical duplicates within 10 squares of the original. They last
until the end of the encounter or until destroyed. The duplicates are
effectively minions with Shadowmire’s defenses, and explode in a burst of acid
when destroyed (Close Burst 2, acid damage, half on a miss). This recharges when
the dragon is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowmire is an interest mechanical variation on an elder black dragon, and his
lore is workable enough, but I think he’s a bit too high level to fit with that
lore. I’d probably make him Level 12 or so. He’s more dangerous and intelligent
than Bitterstrike, but is not seen as a living calamity like Calastryx.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/21/shadowmire.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/21/shadowmire.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Scroll Mummy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-scroll-mummy.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another more generic entry. I first remember seeing scroll mummies in 3e where
they appeared in the Monster Manual III. I wouldn’t be surprised if they date
from earlier editions than that. There’s a bit of an AD&amp;amp;D 2nd Edition vibe to
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the name, these creatures are constructs, not undead. They’re armatures
made from magical detritus (broken magic items, shards of potion vials, and so
on) wrapped in spell scrolls. They style of the wrapping makes them resemble
mummies, so I guess the name stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are however still undead-adjacent because each one is powered by a lich’s
soul. To activate a scroll mummy, you need to destroy a lich and place its soul
vessel inside the finished body of the construct before the lich can
reform. The lich’s soul is bound as a power source, and the mummy rises to obey
its creator like a typical construct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scroll mummies are fairly clever as constructs go, and their construction gives
them the ability to cast the spells written on their wrappings. In the Vale, the
Mages of Saruun know how to create scroll mummies and love using them to guard
their private libraries. Most other people who know the secret of their
construction are more explicitly evil mages and priests, many of which worship
Vecna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a complication here: if a scroll mummy is destroyed and the
soul vessel survives, the lich it belongs to will reform within 1d10 days. It
will likely also be pretty angry at whoever decided to turn it into a glorified
battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first scroll mummy ever created was named Grisgol, and its heart was the
vessel of the lich Asperdies. Legend has it that Asperdies eventually found a
way to break out of his imprisonment and took his revenge on Grisgol’s
creators. To this day, wizards who are particular about terminology prefer to
call these constructs “grisgols” since they aren’t true mummies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grisgols are Large Natural Animates with the Construct keyword, and also Level
15 Elite Soldiers with 276 HP. That puts them at about the same power level or a
bit higher than a typical lich. Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Paralyzing Claw&lt;/strong&gt;,
borrowing the power of a lich’s touch. It’s Reach 2, does necrotic damage, and
immobilizes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per round as a minor action, the grisgol can cast a spell from one of the
scrolls wrapping it. The GM rolls a d6 to determine the effect. All of them are
bursts or blasts with different elemental damage types and riders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boiling Blood&lt;/strong&gt;: Close Burst 2 vs. Fortitude, immediate and ongoing fire
damage on a hit (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice Barrage&lt;/strong&gt;: Close Blast 5 vs. Reflex, cold damage, half on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lightning Lure&lt;/strong&gt;: Close Blast 5 vs. Reflex, lightning damage, pulls 4
squares.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shadowy Tendrils&lt;/strong&gt;: Close Burst 2 vs. Fortitude, necrotic damage, inflicts
necrotic vulnerability (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thunderforce Pulse&lt;/strong&gt;: Close Burst 2 vs. Fortitude, thunder and force
damage, knocks prone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wave of Madness&lt;/strong&gt;: Close Blast 5 vs. Will, psychic damage, target must
choose between making a basic attack against an adjacent ally or taking
extra psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that in past editions these would be standard spells, but here they’re
custom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a grisgol is reduced to 0 HP, it collapses and releases a cloud of
&lt;strong&gt;Choking Dust&lt;/strong&gt; in a Close Burst 2. This attack does both immediate and ongoing
necrotic and poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting that Vecna, who spreads lichdom rituals, would also be the
source of the recipe for scroll mummies. Maybe it was all a scam from the start,
or maybe he feels it’s a waste to simply kill all those “competing” liches who
are affiliated with Orcus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess this also gives a plausible reason for some shady wizards to not want to
become liches. “A lich? You mean like those things I use to power my guards?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition the treasure these things might be guarding, their own bodies might
serve as a plausible source of treasure for an encounter. Maybe one of those
broken magic items isn’t so broken after all, and maybe you can bring combat
scrolls back into 4e by giving them out as consumables that let PCs use one of
the grisgol’s spell attacks once.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/18/scroll-mummy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/18/scroll-mummy.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: River Rats</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-river-rats.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very specific group that makes the city of Fallcrest its home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we talk about the River Rats, I figure it’s useful to talk a bit about
Fallcrest itself. This is information from both the DMG and this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fallcrest grew around a small fort (Moonstone Keep) originally built to guard a
portage site around a big waterfall in the Nentir River. The entire rest of the
river is perfectly navigable, but trade boats arriving at this point need to
unload their cargo so that it can be hauled up or down the limestone cliffs
around the waterfall that would eventually give the city its name. The loading
points are known as the Upper and Lower Quays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fallcrest was a prosperous trade hub for many years, but it was hit hard by the
Bloodspear invasion. It hasn’t recovered completely even after all these years,
since the volume of foreign trade coming into the Vale was severely reduced by
the fall of Nerath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cliffs split Fallcrest into two districts, Hightown and Lowtown. Hightown is
located at the more defensible top of the cliff. It suffered relatively little
during the sack of the city and was the first area to be rebuilt and resettled,
making it the wealthier half of the city in our narrative present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lowtown is the poorer half, located at the foot of the cliff. It was almost
completely razed back during the invasion, and only began to see new
construction much later, as the city began growing again. There are still
significant stretches of it that are abandoned or ruined, which make good
hideouts for the city’s criminal element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That finally brings us to the River Rats, which are a significant faction in
that criminal element. This gang had a Dickensian start, with a band of orphans
who got together for protection and were turned to crime by an unscrupulous
adult. Most of its members are grownups in our narrative present, but they still
recruit new members by taking in street urchins. These new recruits are provided
with food, shelter, training, and a sense of camaraderie they have likely never
experienced before, which makes the River Rats extremely loyal to each other.
They also have something of a “us against the world” mentality, since the world
never gave them any of the things the Rats did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gang’s current leader is Kelson, the halfling who owns the Lucky Gnome
Taphouse and who despite rising from the ranks neatly fills the archetype of the
exploitative leader. The Taphouse is the cheapest and rowdiest of Fallcrest’s
taverns, catering to dockworkers and porters. Despite the unsavory reputations
of the Taphouse and its owner, Kelson has not yet been linked to the activities
of the River Rats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gang has a wide repertoire, but the most profitable of their activities
consists of burglarizing the warehouses near the Lower Quays. Kelson chooses
targets based on the information he overhears in the Taphouse, and his gang is
very enthusiastic about following through. Merchants who make use of these
warehouses must carefully weigh the risk of losing their merchandise against the
abusive monopoly prices charged by the Porter’s Guild to haul the cargo to safer
storage spaces in the Upper Quays. The Porter’s Guild is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in collusion with
the Rats, but the overall picture still adds up to quite a damper on Fallcrest’s
economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelson dreams of expanding the River Rats into a true criminal syndicate with
chapters on every city in the Vale, but before he focuses on that he wants to
eliminate all his rivals in Fallcrest. If his plans succeed, Fallcrest could be
the site of a bloody gang war, likely between the Rats and the Shadow Court plus
whatever other groups the GM wants to add into the mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a hostile faction that resides in Fallcrest itself, the River Rats are early
to mid-Heroic threats. They’re from a variety of “playable” species, and as
mentioned in he Lore section are mostly Unaligned, since their loyalty to each
other is their main motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can easily switch their races around for more variety through the usual
tactic of changing and reassigning the relevant stats and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gang’s signature trait is &lt;strong&gt;River Rat Tactics&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets its owner gain
combat advantage against any enemy who has one of the owner’s allies adjacent to
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lowtown-urchin&quot;&gt;Lowtown Urchin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These halflings are actually around the age of a typical starting adventurer,
but they disguise themselves as human children to avoid suspicion as they pick
pockets and spy on people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our urchin is a Level 1 Skirmisher with 28 HP. As a halfling they have a Speed
of 6 and a +5 bonus to saves vs. Fear effects. They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt;, and
will use the &lt;strong&gt;Cloak of Filth&lt;/strong&gt; that covers them to make themselves harder to
hit. This is a move action that allows them to shift 3 squares and gain partial
concealment for a turn. As a halfling, they can use the &lt;strong&gt;Second Chance&lt;/strong&gt; power
once per encounter to force an enemy who hit them to reroll the attack and use
the new result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bloodied, the Urchin will resort to the &lt;strong&gt;River Rat’s Gambit&lt;/strong&gt; special
attack. This encounter power lets them make a basic attack and cause 2d6 bonus
damage if that attack hits. If it misses, the urchin takes 1d6 damage instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;market-green-grifter&quot;&gt;Market Green Grifter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grifters usually pick pockets or run rigged gambling scams in Fallcrest’s Market
Green area, but might be called in to do other work. They’re not very good at
direct confrontations, but they can play dead like no one else. This one’s a
half-elf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grifter fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt; whose basic attack profile is nothing
special. They’ll make a half-assed attempt at fighting until they first take
damage, and then they’ll &lt;strong&gt;Play Dead&lt;/strong&gt;. This causes the grifter to fall
prone. Until the start of the grifter’s next turn, they have a +5 to all
defenses against close and area attacks, and enemies must spend a minor action
to roll and pass a DC 20 Insight check to target them with melee or ranged
attacks (otherwise, the enemy will believe the grifter is dead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On their next turn, the grifter can come &lt;strong&gt;Back From the Dead&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets them
stand up, shift 3 squares, and make 3 shortsword attacks against an enemy. The
attacks use the basic profile, but also do half-damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the grifter hits 0 HP, they can use &lt;strong&gt;The Jig is Up&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt. They
retain their last hit point and can shift 3 squares, likely as a prelude to
running away at full speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lower-quays-guttersnipe&quot;&gt;Lower Quays Guttersnipe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guttersnipes usually act as lookouts and spies, but are not adverse to a spot of
murder if needed. They’re Level 2 Artillery with 30 HP. This one’s a halfling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to remember that the guttersnipe &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; need to be adjacent to
an enemy to benefit from River Rat tactics! As long as at least one ally is
adjacent to that enemy, the guttersnipe can shoot them with combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have the &lt;strong&gt;Sniper&lt;/strong&gt; trait, which lets them stay hidden if they miss
with a ranged attack from hiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those ranged attacks will be made with &lt;strong&gt;Slings&lt;/strong&gt;. If enemies get too close for
comfort, the guttersnipe can toss a &lt;strong&gt;Hooked Net&lt;/strong&gt;, which acts as a Close Blast
2 that restrains and deals 5 ongoing damage to those it hits (save ends). They
only have one of these, though, and after it’s spent they’ll need to resort to
weak-sauce &lt;strong&gt;Gut Punches&lt;/strong&gt; to discourage melee attackers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have the halfling Second Chance power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;razorclaw-jack&quot;&gt;Razorclaw Jack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacks are part of the Rat’s beefier contingent, and specialize in burglary and
kidnapping. This one’s a Razorclaw shifter, and a Level 3 Skirmisher with 43
HP. When they’re bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Razorclaw Shifting&lt;/strong&gt; gives them a +2 bonus to
Speed, taking it from 6 to 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jack fights with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which deal extra damage if they have
combat advantage. They can also use the River Rat’s Gambit technique. If
conditions are right (recharge 4+) they can use &lt;strong&gt;Skulduggery&lt;/strong&gt; to shift half
its speed as a move action and gain combat advantage against enemies adjacent to
them at the end of the movement. This combat advantage lasts until the end of
the current turn, so the movement must come before an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lowtown-kneebreaker&quot;&gt;Lowtown Kneebreaker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kneebreakers are pure muscle, sent to rough people up or kill them when the time
for subtlety is past. This one’s a human, and a Level 3 Brute with 56 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Clubs&lt;/strong&gt;, can use River Rat’s Gambit, and can do what their
name says as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Crippling Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), which deals extra
damage and slows (save ends). It still does half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kelson&quot;&gt;Kelson&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leader of the River Rats has the only stat block in this entry with an Evil
alignment. Everyone else is Unaligned. I take this to mean that the River Rats
are motivated primarily by loyalty to each other, but that Kelson is exploiting
that loyalty for his own profit. He’s a Level 5 Elite Skirmisher with the Leader
tag and 120 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelson’s skills as a &lt;strong&gt;Gang Leader&lt;/strong&gt; act as an aura (3) that gives allies inside
a +2 bonus to saves. He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt; and throws poisoned
&lt;strong&gt;Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; that deal damage and inflict 5 ongoing poison damage on a hit (save
ends). The &lt;strong&gt;Flickering Blades&lt;/strong&gt; at-will maneuver lets him make a shortsword
attack, shift 3 squares, and throw a dagger at someone else, all within the same
standard action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He can also use River Rat’s Gambit and Second Chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The River Rats are mostly a pretty standard thieves’ guild and are a good tool
for GMs who want to add a bit of urban adventuring to 4e’s standard
points-of-light setup. They’re more straightforward and less problematic than
the Fell Court, and also a bit more morally ambiguous. Most of the River Rats
are in this business simply to make a living and take care of their found
family. This means it’s possible for diplomatic PCs to dismantle the gang using
mostly non-violent means!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’d need to befriend its rank-and-file members, make them turn against
Kelson, and give them the material conditions to leaver their criminal careers
behind for good. More complex than the usual “kill’em all” approach, but
potentially much more satisfying. Of course, less scrupulous but still
diplomatic PCs might end up just replacing Kelson as the boss instead of ending
the Rats’ criminal activities.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/12/river-rats.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/12/river-rats.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Raven Roost Bandits</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-raven-roost-bandits.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new Vale-specific faction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raven Roost is an old manor located about 10 miles to the southeast of
Thunderspire. It used to be the home of a local lord back in Nerathi times, and
got this name because the lord had a gallows assembled at a nearby hilltop and
was in the habit of keeping the bodies of executed criminals on display
there. This attracted a lot of ravens, and gave the property its name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lord and his household are long gone, and today Raven Roost is home to a
fairly sophisticated bandit gang. Their proximity to the Trade Road allows them
to regularly attack travelers and traders moving between Fallcrest, Thunderspire
and Hammerfast. They’re helped in this enterprise by Barton, the cheerful owner
of the Fiveleague House inn near Hammerfast, who sends them advance warning of
juicy targets coming from that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book also mentions the bandits also attack the King’s Road to the south, but
that’s pretty far from their home base and requires them to cut through a bit of
Harken forest to reach it. Harken’s Heart or the Hunter Spiders might have
something to say about that if they exist in your campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banditry was always common along that stretch of road, as the nearby Harken
Forest seems to offer a nice source of shelter and concealment to the deserters,
cutthroats and outlaws who tend to make up these gangs. None of them ever lasted
for very long, though, eventually falling prey to infighting or incurring the
displeasure of the forest’s inhabitants. This changed when the three shadar-kai,
disgraced former servants of the Raven Queen, arrived on the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the three, Samminel was a warlord, Erzoun his court witch, and Geriesh his
chief spy. Erzoun once predicted that Samminel would never advance in prestige
and station if he remained on his Shadowfell domain, so the trio crossed into
the world. Their spectacular displays of violence unburdened by compassion
earned the fear and respect of all the little bands that hid in the Forest, who
decided to swear loyalty to them and beg for training and leadership. Thus were
the Raven Roost bandits formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three leaders don’t actually work together very well, since they have a
tendency to undermine each other’s authority. They know this, however, and have
arranged things so that each of them commands a separate force with little
direct interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raven Roost itself is an excellent home base for them. It occupies a little
hidden valley in the Old Hills that’s supremely defensible and cannot be seen
from the road. It’s also out of Harken Forest proper, which makes the bandits
much less vulnerable to attacks by angry druids. They hide in the edges of the
forest while waiting in ambush, but Raven Roost is where they rest their heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bandits’ initial attacks were shockingly violent, but they’ve toned it down
after their reputation began to spread. They frequently spare the lives of their
victims and accept surrenders, since they know that people fight back harder
when their lives are at stake. Sometimes their reputation allows them to avoid a
fight entirely. Eventually, they plan to capitalize on that reputation to move
from banditry to warlordism, and try to conquer and rule their own stretch of
the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for the three shadar-kai leaders, and for the rank-and-file bandits
they lead. Bandits are usually human, though you could certainly mix things a
bit and add other ancestries here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three leaders have the Shadar-kai &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Jaunt&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, which
lets them teleport 3 squares and become insubstantial for a turn as a move
action. The others have no common traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, we’ll look at them in ascending order of level, with the leaders at
the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raven-roost-harrier&quot;&gt;Raven Roost Harrier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trained by Geriesh, harriers are Level 4 Skirmishers with 53 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;short
swords&lt;/strong&gt; deal physical damage and prevent the target from making opportunity
attacks for a turn on a hit. Their &lt;strong&gt;Crossbows&lt;/strong&gt; have no raiders, but are decent
basic ranged attacks. They can make &lt;strong&gt;Moving Attacks&lt;/strong&gt; that let them move their
speed, attack with the sword at any point, and move away without provoking
opportunity attacks from their target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raven-roost-cutthroat&quot;&gt;Raven Roost Cutthroat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also trained by Geriesh, cutthroats are Level 5 Lurkers with 49 HP. They fight
with &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;garrotes&lt;/strong&gt;. Garrotes target Reflex and grab the target on
a hit. The escape DC is a surprising 22! While the grab lasts, the cutthroat has
superior cover and both it and the victim are immune to forced movement. The
bandit can use an &lt;strong&gt;Aterial Cut&lt;/strong&gt; on its grabbed victim, an attack that deals
both immediate and ongoing physical damage (save ends), and ends the grab on a
hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the victim escapes the cutthroat’s grab, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Quick Cut&lt;/strong&gt; to make a
free dagger attack against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raven-roost-grenadier&quot;&gt;Raven Roost Grenadier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trained by Erzoun, grenadiers are Level 5 Controllers with 61 HP. They’re armed
with a &lt;strong&gt;Shortsword&lt;/strong&gt; and with a large assortment of grenades. They carry 8
&lt;strong&gt;Fire Bombs&lt;/strong&gt; that deal fire damage in an Area Burst 1 and knock the targets
prone on a hit. They deal half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also carry a single &lt;strong&gt;Smoke Bomb&lt;/strong&gt; laced with poison, which attacks an Area
Burst 1 and causes the targets to become dazed and to take ongoing poison damage
(save ends). This creates a zone that lightly obscures its space until the end
of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they carry a bomb that can produce an &lt;strong&gt;Oil Slick&lt;/strong&gt;, which can knock
everyone in an Area Burst 1 prone and as an effect make them vulnerable to fire
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Grenadier’s Rush&lt;/strong&gt; to move their speed
with a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raven-roost-sharpshooter&quot;&gt;Raven Roost Sharpshooter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another Erzoun special, sharpshooters are Level 6 Artillery with 55 HP. They
fight with &lt;strong&gt;short swords&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;crossbows&lt;/strong&gt;, and as expected of artillery the
latter are more accurate and damaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharpshooters can spend their move action to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Careful Aim&lt;/strong&gt;
maneuver. This lets them pick an enemy they can see. If they can still see that
enemy at the start of their next turn, their crossbow attack will attack the
target’s Reflex instead of their AC, and will deal 5 extra damage. So not only
will the attack be more accurate than usual, it will also target a lower defense
(often much lower for heavily armored characters).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharpshooters can also deploy an &lt;strong&gt;Archer’s Decoy&lt;/strong&gt; as a free action, which
grants them a +2 bonus to AC and Reflex for a turn. This recharges when they’re
first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Careful Aim is a move action, sharpshooters are quite powerful when they
can remain stationary. You can help them with that by deploying them behind good
cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raven-roost-outlaw-veteran&quot;&gt;Raven Roost Outlaw Veteran&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Led by Samminel, veterans are Level 6 Brutes with 86 HP. They fight with
&lt;strong&gt;bastard swordS&lt;/strong&gt; and can do a fair few things with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from their basic attacks, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Mighty Blows&lt;/strong&gt;, which do the same
damage, push the target 1 square, and let the veteran shift 1 square to
follow. Their &lt;strong&gt;Swath of Death&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver lets them attack twice and keeps
recharging as long as at least one of the attacks misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Forceful Shove&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to attack a target’s
Fortitude and push then 1 square on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raven-roost-highwayman&quot;&gt;Raven Roost Highwayman&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Led by Samminel, highwaymen are Level 7 Soldiers with 77 HP. They wield the
classy bandit’s choice, a &lt;strong&gt;rapier&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;hand crossbow&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic rapier attack marks for a turn, and despite carrying 10 bolts for
the crossbow they have no ranged basic attack! Instead, they have a special
encounter power named &lt;strong&gt;Bolt to the Gut&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s a ranged attack but does not
provoke opportunity attacks. It deals heavy physical damage, immobilizes, and
inflicts ongoing physical damage (save ends). Even on a miss, it immobilizes for
a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do highwaymen do with the other 9 bolts once they use this? They wait for a
marked enemy to make an attack that doesn’t include them as a target. That lets
them use &lt;strong&gt;Stand, You Coward&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction, which lets them immediately
recharge and use &lt;strong&gt;Bolt to the Gut&lt;/strong&gt; on the offending enemy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;geriesh&quot;&gt;Geriesh&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geriesh is a Level 6 Elite Skirmisher (Leader) with 136 HP. His sneaky
leadership takes the form of a &lt;strong&gt;Swiftshadow Master&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5), which gives all
enemies inside a +4 to Initiative and to Stealth. &lt;strong&gt;Willing Prey&lt;/strong&gt; makes any
enemy marking him grant combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spymaster fights with &lt;strong&gt;katars&lt;/strong&gt;, which deal extra damage against targets
granting him combat advantage. If the attack does more than 20 damage, the
target falls unconscious (save ends). This is possible if he attacks with combat
advantage, since his damage is 3d6+7 in that case. That’s about a 40% chance of
unconsciousness, which of course also happens if he crits because that causes
max damage. His version of &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to perform two attacks
and move up to his full speed between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geriesh replaces the standard Shadow Jaunt power with &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Leap&lt;/strong&gt;, which
doesn’t grant insubstantial but lets him teleport his full speed of 6. Once per
encounter, he can also use &lt;strong&gt;Dagger Flick&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action, which deals
physical damage, immobilizes, and inflicts ongoing poison damage. Even on a
miss, this grazes the target and immobilizes them for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;erzoun&quot;&gt;Erzoun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erzoun is a Level 7 Elite Controller (Leader) with 152 HP. Her witchy leadership
manifests as a &lt;strong&gt;Quickshadow Aura&lt;/strong&gt; (5). Any ally who shifts while inside the
aura can shift 1 extra square. While the bandits under her are fairly martial
sorts, she’s a proper witch and fights exclusively with magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erzoun’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Blackfire Touch&lt;/strong&gt; that does fire and necrotic
damage on a hit, and slides 1 square as an effect. She can attack at range with
a spell named &lt;strong&gt;Beshadowed Mind&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic and psychic damage, and
makes the target unable to see anything further than 2 squares away (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also has a host of limited spells, starting with a fun one. &lt;strong&gt;Witch’s
Prophecy&lt;/strong&gt; is an attack against Will that does no damage, but has a very
interesting effect. If Erzoun hits, she can choose an ally within 10
squares. The target of the spell is weakened when attacking anyone other than
the chosen ally. This lasts until the end of the encounter, and recharges
whenever she misses with it! She’s going to use this to set up the worst match
possible between a PC striker and a beefy ally who can resist their attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erzoun can also create a zone of &lt;strong&gt;Deep Shadow&lt;/strong&gt; in an area burst 1. This is
difficult terrain to enemies inside, and deals 10 damage to those enemies when
they enter the zone or end their turn in it. It lasts for a turn but can be
sustained and moved 4 squares with a minor action. It recharges when bloodied,
so Erzoun might have two of these zones in play at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erzoun gets the standard Shadow Jaunt power, but she also gets a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow
Augury&lt;/strong&gt; reaction that triggers when she’s hit in melee while bloodied. It
recharges Shadow Jaunt and lets her use it immediately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erzoun is hard to pin down and will wreak havoc on the PC’s formations with a
Deep Shadow zone and a prophecy right at the start. Once bloodied, she stays
mostly stationary to sustain her two zones, relying on Shadow Augury to avoid
being surrounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;samminel&quot;&gt;Samminel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall boss of the Raven Roost bandits is a Level 8 Elite Soldier (Leader)
with 172 HP. He’s the more direct and martial of the trio, wielding a
&lt;strong&gt;halberd&lt;/strong&gt; in combat. His leadership instills his underlings with a
&lt;strong&gt;Deathshadow Fervor&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 5) that lets them daze any target against whom they
score a critical hit (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The halberd marks for a turn, and he can also use it in a &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; or
in a &lt;strong&gt;Sundering Sweep&lt;/strong&gt;, which doesn’t mark but hits a Close Burst 2 and
inflicts a -2 AC penalty (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a marked enemy tries to ignore Samminel, he can make a basic attack against
them as an interrupt, scoring a critical on a 17-20. He also gets the standard
Shadow Jaunt power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Samminel is less gimmicky than Erzoun, but is a good enabler for the sort of
direct henchman he prefers to lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see the word “bandits” and immediately think of the sort of generic
opponent that tends to grace each edition’s first Monster Manual. Fortunately
the ones we get here have fairly interesting mechanics that elevate them beyond
the generic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They all work very well together, but the structure described in the Lore
encourages a story where you face each “sub-gang” in order, defeat its boss, and
move up the ladder. The likely order is Geriesh, Erzoun, and Samminel. Depending
on how tightly you couple the bandit stat blocks with the leaders who train
them, you might need to insert some generics in here to pad out your encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t get an exact headcount of the Raven Roost bandits. There’s enough to
give the Hunter Spiders pause and make them avoid “hunting” the same routes,
which means you can use however many you need for your own story. Unlike the
drow, these guys can get new recruits from the constant influx of assholes who
arrive at their territory looking to join.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final stand should definitely involve the three leaders at the same time. If
anything would force them to work together again it’s a bunch of heroes who have
systematically dismantled the rest of their gang.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/10/raven-roost-bandits.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/10/raven-roost-bandits.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Ragewind</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-ragewind.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ragewinds first appeared in Third Edition, and make their Fourth Edition debut
here. They’re mostly generic, with some added hooks for the Vale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also known as sword spirits, ragewinds are undead monsters that can form in
battlefields. They’re made up of the spirits of despondent soldiers who believe
they died for nothing. These shades are individually weak, but they have the
ability to move the weapons they wielded in life. A ragewind arises when many of
these indignant ghosts join to form a single composite entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ragewinds can lie dormant to appear as a random pile of old weapons. When
active, they assume the whirlwind form you can see in the illustration. They can
understand Common and modulate their wind to speak it, but they’re true monsters
and are only interested in killing living people who stray too close to
them. When destroyed, they release the pent-up anger and hatred inside them,
which might cause their enemies to turn against each other. These creatures
carry no treasure save the weapons that make up their form. They might also be
hanging around something worth digging up, acting as accidental guardians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nentir Vale region doesn’t just contain the ruins of a number of old
civilizations - it was also the site of many of their battles. Bloodspear Orcs
against Nerathi, Nerathi against the Hill Folk or the dragons of the Dawnforges,
Arkhosia against Bael Turath, elves vs. drow, and perhaps others that have been
lost to time. Any of these places might house a number of very old ragewinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ragewind is a Large Natural Animate with the Undead tag, and a Level 18
Skirmisher with 112 HP. It has an amazing ground speed of 10 and a flight speed
of 5, and perceives the world through Blindsight 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a literal weapon whirlwinds, a ragewind projects a &lt;strong&gt;Slashing Aura&lt;/strong&gt; (1) that
inflicts 10 damage on enemies caught inside, or 15 when it’s bloodied. Its
&lt;strong&gt;All-Around Defense&lt;/strong&gt; means it doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks when moving,
and it’s under a permanent &lt;strong&gt;Freedom of Movement&lt;/strong&gt; effect that ends any slowing
or immobilizing effects on the creature at the start of its turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is named &lt;strong&gt;Weapon Fury&lt;/strong&gt;, which does physical damage and also
gives the ragewind 10 temporary HP if it’s bloodied. It can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Rush of
Blades&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver to shift 5 squares and use Weapon Fury at any point during the
movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By expanding itself a bit the ragewind can make a &lt;strong&gt;Steel Whirlwind&lt;/strong&gt; attack
(recharge 5+), which attacks a Close Burst 1 and does more damage than a basic
attack, half on a miss. If the creature is bloodied the area is a Close Burst 2
instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it dies, the ragewind triggers its &lt;strong&gt;Death’s Rage&lt;/strong&gt; ability, which attacks
the Will of every enemy in a Close Burst 5 and, if it hits, forces the target to
make a basic attack against its nearest ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are dangerous physical combatants who are hard to pin down and can really
punish PC groups who like close formations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the location of any of the Vale’s ragewinds was known, they’d probably be the
stuff of legends told all over. It’s quite likely that they’re unknown because
no one who met one has lived to tell the tale. With a speed of 10, they’re
almost impossible to outrun even on horseback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the NPC factions we saw so far have a relatively high chance of running
into these things, because they spend their time digging up old ruins and
battlefields: Dythan’s Legion, the Gray Company, the Hunter Spiders. Y’know, our
usual suspects. I imagine this would happen as the climax of their story arcs,
as they’re just about to find what they’re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/01/ragewind.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/03/01/ragewind.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Threats to the Nentir Vale: Phantom Brigade</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-tnv-phantom-brigade.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/tnv/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new group, and a surprise lesson on Nerath’s history!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far we’ve only got the bare minimum of information on the history and
geography of Nerath as a whole. We mostly know that the Vale was part of its
northern frontier, that it did a number on the Vale’s native peoples when it
moved in, and that it fell about a hundred years ago. This entry gives lots of
new information because the history of the Phantom Brigade is intimately tied to
that of the empire of Nerath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Empire of Nerath was founded in the distant south around six hundred years
ago, with the establishment its capital city of Nera. It quickly spread in all
directions and became a world power. Its long history starts with an early
period of rapid expansion, goes through the troubled and despotic rule of
Emperor Magroth, and then through a long period of hegemonic peace and
stability. This peace lasted until the empire’s abrupt fall about 100 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one knows exactly how the fall of Nerath happened (or, if they do, they’re
keeping it a secret). What is known is that a combination of traumatic events
that might have included both monster attacks and natural disasters left the
entire imperial family unaccounted for. Nerath’s armies were left leaderless and
without direction, and all the simmering conflicts between its noble houses blew
up with no one to keep them in line. Soon the complex infrastructure that united
all regions of the empire stopped being maintained and crumbled, turning its
cities and provinces into the scattered points of light we know today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerath had several knightly orders at the time of its fall, and none where more
prestigious than the Knights of the Empire. Imperial Knights were paladins and
rangers selected for their skill, loyalty, and nobility of character. They
answered directly to the Emperor, acting as his personal bodyguards and
extensions of his will. When everything went to ruin, they were one of the few
groups who remained committed to defending the empire and keeping it
whole. Nearly all of them died in the decade between the initial catastrophe and
the day everyone finally acknowledged Nerath was no more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This did not stop the Knights, however. The oaths that bound them to the order
were more than just pretty words. They included a mysterious magical effect or
curse that eventually made the dead Knights return as ghosts. This started
happening decades after the fall. Though the Knights know their empire has
fallen, they are still compelled to seek the honor they could not gain in life,
and fulfill their oaths as best they can. They are now known as the Phantom
Brigade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first recorded appearance of the ghost knights was right here on the Vale,
when three of them were spotted racing through the Gardbury Downs. In our
narrative present they can be seen anywhere the hand of Nera used to reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knights look much as they did in life, though ghostly and translucent. This
means you have a very important decision to make. Is the Nazgul-looking fellow
in the illustration a typical Knight, or is he Sir Georg Edgelord, who is an
outlier and should not be counted? Your answer will say very interesting things
about Nerath either way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their weapons bear the emblem of the Threefold Crown of Nerath, unmistakably
marking their bearers as Knights of the Empire. Those weapons and also serve as
the receptacle for their souls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though we saw in previous entries that Nerath did some pretty horrible shit in
the past, the Knights seem genuinely concerned about upholding its highest
ideals and their original oaths, even though they’re ghosts. They will not
attack random travelers unprovoked and will probably be enthusiastic allies
in the fight against threats to the Vale if they can be convinced of the need
for this alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, they can still come into conflict with the PCs if they try to trespass
upon the areas the Knights still protect (which are full of juicy
treasure-filled Nerathi ruins). In these cases a fight might be avoided if the
PCs can present the Knights with a genuine writ of passage or Nerathi signet
ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phantom Brigade members are Medium Shadow Humanoids with the Undead tag. Most of
them are former humans. They have Darkvision and immunity to disease and poison,
but lack the usual resistances and vulnerabilities. They have ground speeds of
6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ghosts, our knights have both Insubstantial and Phasing. Only force damage
will deal full damage to them, and since they don’t have additional
vulnerabilities the trait can’t be temporarily shut down. They do tend to have
less HP than a typical monster of their level, which somewhat compensates for
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their unique signature trait is &lt;strong&gt;Unrelenting Brigade&lt;/strong&gt;. Whenever an ally who
also has this trait drops to 0 HP within 5 squares of the knight, they gain a +2
to-hit bonus until the end of their next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every single stat block in this entry has Lawful Good as its Alignment, a rarity
in monster and NPC stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Level-wise, the Phantom Brigade can be a threat from the mid-Heroic to the mid
Paragon-tier, putting them on the same bracket as, say, the Gray Company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phantom-brigade-squire&quot;&gt;Phantom Brigade Squire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squires are Level 6 Minion Soldiers. They can attack with their &lt;strong&gt;Soulbound
Short Swords&lt;/strong&gt; and their &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Crossbows&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which deal psychic
damage. If an enemy hits an ally adjacent to the squire with a melee attack,
they can use &lt;strong&gt;Shielding Martyr&lt;/strong&gt; to become the target of that attack instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phantom-brigade-armiger&quot;&gt;Phantom Brigade Armiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armigers are Level 7 Brutes with 71 HP. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Soulbound Bardiches&lt;/strong&gt;
that deal psychic damage, and their charges use the &lt;strong&gt;Charging Rebuke&lt;/strong&gt; special
attack that deals the same amount of damage, push the target 1 square, and knock
it prone. They can also make &lt;strong&gt;Furious Sweeps&lt;/strong&gt; to attack everyone in a Close
Blast 2 for slightly less damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phantom-brigade-justiciar&quot;&gt;Phantom Brigade Justiciar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Level 7 Skirmishers have 54 HP and project an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Blind
Justice&lt;/strong&gt; that inflicts a -2 to-hit penalty on enemies caught inside. They fight
with &lt;strong&gt;Soulbound Hammers&lt;/strong&gt; that can be used in melee or thrown, and they can
&lt;strong&gt;Evade and Strike&lt;/strong&gt; at will. This ends any marks on them, lets them shift 4
squares, and then make a basic melee attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phantom-brigade-banneret&quot;&gt;Phantom Brigade Banneret&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannerets are likely minor officers, since their name means “one who carries a
banner”. They’re Level 8 Soldiers with the Leader tag and 60 HP. Their phantom
banner projects a &lt;strong&gt;Gift of Grace&lt;/strong&gt; aura (3) that grants a +5 bonus to saves to
allies inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banneret fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Soulbound Tulwar&lt;/strong&gt;, which does psychic and radiant
damage. As an effect, it also marks and slows the target for a turn. If a marked
enemy within 5 squares tries to make an attack that doesn’t target the banneret,
they can use &lt;strong&gt;Stalwart Restraint&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This always hits! It
immobilizes the target and inflicts 10 ongoing psychic damage on them (save ends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bannerets are quite danregous. Their attacks always do something and they’re a
lot more dangerous to ignore than your typical soldier monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phantom-brigade-templar&quot;&gt;Phantom Brigade Templar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These imposing undead paladins bring the Brigade into the paragon tier. They’re
Level 12 Controllers with 85 HP. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Soulbound Morningstars&lt;/strong&gt; that
deal psychic damage and slide 2 squares on a hit. They can attack at range with
&lt;strong&gt;Righteous Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; that deal cold and radiant damage, and also slow on a hit
(save ends). And they can use their &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Majesty&lt;/strong&gt; to attack enemies in
a Close Burst 1 and daze them for a turn on a hit. This recharges when they’re
first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phantom-brigade-knight-commander&quot;&gt;Phantom Brigade Knight-Commander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knight-Commanders are high-ranking officers, likely responsible for leading all
Imperial Knights in a given region. They’re Level 14 Soldiers with the Leader
tag and 96 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their weapon of choice is a &lt;strong&gt;Keening Soulbound Backsword&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals psychic
and thunder damage and which marks the target for a turn as an effect. The sword
can be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Soul Strike&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge 5+) that deals more damage
and gives the knight-commander 10 temporary HP. The commander can also attack
enemies in a Close Burst 1 by repeating the &lt;strong&gt;Oath of Nerath&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets
Fortitude and deals psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy within 2 squares that’s marked by the commander chooses to ignore
the mark, the commander can use &lt;strong&gt;Call to Arms&lt;/strong&gt; to allow an ally within 5
squares to shift 3 spaces and make a free basic attack against the triggering
enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If my assumption back in the first paragraph is correct, there’s a
Knight-Commander in the Vale. The book doesn’t give any information about that
individual, so you’re free to come up with their backstory and description
yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out undead in 4e don’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be evil! The magic binding these knights
to the world could still be quite bad, but it has not affected their souls or
personalities. Still, as mentioned, they might end up fighting PCs who insist on
exploring former Nerathi sites the knights consider to be under their
protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very interested in what might happen if the Gray Company or one of their
Nerathi revivalist rivals runs into the Phantom Brigade. I imagine that anyone
who meets with the knights’ approval will have the legitimacy of their claims
greatly bolstered… but I also imagine that Halvath Cormarrin would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have
their approval. On the other hand, the Knight-Commander’s sword is likely the
weapon Cormarrin is after, because that’s an easy and fun connection to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things will turn out very differently it Cormarrin does in fact have a way to
compel the Phantom Brigade to be loyal to him. This could be the thing that
catapults the Gray Company into a paragon-tier threat. In that case, making the
Knights turn against him would be a key step in defeating their imperialist
aims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want the Phantom Brigade to be evil after all, you can use their stats
exactly as they are presented and only change their alignment and behavior. You
can also add some Death Knights to their number, since they are also evil undead
knights with their souls bound to their weapons. You might say those are members
of the order who managed to retain their physical bodies after all this time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/02/23/phantom-brigade.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/02/23/phantom-brigade.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
