<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 18:36:55 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 18:36:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Myconids</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-myconid.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids have been in the game since AD&amp;amp;D as one of its most famous “novelty
humanoids”. They make their 4e debut here in the MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids are sapient fungal humanoids who originated in the Feywild. The
fomorians did &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; to them in the distant past, and they still bear the
scars of that corruption. In our narrative present they can be found in deep
caves or the Underdark both in the world and in the Feywild. Their preferred
environment are underground mushroom forests that provide them with a complete
ecosystem to live in, but they also have an instinctive need to multiply and
spread and so can be found in less ideal conditions as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids communicate by releasing special spores laced with emotions and
sensations, which only other myconids can understand. Only one individual in
each of their colonies, known as the “Sovereign”, can communicate with outsiders
through telepathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mushroom-people aren’t evil, but their expansionist instinct, difficulty
with communication, and the fact that they live in the friggin’ &lt;em&gt;Underdark&lt;/em&gt;
means they tend to engage in conflict with anyone they come across. They often
end up enslaved by drow, fomorians, and shadar-kai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peaceful interaction with myconids is predictably hard - you have to reach the
sovereign, which means infiltrating the heart of their territory or letting
yourself be captured and hoping they take you there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids are Fey Humanoids with the Plant keyword. Sovereigns are Large,
everyone else is Medium. They have Tremorsense 10, which allows them to operate
well in total darkness. Their signature trait is &lt;strong&gt;Roots of the Colony&lt;/strong&gt;, a free
action that triggers when they’re hit by an attack and allows them to split half
the damage between themselves and a myconid ally within 5 squares. Given they’re
level 3-4, this is likely to be the party’s first encounter with something
resistant to focus fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;myconid-rotpriest&quot;&gt;Myconid Rotpriest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconid culture isn’t well-understood enough for people to know if they worship
something, but rotpriests kinda fulfill the “healer” role usually taken up by
clerics in other species. They do so in a much more self-sacrificing way,
though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rotpriests are Level 3 Brutes with the Leader keyword and 48 HP. They have a
speed of 5, and Regeneration 5 that can be temporarily disabled by radiant
damage. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;stipe staffs&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and can also release
&lt;strong&gt;decomposing sprays&lt;/strong&gt; to deal necrotic damage in a Close Burst 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have Roots of the Colony like every other myconid, and when another myconid
uses this ability to deal damage to them, rotpriests can use &lt;strong&gt;Sacrifice for the
Colony&lt;/strong&gt; to take all of the damage from the trigerring attack instead of just
half. The idea is that they then heal this using their regeneration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they finally get killed, they release a &lt;strong&gt;Life Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that heals every
living creature in a Close Burst 1 for 10 HP. This includes both monsters and
PCs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;myconid-sovereign&quot;&gt;Myconid Sovereign&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each colony has one of these acting as its leader. As mentioned before,
sovereigns are the only myconids with any ability to communicate with
outsiders. They’re Level 4 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 58 HP. If
forced into a fight they can defend themselves with &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; and with a variety
of interesting spore bursts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default &lt;strong&gt;Spore Burst&lt;/strong&gt; is a close blast 3 that targets the Will of
nonplants and deals poison damage. There’s also &lt;strong&gt;Commanding Spores&lt;/strong&gt;, which
allows a plant ally within 5 squares to shift 1 square. Sounds like a waste of a
standard action, but it can set up some interesting flanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Sovereign should stay a bit away from the main scrum, spraying it with its
spore pesticides and helping keep the PCs surrounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;myconid-guard&quot;&gt;Myconid Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it’s the last monster in the entry, guards are likely to be the most
numerous foes the party meets. They’re the rank and file of the colony’s
protectors. Guards are Level 4 Soldiers with 56 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;spiny strikes&lt;/strong&gt; from their fists, and can release
&lt;strong&gt;pacification spores&lt;/strong&gt; in a close burst 1 that target enemies’ Wills, do poison
damage, and prevent those hit from taking standard actions during their next
turns. Fortunately, this is only an encounter power. Roots of the Colony is the
last trick on their arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front-liners are going to have a bit of a bad time facing down myconid guards,
since the guards can stagger their spore releases to keep the PCs from attacking
for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myconids can live in any place that provides good conditions to mundane fungi,
such as damp caverns, surface forests, and so on. Encounters with them can
involve any wildlife that also lives in these places, either as “third parties”
or perhaps as pets if the wildlife is also fungal. They can also be found
alongside the several people who enslave their colonies, though in that case you
might need to perform some level adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are an all-myconid party that has just ran into a
deathjump spider (level 3); a pair of myconid guards minding an arbalester for
their bosses near a patch of green slime (level 4); and a geonid accompanied by
a pair of rust monsters and another of rotpriests (level 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these mushroom people, and I like making then relatively friendly once
the PCs manage to breach the communications gap.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/myconid.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/myconid.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Marut</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-marut.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth edition Maruts debuted in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/07/03/marut.html&quot;&gt;first Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;, as enigmatic
mercenaries from the Astral Sea that demanded future favors as payment for their
services and kept detailed ledgers of these in their astral fortresses. Here we
get a bit more lore about them, and three new stat blocks to go with the two
from the first MM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM2 bits of lore seem to have been written by a different author from the
first, and this second author seems to have time-traveled from 3e or 2e. It
talks a lot about Maruts being interested in “the upholding of oaths and
contracts” in the abstract, which doesn’t really match the first book. Yes,
they’re very interested in this stuff, but only when the oaths made &lt;em&gt;by them&lt;/em&gt; or
&lt;em&gt;to them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also another bit that says they consider themselves to be “astral
spirits of the air”, and despite the convoluted justification accompanying this
I don’t think the Astral Sea is a place with strong elemental associations
either way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more interesting bit is the one that says Maruts aren’t an unified block -
they’re divided into groups called “cadres” that hold slighty different
philosophies. Each cadre has their own fortress and interacts with other
sapients in more or less the same way, but I guess they differ in what they’re
stockpiling those favors for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some cadres have started calling in a few of their favors and demanding periods
of indentured servitude from people. Maruts don’t mistreat their servants, but
they’re still demanding and humorless bosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maruts in this entry are Medium Immortal Humanoids. They have Truesight out
to 10 squares, a ground speed of 8, and flight and teleport speeds of 4. They’re
immune to sleep and have Resist Thunder 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the stat blocks in this entry are described as “hunting down those who
oppose marut law”, which again doesn’t quite make sense. Pretty much every Marut
will hunt and fight someone who backed out of a deal with them, so instead of
repeating this I’ll speculate about what someone might hire these new varieties
for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marut-castigator&quot;&gt;Marut Castigator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castigators make good bounty hunters, since they’re good at preventing their
target from running away. They’re Level 21 Skirmishers with 146 HP and all
standard traits. They wield a double sword in combat, and have access to thunder
and lightning-themed magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;double sword&lt;/strong&gt; attack can deal physical or lightning damage, at
the marut’s discretion. They can also make &lt;strong&gt;Double Attacks&lt;/strong&gt; with it, but not
all the time (recharge 4+).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prevent someone from running, they can use the &lt;strong&gt;Punisher’s Lash&lt;/strong&gt;, a Reach 2
vs. Reflex spell that deals weak lightning damage, slows, and prevents the
target from teleporting for a turn. If the target still tries to run, they can
give chase with a &lt;strong&gt;Thunderbolt Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to teleport 4
squares and make a basic attack with bonus damage afterwards. This recharges
when they hit with the two strikes from a double attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marut-prosecutor&quot;&gt;Marut Prosecutor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objection! Prosecutors are probably pretty good at that very role during an
actual trial, with their epic levels of Insight and Intimidate. They can also
use magic to infuse their words with the leaden weight of the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors are Level 21 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 147 HP. They
can punch people with &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; that do bonus thunder damage and slow (save
ends), but their judicial magic is their greatest asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action they can issue a &lt;strong&gt;Dictum&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that
does no damage and immobilizes (save ends). They can also use a minor action to
mark someone with a &lt;strong&gt;Sigil of Indictment&lt;/strong&gt;  (ranged 10 vs. Will), which also
does no damage but forces the marked victim to grant combat advantage to the
prosecutor and take 5 extra psychic damage from all attacks directed at it. This
lasts for a turn and can be sustained, but only one target can bear the Sigil at
a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the prosecutor can take a bit more time and spend a standard action to
harangue someone with a &lt;strong&gt;Biting Testimony&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 10, targets one enemy,
vs. Will). This deals psychic damage, and inflicts a -2 penalty on all of the
target’s attacks, skill checks, and ability checks (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means prosecutors call the shots during a fight, marking someone
with the Sigil and having their allies focus fire on the victim, which they’ll
try to immobilize with Dictums. Dictums can also be used to prevent defenders
from helping a focused squishy. “Close Burst X; targets one enemy” is just a
terse way of saying that power is a ranged attack that doesn’t draw OAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marut-executioner&quot;&gt;Marut Executioner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An executioner is who you call when you need an obstacle removed. When they’re
not doing that, they’re out collecting debts owed to their cadre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executioners are Level 22 Brutes with 205 HP. They wield &lt;strong&gt;Double Axes&lt;/strong&gt; that
does bonus thunder damage, knocks prone on a critical, and can be used in
several other maneuvers. &lt;strong&gt;Slayer’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) allows them to attack
everyone in a Close Burst 1; &lt;strong&gt;Warranted Stroke&lt;/strong&gt; targets a bloodied enemy, does
a ton of damage, always knocks prone, and gives the executioner 1 action point
if it drops the target to 0 HP or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also issue an &lt;strong&gt;Execution Call&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter, a Close Blast 5
that targets enemies’ Fortitude, does thunder damage, and pulls them adjacent to
the executioner. A miss here still does half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the mechanics of these new Maruts, but I dislike the throwback to 3e lore
here. Law is not a universal cosmic principle in 4e!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters have marut mercenary squads accompanying a djinn (level
21) or a trio of rakshasa knights (level 23).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/marut.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/marut.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Mammoth</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-mammoth.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cribbing from paleonthology is one of the classic ways to add interesting
monsters to your D&amp;amp;D world. Dinosaurs are the obvious choice, but there’s also a
bunch of post-dinosaur megafauna that can be slotted in with no problem at
all. Among that set, mammoths are some of the most famous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like the Monster Manual 2 only had one page to dedicate to them, though,
so it decided to skip mundane mammoths altogether and give us a fantastical
variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nyfellar-mammoth&quot;&gt;Nyfellar Mammoth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are native to Nyfell, the same frozen realm in the Elemental
Chaos from which frost giants originally came. They’re partially made of ice,
and subsist on a combination of organic food and ice, so they thrive in the most
inhospitable frozen hells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frost giants have long ago tamed Nyfellar mammoths for use as mounts, and were
responsible for bringing them to the world, where they can still be seen filling
that role. I imagine it’s also possible to find wild specimens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nyfellar Mammoths are Huge Elemental Beasts with the Mount keyword, and Level 17
Brutes with 202 HP. They have Resist Cold 10 and a respectable ground speed of 8
with Ice Walk, which allows them to ignore “icy” difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also possess the same &lt;strong&gt;Icebound Footing&lt;/strong&gt; trait that’s common among frost
giants, reducing any forced movement inflicted on them by 2 squares, and getting
a free save to avoid being knocked prone. They fight with their tusks and big
feet in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tusks are Reach 2 and can either &lt;strong&gt;gore&lt;/strong&gt; as a basic attack or perform a
&lt;strong&gt;Tusk Toss&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) that targets Fortitude, does a little less damage
and slides the target 5 squares. At the end of the slide the target falls from a
height of 30 feed on the destination square, so it really is a toss. The fall
does damage (and can be mitigated) according to the standard rules for falling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feet can &lt;strong&gt;stamp&lt;/strong&gt;, a Reach 1 attack that targets fortitude, does about same
damage as a gore, and knocks prone. The mammoth can also execute a &lt;strong&gt;Blizzard
Trample&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver to move 8 squares, go through enemy spaces, and stamp each of
those enemies. This recharges when the mammoth is bloodied, or when it takes
cold damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If used as a mount, the mammoth can employ a &lt;strong&gt;Bitterwind Charge&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows
it to use a Tusk Toss &lt;em&gt;or a Blizzard Trample&lt;/em&gt; when charging. Yeah, it moves 8
squares then tramples for another 8 in a single standard action. After this
special attack concludes, the rider gets to make a free melee basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is a level 17 frost giant patrol, with 2 giants riding
nyfellar mammoths and accompanied by a rimefire griffon acting as a spotter. The
book notes that giants like to play badminton with PCs by readying actions to
attack victims of Tusk Toss as they fly by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ice mammoths are pretty cool, and I can see why they preferred to include
them over the mundane variety. They have a good synergy with frost giants, which
also debut in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could pretty easily derive a mundane mammoth from the nyfellar stat block,
making it level 10-13 and removing some of the more blatant elemental
abilities. Maybe they could be used as hill giant or ogre mounts then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/mammoth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/11/mammoth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nordlond Bestiary Kickstarter!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gaming Ballistic is about to launch a campaign for the Nordlond Bestiary, and
you can go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; to click a button and be notified of when that
happens. Everyone always says GURPS really needs a good bestiary. Well, here’s
one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributing to Kickstarter campaigns is a bit hard for me, as my bank dislikes
it and tries to cancel my credit card whenever I do it. But if that’s not a
problem for you, by all means click that button. I’ll be here waiting for the
book’s final launch to buy myself a copy in the traditional way :).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/05/nordlond-bestiary.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/05/nordlond-bestiary.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>kickstarter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Lycanthrope</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual had a Lycanthrope entry containing wererats and
werewolves. Here in the second one we get stats for more types, as well as a bit
of additional lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve covered a lot of the basic lore of lycanthropes in the [original
article][2], so please read that. This entry adds a couple of other tidbits. The
first one says that a lycanthrope’s natural form is the “beast-person” one. The
other says that lycanthropes are Melora’s creations, and that the reason they’re
affected by silver and the full moon is because of an ancient feud between
Melora and Sehanine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4e lycanthropes aren’t really forced to change in the full moon, so that’s not a
big deal, but silver can shut down their regeneration. Like in the first MM, all
the stat blocks we get here have “Evil” in their alignment, though there’s no
real lore reason for all of lycanthropes to be evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lycanthropes are natural humanoids, and the two we see here are
Large. Obviously, they have the Shapechanger keyword. They have low light vision
and a ground speed of 6 in either humanoid form or 8 in animal form. Switching
forms is a minor action for them, giving them plenty of flexibility in a
fight. They have regeneration, which shuts down for a turn when they’re wounded
by silver weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Victims damaged by a lycanthrope’s natural attacks while it’s in animal form are
exposed to a disease specified alongside their stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wereboar&quot;&gt;Wereboar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-lycanthrope-wereboar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wereboars are described as brutish and easily angered. Some of them like to hang
out in places where a fight is likely to break out, such as in rowdy taverns and
underground fight clubs. They love to fight in their animal form, and getting
wounded only makes them angrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat block presented here is a Level 6 Brute with 61 HP and all traits
listed above. Its regeneration is 5. He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;maul&lt;/strong&gt; in human form and
&lt;strong&gt;gores&lt;/strong&gt; with his tusks in boar form. The tusks also inflict ongoing damage and
transmit moontusk fever, the wereboar disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When bloodied, the wereboar gains a +2 to all defenses and doubles the amount of
ongoing damage its tusks deal. And when it hits 0 HP, it can make one last basic
attack before dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moontusk fever is a level 6 disease with an “Improve” DC of 17 and a “maintain”
DC of 12, and it fucks you up while you’re bloodied. Stage 1 inflicts a -2
penalty so taves while the victim is bloodied. Stage 2 limits them to one save
at the end of their turn even if they’re affected by multiple save-ends
effects. And the final stage gives you 5e disadvantage on that single save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disease isn’t directly lethal, but it’s a major inconvenience given how
common saves are in this game. I imagine the actual level of the disease and its
DCs should be equal to the level of the wereboar, if you’re changing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;weretiger&quot;&gt;Weretiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-lycanthrope-weretiger.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weretigers are a marked contrast to their porcine relatives, being much sneakier
and more opportunistic than them in a fight. If they become convinced they need
to fight, they’ll stalk their adversary and strike in the most opportune
moment. Their fighting style is highly mobile and cautious in any of their
forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weretigers are Level 11 Elite Skirmishers with 172 HP and Regeneration 10. They
fight with paired &lt;strong&gt;katars&lt;/strong&gt; in humanoid form, and with &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; in tiger
form. The katars are high-crit weapons and do more damage, but the bite
transmits a disease called moon rage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weretiger can &lt;strong&gt;pounce&lt;/strong&gt; when it charges, dealing more damage than a basic
attack and knocking the target prone on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Feline Fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make
two basic attacks with a shift between them, and &lt;strong&gt;Slashing Recoil&lt;/strong&gt; allows them
to make a free basic attack when someone misses them in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this lycanthrope is stronger in humanoid form, there’s still some
incentive to bite the PCs and expose as many of them as possible to moon
rage. This is a disease that turns the victim’s hands into tiger paws! At stage
1 the partial change inflicts a -2 penalty on all attacks. At Stage 2 they gain
a Strength-based claw attack that deals 1d6+STR bonus damage, but can no longer
hold any weapons or implements. And at the final stage their mind is saddled
with predatory instincts that prevent them from switching targets in combat
until their current target is dead. At level 11, the Improve DC is 21 and the
Maintain DC is 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;werewolf-lord&quot;&gt;Werewolf Lord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bigger, stronger, smarter werewolf, usually found leading a whole clan
of lycanthropes. They’re also known as “pack lords”. They’re mostly werewolves
with bigger numbers, but they also have some useful leadership powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lord is a Level 13 Elite Brute with 264 HP and Regeneration 10. They project
a Blood Moon aura (5) that gives allies inside +2 to attacks and +5 to damage
against bloodied targets. They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;falchion&lt;/strong&gt; in humanoid form and
with &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; in wolf form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sword is a High-Crit weapon, and the bite transmits an enhnaced form of moon
frenzy. &lt;strong&gt;Canine Fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make 2 basic attacks per action, and
&lt;strong&gt;Speed of the Wolf&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to shift 6 squares and bite when in wolf
form. Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Savage Howl&lt;/strong&gt; grants 15 temporary HP to every ally within 10
squares and allows them to make free bite attacks if they have any to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greater Moon Frenzy is pretty much werewolf rabies, attacking the nervous
system. Stage 1 is a -2 penalty to Will. Stage 2 has the victim make a save at
the end of each turn to retain control of their actions. A failure means they
must attack a random target within 5 squares or move in a random direction if
there are no targets available. Stage 3 removes the save: the victim must attack
the closest creature in sight or move in random directions until it finds
any. As presented the disease is level 13, with an Improve DC of 23 and a
Maintain DC of 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that the lycanthrope diseases for the wereboar and weretiger are more
inconvenient than lethal. A common complaint about 4e diseases is that they’re
not very dangerous once the party gets access to the Remove Affliction ritual,
which can happen from level 6 onwards. This is true, but curing afflictions can
still spend time, money, and healing surges that would be useful elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By having somewhat less dangerous diseases, wereboars and tigers paradoxically
incentivize players to put up with them for a little longer and try to recover
from them using the standard disease rules. So what if your saves suck when
you’re bloodied? Just don’t get bloodied until you can return to town and
recover!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: A human hexer, 2 half-orc hunters, and 2 wereboars. It’s either a big
brawl in progress, or a group of rowdies looking to start one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 12: An eladrin bladesinger, a will-o’-wisp, and 2 weretigers. Fey of a
dark disposition who enjoy playing boogeymen and waylaying travelers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: A werewolf lord, 3 standard werewolves, and 2 worgs. A powered-up
version of the typical werewolf-led bandit gang.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/29/lycanthrope.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/29/lycanthrope.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Lizardfolk</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-lizardfolk.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already looked at &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/06/23/lizardfolk.html&quot;&gt;lizardfolk&lt;/a&gt; during our reading of the first Monster
Manual and the Monster Vault. As we saw before, there are several different
ethnicities of lizardfolk. The first MM had the human-sized “greenscales” and
the larger “blackscales”. The Vault also contained a “poisonscale” type, which
turns out to have debuted here in the MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poisonscale lizardfolk have a smaller and slighter build than greenscales,
though they’re still Medium. To make up for their lack of brute strength, they
developed a kind of internal alchemy: by eating certain specific plants, they
can sweat poison. They usually apply this poison to their weapons, but some
poisonscales like to apply it directly to their enemies by wrestling with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore in this entry is more focused on the individual stat blocks than on
overall lizardfolk culture, so presumably everything that was said in the first
Monster Manual still applies here. The stat blocks themselves are different
enough from what we got in the MV to be worth discussing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All lizardfolk in this entry are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Swamp Walk
ability, allowing them to ignore swampy difficult terrain. They also usually do
something poison-related, though the specifics vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poisonscale-magus&quot;&gt;Poisonscale Magus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These spellcasters specialize in toxic magic. They occupy positions as honored
advisers in poisonscale communities, but this power and respect comes at a
cost. Their own magic poisons them, and shortens their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magi are Level 2 Artillery with 32 HP and speed 6, carrying &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; into
battle for use as implements and in emergencies. All of their spells target
Fortitude, so they’re a threat to your squishies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight a magus is likely to open up with a &lt;strong&gt;Poison Barrage&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) an
area burst attack that deals poison damage and inflicts Vulnerable 5 Poison on
thise it hits (save ends). A miss does half damage and inflicts the
vulnerability for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they’ll target individual vulnerable enemies with &lt;strong&gt;Poison Blood&lt;/strong&gt;, a
ranged spell that deals immediate and ongoing poison damage (save ends). As a
minor action it can also use &lt;strong&gt;Corrupt Poison&lt;/strong&gt;, a ranged spell that slides
someone suffering from ongoing poison damage 3 squares and slows them (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are enough interesting interactions here that the magus works more like a
fragile Controller than as Artillery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poisonscale-slitherer&quot;&gt;Poisonscale Slitherer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This represents your typical poisonscale warrior. Their slight build makes them
a bit cowardly, but they have good teamwork and their somewhat oversized tails
make them very stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slitherers are Level 2 Soldiers with 36 HP and speed 5. They carry &lt;strong&gt;spears&lt;/strong&gt;
for melee combat, and &lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt; for fighting at range. They prefer that last
one because it’s safer, and because their javelins are poisoned! This manifests
as a secondary attack against Fortitude, which does about double the damage of
the initial hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their ironically named &lt;strong&gt;slitherer bravery&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them a +2 attack bonus
when adjacent to at least one ally, and &lt;strong&gt;slitherer stability&lt;/strong&gt; makes them
immune to knockdowns and forced movement. That’s surprisingly powerful for a
level 2 soldier, and makes them an excellent wizard counter-measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poisonscale-savage&quot;&gt;Poisonscale Savage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This warrior doesn’t bother with fiddly stuff like poisoning weapons or personal
hygiene. It slaps enemies with its tail to cover them in poisoned sweat, and
them clubs them to death while they’re weakened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The savage is a Level 2 Brute with 45 HP and speed 6. It will probably start the
fight with the single &lt;strong&gt;javelin&lt;/strong&gt; it carries, which damages and inflicts ongoing
poison damage because it’s all sweaty. After that it attacks with a
&lt;strong&gt;greatclub&lt;/strong&gt;, and can slap with its &lt;strong&gt;tail&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action. The tail does
no damage, but inflicts ongoing 5 poison damage on a hit (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poisonscale-collector&quot;&gt;Poisonscale Collector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectors are responsible for gathering the special plants that allow
poisonscales to produce their poison. This means they’re also trained
herbalists and alchemists. They’re Level 3 Lurkers with 36 HP and speed 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectors are armed with &lt;strong&gt;Daggers&lt;/strong&gt;, which do physical and ongoing poison
damage. Once an enemy is taking ongoing poison damage from this or any other
source, the collector can do several unpleasant things to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, the &lt;strong&gt;Poison Strike&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait gives them a +2 damage bonus
against poisoned targets. &lt;strong&gt;Blinding Poison&lt;/strong&gt; is a spell that targets a poisoned
creature’s Fortitude, dealing damage and blinding them on a hit (save ends). And
&lt;strong&gt;End Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is a stab that targets someone who can’t see the collector and
does a bunch of physical damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is one of those lurkers who can do something harmful to the PCs every
turn, though it takes a bit longer to activate its ultimate attack. That process
can be sped up if it has additional buddies who can inflict ongoing poison
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poisonscale-myrmidon&quot;&gt;Poisonscale Myrmidon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A veteran warrior, fighting in a more disciplined manner with a club and a
shield. It’s a Level 3 Soldier with 47 HP and speed 6. Its only attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and marks on a hit, but it also has the collector’s
&lt;strong&gt;Poison Strike&lt;/strong&gt; trait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myrmidons can’t poison enemies themselves, so they rely on the support of other
allies who can. They’re good to pad the ranks of an all-poisonscale force,
though you’re probably better off using lizardfolk from the other books if you
have a mixed force or want more interesting mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poison theming here is interesting, and several of these stat blocks don’t
get repeated in the Vault, so it’s worth it to update them. As long as you avoid
the extra-xenophobic lore in the Vault, its stat blocks are good.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/29/lizardfolk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/29/lizardfolk.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on LANCER Against the Giants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember reading a few play reports about a campaign titled “Mecha Against the
Giants” a few years ago. It was run by Mark Langsdorf, using GURPS as a rule
system, and it was vaguely inspired by the Against the Giants modules for AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these days, I really want to run something like that using LANCER. As of
this writing I definitely don’t have the bandwidth for it, but I just thought it
would be nice to write it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lancer-against-the-giants&quot;&gt;LANCER: Against the Giants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armies of Giants invade, out of nowhere and for seemingly no reason!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their relentless assaults threaten to destroy “smallfolk” civilization!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realm’s bravest heroes have fallen against their foe’s overwhelming strength
and numbers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desperate, the King’s wizards and priests spend the last of their power in a
rituat. It purpose: to summon someone, &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; from across the vastness of
existance that has the power to stop the destruction!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They succeed in bringing the 2021st Union Auxiliary Squadron. Your squadron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount up, Lancer, and end this war!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fight off attacking giants and their pet giant monsters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discover the mystery behind these invasions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find a way to end this war that &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; involve genocide, because we’re better
than Gygax!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, at the end of it all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ATTACK AND DETHRONE LOLTH&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/25/musings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/25/musings.html</guid>
        
        <category>lancer</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Krenshar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-krenshar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first saw a krenshar in the 3e Monster Manual, though it’s possible they
originated a bit earlier than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Krenshars are large carnivorous felines somewhat similar in size and behavior to
lions. They live in groups called prides, and use teamwork to hunt. Some
individuals within the pride grow to a larger size than the rest and possess a
pattern of blood red spots on their fur. These seem to have a higher social
position within the pride, and focus on protecting it from threats rather than
on everyday hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing that makes krenshars fantastical is their ability to peel back the
skin on their faces and expose their skulls in order to intimidate their enemies
and frighten their prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I agree a krenshar’s display must be quite a striking sight, your typical
PC is likely to have met quite a few things that are scarier than that even if
they’re relatively low level. This leads me to believe their threat display
might be augmented by natural fear magic, since it’s meant to be effective even
against adventurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gnolls, hobgoblins and humans frequently try to domesticate krenshars for all
the usual reasons. This is a difficult process because it’s hard to suppress
their threat display, so lots of trainers end up paralyzed by fear and killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re given two krenshar stat blocks here. Both are Medium Natural Beasts with a
land speed of 8 and low-light vision. They also have two signature abilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Fearsome Visage&lt;/strong&gt; is an aura (5) that inflicts a -2 penalty to saves
against fear effects to all enemies caught inside. &lt;strong&gt;Unnerving Skull&lt;/strong&gt; is a
minor action usable once per round. It’s a close burst 5 that targets the Will
of one enemy and inflicts a -2 attack penalty on a hit (save ends). This is
a fear power, so it’s enhanced by the aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;krenshar&quot;&gt;Krenshar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 4 Controller with 55 HP and all standard traits. Its
basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;hooking swipe&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and knocks prone on a hit. It
can combine its threat display with a roar to perform the &lt;strong&gt;Roaring Skull&lt;/strong&gt;
attack, a Close Blast 5 that targets Will and dazes (save ends). A target who is
already dazed is instead weakened for the duration of the daze, so there’s
benefit in several krenshars roaring at once. This recharges on a 5+, so it will
likely happen more than once in the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;krenshar-blood-slayer&quot;&gt;Krenshar Blood Slayer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red-spotted variety, focusing more on physical power than on scary
roars. It’s a Level 5 Brute with 75 HP and all standard traits. Its basic attack
is a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that is somewhat weak, but can be used twice per action. If both
attacks hit, the target is grabbed and the slayer can &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; it. Bites hit
automatically and do double the damage of a claw strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess your typical krenshar pack will include a mix of blood slayers and
standard krenshars. The krenshars open up with a “volley” of Roaring Skull
attacks, and then the blood slayers focus on grabbing dazed/weakened individuals
and biting them to death. Grabbing a squishy is always a good move, but it’s
also worth their while to try it with the defenders, since their bites don’t
care about AC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are a pair of deathpledged gnolls wrangling a pack of
krenshars (level 5), and a human slaver with a pair of javelin dancer goons and
a trio of blood slayers (level 6).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/24/krenshar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/24/krenshar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Vault 2: Kenku</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-kenku.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenku are raven-people, humanoid and human-sized but covered in feathers and
with raven heads. They organize themselves into clan-like groups called
flocks. Your typical kenku flock is tightly knit but very distrustful of
outsiders, including kenku from other flocks. Each flock follows no laws but
their own. Despite this, most of them live on or near major cities, and engage
in a variety of illegal activities to survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah. Crime birbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenku criminals tend to prefer non-violent activities such as grifts and cons,
where their natural ability to mimic sounds and voices comes in handy. They can
still fight pretty well if forced to. And despite the stereotyping they’re
typically Unaligned, which means it’s definitely possible to find nicer
individuals and flocks out there. Rural kenku can easily fill the same
“isolationist but ultimately nice” role as cliche elven villages, and an urban
flock could be predominantly performers or even a legitimate company for a nice
change of pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenku are Medium Natural Humanoids. They have low-light vision, a ground speed
of 6, and no innate flight speed despite being birds. They possess two
interesting signature abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flock Effect&lt;/strong&gt; makes them good at teamwork: they gain a +3 attack bonus when
flanking and grant a +3 when using Aid Another, instead of the usual +2 to both
activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mimicry&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to mimic any sound or voice. You have to win an opposed
roll of your Insight vs. their Bluff to realize the sound is fake. Not all kenku
in this entry are trained in Bluff, but the sneakier ones are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their levels are all in the early-to-mid Heroic tier, which in my mind means
they’d be about as common as elves or halflings. They get playable stats at the
end of this book, but I’m not sure if they ever got a full writeup later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kenku-ruffian&quot;&gt;Kenku Ruffian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your typical crime-birb-on-the-street is a Level 3 Minion Skirmisher. They only
have a basic &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt; attack and the universal signature abilities, so they’re
pretty much civilians despite the name “Ruffian”. If forced to fight they rely
on numbers to hold the line while one or two of them go get help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kenku-warrior&quot;&gt;Kenku Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formally trained in a mobile fighting style, the warrior uses paired daggers and
moves in a seemingly random pattern about the battlefield. Warriors are Level 3
Skirmishers with 44 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; can be used as melee or ranged attacks (they carry 6). The
&lt;strong&gt;Fluttering Attack&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver allows them to shift 4 squares and make a dagger
attack during the movement, and &lt;strong&gt;Combat Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; gives them a damage
bonus. They also have the universal traits, so combat advantage is even better
for them and they have an easy time acquiring it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kenku-ringleader&quot;&gt;Kenku Ringleader&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ringleaders lead small gangs of kenku in heists or raids, though they have
enough sense to sound a retreat if guards or rivals show up in force. They’re
Level 4 Soldiers with the Leader tag and 54 HP. They’re trained in Bluff and
and Intimidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a &lt;strong&gt;spiked chain&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and a &lt;strong&gt;sling&lt;/strong&gt; at range. The chain attack
is Reach 2 and marks on a hit. They &lt;strong&gt;Press the Attack&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver is a chain
strike that targets a marked enemy, does the usual damage, and knocks them prone
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have the two standard kenku traits, and they can use &lt;strong&gt;Flock Reaction&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor; recharge 4+) to allow every ally in a close burst 3 to shift 1
square. Perfect for allowing them to disengage and retreat, or finish setting up
a flanking maneuver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kenku-sneak&quot;&gt;Kenku Sneak&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first actual rogue in the crime birb entry, Sneaks are Level 4 Lurkers with
42 HP. They have a higher than usual speed of 7, and they fight with &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt;
both in melee and at range. They’re trained in Bluff, Stealth, and Thievery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, the Sneak engages with 4e’s Stealth rules, which dictate
when someone can make a Stealth check to become “hidden” during combat and how
fast they can move while hidden. I think that by default your speed is limited
to 2 in that case - move faster and you’re detected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenku sneaks have an advantage here in that they can move at speed 4 while
hidden. Their &lt;strong&gt;Disappear into the Flock&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows them to make those
Stealth checks while they have cover from other kenkus, &lt;strong&gt;Hidden Strike&lt;/strong&gt; gives
them a hefty chunk of extra damage if they attack from hiding, and &lt;strong&gt;Sniper&lt;/strong&gt;
allows them to remain hidden if they miss with a ranged attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tactics outlined by these traits are nifty. A sneak will always appear
accompanied by a number of warriors or a huge band of ruffians. They’ll hide
among the crowd and move it with, throwing daggers at the squishier PCs for big
damage from a safe distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kenku-wing-mage&quot;&gt;Kenku Wing Mage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though kenku are flightless, it seems they have a magic tradition that seeks to
correct that injustice. Wing mages practice this tradition, and as a result they
know a lot of air and force magic as well. They’re Level 5 Artillery with 50
HP. Wielding &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; as weapons and implements, wing mages fight with spells
that create wind and summon flocks of crows made of pure force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those force crows can be used in the &lt;strong&gt;Murder of Crows&lt;/strong&gt; at-will attack (Ranged
20 vs. Reflex) which does force damage and makes the target grant combat
advantage to the wing mage (save ends). They can also be used in the &lt;strong&gt;Death
Flock&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power (area burst 1 within 20 vs. Reflex) which does force
damage and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main keep-away spell is &lt;strong&gt;Hurricane Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Fortitude;
recharge 5+), which does force damage and slides targets 3 squares. And finally,
&lt;strong&gt;Wings of the Flock&lt;/strong&gt; (minor; encounter) gives them a flight speed of 6 until
the end of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wing mage is going to take off as soon as the fight starts, and will rain
force crows upon the PCs from a safe elevation. Most ranged magic has a range
smaller than 20, so the party better have some archers with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kenku-assassin&quot;&gt;Kenku Assassin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either an actual killer-for-hire or an elite combatant. Assassins love poison
and unlike most other kenku they rarely surrender. They’re Level 5 Elite
Skirmishers with 126 HP. They fight with envenomed &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; and a
&lt;strong&gt;shortbow&lt;/strong&gt; with envenomed arrows, both of which slow the enemy on a hit (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have the same Fluttering Attack as the warriors, and when attacked they can
use &lt;strong&gt;Gouging Talons&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to hit back. If surrounded, &lt;strong&gt;Feather
Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2; encounter) can automatically blind every enemy in the
area for a turn, allowing them to escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assassins prefer to stay at range, but once in melee they fight much like
warriors. Their “elite extra attack” is a reaction, so they have an incentive to
stay in the thick of it. Two of them, or one of them plus a squad of warriors,
makes for an interesting encounter where no one stands still. They also go well
with monsters that can exploit the “slowed” status, since they cause that at
will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have quite a few kenku encounters here, showcasing the sort of monster they
keep as pets and the sort of allies they make into honorary flock members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 2: 2 kenku warriors, 2 bloodseeker drakes, 1 pseudodragon. Hunters… or
bounty hunters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 3: 1 kenku ringleader, 8 ruffians, and 2 warriors. The whole gang’s
here!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 4: 1 human berserker, 1 ringleader, 6 ruffians, 2 sneaks. Another gang,
this one with an adopted member.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 5: 1 half-elf bandit captain, 2 human berserkers, 1 kenku assassin, 1
kenku wing mage. And this one works the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these kenku, though as usual I’d make their description as dastardly
criminals less universal than the book seems to imply. A setting where they’re
as common as the more traditional haflings and elves would be a cool place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/24/kenku.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/24/kenku.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Hydra</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-hydra.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydras made their 4e debut in the first Monster Manual, and here we get a few
more of them. Their basic lore remains the same and you can check it out on the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/06/06/hydra.html&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt; I made on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hydras on this entry have several passive traits in common: &lt;strong&gt;Threatening
Reach&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make opportunity attacks out to their full melee reach,
instead of only against adjacent enemies. &lt;strong&gt;Many-Headed&lt;/strong&gt; makes it resistant to
being dazed on stunning. These conditions only disable one of its heads for a
turn. And &lt;strong&gt;Regenerating Heads&lt;/strong&gt; causes the hydra to lose a head at 75%, 50%,
and 25%, regrowing two others at the start of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of heads an hyda has is important because of &lt;strong&gt;Hydra Fury&lt;/strong&gt;, an
at-will power that allows them to make a bite attack for each active head they
have. The effect of an individual bite, and the starting number of heads, vary
per hydra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, MM2 hydras are kind halfway between the ones we saw on the first
Monster Manual, and the ones from the Monster Vault. Most of their mechanics
still work like in the MM1, but Regenerating Heads debuts here and reappears in
a slightly weaker form in the Monster Vault. With the MV version you can prevent
head regrowth by dealing fire or acid damage to the hydra before the start of
its next turn, but nothing can stop it in this version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hydras are also lacking the Darkvision and Swim Speed of their relatives
from the other two books, though they still have trained Perception and
&lt;strong&gt;All-Around Vision&lt;/strong&gt; that prevents them from being flanked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;razor-hydra&quot;&gt;Razor Hydra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This species of hydra is covered in gleaming metal scales and has extra-sharp
serrated teeth. It’s drawn to the scent of blood in much the same way a shark
is, and one head bites a victim the others get into a frenzy. Because of this,
it’s also known as the Blood Hydra. They are Large Natural Beasts, and Level 16
Solo Brutes with 640 HP and a ground speed of 7. They start with four heads,
gaining extras at 480, 320, and 160.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A razor hydra’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; has Reach 2 and inflicts &lt;em&gt;stackable&lt;/em&gt; ongoing physical
damage. A healthy target would take ongoing 5 damage (save ends), but if the
target was already taking ongoing physical&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; damage, then that damage would
increase by 5 instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A poor sod on the receiving end of a razor hydra’s Fury attack would have
ongoing &lt;em&gt;20&lt;/em&gt; damage (save ends) to deal with, assuming all four bites hit. A
single save will clear it all, but if that save fails and the hydra bites again,
the total will increase even further. There’s no cap!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Blood Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes it so the hydra gains a +2 bonus to attack
targets who are bloodied, or who are taking ongoing physical damage. That’s
one more incentive for it to focus fire on a single PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the hydra drops to 0 HP, its &lt;strong&gt;Ferocity&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make one last Hydra
Fury attack. At this point it will have seven heads, for a potential 7d8+28
damage plus 35 ongoing damage against a single PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;heroslayer-hydra&quot;&gt;Heroslayer Hydra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interestingly-named hydra occupies the same narrative niche as the one
Hercules faced in his labors. As a Huge Natural Beast and a Level 20 Solo Brute,
it’s likely the most powerful hydra in the natural world, and is stronger than
any PC who isn’t an actual demi-god or equivalent. There are stronger specimens,
but you have to travel to the Elemental Chaos to find them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroslayer hydras have 776 HP and five heads at the start of the fight, gaining
new ones at 582, 388, and 194. Its &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; are Reach 3 and have no riders,
though its &lt;strong&gt;Hydra Fury&lt;/strong&gt; deals 10 extra damage to any target hit by two or more
bites. &lt;strong&gt;Rampage&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to bite every target in reach and inflict 10
ongoing damage to every target it hits. It recharges whenever the hydra suffers
a critical hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The titular &lt;strong&gt;Heroslayer&lt;/strong&gt; trait is a big “Fuck You” to defenders everywhere:
while the hydra is marked, it gains a +2 bonus to attack and a +5 bonus to
damage against the creature that marked it. Yes, this applies to every
individual bite in a Fury combo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we have a hydra with a decent incentive to spread its bites around until
a defender marks it, when it will instead focus exclusively on the defender
until they’re good and dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chaos-hydra&quot;&gt;Chaos Hydra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those stronger species native to the Elemental Chaos. Chaos
Hydras start out with only two heads, but their bites are very strong and
infused with deadly elemental energies. The new heads it grows when wounded also
gain new random elemental abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chaos Hydra is a Huge Elemental Beast and a Level 22 Solo Brute with 848
HP. It has two Reach 3 basic bite attacks, one for each head: &lt;strong&gt;Frostfire Bite&lt;/strong&gt;
deals fire and cold damage, and &lt;strong&gt;Storm Bite&lt;/strong&gt; deals lightning and thunder
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever the hydra grows a new head (at 636, 424, and 212 HP), it gains a new
bite attack chosen by a d4 roll. It can gain multiple copies of the same
attack. Its &lt;strong&gt;Hydra Fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to bite with the two original attacks and
any new ones it might have gained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four additional bites deal less base damage but have “save ends”
riders. They are: &lt;strong&gt;Crushing Maw&lt;/strong&gt;, which slows and deals ongoing 10 damage;
&lt;strong&gt;Mind bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which dazes; &lt;strong&gt;Paralyzing Fang&lt;/strong&gt;, which immobilizes and inflicts
a -2 penalty to all defenses; and &lt;strong&gt;Venom Tooth&lt;/strong&gt;, which inflicts ongoing 10
poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thematically this hydra is all over the place, but that’s the point. It’s hard
for PCs to protect themselves from everything it can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydras are solitary, so you will usually only find one of them at a
time. However, they’re also frequently followed by opportunistic scavengers who
feed on the remains of their meals and who might be impatient enough to give
them a bit of help with killing those meals. Examples given are carrion crawlers
and shardstorm vortex elementals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, a powerful character might be able to capture a hydra for use as a
guardian. The example encounter given is for this scenario, with a razor hydra
and its minotaur cabalist master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydras are cool, particularly those with the regenerating heads
mechanic. However, I think they should be used sparingly to prevent the novelty
from wearing off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I say “physical”, but the strictly correct term would be
“untyped”. Untyped damage is almost always dealt by physical attacks, but
you could have magic powers that also did it. It’s written like “1d8+5
damage” or “ongoing 5 damage” instead of “1d8+5 fire damage” or “ongoing 5
fire damage”. Very few monsters resist it, but none are particularly
vulnerable to it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/17/hydra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/17/hydra.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
