<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 20:30:05 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 20:30:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>De-monk-ifying Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/marching-fire.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Is this guy a Martial Artist? A Swashbuckler? A Knight? Yes.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy has the Swashbuckler template. Swashbucklers are physical
combatants who prioritize mobility and precision over heavy armor and brute
strength. They use a specialized set of weapons, are obsessed with improving
their skill, and strive to learn secret techniques of legendary reputation and
effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy also has the Martial Artist template. Martial artists are
physical combatants who prioritize mobility and precision over heavy armor and
brute strength. They use a specialized set of weapons, are obsessed with
improving their skill, and strive to learn secret techniques of legendary
reputation and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, those descriptions use most of the same words. When you look at these two
professional templates from a large enough distance, they really are two takes
on the same concept. They could, in theory, be represented by the same
template. The reason Martial Artist is a separate archetype in Dungeon Fantasy
is because Monk is a separate class in D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the reason Monk is a separate class in D&amp;amp;D, as far as I can tell, is because
of a particular set of media cliches that have surrounded the words “martial
arts” in a lot of media contemporary with earlier editions of D&amp;amp;D. I guess you
could call it a form of orientalism&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some of these media sources, “martial arts” are this mysterious and exotic
secret from the mysterious and exotic East, much more sophisticated than the
crude flailings of Western barbarians. Knowing it makes you more “enlightened”
and gives you superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In others, they’re this fancy dance for pansies that’s totally ineffective in a
“true” fight, because a Real Man knows he just has to punch the other guy. The
Real Man in this scenario is of course always a man, and always Western too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D monks were originally based on this character named Remo Williams, the
protagonist of the Destroyer series of novels. These novels came out in the 70s,
and they were very much in the “exotic secret that gives you superpowers”
camp. Williams learned a fictional martial art from an exotic foreign master and
proceeded to use it to defeat a string of (usually Asian) bad guys. D&amp;amp;D writers
applied a “shaolin” veneer to the class in later editions but many monk
abilities are still based on stuff Williams did in the novels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS replicated this in Dungeon Fantasy because it tries to replicate D&amp;amp;D, but
its “default” approach to martial arts turns out to be a lot better in my
opinion. It has a supplement named GURPS Martial Arts that treats historical
styles from all over the world with the same level of respect. The message
contained in its rules seems to be that these styles are all different
expressions of the same thing&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. How good an individual combatant is matters a
lot more than where his techniques come from. I really liked that when I first
read it, and I’ve only grown to like it more over the years. It kinda bothers me
to see a game that still treats the subject in that older “Destroyer” way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every character who practices a fighting style and trains to improve their skill
at it is a martial artist by definition, no matter &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; that fighting style
comes from. Whether that training gives you superpowers has always been more of
a genre or campaign “setting” than something that should be assigned to
individual character types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the dungeon fantasy genre, that particular setting is obviously
stuck on “yes”. Every PC can perform impossible feats of badassery, that has
been a given since the very beginning&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Someone who comes from a culture that
talks about things in terms of Chi will likely describe any such character as
possessing “strong chi”. Someone who doesn’t will just describe them as being
really good at fighting. This in no way changes the fundamentals of how their
abilities work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s what I’m going to do in my campaigns from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demonkified-dungeon-fantasy&quot;&gt;Demonkified Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chi Mastery no longer exists as a specific power. There is no Chi Talent, and
all its component abilities lose the power modifier along with the associated
discounts and drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only have access to the DFRPG, do this instead: if a former Chi ability
is described as “working like” another trait, you can buy that trait
instead. For example, Tough Skin instead of Dragon Skin, and Striking ST instead
of Mantis Strike. For abilities that have no parallel… keep the same cost,
it’s simpler. In all cases you no longer get a bonus for Chi Talent, but you
also no longer need Disciplines of Faith: Chi Rituals to keep them either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swashbuckler and Martial Artist become related templates. A Swashbuckler
gains access to the Martial Artist’s abilities and power-ups, and
vice-versa. Characters of each template might still look and behave very
differently on a role-playing level, but there isn’t any fundamental difference
in their mechanics any more. The 30 points that would go to Chi Talent in the
Martial Artist template are instead avaialble to be spent on any template
advantages or skills. And there you go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re also using &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html&quot;&gt;Streamlined Mastery&lt;/a&gt;, this means that a PC built using
the Martial Artist template could start off with True Master and Iron Limbs for
the same cost as the official Trained By a Master and Chi Talent 2 advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-knights&quot;&gt;What about Knights?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything I said about monks and swashbucklers in my introduction applies
equally well to Knights and the other “fighty” templates. However, I still want
to keep it as a separate template because it’s good to still have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt;
guidance when building characters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Combatant who prefers strength and heavy gear” is different enough from
“combatant who prefers precision and speed” to remain a useful distinction. I’d
still allow some judicious cross-aisle shopping for traits that make sense for a
specific PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, combining this with some form of &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/08/30/agnostic-dungeon-fantasy.html&quot;&gt;Agnostic Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; (where
either no spellcaster is a priest or they all are) would leave us very close to
ditching templates entirely, or at least having a collection of “classes” that’s
much closer to that of the oldest of old D&amp;amp;Ds: “warrior” and “magic user”. Maybe
I’ll try that some day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-the-path&quot;&gt;What About the Path?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the side-boxes in the Dungeon Fantasy Companion 2 introduces the notion
of The Path, an alternate progression scheme that a Martial Artist PC can opt
into at character creation. Basically, it makes your Chi Talent levels limit how
many levels you can have in certain traits. As a result those limits are lower
to start with, but with enough time and points they can end up much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think The Path is more appropriate for a campaign that does the reverse of
what I’m trying to do here, where &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; uses chi mechanics. I’ll leave it
out of my games for now and maybe write about it at a future date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though of course I’m not an expert on the subject and will gladly defer to
people who are. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, Bruce Lee said this, and yes, the book does talk about him with great
admiration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Don’t even try to bring the Guy at the Gym fallacy into this. The guy at
the gym will never have 200 HP or be able to fight 50 goblins without
breaking a sweat. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/20/demonkification.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/20/demonkification.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Streamlined Melee Mastery for GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In GURPS, the Trained by a Master advantage allows a character to perform
martial feats on par with those seen in kung fu movies and other similar
stories. The Weapon Master advantage does basically the same in a slightly
different way. They overlap so much that I’m not sure if they were meant to
exist in the same campaign!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think both advantages are fairly priced on their own, but I don’t think both
of them combined are worth 75 points. Choosing to only allow one of them in your
campaign is a fairly simple matter, but what if you want to allow both,
potentially on the same character?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the differences between the two traits are fiddly matters of skill
coverage. Sweeping those aside leaves us with the remaining elephant in the
room, the Weapon Master damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elephant-examination-the-damage-bonus&quot;&gt;Elephant Examination: The Damage Bonus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the damage bonus is the biggest game changer in the entire WM
package. Even if a Weapon Master never learns a supernatural skill and never
attacks or parries more than once per turn, they’re still going to feel like an
entirely different character from someone who has the exact same stats but lacks
the advantage. It feels a bit unfair to me that this bonus is not available to
characters that focus on unarmed strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS uses realistic assumptions as a base for its rules, and under those
assumptions a combatant with a weapon always has a big advantage over one
without. The unarmed fighter risks limb injury on every parry and strike. The
armed one has greater reach and much better damage from using swing attacks or
simply from doing a better damage type than crushing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unarmed fighter with Trained By a Master can approach that by taking other
traits… But then they’ve spent 60 points and bought a Hard combat skill to be
on par with someone who bought an Average skill and took Weapon Master (single
weapon) for 20 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t feel a need to keep this “effectiveness gap” between armed and unarmed
skills when we’re dealing with a campaign that allows “mastery” advantages in
the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-traits&quot;&gt;New Traits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solution to the above situation is to rejigger the existing traits. The new
and altered traits below are available in any campaign that also allows both
Trained by a Master and Weapon Master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;true-master-50-points&quot;&gt;True Master (50 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through either decades of dedication or being some sort of war god, you have
mastered all forms of “archaic” combat. You gain &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the benefits from having
both Trained by a Master and the full version of Weapon Master. Your unarmed
strikes enjoy the same damage bonus described under Weapon Master. This bonus
&lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; stack with other bonuses from high striking skills and from traits like
Claws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those two advantages still exist, and represent a slightly less comprehensive
form of mastery. You can upgrade from any of them to True Master by spending the
difference between their point value and 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iron-limbs-10-points&quot;&gt;Iron Limbs (10 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your limbs are immune to incidental injury during unarmed combat. Enemies can’t
damage your limbs when they parry your unarmed attacks with a weapon, nor can
they switch targets and damage your limbs when you fail to parry their
attacks. You also don’t hurt yourself when hitting armored opponents with
unarmed strikes. Your limbs can still be deliberately targeted by enemy attacks,
however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trait replaces Unarmed Master, as it is basically Unarmed Master without
the damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like those two traits, though as of this writing I still need to actually
field-test them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns that use these two new advantages, an unarmed specialist &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt;
turn their limbs into Strikers. That’s what Unarmed Master did, and we did away
with it. IF the specialist in question happens to belong to a non-human species
that has natural Strikers, though, &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; would stack with True Master. Beware
of boxing crab-people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron Limbs doesn’t have any prerequisites: you could buy it without having any
of the “mastery” advantages. This allows it to be used to represent an extremely
focused blessing, or a creature whose limbs are naturally hard to hurt or even
naturally made of metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you feel 10 points for Iron Limbs is too expensive for someone who
is already a True Master, you could try rolling it into True Master at no extra
cost, and eliminating the separate Iron Limbs advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a GURPS Spaceplane: The Second Iteration</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/mac-rebisz-20150220-esa-spaceplane-001.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fictional ESA spaceplane.
    Illustration by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/3q14v&quot;&gt;Maciej Rebisz.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/03/06/spaceplane.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we used GURPS Spaceships rules to build a “minimum
viable spaceplane” at TL8, with no superscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company, Octopus Aerospace, builds one of those and sells it to the
Kerbal Space Program for close to a billion GURPS dollars&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and after using
it for a few launches Director Kerbman comes back to us with a few change
requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His astronauts have complained that the Mark I Spaceplane handles very poorly
for its size. They’re entering a phase of their program where future missions
will require a lot of precise orbital maneuvers, like docking and such, so they
need a ship that can do better at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to satisfy KSP’s requests because we want a slice of their inifinte
budget, but we’re also committed to making only Single Stage To Orbit craft. How
can we satisfy both of these requirements?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-mark-ii&quot;&gt;Building the Mark II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still using “realistic” TL 8 for our Mark II, and it’s still streamlined
and winged just like its predecessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in our previous post, a TL8 craft capable of reaching orbit can only
spare 10% of its mass to systems that are not fuel tanks or chemical engines. We
achieved that in the Mark I by shrinking our control systems and cargo bay,
filling the freed space with additional fuel tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want a full size control system for the second iteration, but having that
means we’ll be short on delta-V and can’t make an orbital insertion. We have to
shrink something else to compensate. We’re already shrunk the cargo bay, and I
don’t want to shrink the armor because I’m envisioning as the craft’s heat
shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about the engine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our resulting configuration is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x Metallic Laminate Armor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x SM +8 control room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x 15-ton cargo bay&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;17.33 x Fuel Tanks (865 tons rocket fuel)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x SM +7 Chemical Rocket Engine (1G Acceleration)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One lone G of acceleration is useless for leaving Earth… in a traditional
rocket. We have wings! According to GURPS Spaceships p. 37, a winged craft can
take off and reach Earth orbit even if its acceleration doesn’t exceed 1G.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leaves us with the following stat line for our Mark II space plane:
&lt;strong&gt;dST/dHP&lt;/strong&gt; 70; &lt;strong&gt;Air Hnd/SR&lt;/strong&gt; +3/4; &lt;strong&gt;Space Hnd/SR&lt;/strong&gt; -2/4; &lt;strong&gt;Move&lt;/strong&gt; 1G/6.05mps;
&lt;strong&gt;LWt&lt;/strong&gt; 1000; &lt;strong&gt;Load&lt;/strong&gt; 15.3; &lt;strong&gt;SM&lt;/strong&gt; +8; &lt;strong&gt;Occ&lt;/strong&gt; 4; &lt;strong&gt;dDR&lt;/strong&gt; 0/2/0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model’s Air Handling and Stability is pretty awesome when compared to that
of most contemporary airplanes. Its space handling is still not exactly
spectacular, but it’s the best we can do for a ship of this size at TL 8, and
should help with those delicate maneuvers. It takes longer to reach orbit due to
its lower acceleration, but it still has the same Delta-V. Finally, it has space
for one additional crew member, allowing KSP to bring extra scientists or other
mission specialists along with the payload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheaper engine and more expensive control room balance themselves out. The
Mark II costs the same as the Mark I: a nominal $8.8M for the craft and $693,200
for a full load of rocket fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-notessales-pitch&quot;&gt;Bonus Notes/Sales Pitch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I forgot to mention in the previous post: both the Mark I and
Mark II Octopus Carnival Spaceplanes can take off from conventional runways,
dispensing with the need for an expensive launch pad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mark I would probably require a launchpad if you want to use those 3Gs of
acceleration right away, but if I remember correctly liquid fuel engines can be
throttled. So you can take off using a jet-engine-equivalent 1G and throttle up
when you reach a higher altitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you multiply their nominal cost by 100 for the extremely limited
production run, you still end up with a cost-effective system. SpaceX’s
semi-reusable rockets cost between $50M and $150M &lt;em&gt;per launch&lt;/em&gt;. The real-world
Space Shuttle cost between $500M and $1.5B per launch. The Saturn V cost about
$1.6B per launch in modern dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our fictional spaceplane would cost little more than the cost of a load of
fuel. Sure, it’d need to undergo maintenance between flights, but it probably
wouldn’t need to be practically rebuilt like the real-world systems. So perhaps
we’re looking at $2M per launch or so? It practically pays for itself in six
launches or so when compared to the “competition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, that’s a very optimistic assumption. In your games you’re always free
to assume Octopus Aerospace is full of shit and this thing is a lemon in all its
incarnations. It’s what prevented all those real world spaceplane projects from
going forward, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;$880M, or its nominal cost multiplied by 100 because it’s a production
run of one. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/10/spaceplane.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/10/spaceplane.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>spaceships</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a Spaceplane: A GURPS Spaceships Exercise</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/mac-rebisz-20150220-esa-spaceplane-001.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fictional ESA spaceplane.
    Illustration by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/3q14v&quot;&gt;Maciej Rebisz.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading about Kerbal Space Program recently, and it made me want to
try my hand at designing some GURPS spaceships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the terms that often gets thrown about when talking about near-future
space tech is “Single Stage to Orbit”, or SSTO. This would be a vehicle that can
go from ground to orbit all by itself, without needing any detachable
boosters. In the real world, a lot of plans for building one of these have been
conceived and dropped, but we don’t have a real example yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How close does GURPS Spaceships think we are to such a thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll try to design a spaceplane, a popular type of theoretical SSTO
craft. The basic idea is that they take off and fly to the upper atmosphere
using air-breathing engines, and only then activate their rockets to reach
orbit. After completing their mission, they can re-enter atmosphere and land by
gliding. Spaceplanes are an attractive concept because they can use a lot less
fuel to reach orbit, are fully reusable, and easier to maintain. Plus they tend
to look really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mission-statement-and-design-options&quot;&gt;Mission Statement and Design Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this attempt, we’re going to assume a realistic TL8 setting (“present-day
technology”), giving us access to TL7 and 8 items from the book. I’ll
arbitrarily assign it SM +8, making it a 1000 ton craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, our craft is SM +8, TL8, streamlined, and winged. It must take off
from the ground on Earth and reach orbital velocity using without the aid of
external boosters or detachable stages, while carrying a multi-ton payload in
its cargo hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means it must have a total delta-V exceeding 5.6 miles per second after all
the calculations are done&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We get a bonus 0.3 mps if we launch eastwards
from the equator, but having the craft reach the number on its own would allow
it to launch from anywhere in the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fixed-systems&quot;&gt;Fixed Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design options above lock down 3 of the 20 systems we have available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need 1 armor system because we’re streamlined.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a control room (1 system).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a cargo bay (1 system).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our purposes in this post it doesn’t matter what the armor is made of, but
we might as well use Metallic Laminate since we’re designing a “cutting edge”
craft. The remaining 17 systems will be split among engines and fuel tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At our TL, we have two engine options: the Chemical Rocket and the Jet
Engine. They both help, but use different fuel sources. Adding jet engines means
we need to figure out their top airspeed and subtract that from the necessary
delta-V to reach orbit. Rocket delta-V is purely a function of how many tanks we
dedicate to rocket fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempt-1-mixing-rockets-and-jet-engines&quot;&gt;Attempt 1: Mixing Rockets and Jet Engines.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first draft had the following configuration for our 17 “free” systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 Jet Engines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Chemical Rocket Engine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14 Fuel Tanks (13 for rocket fuel, 1 for jet fuel).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jet fuel allowed us to run the jets for half an hour, which was more than
enough to reach maximum speed and altitude. They lowered our target to 4.63 mps,
but that’s not enough. Combining the rules for chemical rockets and fuel tanks,
our rocket had 3.12 mps of delta-V available to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be good for a fancy passenger plane for people with money to burn,
but not for a SSTO vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempt-2-rocket-plane&quot;&gt;Attempt 2: Rocket Plane&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we build an all-rocket engine assembly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 Chemical Rocket Engine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16 fuel tanks (all rocket fuel)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding up the delta-V for this version is easier, and we do end up with more of
it, but it’s still not enough. We get 4.8 out of 5.6 mps. So close, yet so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this configuration gives us is a reusable &lt;em&gt;launch-assist vehicle&lt;/em&gt; can get
its 50-ton payload &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; to orbital speeds. The payload itself would need to
be another vehicle that could provide the remaining 0.8 mps of delta-V itself,
and perhaps include a bit more for maneuvers once in orbit. The LAV can spend
all of its own fuel and glide down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempt-3-cheating-with-optional-rules&quot;&gt;Attempt 3: Cheating with Optional Rules.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve run up against one of the harsh realities of the Spaceships design
rules. Using only TL7-8 chemical rockets, you simply can’t make an orbit-capable
vehicle with less than 17 fuel tanks. A traditional disposable rocket can be
modeled with 1 chemical rocket system, 17 fuel tanks, and an upper stage with an
SM 2 smaller than the rocket itself. This upper stage has the armor needed by a
streamlined craft, and the discarded lower stage burns up on re-entry. Our
spaceplane faces some trouble because it needs to include that armor system
itself, leaving us 1 fuel tank short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way we can make it work is by pulling in an optional rule from GURPS
Spaceships 7 p. 4: Smaller Systems. By shrinking both our cargo bay and control
room to SM +7, we decrease our cargo capacity to 15 tons, decrease our
Handling/SR in by 1, and add 1.33 fuel tanks to our all-rocket spaceplane. That
gets us 6.05 mps of delta-V, enough to launch from anywhere on the planet and
still leave us some reserves for maneuvers and corrections. It carries less than
the equivalent disposable rocket but is fully reusable, able to land by gliding
even with an empty fuel tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We leave the armor system at the same size because it’s meant to serve as a heat
shield on re-entry, so it’s probably placed in the central hull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img width=&quot;512&quot;
  src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/c2/ED97-43938-1mod.jpg/512px-ED97-43938-1mod.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A X-33 and a VentureStar craft. NASA, public domain, via Wikimedia Commons.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing we just designed is remarkably similar to the Lockheed-Martin
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VentureStar&quot;&gt;VentureStar&lt;/a&gt;, at least if the stats in the Wikipedia article are to be
believed. This is a project for a SSTO spaceplane whose most famous product is
the X-33 prototype, a scaled-down version of the final design intended to test
some of its technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VentureStar was supposed to be a lot simpler to maintain than the space shuttle,
and was intended to be available for sale to private companies and not just to
NASA, kick-starting a wave of private space exploration. The project was
cancelled in 2001 because its fuel tanks were too hard to manufacture using the
technology of the time. Ironically, better manufacturing techniques were
discovered a few years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from having to contend with the “harsh truth” of the design rules we
already mentioned, our spaceplane also illustrates what seems to be a constraint
plaguing real-world designers: separate air-breathing and rocket engines are
inefficient. Go rocket-only or get you an engine that can do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its final stats are: dST/dHP 70; Air Hnd/SR +2/3; Space Hnd/SR -3/3; Move
3G/6.05mps; LWt. 1000; Load 15.3; SM+8; Occ 3; dDR 0/2/0. The Space handling is
terrible, but workable when the mission is “get up, release the payload, get
down”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our spaceplane costs $8.8M according to the design rules. Of course, that’s its
price if it was mass-produced and commercially available. The rather more
bespoke space program manufacturing model means it could cost up to 100 times
more. It runs on liquid hydrogen/liquid oxygen rocket fuel, a full load of which
costs $693,200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LAV version has better handling and stability (+3/4 in air and -2/4 in
space) and costs about $40K less to fuel, and can deliver a bigger payload as
long as that payload has some delta-V of its own. But it’s not a spaceplane, so
nyeh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I like using a proper measurement system, but all of the book’s formulas
are in miles, so I’ll have to use that to avoid getting confused during the
design process. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/06/spaceplane.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/06/spaceplane.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>spaceships</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How I Started Role-Playing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lich van Winkle has &lt;a href=&quot;https://lichvanwinkle.blogspot.com/2021/01/how-you-started.html&quot;&gt;a post in his blog&lt;/a&gt; where asks people how they started
role-playing. I figured I’d answer that here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I start, it’s worth noting that I’m Brazilian, so my story is going to be
a bit different than that of most people reading this blog. I also grew up in
the state of Mato Grosso, which in the 80’s and 90’s meant “far out in the
boonies” as far as RPGs were concerned. Most of my acquisitions happened during
trips to visit family in Curitiba, a bigger city in another state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The year you began, and with which role-playing game&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you figure it out alone, or were you introduced by a lone but
experienced GM, or by joining a preexisting group?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first contact with the concept of role-playing games actually happened
through Choose Your Own Adventure books. Y’know, those books that had a couple
hundred numbered sections and directed you to different numbers based on your
decisions. There were a bunch of those in my school library, which was a small
miracle since that library only had like four bookshelves. This was 1991 or so,
which means I was 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on I’d convince my parents to buy me similar books - my first Fighting
Fantasy titles, in their Brazilian editions. These were more complex, with an
actual character sheet and die rolling. I remember this book from some other
series, where you played Robin Hood, and which had a combat system complex
enough to rival AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first actual RPG experience was around 1994, with a version of Basic D&amp;amp;D that
was translated by a company named Grow, and packaged as a board game. I think it
might have been a boxed set as well in the US - it was the one with Zanzer Tem’s
dungeon on it, and had rules for PCs of up to level 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that I got into GMing, and my games of choice were Tagmar (a
Brazilian-made fantasy game) and later a very badly translated Shadowrun 2nd
Edition. I also got familiar with GURPS and Storyteller at around this time,
though I didn’t play them regularly. In 1996 I went on a one-month student
exchange trip to the UK, and came back with a backpack full of Shadowrun
supplements in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was your first group like? Was it private among friends, in a game
store, or in a club? Were they older, younger than you? Did their style of
play shape the way you played later?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group was my brother and a couple of other friends. Almost everyone was
around the same age as me (except for my brother, who was a bit younger). We
usually played at my home, and I’d say my style of play shaped theirs more
than the other way around, since I was always the GM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I was the only one out of that bunch who kept being a part of the
hobby once we split, though. Dunno if that speaks well or badly of my GMing
skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your favorite role-playing game. (Was it the game you started with?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s GURPS, and it’s not the one I started with. Lately I’ve also taken a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;huge liking to Lancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anything else you want to share reflecting the impact of how you started on
how you play(ed).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being from a different country and having ready access to a very small
pool of games when compared to someone from the US, my experience bears some
striking similarities with Lich van Winkle’s in that D&amp;amp;D was a very small part
of my formative experience. I remember finding its many arbitrary limitations
very confining, so I spent most of my time in other games that didn’t have
them. Though some of those limitations have been removed, a lot of them still
remain in the game’s latest edition.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/how-i-started.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/how-i-started.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Are Mecha Silly?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I saw someone start a thread on the RPG.net forum, with the title “Why
are mecha silly?”. The person in question was of the opinion that not only were
mecha not silly, they were &lt;em&gt;plausible&lt;/em&gt;, and went on to list reasons they thought
so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of those were swiftly debunked by posters, but I think the thread
kinda got away from the main point after a while. So I thought I’d write a bit
about this subject here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thread’s title had a bit of an unfortunate framing, because it started from
the premise that mecha &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; silly even though its opening poster didn’t think
so. A better question to ask might be “Are Mecha Silly?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My answer is somewhat nuanced, but it can still be summed up as “No”. Giant
robots are definitely &lt;em&gt;cinematic&lt;/em&gt;, but they’re not inherently sillier than any
other cinematic trope. It’s all about the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using “mech” and “mecha” here to mean a humanoid (or at least legged)
piloted machine that’s used in about the same role as an armored fighting
vehicle or tank. Non-combat versions are usually used as heavy construction
equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the traditional excuses for mecha: Legs make them able to
handle any terrain type better than wheels or threads. A humanoid form makes
them more agile and versatile than traditional vehicles. Something about the
specific technology used to build them makes them better weapons than
traditional vehicles (this last one varies per setting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these would hold up under scrutiny under a strictly realistic
setting. While some people are building smaller autonomous robots and
experimenting with load-bearing skeletons, building a giant mech is still far
beyond us and the general consensus on that seems to be that it’s not worth the
effort. Better to work at improving the specialized vehicles we know than
worrying about leg movement and the ground pressure exerted by two giant metal
feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you get more cinematic mecha become a better fit. An “action movie setting”
that makes you accept some people do the impossible because they’re just that
badass shouldn’t have a lot of trouble selling the idea that sometimes tanks
have legs. Full Metal Panic in its more serious moments is a good example of
this. The show itself is silly most of the time, but the robot fights are trated
in a more serious cinematic manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science fictional settings have more leeway than contemporary ones, because the
same classical excuses are still valid and it’s easier to assume that the
practical engineering concerns have been solved in the future. A lot of the
Gundam shows are in this territory, as are many other similar franchises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s just the shows that even bother to offer up excuses! You see, there
are two main “sub-genres” of mecha shows. The ones that bother to think about
excuses and to insert their mecha into a wider military context are called “Real
Robot” shows. The original Mobile Suit Gundam back in 1979 was the first of
these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other side of the coin are “Super Robot” shows, who don’t even bother with
that. Sometimes a 12-year old kid just inherits a fifteen story tall robot from
his dad, and flies that robot out of the secret hangar at the bottom of his
swimming pool to fight space monsters. Super Robot shows date from the early
seventies, and their overall aesthetic is closer to that of a gold or silver age
supers story than “proper” science fiction. They require the same kind of
suspension of disbelief. If you can accept Superman, you can accept Mazinger Z.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Real or Super, no type of mecha is inherently silly as long as you place
it in the type of story it was meant to go in. Just like any other cinematic
trope.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/01/mecha.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/01/mecha.html</guid>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lancer</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Stormtrooper Armor Conundrum</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you know what is the second hardest thing to convert when adapting Star Wars
to the tabletop? Stormtroopers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. From an in-character perspective they vastly
outnumber and outgun the scrappy rebel protagonists, with deadly blaster
carbines and that iconic heavy armor. Yet in the actual narrative they almost
never hit a shot and always get taken out in one hit from one of the heroes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their poor aim has actually made it into GURPS as an optional cinematic rule
named “Imperial Stormtrooper Marksmanship Academy”, which reduces the deadliness
of enemy shooters. But the armor thing has tied people’s brain in knots, because
it can’t be explained away with a joke. Why does their armor do nothing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are almost as many explanations and solutions to this as there are Star
Wars adaptations. Some say “all armor is bad, actually” and have PCs rely on
plot protection. Some have an armor system but go out of their way to explain
why trooper suits specifically are actually bad. And some have an armor system
that rates trooper armor highly but then go on to state that fun shootouts from
the movies are lies and legends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me, I think I hit on a solution that allows me to keep those fun fights while
still having armor be cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;imperial-stormtrooper-armor-drills&quot;&gt;Imperial Stormtrooper Armor Drills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cinematic rule meant for science fiction settings where highly
effective armor is common, but you want the PCs to have fun battles against
armies of heavily-armored mooks. Star Wars and stormtroopers are the most
obvious examples, but it also works for settings such as Waframe’s with its
Grineer soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this rule, armor worn by “mook” or “fodder” enemies has no protective
value, and is mostly a cosmetic detail! Any solid hit will take them down,
regardless of whether it would have penetrated their DR under standard
rules. Armor worn by PCs and other important characters still uses all the
default rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows you to frame a particularly badass trooper as a real threat and have
them survive several attacks without giving them different protective gear. It
also allows PCs to loot armor from a fallen mook and have it actually provide
benefit beyond a temporary disguise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optionally, you could perhaps take this a bit further and subject certain
stormtroopers to the Inverse Ninja Rule. See a full platoon of troopers gunning
for you? Easy. See &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; trooper approaching? Danger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The first is the Force, but we all know that. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/10/27/stormtrooper-armor.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/10/27/stormtrooper-armor.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>star-wars</category>
        
        <category>science-fiction</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Irony At the Heart of Shadowrun</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For a very long time Shadowrun was my favorite game system and setting. These
days I still like the setting, but my annoyance at a host of small details in it
is stronger than my wish to play in it as written. Still, it’s useful to think
and talk about these details. It allows me to figure out what I want to do
better in my eventual home-brewed rewrite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these details isn’t small at all, however. In fact, I’d go as far as
calling it the great irony at the heart of the game, as the title of this post
implied. It was developed from some forum posts I made on RPG.net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-first-the-good-parts&quot;&gt;But First, The Good Parts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to be unfairly critical of Shadowrun&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I know a few people who
write for it, and the last thing I want is to give the impression that I’m
attacking them. I’m not. This entire article is my personal opinion and in no
way meant to disparage any of the fine people who are passionate enough about
Shadowrun to write for it professionally. So let’s begin by talking about
something that this game does &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about the setting design of Shadowrun is that it presents
players with a very clear mission-based structure. The infamous question of “But
what do we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; in this world?” is answered very early and very clearly. This is
a game about completing dangerous missions for money, just like D&amp;amp;D is about
killing monsters and looting dungeons. Someone asks you to play Shadowrun, 99
times out of 100 you know the rough overall shape that campaign is going to
take. You see a heist movie and you start thinking about it in the context of
Shadowrun in your head, even if it doesn’t have all the same style elements,
because the premise is strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowrun nailed the answer to this important question so well that it kinda
spilled over to other similar games. It became the default playstile for
Cyberpunk 2020 against the wishes of its own authors, and it often gets adopted
as the answer to “what do we do” in Transhuman Space&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which is so adamant
about offering none in its pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of Shadowrun setting elements, though, this structure has an
excellent &lt;em&gt;premise&lt;/em&gt; but its implementation gives rise to a lot of unintentional
oddness. Or, in this case, to a Great Irony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This irony, I think, emerges when the strong premise above gets combined with
AD&amp;amp;D-style adversarial GMing, which was very popular when Shadowrun was first
written. I believe it to be entirely unintentional, since as far as I can tell
Shadowrun’s design methodology was mostly based on the Rule of Cool with a dash
of “everyone else does this”. If it’s intentional, though, it’s among the
greatest acts of trolling in all of gaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;isnt-it-ironic&quot;&gt;Isn’t it Ironic?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so the Sixth World is ruled by megacorporations who control every aspect
of people’s lives. Most of these people live hand-to-mouth and work themselves
to death in order to prop up the decadent lifestyles of a few billionaire
executives. “Wage slave” is pretty much a synonym for “low-level megacorporate
employee” in this setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as the flavor text tells us, player characters are supposed to have managed
to escape this cycle of misery. They live in the shadows cast by those giant
corporate towers, and they have the skills to oppose the megacorps and make
their independent way in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or do they?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit I don’t know how things are structured in the most recent
editions&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but I remember that the Shadowrun Companion for Second Edition
contained detailed advice on how much money your PCs should be paid for those
risky missions.  I call it the “rent plus change” model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the book, GMs should pay PCs enough for them to cover their
lifestyle payments (i.e, rent and food) for the next month, with a little bit
left over for resupplying consumables and eventually upgrading a piece of gear
after a while. This was &lt;em&gt;per month&lt;/em&gt;, not per run. If you had only one big run
that month, it would pay this amount. If you had several, they would pay
proportionally less so you’d receive the same “rent plus change” amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was perfectly in-keeping with the AD&amp;amp;D school of GMing and design, which
demanded PCs “earn” their power and had cool gear that cost money as a
significant part of that power. If they earn “too much” money, they would get
“too powerful”, and no one wants that! If your players look like they do, it’s
because they’re cheating cheaters who cheat and should be punished for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all published adventures started with a scene where the party met with
Mr. Johnson to discuss the job. In the vast majority of these adventures,
Mr. Johnson is a shady corporate exec working for one of the megas. And the GM
text for this scene always included the oh-so-funny “If the players refuse the
job, announce that the adventure ended, pack up your things and go home.” This
is a joke about how the PCs don’t have any choice but to take the job as
presented. In fact, the flavor text for the same scene almost always assumes
they’re hurting for cash just before they get that call from their contact
setting up the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, those fiercely independent PC shadowrunners? &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;They’re all wage slaves
too&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. And the game advises the GM to keep them that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were the original writers oblivious to these implications, or are they still
laughing today about how no one seems to have noticed? I don’t think I have seen
any official discussion about this contradiction in any of the books I’ve
read. It’s just taken as a given, and never questioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This central irony gets funnier when you add in two sets of rules that were
published in the same edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;orichalcum&quot;&gt;Orichalcum&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early SR2 sourcebook called The Grimoire contained rules for making magic
items. It required a lot of skill tests and time, and the materials were still
super-expensive, but the final monetary cost was cheaper than buying the item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Do you buy or make your items?” would have been mostly a question of personal
preference… if the book didn’t also have rules for making those materials from
raw natural resources. You could use them for enchanting or sell them for half
list price. You could even make orichalcum, the magical metal used in the
creation of the most powerful magic items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orichalcum was so expensive that a single 10-gram “unit” cost the same as a
sports car or as almost nine months of High Lifestyle. The process for making it
was time consuming and laborious, but not really dangerous or illegal. And a
skilled character could end up with multiple units of orichalcum at the end of
that process. Selling even a single unit would more than pay the cost of the
necessary equipment, which was reusable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these rules, a team of PCs that includes at least one magician has no
financial reason to run the shadows. They can just set up an orichalcum-making
operation instead, and live like kings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stolen-cars&quot;&gt;Stolen Cars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shadowrun Companion sourcebook includes rules for stealing cars and selling
them on the black market, which theoretically were meant to be used in a
campaign where the characters were gangers instead of Shadowrunners. You could
sell an entire stolen car for a fraction of its market value, or break it down
for parts and sell those over several days and get money equal to the car’s full
list price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stealing cars is of course illegal and dangerous, but it was trivial for the
typical PC party in this game. After all they have the skills to routinely break
into top-secret research labs full of intricate and deadly security measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheapest four-wheeled vehicle in the book was the Ford Americar, your
typical “generic crummy sedan” that filled every street. Stealing and
dismantling one of those every week would pay roughly five times the amount
recommended in the “rent plus change” advice in &lt;em&gt;the very same book&lt;/em&gt;. Or perhaps
you could steal one limousine or fancy sports car per quarter. In either case,
it was again much safer and more profitable than running the shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shadowrun--irony--awesome&quot;&gt;Shadowrun + Irony = Awesome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When these two “oopsies” were first discovered, I remember seeing a lot of GMs
go absolutely ballistic over them. The accusations of “munchkinism” flew thick
and fast, but in true those GMs were mad that the PCs were doing something that
wasn’t in the script. They reveled in describing the disproportionate response
law enforcement or competitors would visit upon the PCs, which was just an
excuse to punish the players for veering off the rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I think these two altertane activities are fraggin’ awesome,
precisely because they allow the party to truly break free from the grind. If
your players decide to retire from shadowrunning and make orichalcum or boost
cars for a living, I fully believe that the right response is to play along and
make the campaign be about that! All of those things mentioned as hard blocks by
curmudgeonly controlling GMs are actually excellent adventure hooks. And I’m
pretty sure any decent player group is going to keep finding non-monetary
reasons to return to the shadows. There’s still people to help and megacorps to
destroy, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I say that the first thing a team of shadowrunners needs to do is to find a
way to leave classic shadowrunning behind for good. It’s a sucker’s game. Stay
independent, take care of your community, tear down the system, make the Sixth
World better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Which already makes me nicer than most of the people who proclaim
  themselves its true fans. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though THS PCs tend to be working for government agencies or corporations
  rather than being freelance criminals. This is, after all, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/06/on-transhuman-space.html&quot;&gt;a cyberpunk setting
  as viewed by the bad guys&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I stopped at the end of Fourth. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/28/shadowrun-irony.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/28/shadowrun-irony.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cyberpunk and Plagues</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;preface&quot;&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been sitting on this one for a while now. I’m not gonna lie, writing and
publishing those Monster Manual posts is quite soothing. Particularly the
releasing part, which is just a few mechanical actions now that I have so much
pre-written material for it. Every once in a while I’ll sit and write something
that’s on my mind, and hesitate a bit before posting it. This is one such post,
which I’d say was written somewhere around late April or early May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-post&quot;&gt;The Post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the outtakes from &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/16/on-transhuman-space.html&quot;&gt;my last screed against Transhuman Space&lt;/a&gt; was a
rebuttal to the bit where it says it’s better and more realistic than cyberpunk
because it doesn’t have any apocalyptic disasters in its Very Serious history of
the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had had whole paragraphs mapped out in my mind about how yes, the insistence
of 90’s cyberpunk RPGs in inserting these catastrophes was kinda silly. About
how they probably had their roots in their authors believing in that “end of
history” bullshit just as hard as the text of Transhuman Space itself did, and
how they couldn’t see the future being a shitty place if there wasn’t a plague,
a nuclear meltdown, or a big war somewhere in there to muck things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was going to end with an assertion that no, you don’t need a big, clear,
forced disaster to head down a bad path. A lot of those cyberpunk tropes (evil
corporations, authoritarian governments disguised as democracies, and so on)
happened all on their own without needing such a push. William Gibson’s concept
of the Jackpot, presented in his novel &lt;em&gt;The Peripheral&lt;/em&gt;, encapsulates all of
this a lot better than Transhuman Space’s bright future. Well, he is William
friggin’ Gibson, and he had almost twenty extra years of history to look at, but
still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That post is all ruined now, of course, because it turns out those
disaster-licious 90’s games were on to something after all. Here we are, amid a
deadly pandemic that’s causing an untold number of tragedies and turning whole
societies upside-down as enforced quarantines and lockdowns push them to change
their habits in a rush. It’s not nearly as bad as a genuine 90’s RPG disaster,
but, in true Jackpot fashion, it doesn’t have to be. It’s not the &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; of the
evil corps’ and authoritarian governments’ rise to power, but a &lt;em&gt;consequence&lt;/em&gt; of
it. And I don’t think either THS or the 90’s games would ever have predicted
that rich capitalists would, when faced with a plague, suggest that it was OK to
let vast numbers of people die from it as long as it kept the economy
growing. THS has far too much faith in its Very Smart Neoliberals to suggest
such a thing, and it sounds too bleak even for a 90’s-style dystopia.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/19/cyberpunk-plagues.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/19/cyberpunk-plagues.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dungeoncrawl Procedures at Nature Kills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I published a post on “&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/01/24/old-school-movement.html&quot;&gt;Old School Movement&lt;/a&gt;” with a simple
set of rules I could use when GMing converted old-school D&amp;amp;D and AD&amp;amp;D dungeons
in Dungeon Fantasy. Recently, the Nature Kills blog has also published &lt;a href=&quot;https://gurpshexytime.blogspot.com/2020/06/dungeoncrawl-procedures.html&quot;&gt;their
own take&lt;/a&gt; on the same subject in a post titled “Dungeoncrawl Procedures”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find most interesting on that post, and on the sources it links, is that
they see the lack of this detailed procedure in recent D&amp;amp;D editions as a grave
omission in that system. Having a canonical procedure to crawl a dungeon or to
perform any other sort of exploration is a vital pre-requisite for properly
designing these dungeons and other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual procedure outlined there is similar to mine in nature, but differs in
some details and adds others I didn’t cover. The ones I found most interesting
are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This procedure should apply to all dungeon exploration, not just to AD&amp;amp;D
adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Default movement speed is double what I guessed (encumbered Move x 20m per
turn).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Traps are only sprung 2 out of 6 times. A direct translation of an old-school
mechanic that’s perfect for use when you’re not constantly using a map and
miniatures.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have convinced me to apply this mechanic to all dungeon crawls, but I
disagree with enough of their details that I feel I have to revise my own
procedure. That will happen some other time.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/09/exploration-procedures.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/06/09/exploration-procedures.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>link</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
