<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 17:19:43 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 17:19:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Trolls</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-troll.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a situation that has been common in this reading, we’re in a halfway place
when it comes to trolls. The Monster Manual marks their debut in this edition,
and the Monster Vault gives us a final selection of updated stat blocks. Here in
the Monster Manual 2, published between those two books, we have a selection of
trolls that expands the options from the MM, but is not yet updated for the MV’s
math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ice-troll&quot;&gt;Ice Troll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear from the text whether ice trolls are a variant troll species or
just a variant culture. They inhabit the Frostfell, one of the world’s coldest
regions, but occasionally make their way to slightly warmer climates. Ice trolls
have a more complex and technically advanced culture than that of “typical”
trolls. They know how to make weapons, and prefer to use them in combat instead
of their claws. They also emanate a cold aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to portray your trolls less universally hostile, ice troll
communities could make good trading partners in cold regions, trading their
weapons and crafts for other products they need. Ice troll mercenaries might
also be found among the forces of anyone who sets up shop in the frozen regions
of your campaign world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ice trolls are Large Natural Humanoids and Level 10 Soldiers with 109 HP. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Emanating Cold&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) slows any enemies caught inside for a turn. They
have a ground speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ice troll regeneration works exactly like that of standard trolls: Regeneration
10 plus Troll Healing that allows them to keep regaining HP after
hitting 0. Both are shut down for a turn if the troll takes acid or fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This troll wears scale armor and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;maul&lt;/strong&gt;. If their maul attack
bloodies an enemy, &lt;strong&gt;Frenzied Strike&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make another free
attack. This &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; lead to a big chain combo if the ice troll manages to hit
several near-bloodied PCs, but most likely you’ll be looking at one extra attack
when this triggers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weapon use would make ice trolls a lot more dangerous than standard ones in a
“realistic” system like GURPS, but here it’s mostly for color since damage is
entirely level-based. It does allow you to place magic weapons and armor as
treasure by saying the troll was using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bladerager-troll&quot;&gt;Bladerager Troll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This troll was updated for the Monster Vault, so we already saw its numbers on
the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/09/troll.html&quot;&gt;MM/MV reading&lt;/a&gt;. A new bit of lore in this entry says that some of the
weapons and armor implanted on a bladerager are magic, which gives GMs an excuse
to place magic items as treasure in bladerager encounters. This makes them the
only monster in the game to have literal loot drops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troll-vinespeaker&quot;&gt;Troll Vinespeaker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s something you don’t see every day: a troll spellcaster with genius-level
intellect! You go, vinespeaker! Break those stereotypes! Unfortunately the
vinespeaker doesn’t break &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; troll stereotype, so it’s still Chaotic
Evil. You’ll have to break that one yourself if your campaign calls for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vinespeakers use a style of primal nature magic that involves wrapping
themselves in thorny vines and letting their blood soak the plants to gain
control over them. This would be lethal for any other practitioner, but for a
troll it’s no trouble at all. With their magic power and high intelligence,
vinespeakers tend to become leaders or revered advisors of larger troll
communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vinespeakers are Level 14 Controllers with 142 HP. They have Regeneration 10,
Troll Healing, and the usual vulnerabilities, as well as the usual Speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can use their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; to fight like a typical troll, but their vines give
them many more options. They have a ranged attack named &lt;strong&gt;Ray of Thorns&lt;/strong&gt; that
deals physical damage, and an area burst attack named &lt;strong&gt;Thorny Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that
deals light physical damage and immobilizes (save ends). This also creates a
zone of thorny difficult terrain that deals damage to those caught inside, and
lasts until the end of the encounter. If any of these attacks bloodies a target,
the vinespeaker gets to make a free claw attack. No target is specified, so any
PC within reach will do fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: Thorny Burst is at-will. Vinespeakers can turn the entire battlefield into
a spiky mess in no time at all. A good tactic for the is to spam this attack
until there’s no more ground to cover or until the PCs are all immobilized, then
target the most vulnerable foes with the single-target Ray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they have an encounter ability named &lt;strong&gt;Chant of Power&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives
allies in within 5 squares 10 temporary HP and a +4 damage bonus while the
temporary HP lasts. This works wonderfully as either a fight opener or a
mid-fight boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these MM2 trolls, they do a good job of subverting the troll stereotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: 2 ice trolls, 2 worgs, and 1 manticore. Lots of raw melee power in
this one, with a maneuverable skirmisher thrown in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 12: 3 bladeragers, 1 duergar blasphemer, 1 duergar hellcaller. Duergar
diabolists are exactly the sort of person who’d make bladerager trolls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 15: 4 war trolls, 1 destrachan far voice, 1 vinespeaker. The war trolls
can more or less ignore the thorns. They’ll be slowed by the difficult
terrain, but so will everyone else. The destrachan offers some artillery
support and can stay far away from the thorn zones.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troll.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Troglodyte</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-troglodyte.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already saw troglodytes in our reading of the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual and Vault&lt;/a&gt;,
and their basic lore remains the same. We get a few additional entries with
their own lore here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like before, these troglodytes are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Reptile
keyword, and their signature ability is the &lt;strong&gt;Troglodyte Stench&lt;/strong&gt;, an aura that
inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks. They have Darkvision and a speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troglodyte-thrasher&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Thrasher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already discussed their lore in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html&quot;&gt;MM/MV post&lt;/a&gt;, so I’m not going to
repeat that discussion here. However we do get a bit of additional lore. It
seems thrashers are actually &lt;em&gt;nonsapient&lt;/em&gt;, and their fellow troglodytes keep
them in cages when not using them as attack beasts. I wouldn’t use this
“charming” bit of lore in my own campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troglodyte-deepscourge&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Deepscourge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deepscourges are spellcasters. Like some poisonscale lizardmen, they follow a
tradition based on internal alchemy. The specific variant practiced by
deepscourges centers around manipulating and empowering their natural malodorous
secretions to turn them into damaging and debilitating spells. Like Curse
Chanters from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html&quot;&gt;MM/MV post&lt;/a&gt;, deepscourges act as priests and leaders of
troglodyte tribes, or as advisors to those leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deepscourges are Level 9 Artillery with the Leader keyword and 78 HP. Their
slime is turbocharged: it projects the same Troglodyte Stench aura as the
others, but it also projects an aura of &lt;strong&gt;Dizzying Stench&lt;/strong&gt; out to 10 squares!
Despite the name this is actually a “buffing” effect, increasing the radius of
the stench of any troglodytes inside by 1 square. I wonder if the auras of
multiple deepscourges stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main ranged attacks are an at-will &lt;strong&gt;Debilitating Ray&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
physical damage and weakens the target for a turn if it’s inside a stench
aura. The stat block doesn’t list an attack roll, but I guess this is an
editorial error and it should target AC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also attack with an area-effect &lt;strong&gt;Rancid Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which
only affects “non-reptiles”, targets Fortitude, does more damage than the ray
attack, and weakens for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hit by an attack the deepscourge can project a &lt;strong&gt;Blinding Stench&lt;/strong&gt; in a
burst around itself, targeting Fortitude and blinding (save ends) with no
damage. If that doesn’t give it space to move away, it will be forced to use its
weak &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troglodyte-temple-champion&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Temple Champion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, these are troglodyte holy warriors, usually tasked with
guarding their temples. These temples usually honor Torog, but some are
dedicated to even worse entities like Demogorgon or other demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blessings they receive tend to be subtle, of the type that makes them
smarter and more disciplined. They use a highly technical fighting style and
carry much better equipment than the rank and file. Though champions can be most
often found guarding a temple, they’re also sometimes sent on divine missions at
the head of troglodyte expeditionary forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Troglodyte Temple Champion is a Level 9 Soldier with 101 HP. It wears scale,
wields a flail, and also carries 2 javelins into battle. The &lt;strong&gt;flail&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt; make up their basic attacks, and they also have a couple of special
techniques. &lt;strong&gt;Sweeping Trip&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will maneuver that does a bit less damage
than an attack and knocks prone. &lt;strong&gt;Whirlwind Attack&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that
does basic attack damage in a Close Burst 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No marking mechanic here - the champion’s stickiness comes from their liberal
use of Sweeping Trips to keep opponents prone at their feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the Deepscourge notable for being the first troglodytew stat block that
can’t be easily re-skinned into another humanoid opponent. Its abilities are all
about the stench, both its own and that of its allies. It’s a uniquely
troglodytic monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, my opinion on troglodytes hasn’t changed much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s four sample encounters between levels 7 and 12, and they’re all assorted
bands of troglodytes. Sometimes they’re accompanied by drakes, and one of them
has a balhannoth that likely appears as an opportunistic predator during the
fight.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troglodyte.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troglodyte.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Tiger</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-tiger.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tigers are real animals and have been part of the game since its
beginnings. They’re some of the only animals whose “mundane” version was
considered worthy of a monster stat block at this point in the edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book describes tigers as powerful and cunning predators that can be found in
“rugged natural environments”. Let’s elaborate on that a bit, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Wikipedia “rugged natural environments” means mostly flat or hilly
forests, but those can range from cold Siberian taigas to temperate forests to
tropical jungles. A tiger requires a large amount of territory, which allows it
to range far and hunt its prey (usually large herbivores). Tigers are “solitary
but social”: they hunt alone but might nest together, with their range areas
overlapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 does add a bit of interesting fantastic lore by saying
tigers are sometimes domesticated by &lt;em&gt;ogres&lt;/em&gt; of all people to serve as guard and
hunting animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wild D&amp;amp;D tiger is not shy about including adventurers in its menu. If they run
across a battle while hunting, they might stalk its edges and pounce on any
combatant that gets separated from the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire tigers are as usual larger, stronger and spikier. They’re bolder and less
opportunistic, directly stalking prey that seems to be alone and weaker than
them. Their behavior is a lot closer to that of the tiger in &lt;em&gt;The Jungle Book&lt;/em&gt;
than that of a real-world animal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both mundane and dire tigers are Large Natural Beasts with low-light vision, a
ground speed of 8, and a climb speed of 4. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Feral
Surge&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that allows them to take a move action as a minor
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiger&quot;&gt;Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mundane” tigers are Level 6 Skirmishers with 73 HP. Their basic attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does immediate and ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a fight, the tiger always wants to be moving and charging, as being on
the move makes it much more dangerous. If forced to choose between a static
fight and running away, it will likely take the second option every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traits that make it want to move are &lt;strong&gt;Blur of Fur&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives it +4 AC
against opportunity attacks in any turn where it moves 2 or more squares; and
&lt;strong&gt;Charging Pounce&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives it bonus damage on charge attacks and makes it
so charging &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; end its turn. So it could use its standard action to
charge, and then either a move action or Feral Surge to move away immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dire-tiger&quot;&gt;Dire Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire Tigers are Level 8 Soldiers with 89 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; are stronger, and
they’re much more likely to accept the challenge of a stand-up fight. Even then
they’ll try to single out the weakest available target and kill it first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hunter’s Instinct&lt;/strong&gt; is an ability that helps then with that. It works exactly
like the Hunter’s Quarry ability of a PC ranger. The tiger spends a minor action
to make the nearest enemy its quarry, which lasts until the end of the encounter
or until it uses this ability again. The quarry takes extra damage from all of
the tiger’s attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dire tiger can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction whenever its
quarry is within 5 squares. It allows the creature to shift to a space adjacent
to the quarry and bite it. Since this is a leap, the tiger can cross enemy
spaces during the shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marking the right quarry requires some clever positioning, but once that happens
it will be hard for the other players to protect the victim from the tiger’s
leaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tigers have some cool mechanics to them, which is better than the generic
bags of HP I remember them being in previous editions. They also feel pretty
different from each other! I still would hesitate a bit before placing wild
tigers as opposition to my PCs, what with them being endangered in reality and
all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two sample encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: A couple of ogre savages taking their two pet tigers and their pet
macetail behemoth out for a stroll. Shrek and Fiona?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A weretiger running with a pack/harem of three dire tigers. The fact that you
have tigers running in packs should be a hint that there’s something unnatural
going on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/tiger.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/tiger.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Steel Predator</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-steel-predator.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I first saw this monster in one of the “late” Monster Manuals for 3.x,
which makes it fairly recent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed by Bane himself (“Original Design: Do Not Steal”), these living
constructs are designed as long-ranging assassination engines. They seem to be
his take on the “Retriever” concept pioneered by the primordials, with the main
difference being that the god of war is not interested in taking prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steel Predators are a little weaker individually, but unlike the retrievers
they’re still in production. They can travel the planes in search of their
target, though their means of travel is not quick enough to be a combat
ability. These things just love eating magic items: the more loaded the victim,
the more vigorous the pursuit. Once a steel predator kills its target it will
usually devour them, items and all. They also have a bit of golem-like magical
resistance that means they get stronger when they take thunder or lightning
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side effect of this refined palate, steel predator bodies are rich in
residuum, which can ironically make them a target for powerful, brave or
foolhardy hunters looking for a big score. When not on a mission, most steel
predators hang out in Bane’s native plane of Chernoggar, patrolling it alongside
platoons of bladelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steel Predators are Large Immortal Animates with the Living Construct
keyword. They’re Level 20 Elite Soldiers with 388 HP, darkvision, and a ground
speed of 8. As mentioned above, they can cross planar boundaries but this
ability doesn’t make it into their combat stat block. They have a +2 bonus to
saves against ongoing damage (for a total of +4 when combined with their elite
save bonus).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures have the body structure of a big cat, and they fight
accordingly, pouncing and biting with their metal jaws. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;
attack marks for a turn on a hit. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Vicious Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; that
works as a charge against Fortitude, does the same damage as a bite, and knocks
prone. Their multiattack ability is a bit weaker than a standard double attack,
but it’s still flavorful: &lt;strong&gt;Snap Jaw&lt;/strong&gt; allows the steel predator to make a bite
attack. If that hits it also knocks the target prone, and the creature can make
another bite attack against a different target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their most overtly supernatural attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Resonating Roar&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Burst 3
attack that deals heavy thunder damage, dazes, and deafens (save ends
both). This is a “recharge 5+” attack, but it also recharges automatically when
the predator takes thunder or lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when an adjacent creature shifts, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Shifting Steel&lt;/strong&gt; as a
reaction to shift into the vacated square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactics are fairly simple: pounce, roar, then keep biting with Snap Jaw until
the roar recharges. This should keep the PCs quite busy while the other monsters
attack them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things look enough like xenomorphs from &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; that I’m surprised they
don’t have acid blood. Maybe that would be too on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, Bane often sends steel predators on remote missions. They
end up working alongisde other servants of the god, or with other creatures that
share the same immediate goals. In that latter case, they’re known for turning
on their allies of convenience if those allies behave in a way that displeases
Bane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example encounter is Level 21, and has 2 steel predators accompanying 2
marut castigators. The maruts are likely mercenaries hired by an agent of Bane.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/09/steel-predator.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/09/steel-predator.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Star Spawn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the Warlock class was introduced late in D&amp;amp;D 3.x, it was Fourth Edition
that really made it shine. In addition to the infernal warlocks of the previous
edition, the Player’s Handbook also gave us fey and star pact
warlocks. Different pacts provided different mechanical and lore flavor, and
made the class approachable to people who didn’t want to play someone who had
literally sold their soul to the devil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fey warlocks were an immediate hit because they tied to the lore of the Feywild,
which was awesome from the start. You get your powers from David Bowie’s Goblin
King, what’s not to love about that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I personally loved star warlocks, their lore required a certain previous
familiarity with “cthulhoid” narratives that was by no means universal among D&amp;amp;D
players. I mean, in this one-shot I GMed shortly after acquiring the books I had
a player who honestly believed they were supposed to be New Agey
astrologers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I’m talking about PC warlocks in a Monster Manual reading is that
those paragraphs provide the context you need to understand why the &lt;em&gt;Wish Upon a
Star&lt;/em&gt; article from Dragon #366 was such a big deal. While it was mostly focused
on adding more options for star warlocks, it also included the first concrete
bit of lore on the “pact entities” for star warlocks. More information about
them would be added in subsequent books, and in the Monster Manual 2 they get an
entry for monsters themed after them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people in 4e’s implied setting don’t think too hard about the stars in the
night sky. To many they’re just pretty lights. Amateur astronomers can point out
constellations and identify a few specific stars by name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True scholars of the stars know about the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; constellations. They know that
some of those stars have fallen under the influence of certain powerful
entities, who use them to gaze at the world from across the infinite void. Their
gazes might be filled with fury, with hunger, or with emotions unfathomable to
feeble mortal minds. When you speak their true names, they listen, and might
even answer. Opinions differ as to whether that is a good or a bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stellar entities are usually associated with the Far Realm. Traditional
lore about the Far Realm says it’s a separate plane of existence, so according
to that it could be that these entities are using their stars as windows to our
plane. But this also raises an alternate, scarier possibility: maybe the “Far
Realm” isn’t a separate plane at all. Maybe it’s just what you find if you
travel far enough into the void.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every star is the avatar of an eldritch alien being, though some star
warlocks have recurring nightmares where every star in the sky opens up to
reveal an eye staring at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the information on the known eldritch stars comes from a scroll known as
&lt;em&gt;The Revelations of Melech&lt;/em&gt;, which is the sort of rare sanity-blasting tome that
should be very familiar to Call of Cthulhu players. It has the same in-world
status the Demonomicon of Iggwilv (which lists demons) or the Codex of Betrayal
(devils).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we get into the lore contained in the MM2. The most learned students of
the sky know of an orange star named Allabar, The Opener of the Way. Allabar
only appears when the world is about to enter a time of great turmoil, be it a
great war, a mighty ritual, or something similar. It races across the sky in a
seemingly random trajectory that passes by one or more of the other “special”
stars. When this happens, the way is opened for that star to release a Star
Spawn into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star Spawn are the anthropomorphic personifications of a specific star’s
will. Once they enter the world, they seek to enact that will. Some stay for
only as long as the conjunction with Allabar lasts, other can remain
indefinitely or until defeated. Some are solitary, others gather cults and
minions around themselves. Regardless of their specific MOs, star spawn tend to
be pretty evil from a mortal’s point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one knows for sure how or why this whole process happens. Is Allabar a
natural phenomenon of the void, or a sapient being with designs of its own? Is
there a rhyme or reason to its wanderings? The warlock Thulzar claimed to have
charted every star spawn incursion since the fall of Bael Turath and found a
pattern, but he vanished along with his tower and all his notes after a starless
night, leaving only a glassy crater behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 contains three Star Spawn in this entry, and we’ll look a
bit more into their specific lore and the lore of their star in their sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star Spawn are Aberrant Humanoids. The first one in this entry is Medium, all
others are Large. All of them have Darkvision, a ground speed of 6, and
communicate using telepathy with a range of 10 squares. Everything else about
them varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;herald-of-hadar&quot;&gt;Herald of Hadar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-star-spawn-herald.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morinbund Hadar used to be the brightest star in the sky. During the
tribulations that led to the fall of Bael Turath, it flared up into a burning
brand visible even during the day. Afterwards, it faded to a barely visible red
ember. Hadar’s dying gasps send its heralds into the world so they can harvest
life energy and delay its inevitable end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only Medium star spawn in this entry, heralds of Hadar look almost human
save for their glowing eyes and hostility to all forms of life, which they
attempt to drain. They’re Level 15 Brutes with 180 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heralds use their &lt;strong&gt;Hungry Claws&lt;/strong&gt; to fight, and they can make two basic attacks
with a single action. Once per encounter they can step it up and use &lt;strong&gt;Feeding
Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; to make up to three attacks (though no more than two on the same
target). Their life-force drain is the &lt;strong&gt;Breath of a Dying Star&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Blast
5 encounter power that targets Reflex, does good damage, and prevents targets
from regaining HP and spending healing surges (save ends). I imagine the claw
attacks drain life as well, but that’s probably just represented as part of
their damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever someone spends a healing surge within 5 squares of the herald,
&lt;strong&gt;Hadar’s Hunger&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to react in a variety of ways. Choose one whenever
this triggers: shift 3 squares closer to the triggering creature; make a basic
attack; regain the use of an encounter power; gain +2 to attacks for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like the Herald will want to focus most of its attacks on a single PC,
but will use the Breath on the others. That way it will leave someone still able
to spend healing surges so it can recharge its powers. Despite their “berserk”
fighting style, heralds are still sapient and capable of making alliances of
convenience with other creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;maw-of-acamar&quot;&gt;Maw of Acamar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-star-spawn-maw.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Hadar is dying, Acamar is already dead. This corpse-star is a black void that
devours everything that passes by it, even other stars and their light. Its
hunger is endless and without a purpose other than consumption itself. The Maws
of Acamar are avatars of that hunger, living gateways through which the dead
star can extend its ruinous grasp to the world. Unlike the other Spawn, they
come to the world under their own power, for even The Opener of the Way avoids
passing too close to Acamar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maws are Level 15 Controllers with 145 HP. Where Heralds of Hadar fight with
berserk intensity, Maws of Acamar just kinda stroll around the battlefield and
let the constant effects of their presence do the work for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gravitational field of their black hole progenitor is expressed as an aura
(5) named &lt;strong&gt;Hungry Star&lt;/strong&gt;. Anyone inside who wishes to move away from the Maw
must pay 3 movement points per square instead of the usual 1. Even if they do
it’s futile because the Maw can use &lt;strong&gt;Corpse Star’s Grip&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 5
vs. Fortitude; minor action) to pull them 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The destructive part of that gravitational pull is expressed as 2 different
attacks, both of which inflict ongoing damage instead of instant
wounds. &lt;strong&gt;Devouring Star&lt;/strong&gt; is a Close Burst 3 attack targetting Fortitude that
inflicts 10 ongoing damage; &lt;strong&gt;Devouring Touch&lt;/strong&gt; is a focused Reach 2 version
that inflicts 15 ongoing damage on a single target. In both cases the
&lt;strong&gt;Destroyer of Life&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait prevents adjacent enemies from shedding all
of that damage with a single save. The save only reduces the total damage by 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it’s possible to meet multiple Maws at once. They love to surround foes and
tear them apart by pulling them in several directions at once. I’d probably make
them immune to each other’s attacks, but that’s wouldn’t be the case for any
other ally. Anything and anyone who stands too close to a Maw is going to be
sucked in. If you pair them with other monsters, they would do well to stay away
from their “buddy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scion-of-gibbeth&quot;&gt;Scion of Gibbeth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-star-spawn-scion.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gibbeth is a cursed green sun which gestates at its core an unknowable
being. Warlocks and the like say that this being will only show its true face at
the end of the world, and this will send the tattered remains of the universe
into inescapable madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scions of Gibbeth are shards of this green star, providing a little taste of
what is to come. No two people who see one can agree on its appearance, save to
say it is horrible. Perhaps its true form is literally incomprehensible to
mortal minds, and the varied appearances described are a result of the people in
question instinctively trying to cope with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These abominations wander the world pursuing their enigmatic goals. They tend to
attack any living creature that draws too close, but they tolerate the presence
of worshippers and cultists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scions are Level 17 Controllers with 163 HP. Their abilities work at range and
are designed to keep PCs away. They’re surrounded by an &lt;strong&gt;Aura of Revulsion&lt;/strong&gt;
with size &lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;, enough to cover most of the battlefield. Creatures inside can’t
target the Scion with melee or ranged attacks unless it’s the enemy nearest to
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack are vanilla &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt;, but the others make up for
it. &lt;strong&gt;Mind-Splintering Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (range 20) deals light psychic damage and
dominates (save ends); &lt;strong&gt;Gibbeth’s Baleful Glare&lt;/strong&gt; does the same damage and
slides the target 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sets up the Scion’s basic tactics: stay well away from the PCs and dominate
them, gently nudging them away when they attempt to close. If they do manage to
close, there’s a couple more tricks available to the creature. &lt;strong&gt;Offering to
Gibbeth&lt;/strong&gt; gives it a +2 attack bonus for a turn whenever a PC spends a healing
surge within 2 squares of it; and &lt;strong&gt;Revelation of Gibbeth&lt;/strong&gt; is a burst 5 that
triggers when the Scion dies. This glimpse of its true form acts as an attack
against Will. Affected targets are Dazed, and must spend their sole action
charging or making a basic attack against their nearest ally. This is a &lt;em&gt;save
ends&lt;/em&gt; condition, so even if the dead Scion was the last monster on the board,
the party might still need to contend with the effect for a few rounds until
everyone makes their save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love all of this star lore! It feels so new, you know? It’s “cthulhoid”
without actually involving the Cthulhu Mythos and this is a big entry about
aberrant monsters that doesn’t contain a single tentacle anywhere in it. It’s
also scarier in places than even the traditional fiend lore. “There’s a place in
a different plane that’s full of evil fire” doesn’t quite have the same visceral
kick as “each star opens to reveal an eye and they’re all looking at you”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even think it’s cool that Hadar’s and Acamar’s basic descriptions are the
result of taking a real astronomical entity and running it through a Lovecraft
and/or Death Metal translator filter. A red supergiant is “ancient and dying,
gasping for breath as it tries to prolong its doomed existence”. A black hole is
a Corpse Star!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think they ever officially added Atropus from Elder Evils to the star
“pantheon”, but he’s a perfect fit. “The World Born Dead orbits The Corpse
Star!”, cries the mad warlock as invisible star spawn tear him limb from limb in
broad daylight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only place where I think this entry stumbles a bit is the sample
encounters. The lore of the star spawn is cool but it makes them stand a bit
apart from the more traditional D&amp;amp;D monsters, so it feels strange to see them
paired with those same monsters. You might need to reskin some of those monsters
to make them more star-aspected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: A Herald of Hadar teams up with a Beholder Eye of Flame and 2 Battle
Wight Commanders. A classic front-line and artillery formation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: A Maw of Acamar is accompanied by 2 hook horrors and 2 mind flayer
infiltrators. Here you want the others to form a perimeter around the Maw and
try to keep the PCs boxed in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There were also mechanical reasons for why they didn’t become as popular,
  but these have been more extensively discussed elsewhere and don’t quite
  fit a monster-focused post. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/03/star-spawn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/03/star-spawn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Sprite Swarm</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-sprite-swarm.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprites are super-tiny humanoid fey, tinier even than the pixies that would show
up as a playable option in &lt;em&gt;Heroes of the Feywild&lt;/em&gt;. I think they’ve been in the
game since at least AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition in some for or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprites in earlier editions tended to be described as just tiny fairy folk who
liked all the usual Victorian Fairy things like song and dance and pastoral
nature. They might have a propensity for pranks, but normally didn’t get more
aggressive than that unless the PCs were out to exterminate them. A single
sprite was pretty much harmless, but they often came in large numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t the sprites from earlier editions. These are Umbral Sprites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umbral Sprites are just as tiny as the nice variety, but they’re cruel,
violent, and territorial. Interactions between them and the PCs skip right past
the talky and pranky stages and go right to combat as swarms of these things
descend upon them. A single umbral sprite is still harmless to an adventurer,
but a swarm of them is dangerous enough to get monster stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though these tiny terrors are native to the Feywild, they tend to seek out areas
that contain crossings to the Shadowfell to claim as territory. Spriggans and
ill-intentioned gnomes tend to ally with them and use them as diversions for
subtler schemes. It’s hard to notice gnomes sneaking into your vaults when you
have a cloud of angry sprites poking out your eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry gives us stats for a fairly small swarm of umbral sprites. This is a
Medium swarm composed of Fey Humanoids, and counts as a Level 4 Controller with
55 HP. It has blindsight with range 6, a ground speed of 4, and a flight speed
of 6 with Hover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also has the standard swarm traits: it takes half damage from single-target
attacks, and extra damage from area attacks. Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) deals
3 damage to creatures caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Fangs and Blades&lt;/strong&gt;, but aside from the name
it’s nothing spectacular. Their special &lt;strong&gt;Darkwave&lt;/strong&gt; attack (recharge 5+) is
more impressive. It’s a Close Burst 3 that targets Reflex, does necrotic damage,
and creates a zone of darkness that lasts for a durn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have the gnome’s &lt;strong&gt;Fade Away&lt;/strong&gt; power, becoming invisible as a reaction
to taking damage once per encounter. This invisibility lasts for a turn, or
until they hit or miss with an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When fighting a group of PCs, they’re going to rely on Darkwave to keep them in
the dark and will use basic attacks and the swarm aura to deal damage while that
power recharges. The sprites are unaffected by their own darkness due to their
blindsight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can model a larger group of umbral sprites by using several swarms in an
encounter, or by increasing the level and size of a single one. They also make
me think about adapting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/152691/The-Dreams-of-Ruin&quot;&gt;The Dreams of Ruin&lt;/a&gt; to 4e, because they look like
they are the base creature for Murdersprites. A murdersprite swarm is probably
more like a Colossal Level 14-18 Brute, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 5, and is a grab-bag of Feywild hazards: 2
ettercap fang guards working with 2 sprite swarms and 2 fey panthers.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/01/sprite.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/01/sprite.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Spriggan</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-spriggan.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t find spriggans in my 2nd edition and earlier books, but I know they’re
in Pathfinder, so they were probably introduced in D&amp;amp;D 3.x. This entry is their
4e debut. It feels like there’s been some condensing here because this entry
also uses several other names that I’m sure belonged to separate “small evil
fey” enemies, like “redcap” and “powrie”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/21/gnome.html&quot;&gt;post on gnomes&lt;/a&gt;, we already saw that the gnome people used to be
enslaved by the fomorians in the ancient past, but that they managed to
escape. Here, we learn that not all of them managed to get away. Those
unfortunates were eventually twisted into spriggans by fomorian magic. It’s
unclear whether this happened as punishment for the escape attempt, or during
some subsequent experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book doesn’t describe present-day spriggans as fomorian slaves, so maybe
they were discarded by their former masters as failures. They live in
underground settlements excavated under rugged terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fomorian magic warped spriggan hearts as much as it did their bodies. Soaking
stuff in the blood of enemies seems to be a big deal to them. Their habit of
doing that to their hats caused them to also be known as redcaps by other
sapients. Spriggan communities delight in raiding, tormenting and extracting
tribute from their weaker neighbors, behaving pretty much like bandit gangs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spriggans are Small Fey Humanoids with low-light vision and a ground speed
of 6. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Redcap Zeal&lt;/strong&gt;, a free-action encounter power
that grants them temporary HP when they bloody or defeat an enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spriggan-giantsoul&quot;&gt;Spriggan Giantsoul&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giantsouls tap into the fomorian magic in their blood, which gives them enhanced
strength and the ability to stretch their arms to gain a giant’s reach. They’re
Level 8 Brutes with 106 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These spriggans fight unarmed, using &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; as their basic attack. The
stretch-arm thing comes into play in the &lt;strong&gt;Giantsoul Slam&lt;/strong&gt; special attack
(recharge 4+), which is Reach 2, does the same damage as the slam, and knocks
prone on a hit. Both attacks deal bonus damage when the spriggan is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, the giantsoul can use a &lt;strong&gt;Surprise Slam&lt;/strong&gt;, an interrupt that
triggers when an enemy within 2 squares of them attacks an ally. This allows it
to use Giantsoul Slam against the triggering enemy, recharging the ability if
necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re good frontliners, with a limited ability to protect squishier allies
when the PCs try to get around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spriggan-powrie&quot;&gt;Spriggan Powrie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All spriggans use iron-shod boots as part of their combat gear, but powries have
a particular dedication to the fine art of stomping. They’re Level 7 Skirmishers
with 79 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The powrie fights with a &lt;strong&gt;sickle&lt;/strong&gt; that does light physical damage and inflicts
ongoing damage. It can also be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Hamstring&lt;/strong&gt; special attack that has
the same effects and also knocks prone and slows for a turn. This recharges when
the powrie is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against prone enemies it can use the amusing &lt;strong&gt;Punt The Fallen&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which
deals the same damage as the sickle and pushes 3 squares. The best thing about
this attack is that it’s an at-will minor action!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the powrie has combat advantage against a creature taking ongoing damage,
attacking that creature with any of the above will also increase their ongoing
damage by 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the &lt;strong&gt;Blood Slide&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait prevents the powrie from provoking
opportunity attacks when leaving a square adjacent to a creature who’s bloodied
or taking ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So most of the time a powrie will be attacking enemies with the sickle and
moving around the battlefield with the aid of Blood Slide in order to spread as
much ongoing damage around as possible, and will then seek combat advantgae
against a single target. Hamstring and Punt the Fallen is an hilarious
combination, and the latter means powries pair really well with other enemies
who can drop targets prone more often. Multiple powries in a fight mean you can
begin an impromptu soccer match with a prone PC as the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spriggan-thorn&quot;&gt;Spriggan Thorn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spriggan thorn is armed with a short sword and a light shield, which are
imbued with a curse of thorns. The sword itself is enveloped in them, and the
spriggan can curse an enemy and cause thorns to spring from under their
skin. It’s a Level 6 Soldier with 71 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt; damages and inflicts ongoing damage (thorns!). It can be
enhanced with the &lt;strong&gt;Drowsing Puncture&lt;/strong&gt; power as a minor action. This makes the
next attack daze the target for a turn and knock them prone, if it hits. It
recharges when the thorn is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse is called &lt;strong&gt;Mark of Thorns&lt;/strong&gt;, and it’s an encounter power that
automatically hits a target in a Close Burst 5. A cursed target can’t make
opportunity attacks against the thorn, and takes 4 damage at the end of any turn
in which it didn’t attack the thorn. Any allies of the target that start the
turn adjacent to them also take 4 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drowsing Puncture is a fine skill to use against PC defenders, and the Mark is
quite versatile. When used against a defender, it allows the thorn to slip past
the PC front-line unmolested. It also works to diver the attention of any PC who
would normally gain more by attacking one of the spriggan’s more fragile
allies. They pair really well with powries, who can end up increasing the
ongoing damage caused by the swords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spriggan-witherer&quot;&gt;Spriggan Witherer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witherers are spriggan spellcasters who specialize in harmful weather control
magic. They can probably cause serious trouble to agrarian communities with
rituals, and they can also create more localized effects useful in
combat. They have an obsession with soaking the earth in blood, so they pair
well with enemies with a similar imagery. They’re Level 8 Artillery with 70 HP
and the Leader keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;whithering touch&lt;/strong&gt; vs. Reflex that deals necrotic
damage. Their main single-target ranged attack is &lt;strong&gt;Sun Scorch&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10
vs. Reflex) dealing fire and radiant damage. They can use a spell named
&lt;strong&gt;Flattening Wind&lt;/strong&gt; either as a close blast 3 or as an area 3/range 10 attack
vs. Fortitude. This deals physical damage, pushes 2 squares, and knocks
prone. It recharges when they’re first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After they’re bloodied, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Blood For the Earth&lt;/strong&gt; at will. This is an
area 2/range 10 attack that deals light physical damage, inflicts ongoing
damage, and gives 5 temporary HP to any allies caught in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes for an artillery threat that starts off fairly aggressive and
switches to more of a support role as the fight proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spriggans are fairly good at fulfilling the “small evil fey” niche, and I love
the ties to fomorian lore. There are some good synergies between the stat blocks
presented here,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spriggans can still be found working for fomorians, but some also work for evil
eladrin or run their own rackets. They keep dangerous plants and animals around
their settlements for protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 9: an evil eladrin twilight incanter with a pet
shambling mound and a quartet of spriggan goons (2 giantsouls, 2 witherers).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/01/spriggan.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/01/spriggan.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Spider</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If there’s one thing that D&amp;amp;D doesn’t lack, it’s monstrous spiders. The Monster
Manual gave us a bunch of them; the Monster Vault would update some of these and
add new ones. The Monster Manual 2, published between those two books, adds a
whole new batch that doesn’t overlap with either of the other books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the spiders here have Tremorsense 10 and a climb speed enhanced by the
Spider Climb trait, which allows them to walk on ceilings. They also have a Web
Walker trait that allows them to ignore difficult terrain caused by
webs. Finally, they have the very obvious Spider keyword, which allows them to
be affected by all those drow and ettercap abilities that benefit “spider
allies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bristle-spider&quot;&gt;Bristle Spider&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-spider-bristle.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These elephant-sized arachnids were originally bred by oni to serve as their
mounts. In our narrative present, several other peoples have adopted them as
well. Their biggest fans are the ettercap and the drow, neither of which have
ever met a spider monster they didn’t like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bristle spiders can also be found in the wild, where they inhabit dense jungles
and caves. These environments tend to have enough cover to allow even these huge
monsters to hide effectively and ambush their prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bristle Spiders are Huge Natural Beasts, and Level 15 Elite Lurkers with 232
HP. They have a ground speed of 8 and a climb speed of 6. I don’t know if they
make webs themselves, but they still have Web Walker. As lurkers, they’re
trained in Stealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a venomous &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; that deals damage with slow and
ongoing poison damage riders. They can also spit an &lt;strong&gt;Acidic Poison Spray&lt;/strong&gt; in a
Close Blast 5. This targets reflex and deals both instant and ongoing “acid and
poison” damage, and also slows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those bristles are also useful in combat as part of the &lt;strong&gt;Bristle Blast&lt;/strong&gt; attack
(recharge 4+). This is a minor action, Close Blast 5 attack against
Fortitude. It deals no damage, but a hit blinds and dazes the target for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being an elite, the bristle spider lacks a double attack
ability. Instead it relies on its at-will acidic poison blast to hit multiple
PCs per attack, with a side order of bristles to keep them vulnerable. It would
probably work better as an elite controller than an elite lurker, with more HP
and better AC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 14 and has a bristle spider acting as a palanquin
for a drow priestess and her drow blademaster bodyguard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phase-spider&quot;&gt;Phase Spider&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-spider-phase.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A returning classic, Phase Spiders have undergone some changes to account for
the absence of an Ethereal plane in 4e. Here, they’re fey spiders with innate
teleportation powers. They were originally created by the eladrin as biological
weapons meant to infiltrate the halls of the drow and wreak havoc inside. It’s a
spider arms race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These spiders can survive nearly anywhere as long as they have prey to
hunt. Their favorite targets are fey creatures, to the extent that they’ll go
after the fey members of a mixed-origin party even if a non-fey target would be
more advantageous. This behavior was probably an attempt by eladrin wizards to
get them to go after drow. You can imagine how that turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase Spiders are Large Fey Beasts, and Level 8 Skirmishers with 87 HP. They
have ground, climb, and &lt;em&gt;teleport&lt;/em&gt; speeds of 6. Good luck pinning them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; deal somewhat low damage, but have a dangerous rider: targets
are initially slowed, but after the first failed save they become
unconscious. This is also a (save ends) condition, but the victim is completely
unable to act while it lasts &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; is even more vulnerable to attack than if
they were “just” stunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethereal Bite&lt;/strong&gt; allows the spider to teleport 10 squares and make a bite
attack, working as a good ambush starter. &lt;strong&gt;Ethereal Repulsion&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt
that triggers when an enemy moves adjacent to the spider: it attacks their Will
and teleports them 4 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes ranged attacks the best way to deal with phase spiders. They, in
turn, will eagerly teleport to the party’s back line and munch on the squishies,
relying on Ethereal Repulsion to delay any rescue by the melee defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 7 and features two eladrin fey knights leading a
pack of three trained phase spiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tomb-spider&quot;&gt;Tomb Spider&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-spider-tomb.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These rotund arachnids are a Shadowfell species that has particularly strong
incentives to seek out passages into the world. Their lifecycle requires them to
lay eggs inside corpses, so they seek out crypts and graveyards for use as
breeding grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the eggs hatch they animate the corpse, which acts as ambulatory shelter
for the hatchlings until it finally splits open and lets them out. Orcus
cultists just looove tomb spiders, as do all other types of death-themed
villain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomb Spiders are Large Shadow Beasts, and Level 11 Elite Controllers with 226
HP. They have Resist 10 Necrotic, along with ground and climb speeds of 6. Their
&lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; damage, daze, and inflict ongoing necrotic damage (save ends
both). Someone bitten by the spider can’t use the Second Wind action until the
end of the encounter, though they can still be healed by other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These spiders definitely to spin webs: they can shoot &lt;strong&gt;Web Nets&lt;/strong&gt; at single
targets as a minor action (Ranged 10 vs. Reflex). A hit restrains the target and
makes them vulnerable to necrotic damage until they pass a save. Less often,
they can squeeze out a glob of &lt;strong&gt;Webbed Terrain&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which affects a
large area and immobilizes on a hit. Hit or miss, the webs remain as difficult
terrain until the end of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 11 and features a deatphriest of orcus leading 2
battle wights and 3 cultists to battle, using the tomb spider as armored
support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tomb-spider-broodswarm&quot;&gt;Tomb Spider Broodswarm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-spider-tomb-broodswarm.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a swarm of tiny tomb spiders that has just burst out of their corpse
nest. It’s a Medium Shadow Beast (Swarm), and counts as a Level 10 Lurker with
84 HP. It has the standard spider traits from this entry, and the standard swarm
traits of being resistant to melee and ranged attacks, and vulnerable to area
attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) slows those caught inside. Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Bites&lt;/strong&gt;
attack is a lesser version of mommy’s bite, and instead of attacking it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Shadow Drift&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) to shift shift 5 squares and gain +4 to all
defenses for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no stats for the undead corpse that houses the spiders, but you can
probably use something like a non-royal mummy described as being wrapped in webs
instead of linen wraps. Depending on your tastes, it could be a minion that
disgorges a Broodswarm when killed, a &lt;em&gt;regular&lt;/em&gt; that does the same (and thus
counts as an elite two-stage monster), or a regular reskinned mummy if you want
the young swarm to die when it dies instead of bursting out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No sample encounter here, as the adult tomb spider used the space for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda like the phase and tomb spider mechanics… but in the end, it’s more
spiders. By the end of the edition we’ll end up with enough spider variants that
you’ll have one for every situation, but you should definitely not use all of
them in the same campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/20/spider.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/20/spider.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Sphinx</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-sphinx.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sphinxes already made their 4e debut on the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/12/27/sphinx.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;, and the MM2
gives us an additional variant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore-of-the-sphinx-mystery&quot;&gt;The Lore of the Sphinx Mystery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All sphinxes have a common origin as sacred guardian beasts, as described in the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/12/27/sphinx.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual entry&lt;/a&gt;, but not all of them are exactly alike. This stat
block represents an individual with preferences and abilities different from
those of the typical MM1 sphinx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All sphinxes have the ability to propose challenges that help separate intruders
from visitors who have a right to be at the places they guard. Riddles are a
classic but are far from the only option, and the MM1 entry made some effort to
stress that part. Here, though, we go the other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sphinx Mystery is an individual who’s &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; into riddles. She doesn’t just
use them as her basic authentication scheme: she also uses them as weapons in
the middle of an actual fight. She likes riddle games so much that she might
just choose to keep playing rather than fighting with lethal intent, if her
opponents can keep the game fun for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intruders who can’t answer those riddles are in real trouble, though, because
they do real damage and are as sticky as warlock curses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sphinx Mystery is a Level 19 Brute with 224 HP. Despite being a regular, she
still has an action point. This might be an editorial error, but it’s fun so I’d
keep it. She also has low-light vision, and moves at ground and air speeds of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of her attacks are part of the standard lion beast arsenal. The likely
fight-opener is a a &lt;strong&gt;Terrifying Roar&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) that targets Fortitude,
deals thunder damage, pushes 5 squares, and knocks prone. Her basic attack are
&lt;strong&gt;Ancient Claws&lt;/strong&gt; that do heavy damage, and she can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Bite
of Ages&lt;/strong&gt; that deals light damage, knocks prone, and immobilizes with the weight
of history (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the Mystery can use &lt;strong&gt;Riddle Me This&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10). This is
an at-will ability that represents the sphinx compelling someone to solve a
riddle. This “hits” automatically, and dazes the target until the riddle is
answered or until the encounter ends. Answering the riddle requires spending a
minor action and succeeding at a DC 25 History check. Anyone can attempt the
test on their turn, not just the affected PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the targetted PC doesn’t attempt to solve the riddle on their turn, they take
2d8 psychic damage at the end of that turn. They also take this damage if
someone else answers the riddle for them. This damage is light, but about in
line with the amount of “traditional” ongoing damage an effect at this level
would cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the target will be dazed, which means that if they attempt to answer
the riddle, that’s the only thing they can do on their turn. So it might be
better to let an unaffected buddy answer it and eat a single instance of that
psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mystery’s last attack is the amusingly named &lt;strong&gt;Corrective Maul&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a
claw attack that does even more damage and recharges whenever anyone fails to
answer one of her riddles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The riddle mechanic is awesome! It makes the sphinx very controllery despite her
being a Brute. Since the riddle is ranged, you’ll want to delay her entry into
melee combat a bit until she can apply it to every PC. As a regular monster, the
sphinx will always be found alongside a few buddies, so they can help with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 16: 2 nothic cacklers, 2 savage minotaurs, and a
sphinx mystery. This is either an evil sphinx running with other assorted
marauders, or a more traditional guardian who has managed to recruit several
would-be intruders to her service through riddles and bets.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/19/sphinx.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/19/sphinx.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Slaughterstone Construct</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think Slaughterstone Constructs first appeared on the D&amp;amp;D Miniatures game in
late 3e. Their naming style marks them as a construct created after the
“(Material) Golem” namespace had been mostly exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach to an underground dwarf fortress usually consists of a number of
narrow tunnels, and that’s where most of the fighting happens when these places
are attacked. Tunnel fighting is a nasty affair, particularly when it’s two
large armies going at it. No place to run, no place to hide. Each inch of ground
is bought with lives, and when you advance you step on the bodies of foe and
friend alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaughterstone Constructs are the dwarven answer to this problem. They’re
defensive siege engines built for the singular purpose of making sure the only
ones who die are the invaders. Their intended usage is that you set them loose
on a tunel and watch them run through it while turning everyone inside into
chunky salsa. Their extreme toughness and strength means not many armies can
stand up to them even in a more open field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a proper slaughterstone construct is quite difficult. To sculpt the
body, you need a solid block of stone upon which the blood of a hero has been
shed. Even if you have that stone, only the very best dwarf artificers can turn
it into a construct. You’ll only find these things defending the largest and
wealthiest dwarven kingdoms, or other places that have good relationships with
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the blood requirement doesn’t mean you need to &lt;em&gt;sacrifice&lt;/em&gt; a hero on
the stone block. You could cut the stone from a cave or tunnel where that hero
has fought. Alternatively, if your GM likes this sort of technically correct
solution you could get yourself a brand new stone block and ask a certified war
hero to prick their finger and let a drop of blood fall on it. Neither of these
methods is easy (heroes don’t grow on trees!) but they’re far more ethical than
sapient sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have neither a master artisan nor a source of heroic blood but you still
want your blender tank, you can pay a middling craftsdwarf for a knockoff that’s
less reliable but still pretty strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three varieties of slaughterstone constructs here. Two “genuine” models
and a knockoff. All of them are Large Natural Animates with the Construct
keyword. They have darkvision, a ground speed of 6, and the ability to squeeze
into Medium passages without any penalties and without granting combat
advantage. They’re immune to poison, disease, and sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Int is 1, the worst possible score, but you don’t need more than that when
your only two functions are “walk forward” and “kill”. They probably respond to
commands of equivalent complexity like “stop killing” and “go back to your
garage”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slaughterstone-eviscerator&quot;&gt;Slaughterstone Eviscerator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-slaughterstone-eviscerator.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eviscerators are armed with a large number of whirling scythe blades, and look
a bit like super-edgy stone mantids. They’re Level 18 Brutes with 212 HP. The
blades never stop moving, and to model that they have a &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Blades&lt;/strong&gt; aura
(2) that deals 10 damage to anyone caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As weapons, those blades are are Reach 2 and have the High Crit property. Their
basic attack deals heavy damage to a single target, and they can also be used in
a &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Bladestorm&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) that hits everyone in a Close Burst 2
for average damage. This makes them as dangerous in the open as in a tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slaughterstone-hammerer&quot;&gt;Slaughterstone Hammerer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-slaughterstone-hammerer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are more robust than eviscerators and mount stone hammers instead of
blades. Once they reach you, it’s really hard to get away from them. Hammerers
are Level 25 Soldiers with 233 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They project a &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Step&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that slows those caught inside. The
hammers can be used in two different attacks: a basic &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
average damage and knocks prone, and a &lt;strong&gt;Hammerstrike&lt;/strong&gt; that deals the same
damage and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the hammerer’s skills mark enemies, but if you use them properly enemies
will have no option but to attack the hammerer anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slaughterstone-slicer&quot;&gt;Slaughterstone Slicer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our “knockoff”, described as a less powerful version of a genuine
eviscerator. It’s a Level 11 Elite Brute with 276 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slicers have pretty much the same attacks and traits as eviscerators, with
smaller numbers due to the level difference. Their Bladestorm is supposed to be
an encounter power that recharges when the slicer is first bloodied, despite the
“at-will” tag on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a tendency to malfunction, becoming dazed for a turn after they
either deal or take a critical hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth Edition’s combat rules make these constructs even more dangerous than the
lore indicates. Both the lore and the rules say a construct “plugs” a tunnel and
prevents enemies from passing through. The rules also say that allies may freely
move and attack through each others’ spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means slaughterstone constructs pair really well with artillery monsters,
and with controllers that have good ranged attacks. They’re also pretty good
with skirmishers who can dart forward, attack, and move behind the construct
again. Even if they can’t do all that in the same turn, their exposure to the
PCs is still reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our example encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 11: 1 duergar blasphemer, 2 duergar fleshtearers, 1 slaughterstone
slicers. Looks like it’s not just dwarves who build these.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 18: 2 Eldritch Giants, 1 Nothic Mindblight, 2 Slaughterstone
Eviscerators. Maybe they conquered a dwarf fortress and stole the constructs?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 25: 1 Beholder Eye of Chaos, 1 Oni Thunderer, 3 Slaughterstone
Hammerers. This is the “strong artillery”, “mobile skirmisher” setup I
mentioned, in its epic incarnation. You think you’re safe because the corridor
is 6 squares wide, and then you see three constructs side by side blocking all
of it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/16/slaughterstone-construct.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/16/slaughterstone-construct.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
