<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 14:44:27 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 14:44:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I write this, I’ve just finished writing all of the articles of my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;Let’s
Read series on the Monster Manual 2&lt;/a&gt;. So now I’m going to start on the
Monster Manual 3!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 3 is obviously the third big monster book for Dungeons &amp;amp;
Dragons 4th Edition, and it was published in June 2010, about a year after the
MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the stuff I’ve written on the intro to the MM2 linked above also
applies to the MM3. Monster roles remain the same, as does the gradation that
goes from Minion to Regular to Elite to Solo. The encounter design system is the
same as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things have changed dramatically, though! While you still have the lore
tables with skill DCs, the surrounding flavor text has gotten a lot bigger,
replacing the minimalist sentences of past books with larger paragraphs written
in a more dramatic tone. The extra space taken up by this text means we no
longer have sample encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks themselves also changed a lot, with monster abilities separated
and listed according to the type of action they use (passive traits, standard,
move, minor, triggered, always in that order).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the math for basic monster numbers has finally reached its
final, fully fixed form. Attacks, defenses, HP and average damage all follow the
basic formula in the legendary &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogofholding.com/?p=512&quot;&gt;Monster Manual 3 in a Business Card&lt;/a&gt;
post. This updated math was also published as an errata update to the Dungeon
Master’s Guide, but the Business Card has it in even more condensed
form. Chronologically, this is the first book where you wouldn’t need to apply
any blanket fixes to monster damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were following my Let’s Read posts while reading the actual books, you’ll
be familiar with all of these changes from the Monster Vault, which I read in
parallel with the first MM &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The MV would be published in November
2010, updating the most “iconic” monsters from the first two books to the new
format and collecting some from this one as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Vault would in turn be followed by “Monster Vault: Threats to the
Nentir Vale”, the final monster book I intend to cover in my readings. But
that’s still a ways away. For now, we look to the MM3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book has monsters of all levels, but focuses a bit more on the higher
end. The index in my PDF copy is a little wonky because it lists each individual
stat block in alphabetic order, but I’ll still read them in the order in which
the larger entries appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes in math also mean that monsters are much less likely to have healing
powers. Leader monsters from the MM3 are much more likely to provide combat
buffs than to heal their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/23/mm3-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/23/mm3-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Traits Appendix</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the last in a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the first Monster Manual before it, the Monster Manual 2 ends with a short
appendix containing rules for using some of the humanoids from the book as
playable characters. This one is a lot smaller than the MM’s appendix, and I
don’t think any of the races in it got much in the way of subsequent support or
more complete versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three writeups and their notable traits are listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bullywugs&lt;/strong&gt; have Swamp Walk and get Primordial as a bonus language. Their
racial power is the Rancid Air aura from their monster writeups. +2 to CON and
DEX.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duergar&lt;/strong&gt; are predictably similar to dwarves, but they get Deep Speech as a
bonus language and the Infernal Quills racial power. +2 to CON and WIS.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kenku&lt;/strong&gt; get the Flock Effect and Mimicry abilities from their monster
writeups, but don’t have any bonus languages. Flock Effect is a pretty awesome
ability for a rogue. +2 to DEX and CHA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with this we can finally close the MM2, and move on to the next book in my
planned series. See you on the Monster Manual 3 Let’s Read!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/13/traits-appendix.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/13/traits-appendix.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Xorn</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-xorn.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see xorns in my copy of the AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition monster manual, so they date from
at least that far back. This is their 4e debut, and they’re the last monster in
the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xorns are earth elementals native to the Elemental Chaos, but they long ago
spread to the deep subterranean tunnels and caverns of the world. Their
three-lobed radial symmetry makes them seem quite bizarre to natives of the
world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xorns can swim through rock and earth as if it was water, and must feed on
certain rare metals and gems. They’re sapient, and will often bargain with other
people, aiding in their mining or smelting efforts in exchange for their
“food”. It seems they’re not very concerned with much beyond their own survival,
so they’ll happily ally with creatures of all dispositions, from dwarves and
galeb dhur to duergar and fire giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xorns found in the wild are likely to be drawn to the gems and magic items
carried by PCs. The PCs might be able to negotiate with them and avoid a
fight… but some less scrupulous xorns tend to use these negotiations to help
set ambushes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two stat blocks here, but they’re very similar, so I’ll discuss the first
one and then note how the second one differs from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;xorn&quot;&gt;Xorn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Medium Elemental Magical Beast (Earth), and a Level 9
Skirmisher with 102 HP. Its senses include darkvision and all-around vision,
which prevents it from being flanked. It has a relatively low ground speed of 5,
and a burrow speed of 5 that’s enhanced by the &lt;strong&gt;Earth Glide&lt;/strong&gt; ability. It
allows the xorn to burrow through solid rock as if it was loose earth, using its
full burrow speed at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The xorn’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Triple Strike&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make
three of those against different targets. If there’s only one foe in range, it
will use its &lt;strong&gt;Earthy Maw&lt;/strong&gt; instead since it does about double the damage of a
claw strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the xorn can &lt;strong&gt;Submerge&lt;/strong&gt;, partially burying itself and
gaining a +2 bonus to AC until it moves. When it’s missed by a melee attack, it
can &lt;strong&gt;retreat&lt;/strong&gt;, burrowing its speed as a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight, a xorn will jump from inside a wall or floor, submerge for the AC
bonus, and claw or bite the party’s squishies. If a missed attack doesn’t make
the creature retreat automatically, it will do so on its next turn so it can
repeat this pattern. Earth Glide makes it extremely mobile despite its poor
speed, particularly in an underground environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diadmondhide-xorn&quot;&gt;Diadmondhide Xorn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an older or simply well-fed specimen, who lives in a place of the
Elemental Chaos where its preferred food is more plentiful. Its hide glitters
with the minerals it has ingested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diamondhide xorns are Large in size, and are Level 16 Skirmishers with 160
HP. They have all the same attacks and abilties as the basic xorn, with bigger
numbers. They also have a new attack named &lt;strong&gt;Undermine&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) in which
the xorn burrows its speed and attacks a creature it passes under. This targets
Reflex, does heavy damage, and restrains the target (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 9, and consists of a pair of xorns in cahoots with
a troop of duergar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to see xorns here. Their weird looks make them an iconic D&amp;amp;D monster
in my mind. A nice way to close the book.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/05/xorn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/04/05/xorn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Exalted Martial Arts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s this post on Mailanka’s Musings that talks about two different ways of
modeling martial arts in RPGs. The first is something he calls “Move-Based”, and
the second “Skill-Based”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based martial arts is how most RPGs in the 90’s did it. You bought a style,
and that gave you access to a series of “moves” that were essentially special
powers with individual rules for what they did. Some systems made you buy each
individual move as well, usually as a way to model your progression in the
style - advanced practitioners know more moves. Your move set is as or more
important than your raw skill level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skill-based martial arts are what GURPS does. Everyone uses the same skills to
fight, and knowing one style or another is mostly a matter of flavor with a few
minor mechanical bonuses thrown in. What really matters are your skill levels:
people with different style familiarities but similar skill levels are equally
effective. The same applies to someone who “knows” a style and someone who just
has the combat skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based rules might allow you to emulate some classic kung-fu stories that
are all about how some styles are objectively superior to others, or how there’s
a secret style or ultimate technique that’s jealously guarded by a cranky old
master. Skill-based rules are closer to Bruce Lee’s philosophy, or modern views
of martial arts in general, where individual skill is more important and the
“ultimate power” is learning from multiple sources and combining everything into
something that works for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer skill-based rules, largely due to my exposure to GURPS
Martial Arts for Fourth edition. Everything it introduces can be done by someone
who isn’t using the style rules. It covers styles from the whole world without
treating any of them as inherently superior, and it acknowledges that basically
any organized system of fighting counts as a “style”. The “generic swings” other
systems describe as the standard form of fighting only happen if you’re
completely untrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this preference, it comes as no surprise that I have a few weirdly
specific hangups about how Exalted handles its martial arts. Let’s talk about
them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exalteds-martial-arts&quot;&gt;Exalted’s Martial Arts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exalted’s &lt;em&gt;whole system&lt;/em&gt; is entirely move-based. Every PC has a large set
of “Charms” that are usually linked to skills, and represent magic techniques
they can use to enhance uses of that skill. Getting to the maximum possible
skill level is trivial, and it’s your Charms that make the difference when going
against similarly supernatural opposition. This goes even for non-combat skills,
though the fighty bits tend to take up a lot of attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martial Arts are part of this system, but the game still takes pains to make
them extra-special, even as it struggles to explain what makes them different
from standard combat powers. Exalted First Edition had a separate Martial Arts
skill, whose associated Charms were structured as “Martial Arts Styles”. They
didn’t really “mix” with charms of other skills. As a result, a lot of each
style’s Charms end up duplicating the effect of basic combat Charms in different
ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second Edition merged “standard” unarmed combat and Martial Arts, and made it a
little easier to mix and match charms from a few different styles. Third Edition
doubled down on the original position and made it so each style had its own
separate skill, thus coming full circle on the ‘martial arts cost more because
they are exotic and special’ trope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-id-do-it&quot;&gt;How I’d Do It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had I been writing these rules, I’d probably take them in a different direction
entirely, and more towards the way GURPS sees things. There would be no Martial
Arts skill. Each style is associated with a single standard combat skill, and
consists of exactly three Charms representing its advanced or iconic
techniques. The basic stuff is already covered by the standard skill and
standard Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Charms I’d reuse the “lotus” metaphor, so they would be the Root, Bulb
and Blossom Charms. You learn them in this order. Each has the previous one as a
prerequisite, and probably an increasing Essence score. They’re meant to be
combined with the standard Charms for that skill, relying on them for the basic
dice-adding mechanics and such. If you know Charms of multiple styles you can
explicitly combine them as long as the combination is otherwise rules-legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who learns to fight is a martial artist, even if they never pick up
style Charms. Every martial artist ultimately develops their own personal style
by learning from as many sources as possible and keeping what works for
them. And you can certainly describe the way your kung-fu looks as being a
certain style even if you don’t have the Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example-snake-style&quot;&gt;Example: Snake Style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t originally plan on doing this, but what the heck, let’s go! Snake Style
has traditionally been the main corebook style, so let’s see how it would look
in this format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what the lore says about it: it’s a style focused on speed and
precision, aiming to take down better armed and armored opponents before they
have time to act. It uses two-fingered strikes to hit pressure points and
exposed tendons. Masters of the style can “pierce through armor”, “paralyze
opponents with pressure point strikes”, and “deliver poisonous Essence through
their fingertips”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of what to keep in our new format is pretty easy - each of the things
masters of the style can do references a specific Charm. We want those. All the
others increase basic numbers in different ways and can be replaced by standard
charms from Brawl and other trees. Want to dodge like a snake? Take Dodge
Charms. Want the “tough scales” effect? Take Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our new Snake Style is an unarmed style linked to Brawl. Our Root Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Crippling Pressure Point Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (Ex3 p. 428). Our Bulb Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Armor-Penetrating Fang Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Our Blossom Charm is &lt;strong&gt;Essence Venom
Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Their skill level and Essence prerequisites remain the same, but read
Brawl in place of Martial Arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quick and dirty sketch, and some additional work would be
required. Essence Venom Strike needs to be rewritten a bit, since half of its
effects reference Charms we’ve eliminated. We might also want to rewrite some of
the base Brawl charms, though I haven’t looked at them in much depth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>exalted</category>
        
        <category>martial-arts</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Wood Woad</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-wood-woad.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I remember seeing mention of Wood Woads in AD&amp;amp;D somewhere, but I
couldn’t find them in my books. This is their 4e debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood Woads are fey creatures distantly related to dryads. Like dryads, they
devoutly protect the natural environment of their home region. Unlike dryads,
they all look male and have absolutely zero chill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do wood woads attack would-be despoilers of nature with murderous
intent, they tend to blame each new intruder for the crimes of all the previous
ones. So even if you’re careful with the environment and try to approach them
peacefully, they’ll still try to kill you because some fool cut a tree down
years ago and managed to run away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood woads tend to ally with other sworn protectors of nature, like dryads,
centaurs and some elves or other fey. So I guess you could still deal with them
peacefully if you manage to approach those allies first and get them to vouch
for you, or have them act as intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a single Wood Woad stat block. It’s a Medium Fey Humanoid with the Plant
keyword, and a Level 8 Soldier with 92 HP. It has trained Perception, and a
ground speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood Woads wield wooden shields and clubs. Their basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt;,
which does average damage and has no special effects. They can channel magic
through it to inflict &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Judgment&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+, Reliable) on a
target. This is an attack that does more damage than the basic club,
immobilizes, and inflicts ongoing physical damage on the target. When the target
takes this ongoing damage, the closest fey or plant ally of the wood woad heals
the same amount of HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reliable keyword means this power isn’t used up if the attack misses. The
wood woad can keep trying to use it until it hits someone, and only them will it
need to make recharge rolls. This attack becomes more useful if all of the wood
woad’s allies are either plants or fey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can also curse someone with &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Mystery&lt;/strong&gt; as a
minor action. This inflicts a -2 penalty on all of the target’s attacks,
defenses, and saves. The save to end this effect has an &lt;em&gt;additional&lt;/em&gt; -5 penalty
unless the target can succeed at a DC 20 Nature check before rolling it. Guess
this spell has a loophole somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is different from the sphinx ability we saw earlier in this Let’s Read,
because no one else can make the Nature test in the target’s place. This makes
Nature’s Mystery an excellent ability to use on most defenders, since they tend
to have low-to-middling Wisdom and no training in Nature. Wardens are the big
exception to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Targets affected by this Nature’s Mystery are also prime targets for Nature’s
Judgment. Make sure to surround them with plant and fey monsters after they get
hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: Two dryads, two vine horror spellfiends, 2 wood woads. Did the vine
horror manage to convince the fey it’s part of the local natural environment?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 1 Gnome Entropist, 1 Satyr Piper, 1 Shambling Mound, 3 Wood Woads. I
guess the gnome is a actually a druid using the entropist stat block.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the feel of the mechanics on this one, but the lore is once again a bit
uninspiring. It’s another humanoid fey plant that’s fanatical about protecting
nature, just like dryads and treants. I guess they can round out the cast when
you want to focus a game on a faction of such beings, but we already have a lot
of other possible creatures that belong there as well (satyrs, centaurs, elven
druids, and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use the wood woad stat block but don’t want to say they’re a
completely separate species, just say they’re small treants instead.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Winter Wolf</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-wolf-winter.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual already gave us &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/13/wolves.html&quot;&gt;wolves normal and dire&lt;/a&gt;, and it also gave
us &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/19/worg.html&quot;&gt;worgs&lt;/a&gt;. Now the Monster Manual 2 continues to climb the wolf power
ladder. I first remember seeing Winter Wolves in the 3e monster books, but I’m
pretty sure they’ve been around longer than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I tried to explain how all of these monsters fit together I suppose I’d say
it all starts with the Sons of the Spirit Wolf. The Great Spirit Wolf is a
godlike primal spirit, and his progeny wander the world forever trying to
satisfy their endless hunger. I guess they’re more or less equivalent to the
various wolf spirits worshipped by the Uratha from Werewolf: The Forsaken, only
not nearly as nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These primal spirits probably had descendants themselves, which would be your
“standard” winter wolves. These fit above worgs in the Wolf Power
Ladder. They’re a bit smaller than worgs, but are much deadlier, much smarter,
and just as evil. They also have ice powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point a primordial entity of ice and cold might have taken a look at
the Sons of the Spirit Wolf and thought hey, I want me some of that. So it
developed a process where it takes the living heart of an elemental blizzard and
fashions a Rime Hound out of it. Unlike the creatures they are modeled after,
Rime Hounds are entirely made of ice. Their creators give them as gifts to loyal
servants and worshippers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the creatures in this entry are Magical Beasts. Winter wolves are Natural,
and the others are Elemental. They all have low-light vision and a ground speed
of 8 with Ice Walk, which means they ignore cold-themed difficult terrain. Sons
of the Spirit Wolf have Resist Cold 30, all the others have Resist Cold 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their powers are a combination of the usual wolfy bites and takedowns with a
suite of frost breath weapons and the like, but the specifics vary with each
stat block. Their Int scores are in the average human range. We’ll look at them
by order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winter-wolf&quot;&gt;Winter Wolf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winter Wolves are Medium, and are Level 14 Skirmishers with 141 HP. They attack
with &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; that deal bonus cold damage, and deal about double damage to
prone targets. They can get people prone with a &lt;strong&gt;Takedown&lt;/strong&gt;, a charge attack
that’s stronger than the basic bite and knocks the target prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a winter wolf is adjacent to a prone target it can use &lt;strong&gt;Drag&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will
minor action that allows the wolf to shift 1 square and pull the prone victim
along with it. It’s more than smart enough to use this to put the victim in a
position to be surrounded by its wolf buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, winter wolves can use a &lt;strong&gt;Freezing Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a Close
Blast 5 that targets Reflex and deals cold damage (half on a miss). This
attack’s damage is smaller than the wolf’s cold resistance, so a pack of winter
wolves is going to try to get the party all bunched up and then hit them with
multiple blasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winter-wolf-snowfang&quot;&gt;Winter Wolf Snowfang&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snowfangs are Level 16 Lurkers with 124 HP, representing the sort of wily wolf
that keeps out of sight and nips at your heels until you’re too weak to fight
back. Rather than relying on takedowns, it tries to freeze its victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do bonus cold damage, and are stronger against victims who are
taking ongoing cold damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;Frigid Breath&lt;/strong&gt; works like that of the
standard winter wolf with an added ongoing cold damage rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snowfang’s lurker-y ability is &lt;strong&gt;Snow Zephyr&lt;/strong&gt;, a reaction that triggers
when it gets damaged and turns it into a whirlwind of snow. This causes the
snowfang to become insubstantial, and to gain the ability to shift its speed as
a move action. In this form it can only attack with Frigid Breath, which also
causes it to revert to wolf form. It can also revert voluntarily as a minor
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These powers allow snowfangs to act as very effective harriers: they charge in,
use Freezing Breath, and fight until damaged. Then they shift away in Snow
Zephyr form, and vanish for a while. Then they come back, perhaps even still in
zephyr form, use Freezing Breath again, and repeat the process. You could use
them like this as persistent foes who refuse to have a stand-up fight to the
last, and who pop up to make opportunistic attacks in the middle of other
encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rime-hounds&quot;&gt;Rime Hounds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These knockoff winter wolves are quite well-made! They’re Huge in size, and are
Level 17 Elite Skirmishers with 332 HP. They have the Earth, Cold, and Mount
keywords, so they’re appropriate mounts for ice giants!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have Reach 2 Bite and Takedown attacks identical to those of a winter wolf,
with bigger numbers. They have the same Drag ability as well. Instead of a
Freezing Breath, they have &lt;strong&gt;Frost Storm&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Burst 3 that targets
Fortitude and deals cold damage (half on a miss). This creates a zone of frozen
difficult terrain that lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, their “elite multi-attack” power is actually a reaction: &lt;strong&gt;Ice
Spikes&lt;/strong&gt; which extend whenever the hound or its rider are missed by an enemy
melee attack. This acts as a free attack on the triggering enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;son-of-the-spirit-wolf&quot;&gt;Son of the Spirit Wolf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Large wolfy demigods are Level 26 Elite Skirmishers with 486 HP. Their
surrounded by an aura (1) named &lt;strong&gt;Everfrost Coat&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals 10 cold damage
to enemies who enter it. Enemies damaged by the aura can’t make opportunity
attacks for a turn, which allows this wolf to freely disengage from most PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do the usual physical/cold damage mix and grab the
target on a hit. They can then use &lt;strong&gt;Drag Away&lt;/strong&gt; to either shift 1 square or
move their speed while pulling the victim along. They can also use &lt;strong&gt;Rending
Jaws&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) against the grabbed victim, a much stronger attack than the
basic bite that also pushes the target 5 squares and knocks them prone as the
wolf ends the grab and flings the victim away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing in the text forbidding the wolf from using normal bites on other
enemies while it has a victim grabbed. You are of course free to forbid it since
it only has one mouth… but what if it doesn’t? What if this is a vaguely
wolf-shaped ball of dark spirit stuff instead of being just a big wolf? What if
it can grow extra mouths to bite people with? Maybe it’s not canon, but it’s
metal as fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the thing’s last attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Black Ice Breath&lt;/strong&gt; which is kind of a
hybrid between the breaths of the other two varieties: big cold damage in a
Close Blast 5, and it leaves a zone of frozen difficult terrain that lasts for
the whole encounter. This is an encounter power that recharges when the wolf is
first bloodied, just like dragon breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the links between the different monsters here are purely my
invention. Judging from the descriptions of the book alone, they don’t have
anything in common other than being generally wintery and wolfy. The individual
stat blocks have good mechanics, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 14: a Chillfire Destroyer elemental and a pair of
winter wolves being bossed around by a Beholder Eye of Frost.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wolf-winter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wolf-winter.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Witherling</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-witherling.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witherlings feel like a new monster to me. They’re certainly new to 4e, making
their debut in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, those deranged cannibals who worship Yeenoghu don’t
actually eat everyone they kill. Sometimes they raise their victims as undead
abominations. This is a relatively new development, as the technique was only
recently handed down from the demon lord to its cultists. They are both a new
weapon in the war brewing between Yeenoghu and Orcus, and a way for the former
to muscle in on the latter’s territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process to create a witherling involves replacing the corpse’s head with
that of a hyena, and summoning the essence of a demon into the resulting piece
of “art”. Gnolls and other Yeenoghu cultists prefer to do this to the corpses of
their slain foes, not those of their own side. The result tends to be a lot
faster, smarter and more versatile than that of your typical zombie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All witherlings are Natural Animates with the Undead keyword. They have no
particular resistances or vulnerabilities. Their signature trait is a lesser
form of the gnoll &lt;strong&gt;Pack Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, giving them a +2 damage bonus when two or
more of their allies are adjacent to the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling&quot;&gt;Witherling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is usually made from the corpse of a Small humanoid like a
goblin, kobold, or halfling. It’s a Level 4 Skirmisher with 56 HP and a Speed of
8 (Climb 6).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witherling &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are a bit weak, but they slow on a hit (save ends) and the
creature can make a &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; with them. It also deals extra damage when
it has combat advantage. While bloodied, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Blood Dance&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 2
squares instead of 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its final ability is a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Leap&lt;/strong&gt; that allows it to jump 4 squares and gain
a +5 to AC against opportunity attacks during the jump. If an enemy misses the
witherling with an opportunity attack while it’s jumping, the witherling gains
combat advantage against that enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So these things will come at you en masse from the walls and the bottoms of
pits, and use Sudden Leap to jump juuust a bit past the PCs and attack them from
behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-death-shrieker&quot;&gt;Witherling Death Shrieker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made from the corpse of a Medium creature, the Death Shrieker is a Level 5
Controller with 65 HP and the Leader keyword. Its a bit slower with a ground
speed of 6 and no climbing ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are just a typical basic attack, but it shrieks do damage over a
wide area (close blast 5). The most common one is the &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Shriek&lt;/strong&gt;, which
targets only enemies, does thunder damage, and pushes 2 squares. There’s also
the &lt;strong&gt;Death Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which also targets only enemies and does
untyped damage. Any undead ally adjacent to an enemy hit by this recovers 5
HP. There’s a note saying allies can only benefit from this once per round, so
if you have multiple shriekers they should coordinate and stagger their screams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-horned-terror&quot;&gt;Witherling Horned Terror&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is Large, and made from a minotaur. Since Yeenoghu is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; locked in
eternal battle against Baphomet, they’re more common than you think. Minotaurs
of all alignments hate these things, which is perfectly understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horned Terrors are Level 8 Brutes with 107 HP and a ground speed of 7. They have
a decent &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack, and can use their &lt;strong&gt;Horns&lt;/strong&gt; to the same amount of
damage and push the target 2 squares. They can also perform a &lt;strong&gt;Rampaging
Charge&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which uses the horns to attack and allows them to make
up to three additional attacks against different targets who happen to be in
reach at the end point of the charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-rabble&quot;&gt;Witherling Rabble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a witherling whose creation process glitched out, producing an inferior
specimen. I guess they’re stockpiled and sent out as a huge mob against
enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This defective undead has the exact same attacks as a standard witherling, but
is a Level 9 Minion Skirmisher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eh… I guess witherlings are okay mechanically, and they’re a nice addition to
a campaign focused on battling Yeenoghu and evil gnolls, but they don’t do much
for me personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are different groups of gnolls with witherling
support. One of them also has a cambion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/witherling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/witherling.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Will-O'-Wisp</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-will-o-wisp.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will-O’-Wisps in D&amp;amp;D are inspired by folklore, and their legend is in turn
inspired by the natural phenomena that make swamp gas glow at night. I think
they’ve been in the game since AD&amp;amp;D, though their exact lore might have changed
a bit over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will-o’-wisps are cruel fey spirits who feed on the fear and despair of other
sapients. They like to hang out in swamps and marshes, whose natural mists and
swamp lights provide them with hiding places. Their bodies are orbs of gauzy
material, and they glow with an otherwordly light that has the power to lure
unwary victims. It can also burn their flesh and drain their spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their tactics are pretty much iconic - lure victims to an isolated place full of
hindering terrain and kill them in a way that produces maximum horror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures can communicate in Elven, and when they speak they have that
cool effect where they brighten and dim in compass with their speech. They can
also douse their light for better stealth, but this also prevents them from
using it as a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will-o’-Wisps are Small Fey Magical Beasts, and Level 10 Lurkers with 57
HP. They count as Insubstantial, taking only half damage from non-force
attacks. They have low-light vision and a flight speed of 6 with Hover, and an
altitude limit of 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, wisps can turn their light on or off using the &lt;strong&gt;Fey Light&lt;/strong&gt;
ability (minor action 1/round). A darkened wisp has concealment and can make
Stealth checks to become hidden, but it cannot attack. If a wisp is missed by an
attack, it can &lt;strong&gt;Blink Out&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. When this happens, the wisp darkens
and teleports 5 squares. I guess it can make that Stealth check as part of this
action too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wisp’s attacks are all light-based. The most classic one is of course
&lt;strong&gt;Luring Glow&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a Close Burst 20 that targets one non-blinded creature,
which is another way to say it’s a ranged attack that doesn’t draw opportunity
attacks. It targets Will, does no damage, pulls the victim 3 squares, and dazes
it (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the victim is in range and vulnerable, the wisp is going to hit it with its
basic &lt;strong&gt;Glimmer Wisp&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which is Reach 2, targets Reflex, and does
radiant damage. Once per encounter it can also use &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Drain&lt;/strong&gt; on a
bloodied target. This is a Reach 3 attack that targets Fortitude, deals psychic
damage, weakens (save ends) and heals the wisp for 14 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisps are lurkers and have a couple of good stealth powers, but they don’t
seem to have a lot of ability to take advantage of this stealth. Their best
power is the very controller-y Luring Glow. When building wisp fights, you
should pair them with other opportunistic monsters that can bring the hurt to
those dazed characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our sample encounter is level 9: two wisps and a quartet of spriggans (two
powries, 2 thorns). Evil fairies all around.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/will-o-wisp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/will-o-wisp.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Warforged</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-warforged.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged were originally introduced with the Eberron setting in 3e, as a
playable option. They made their 4e debut in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/07/warforged.html&quot;&gt;first Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;,
which a couple of “monster” stat blocks for warforged and some abbreviated rules
for using them as PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full support for playable warforged in 4e would arrive with the Eberron Player’s
Guide, published in June 2009. However, just before that happened we’d get a few
more NPC stat blocks here in the MM2, which was published in May 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic lore for warforged remains the same as in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/07/warforged.html&quot;&gt;the Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;. The
Eberron-specific info would only appear on the Eberron Player’s Guide, but I
guess the two books were developed in parallel because the extra stat blocks we
get here seem like a particularly good fit for that setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature traits remain the same: the Living Construct keyword, a +2 to
saves against ongoing damage and the &lt;strong&gt;Warforged Resolve&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power (see
the link above to read about what this does).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-resounder&quot;&gt;Warforged Resounder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are warforged spellcasters whose power derives from a retained echo of the
ringing sound of their creation forges. Their spells tend to have themes of
sound and impact, dealing a mix of thunder and force damage. They wear robes and
wield staffs, so I guess they’re meant to come across as “arcane”, but you could
easily use their lore for a more priestly type since it’s so close to that of
the Anvilpriest (below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resounders are Level 6 Artillery with 57 HP and the common traits described
above. Their &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaves&lt;/strong&gt; are weak melee attacks, so they prefer to stay
away and cast &lt;strong&gt;thunder orbs&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that do good thunder
damage and push 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a couple of encounter spells: &lt;strong&gt;Resounding Sphere&lt;/strong&gt; is an area
version of Thunder Orb that knocks prone instead of pushing, making it a good
fight opener; and &lt;strong&gt;Rumble Staff&lt;/strong&gt; is a “keep-away” melee power that does
thunder damage, pushes 1 square, and knocks prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their final encounter spell is the amusing &lt;strong&gt;Collision Bolt&lt;/strong&gt;, a ranged attack
that targets two enemies and slams them together. It works by dealing force
damage to both targets, and sliding the second one 3 squares towards the
first. If the slide ends with both targets adjacent to each other, they’re both
knocked prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-savage&quot;&gt;Warforged Savage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an unfortunate name and a somewhat unfortunate illustration, this is a
warforged who feels emotions more intensely than most of its kin, and channels
all of that extra intensity into anger. It was likely produced in a forge
belonging to the Lord of Blades, since the Cannith smiths tend to go for
cool-headed discipline instead. It’s a Level 7 Brute with 98 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This warforged has the &lt;strong&gt;Battlefield Tactics&lt;/strong&gt; trait that was common in the MM1
entries, gaining a +1 to melee attacks when an ally is adjacent to their
target. It also gains 4 temporary HP whenever it hits with an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warforged savage uses a &lt;strong&gt;scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; to fight. This is a High-Crit weapon,
and when it hits it deals a bit of automatic damage to another enemy adjacent to
its target. It can use the weapon to attack in a Close Burst 1 (recharge 5+),
and to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Wild Charge&lt;/strong&gt; that deals heavy damage, and gives it a +3 AC
bonus during the movement part of the charge. This recharges whenever the
warforged hits two or more enemies with the burst attack. All of these maneuvers
benefit from the scimitar’s High-Crit property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-anvilpriest&quot;&gt;Warforged Anvilpriest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the resounder, this spellcaster retains a bit of the power of its creation
forge and uses that as a source of magic. The main difference is that the
anvilpriest focuses on the searing heat of forge-fire. Despite the name, many
anvilpriests aren’t all that religious. Some are real clerics, though, and a
small number of them actually worship the creation forges themselves. I guess
the latter are mostly found amid the Lord of Blades’ forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anvilpriests are Level 8 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 89 HP. They
wield a &lt;strong&gt;fiery warhammer&lt;/strong&gt; that does bonus fire damage and inflicts a -2 AC
penalty for a turn. They can use that to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Heat of Battle&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver
(recharge 4+), which is like a basic attack but replaces the AC penalty with
ongoing fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this they have two encounter spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is &lt;strong&gt;Blunted Mind&lt;/strong&gt;, an area burst that targets Will and inflicts
psychic damage. It also inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks and a -4 penalty to
damage on a hit - the first save improves this to a -2 damage penalty, and only
the second removes it entirely. This only targets enemies, so it’s safe to cast
into a messy melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is &lt;strong&gt;Mending Flash Fire&lt;/strong&gt;, a close burst that deals fire damage to all
enemies inside (vs. Reflex) and gives both the caster and any allies in the
burst 5 temporary HP. If those allies are Warforged, they can also use their
Warforged Resolve power as an immediate reaction to this power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-titan&quot;&gt;Warforged Titan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-warforged-titan.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titans were some of the earliest models of warforged developed by Cannith
engineers. They’re as big and as powerful as their name implies, but they’re
also only barely sapient. In a battle, they fulfill the same role as tanks or
siege engines, but they need to be accompanied by smarter infantry or at least
by a minder who can direct them. They’re loyal to whoever holds or displays a
symbol of the titan’s creator, regardless of whom it may be or how long it’s
been since their creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged Titans are Huge Natural Humanoids with the Living Construct
Keyword. They’re also Level 19 Elite Soldiers with 362 HP, which makes them
plausible counters to Slaughterstone Constructs and other near-epic giant
monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These towering creatures fight with their built-in weapons. Their basic attack
is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Axe&lt;/strong&gt; with the same “splash damage” effect as the Savage’
scimitar above, and that also marks on a hit. As a minor action they can also
use a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Hammer&lt;/strong&gt; that does more or less the same damage, slides the
target 2 squares, and knocks it prone. It does a bit of damage even on a miss,
likely from the shockwave. Both of these weapons enjoy the benefits of
&lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the titan’s &lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable Charger&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes it so a charge attack
&lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; end its turn. It can perform any actions it still has after charging,
such as using a Move to shift or reposition, or a Minor action to perform a
hammer follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged are people. You can find them fighting for any cause people tend to
fight for. Good, evil, or just plain selfish. They’re relatively recent
creations in Eberron, but other settings might have then as ancient
survivors/relics of a fallen empire. Titans work well as McGuffins in that role,
since they’ll obey anyone who displays the mark of their creator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: A resounder, an anvilpriest, and 3 savages. Lord of Blades patrol?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: A cambion hellfire magus, a steel predator, and a warforged
titan. Someone found themselves a few control amulets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/warforged.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/warforged.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Moster Manual 2: Vine, Predatory</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-vine-predatory.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the actual title of the entry, so we have another case of Old School
Titling here. Dangerous plants have been a part of the game since its
beginnings, and I bet a lot of the individual monsters collected in this entry
appeared before in some form or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, there isn’t much on these other than “they exist”. They don’t have
strange magical origins like some of the other plant creatures we saw before,
they’re just ambulatory carnivorous plants with enough strength and mobility to
hunt people. D&amp;amp;D worlds are already filled with impossibly lethal predators, so
it’s not such a stretch to say some of those are plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the monsters in this entry are Beasts, which in rules terms means they
behave like “animals” rather than like people. They also have the Plant keyword
(obviously). Their Int score is 2, so their behaviors are all
instinctive. Everything else varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ambush-vine&quot;&gt;Ambush Vine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apex predator of the plant kingdom, ambush vines can hunt anywhere: on the
surface, underground, and even in water. Wherever they are, they’re always
hunting, and using the tasty nutrients of their victims to fuel their explosive
growth rate. Ambush vines can form blights so vast they threaten civilization,
and its rumored that this contributed to the fall of the old eladrin empire of
Cendriane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As their name implies, ambush vines are a lot more cunning than your average
plant. They can burrow just under the surface or blend into the surrounding
normal vegetation to wait for victims, and then launch surprise attacks against
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambush Vines are Large Fey plants, and Level 16 Elite Controllers with 308
HP. They have tremorsense 20, and nothing in their stat block says they’re blind
so I guess they can see as well even without eyes. Their speed is 6 in almost
any mode of movement other than flight. They can move over the ground with
Forest Walk, climb, burrow and swim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vine’s most basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Poison Lash&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex,
deals physical damage, and inflicts ongoing poison damage. It can also attack
with &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Vines&lt;/strong&gt; in a Close Burst 4 pattern, which does more damage than
the basic attack. It’s also super-effective against immobilized targets, dealing
extra damage and healing the vine for 5 HP. As a minor action, the vine can use
a Reach 4 &lt;strong&gt;Foot Snare&lt;/strong&gt; to deal the same damage as the basic attack and knock a
target prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though ambush vines deal extra damage to immobilized foes, they can’t do the
immobilizing themselves, so they must be paired with other monsters capable of
it. Fortunately, they can make their own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the vine is first bloodied, it undergoes &lt;strong&gt;Rapid Growth&lt;/strong&gt; as an emergency
response, producing two Ambush Vine Shoot minions (see below). It can also make
a minion voluntarily using &lt;strong&gt;Sprout Vine&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action which costs 10 of its
own HP and produces a single minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ambush-vine-shoot&quot;&gt;Ambush Vine Shoot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the juvenile form of the ambush vine. It’s a Medium Fey plant, and a
Level 15 Minion Controller. Their senses are the same as those of an adult
specimen, though their only special movement mode is burrowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These minions have a single attack, &lt;strong&gt;Wrapping Vines&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals minion-tier
damage and restrains (save ends). “Restrained” is one step worse than
“immobilized”: it roots the victim in place and inflicts a -2 penalty to
attacks. A restrained target also counts as immobilized, so the shoot’s “parent”
vine can deal extra damage against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shoot also has a passive trait named &lt;strong&gt;Enwrap&lt;/strong&gt;, which affects adjacent
enemies and inflicts a -2 penalty to their saves against being immobilized or
restrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloodthorn-vine&quot;&gt;Bloodthorn Vine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a vine with pale leaves and one single large thorn. It feeds by impaling
victims on that thorn, which is hollow and capable of draining blood. As it does
so, the vine’s leaves take on a reddish coloration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bloodthorn vines are Medium Natural plants, and Level 2 Soldiers with 41 HP. By
the logic I’ve been using, them being low-level means they might occur near the
archetypical Starting Village. This means they’re one more threat common
civilians must be wary of in their daily lives, along with stirges, anhkegs, and
giant ants. Bloodthorns are much less lively than Ambush Vines, having only a
ground speed of 5 with Forest Walk and no special movement modes. They have
Blindsight 10 but again are not blind themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Striking Vine&lt;/strong&gt; with no riders on its physical
damage. The real danger here is the &lt;strong&gt;Impaling Thorn&lt;/strong&gt;, which does the same
damage and grabs the target. The vine can sustain the grab with a standard
action to deal heavy automatic damage to the victim and heal 5 HP. It can use
&lt;strong&gt;Pulling Vines&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to shift 1 square and pull a grabbed victim
along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the bloodthorn vine can only impale a single victim at a
time… but you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; have multiple bloodtorn vines on the same encounter group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;greenvise-vine&quot;&gt;Greenvise Vine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-vine-greenvise.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So named because “Piranha Plant” is already taken. This is a Large Natural
plant, and a Level 7 Soldier with 83 HP. Its speed is only 4, so it relies on
grabbing targets to prevent them from running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greenvise’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Striking Vine&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can also use an
&lt;strong&gt;Ensnaring Vine&lt;/strong&gt; vs. Reflex to do the same damage and grab the target. That’s
when the big chomper comes into play: &lt;strong&gt;Vise Bite&lt;/strong&gt; targets a grabbed victim’s
Fortitude, deals a bit of initial damage, restrains, and inflicts ongoing
physical damage. A save ends both the restrained condition and the ongoing
damage &lt;em&gt;but does not end the grab&lt;/em&gt;. You have to escape from that using the
default rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greenvise also has the same Pulling Vines trait as the Bloodthorn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually have an easier time distinguishing between killer plants when I see
them all together than when I see them in separate entries over multiple books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have three encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 2: 3 bloodthorn vines and 3 stirges. Probably competing to see who can
drain the party dry first.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 2 greenvise vines, 1 spectral panther, 3 quickling runners. The
quicklings and the panther can be used to herd the party towards the
slow-moving plants.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 17: 1 ambush vine, 1 lingerer fell incanter, 1 lingerer fell
knight. Sinister vestiges of lost Cendriane.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/vine-predatory.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/vine-predatory.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
