<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 20:50:09 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 20:50:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ultra-Tech Dungeon Delving in GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I started writing this post a few years ago when I was GMing the Iron Gods
adventure path for Pathfinder using the Dungeon Fantasy RPG rules. My approach
to that campaign was pretty slap-dash, and after I stopped I began thinking of a
more structured way to do it. Since a recent comment here on the blog asked for
specifics, I though I’d dust the post off and publish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a Dungeon Fantasy game where you want your characters to get
into contact with more advanced technology. How would you go about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ultra-tech-delving-a-survey&quot;&gt;Ultra-Tech Delving: A Survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Jackson games did a little foray into this area in Pyramid #3/60, in an
article entitled “High-Tech Dungeon Crawl”, which focused on bringing modern-day
characters with guns into fantasy dungeons to mow down orcs with autofire and
take their stuff. This raises the inherent level of colonalism in the genre from
“concerning” to “yikes!”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to focus on here is in an older variation on the theme: fantasy
characters exploring “dungeons” filled with elements you might be more used to
seeing in science fiction stories. When I say “older”, I mean it’s &lt;em&gt;older than
D&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt;: Dave Arneson’s Blackmoor campaign featured a whole ultra-tech city-state
descended from the crew of a crashed spaceship, and it was played for several
years before what became the OD&amp;amp;D rules were finalized and officially
published. D&amp;amp;D proper would explore the same territory with its famous
“Expedition to the Barrier Peaks” module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathfinder dedicates a whole kingdom in its setting to the idea: the land of
Numeria is a barbarian kingdom where a giant spaceship crashed millenia ago,
breaking up during atmospheric entry and scattering its many modules all over
the region. And, of course, in Gamma World and other post-apocalyptic games
&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; “dungeons” are ultra-tech because they’re the ruins of the futuristic
civilization that preceded the apocalypse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ultra-tech-delving-in-gurps&quot;&gt;Ultra-Tech Delving in GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS is of course a uniquely well-suited system for this kind of thing. Its
rules already support a wide range of genres and technology levels from the
corebook onwards. We only need a few adjustments depending on the sort of
campaign we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After The End&lt;/em&gt; already deals with the post-apocalyptic angle and offers a set
of detailed rules. What I want, however, is something simpler and more suited to
a Barrier Peaks/Numeria scenario. The ultra-tech stuff is alien, but characters
can gain an understanding of it with some investment, and the gap between their
usual medievalish milieu and the lofty heights of alien tech isn’t completely
impossible to cross. How would I do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-level-or-the-lack-thereof&quot;&gt;Tech Level, or the Lack Thereof.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on one side we have the usual “medievalish” dungeon fantasy setting. In
GURPS, that’s roughtly TL 4, but without gunpowder. On the other side we have a
space-opera intrusion, which corresponds very roughly to a TL9-10 selection with
a few outliers (personal shields are TL11-12, but they fit the flavor). With
these vague numbers in mind, we can ditch the concept of Tech Levels completely
for our treatment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Default GURPS Tech Level rules are only useful for giving us a starting set of
gadgets to work with. In actual play, the only thing that matters is if a given
thing is “low-tech” and thus familiar to everyone, or “high-tech” and thus a
mystery to the uninitiated. How to differentiate both? With the following
advantage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-familiarity-10-points&quot;&gt;Tech Familiarity (10 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a layman’s knowledge of the basic principles behind the advanced
technology scattered through your otherwise medieval fantasy world. You
understand why it isn’t magic. You know about electricity and how it powers
high-tech devices. You grasp enough of the high-tech design aesthetic to easily
spot a device’s charging port or battery, its control surfaces (be they
switches, triggers, or touchpads), its information displays, and its business
end even if you don’t know what the thing actually &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt;. You can identify the
high-tech civilization’s writing even though you can’t read it, and you can
identify its iconography for “danger”. You can also recognize hazards like
exposed live wires, recognize which type of power cell goes into a device, and
plug it in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a form of Unusual Background that makes you immune to the sort of
amusing accident which plagues other low-tech explorers confronted with
high-tech devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, Tech Familiarity is a pre-requisite for learning high-tech
skills, and the language of the high-tech civilization (if any). With this
advantage, you can spend points on those things normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is quite similar to High TL from the core book, but much cheaper. The
reason is that paying 30-35 points in High TL to get the same benefits is way
too expensive for a campaign in this mold. This advantage doesn’t give you any
familiarity with deeper aspects of the high-tech civilization, just what’s in
the first paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-skills&quot;&gt;Tech Skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skills that would require a /TL specialization in standard GURPS rules have only
two versions here: standard (no suffix) and “/Tech”. That way, you don’t need to
change anything about how you write down a standard “medievalish” character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two specialties don’t overlap at all: they don’t default to each other, and
can’t be used at all across the “tech divide”. If you only have standard
Lockpicking, you can’t open a high-tech door with a magnetic lock. If you only
have Lockpicking/Tech, you can’t open low-tech mechanical locks with
old-fashioned picks, tough you might be able to operate a machine that does it
for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-tech weapons are usually firearms of beam weapons - the skills to operate
them properly are always “/Tech” skills. High-Tech &lt;em&gt;melee&lt;/em&gt; weapons are a
possible exception to the “no defaults” rule above, though the GM would need to
rule on each case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weapons that use the same skill as their low-tech counterparts can be used
normally by anyone if the only difference is in their construction (such as a
superfine or hyperdense blade). If they have some additional feature that
requires power (such as a vibroblade or shock baton) then the character has a -2
penalty to use that feature unless they have Tech Familiarity. If they require
an exclusive skill to operate (like a force sword or monowire whip) then that
skill has the “/Tech” suffix. You might be able to get away with a default to a
low-tech skill here, but the only way to improve on that is to buy Tech
Familiarity and the high-tech skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ultra-tech-gear&quot;&gt;Ultra-Tech Gear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the character stuff out of the way, we can talk about the goodies! As I
mentioned above, one advantage of GURPS is that it has entire books of high- and
ultra-tech gadgets that can be plugged straight into your fantasy
campaigns. Therefore, we don’t need to talk about how to stat this stuff up at
all! What we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; need is talk about the effects it’s going to have on your
campaign, which in turn will aid you in selecting which items to include.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-much-is-this-stuff-worth&quot;&gt;How much is this stuff worth?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vital question in the dungeon fantasy genre! Going more or less by the book,
high-tech items should be worth roughly 30 times their list price in a dungeon
fantasy setting. That makes even a relatively innocuous gadget into a major
piece of loot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem a bit too much for a dungeon fantasy setting where magic and
magic items are relatively common, but I think it kinda makes sense. Ultra-tech
items are going to be a lot rarer than magic items, particularly in settings
where they come from that single crashed spaceship. They work regardless of the
local mana and sanctitiy levels. And they can be enchanted! These are exactly
the same reasons why a suit of fine plate armor costs more than a standard suit
enchanted with Lighten 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: A superfine broadword would cost $3600 in its native ultra-tech
society. Recovered from a crashed spaceship in a dungeon fantasy setting, it’s
worth $108,000!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sword gives a +2 bonus to damage and a (2) armor divisor. The closest
“low-tech” equivalent would be a very fine sword with a Penetrating Weapon
enchantment, worth $17,000, almost ten times cheaper. Even if all the bonuses
were from magic, it would still cost only $25,600. However, the superfine blade
will lose none of its functionality in a low- or no-mana zone, and it could be
enchanted with the same magic as the low-tech sword to become even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think that this is too much, you could say that the value of
ultra-tech gear is capped by the value of magic items with similar
properties. The sword from the example would be worth $17,000 then. Gear that
has no magical equivalent might still use the “uncapped” price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;timeworn-gear&quot;&gt;Timeworn Gear&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One concept from Pathfinder that’s useful to borrow is that of timeworn
items. In Barrier Peaks-style setups, most of the high-tech stuff the PCs come
across has been sitting around in derelict ruins for a very long time; even if
it was very well-built, it might not have withstood the passage of the ages
intact. To model that, we introduce the following equipment modifier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timeworn&lt;/strong&gt;: This can be applied to any high-tech armor, weapon, or device that
requires power or ammunition to function. These items can’t be recharged. After
whatever reserves they contain when found are used up, they’ll break down and
become useless. They may also have other quirks arising from their almost-broken
state at the GM’s discretion. Divide final price by 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;weapons-and-armor&quot;&gt;Weapons and Armor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weapons and armor deserve special mention because Dungeon Fantasy is a
combat-heavy genre, and this combat has a very specific “feel” to it. Therefore,
high-tech combat gear will have an outsize impact on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baseline Dungeon Fantasy suggests that PCs should have a maximum total DR of
about 15, as anything more than that will make them invulnerable to too many
monster attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC damage also has some upper bounds. Spellcasters with missile spells and a
spellcasting talent of 6 can do a maximum of 18d damage, though that requires
enough setup to only be possible about once per fight, and not on all
fights. The maximum amount of “at-will” melee and ranged damage a PC can do is
equivalent to about 7d per attack&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing ultra-tech armor into the game almost certainly means you’re going
to exceed the DR cap. Even non-combat safety gear at these tech levels has as
much DR as low-tech plate, while being much lighter. Proper combat armor is much
tougher. Most of the published DF enemies will have trouble getting past the DR
of a PC in full ultra-tech armor with their physical attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, high-tech weapons can change the shape of combat in your
campaign. Dungeon Fantasy usually considers melee to be the main event and
ranged combat to be a specialist niche, but if guns and beam weapons are common
these two are going to swap places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultra-tech melee and ranged weapons can also allow PCs to approach or exceed the
upper damage bounds described above much more easily. Both “boundaries” are
roughly equivalent to rolling 7d of damage per attack. A force sword does 8d; a
laser rifle does 6d, and can can fire many more shots per turn than a bow with
no penalty. Both of those have armor divisors too, which make enemy DR become
much less of an obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step when addressing these issues is to carefully consider which items
are available. What do you want your campaign’s new DR cap to be? What is the
highest armor divisor you’re comfortable with? What sort of maximum damage do
you want your PCs to do with a melee or ranged attack they can use every second?
And, to quote Mister Torgue from Borderlands 2: EXPLOSIONS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second step is to consider the same thing from the side of the opposition:
what’s the highest DR and damage you estimate &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; will be able to routunely
bring to the table? The gear available to the PCs should give them a chance to
match those figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can then safely remove anything that exceeds your new planned limits. That
will end up giving you a pretty good set of guidelines for what the ultra-tech
culture and their ruins look like. A civilian medical lab infested with
non-sapient monsters and low-tech looters might have plenty of medkits and
wonder drugs, but no weapon heavier than a couple of timeworn electrolasers and
some scalpels the thief can use as superfine daggers. For a military base filled
with killer robots and with a tank at the end as a boss fight, the sky is the
limit, though those anti-tank weapons might all be timeworn if you don’t want
the PCs using them outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The article itself includes a section titled “The Sociological
Ramifications are Appalling”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A ST 20 Knight with Weapon Master and a halberd can easily attack twice
every turn and do 3d+13 per attack. This is theoretically possible right out
of character creation if your knight is a half-ogre. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A ST 20 Scout with Weapon Master and Strongbow might be able to shoot once
per turn and do about 4d+10 per shot. This particular boundary is hard to
reach, so your highest “at-will” ranged damage will probably be less than
that. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/13/ultra-tech-dungeons.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/13/ultra-tech-dungeons.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Gaj</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-gaj.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A gaj perched on a desert rock.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book opens this entry by that the wastelands of Athas “sometimes spawn
monsters so terrible not even the merciful can permit them to live”. Cheery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The illustration makes me think a gaj is what you get when you mix a mind flayer
with a beetle. These aberrations have human-level intelligence, strong
telepathic powers, and a taste for the flesh and fear of sapient
creatures. They’re too anti-social to practice infiltration like mind flayers
sometimes do, but there’s still a lot about them that’s familiar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaj dwell in extensive burrow networks that technically form a community, but
they rarely interact with each other. They’ll band together to defend their
home, but they mostly hunt alone or in mated pairs. They attack their prey with
their claws and mandibles, and with invasive telepathy focused through their
feathery antennae. Once a gaj has a firm grip on a victim, the touch of those
antennae will rapidly disassemble the creature’s mind and use it to fuel further
psychic assault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain specimens mutate to assume a sort of leadership role in a gaj
community. Their powers specialize on inflicting pain, and they take upon
themselves the job of keeping victims captive in the burrow as dominated slaves
and/or reserve rations for lean times. These Pain Tyrants are one of the few
things that can get a whole burrow together for a bigger hunt or a raid against
a settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; lean times, when gaj cannot find new victims and have already
devoured all of their captives, they’ll turn on each other - even their own
mates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, just as gaj like to hunt other sapients, so are they hunted in
return. They’re very popular in the arena, so those ubuquitous slavers often
mount expeditions to find and capture them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaj are Medium Aberrant Magical Beasts with a ground speed of 6, a burrow speed
of 3, Darkvision, and Tremorsense 5. Their signature trait is &lt;strong&gt;Warding Shell&lt;/strong&gt;,
which gives them +2 to defenses against any creature marking them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the stat blocks here are Chaotic Evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaj-mindhunter&quot;&gt;Gaj Mindhunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the typical specimen, so named to distinguish it from the Pain
Tyrant. Mindhunters are Level 8 Elite Controllers with 172 HP. Their basic
attack is a bite with their &lt;strong&gt;Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt;, which grab on a hit. Once the
mindhunter has a victim in its jaws, it can only use this attack against it, and
not against others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Invasive Presence&lt;/strong&gt; has no such restrictions. It’s targets one or two
creatures within Range 10, deals psychic damage on a hit, and pushes 1
square. There’s also &lt;strong&gt;Mind Wrench&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which targets a creature
within a Close Burst 3 and dominates on a hit (save ends). Each time the target
fails the save, the mindhunter’s grabbed victim takes 2d6 psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, once per round, the mindhunter can use its &lt;strong&gt;Feathery Probe&lt;/strong&gt;
on the grabbed victim. On a hit this deals light psychic damage, 5 ongoing
psychic damage, and dazes (save ends). If the target is already taking ongoing
psychic damage, that damage increases by 5. Yes, repeated hits with this attack
will result in more and more ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this paints us a picture of the mindhunter’s preferred tactics: choose a
victim to bite and grab, get away from the PCs, and keep using Invasive Presence
and Mind Wrench to keep them busy while they nom on the victim with Feathery
Probe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaj-pain-tyrant&quot;&gt;Gaj Pain Tyrant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pain Tyrants are considerably stronger than mindhunters, being Level 13 Elite
Artillery with the Leader tag and 200 HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt; have no special
effects other than damage. Its ranged basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Mind Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; with
range 20, that targets 1-2 creatures, and on a hit deals psychic damage and
dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often they can use &lt;strong&gt;Agonizing Insight&lt;/strong&gt;, an Area Burst 2 Within 20 with a
lot of complicated effects. This weaponized anxiety attack inflicts 20 psychic
damage on a hit (save ends). Whenever the target takes this ongoing damage, each
of its allies within 3 squares also takes 5 psychic damage. So, if it hits 3
PCs, in the next round each of them is going to take a total of 30 psychic
damage if they stay together: 20 from the main effect, 10 from splash damage. It
recharges when the tyrant scores a critical hit with Phrenic Probe (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an &lt;em&gt;effect&lt;/em&gt; the attack also makes each enemy inside the burst grant combat
advantage for a turn even if they weren’t hit by the main attack. It also lets
allies in the burst use a free action to either shift 1 square or move half
their speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against a dazed target, the Pain Tyrant can use &lt;strong&gt;Phrenic Probe&lt;/strong&gt; as a 1/round
minor action. This is a version of the mindhunter’s Feathery Probe that has
range 20! Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Vicious Goad&lt;/strong&gt; lets an ally within 20 squares move its
speed and make a basic attack against an enemy of the tyrant’s choice as a free
action. The ally is then dazed for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like the most common gaj encounter in the wilderness is a pair of
mindhunters. A Pain Tyrant leading a larger group is also possible, but in this
case I’d recommend making the accompanying mindhunters into regulars of a
slightly lower level than their boss. Enslaved humanoids can round out the
group. And you can also find mindhunters being used as arena fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These seem to be very tricky to fight.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/12/wir-dscc-gaj.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/12/wir-dscc-gaj.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Floating Mantle</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-floating-mantle.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An red floating mantle.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silt Sea makes up the eastern border of the known regions of Athas. No one
knows what’s on the other side of it, and they have only the barest idea of
what’s under the dust. Sometimes, weird creatures will drift in from those
far and deep regions. One of these weirdoes is the floating mantle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floating mantles are giant flying jellyfish, though no one in Athas calls them
that because they don’t know what a fish is. Despite their strong psionic
powers, their flight is entirely mundane. Their bodies secrete a lighter than
air gas into internal cavities to keep them aloft, and they expel small
quantities of this gas to propel themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures live in small groups called colonies, which are psychically
linked to form a collective consciousness. They have some fairly obvious sexual
dimorphism: males are a pale red in color, while females are a pale yellow. Both
grow much more vivid in coloration when they feel agitated or threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During their reproductive cycle, the female will carry a large litter of
“polyps” to term. This causes her to become larger, bluish in color and much
more irritable, as the pregnancy is highly uncomfortable for her. When in this
state, she’s known as a “bluesting”. When threatened, a bluesting might
prematurely release some of its polyps, which can fight ferociously but don’t
last long. Even when they’re properly birthed at the right time, polyps are
still fragile and only a small fraction of them will grow up to join the colony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book describes floating mantles as “quiet and inoffensive”, which I guess
means they only attack sapients if they feel threatened, or to defend their
young. They probably feed on small animals, and mainly hunt on the Silt
Sea. When they do fight, they use the same natural weapons they use for hunting:
sting-covered tendrils that deliver a paralytic poison, and the ability to drain
the life force of a helpless victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hurt, a floating mantle emits a psychic scream that stuns attackers and
warns their fellows of danger. Finally, the gas that they use is probably
hydrogen, because it gives them an unfortunate tendency to explode when exposed
to fire or electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floating Mantles are Aberrant Magical Beasts with the Blind tag, which makes
them immune to blinding effects and gaze attacks. They perceive their
surroundings with Blindsight 20. Mantles have a flight speed of 6, with an
altitude limit of 3 and the ability to hover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adult mantles are vulnerable 10 to fire and lightning. Polyps have too little
stored hydrogen for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flying mantles are also immune to the effects of their Psychic Scream powers,
whether used by themselves or by another mantle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;floating-mantle&quot;&gt;Floating Mantle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This typical specimen is Small in size, and a Level 13 Controller with 126
HP. Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Rake&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. reflex) that deals
poison damage and slows for a turn. If they have combat advantage against a
target, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Life Leech&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. Fortitude) as a minor
action. This deals poison damage, dazes and immobilizes (save ends both) and
gives 10 temporary HP to the mantle. Of course, a target who’s hit by this once
becomes susceptible to it until they save against that daze, since dazed
characters grant CA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also as a minor action, the mantle can squeeze out a &lt;strong&gt;Jet&lt;/strong&gt; to shift its
speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the mantle is first bloodied, a lot of stuff happens. First, &lt;strong&gt;Jet&lt;/strong&gt;
recharges. Then it lets out a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Scream&lt;/strong&gt;! The scream is a free action
attack vs. Will in a Close Burst 2. On a hit, it deals psychic damage, and makes
it so the affected targets take 10 psychic damage whenever they make an attack
against the creature (save ends). As an effect, the floating mantle becomes
invisible until the end of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the mantle is reduced to 0 HP by fire or lightning, it &lt;strong&gt;suddenly explodes&lt;/strong&gt;!
This is another Close Burst 2, vs. Reflex this time, dealing high fire damage
and pushing targets 1d4 squares. On a miss, it does half damage. This is
probably the only variable push I ever saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;floating-mantle-bluesting&quot;&gt;Floating Mantle Bluesting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bluestings grow to Medium size. They’re Level 15 Artillery with 111 HP, and a
greater blindsight range of 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Rake&lt;/strong&gt; Attack has reach 3 and does more damage than the common
mantle’s, and they also gain the ability to fling their tiny stingers at distant
targets. This &lt;strong&gt;Flinging Nettles&lt;/strong&gt; attack targets Fortitude and deals poison
damage out to range 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If enemies manage to get close, the bluesting can let out a &lt;strong&gt;Toxic Burst&lt;/strong&gt;,
which targets creatures in a Close Burst 1 and deals poison damage on a hit. If
the bluesting has less than four accompanying polyps, one appears in an adjacent
square, acting right after the bluesting in initiative order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have the same &lt;strong&gt;Jet&lt;/strong&gt; ability as the common specimen, and can also perform
a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Birth&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) as a minor when pressed. This is more or less
the same as the secondary effect of the Toxic Burst above: it puts a new polyp
in play within 3 squares if there are less than four accompanying the bluesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychic Scream&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Explosion&lt;/strong&gt; work the same as in the common
specimen, but do more damage since bluestings are higher level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;floating-mantle-polyp&quot;&gt;Floating Mantle Polyp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Tiny youngsters can either be pre-placed in an encounter, or be produced
by bluestings (in which case they’re not worth XP). A previously-placed polyp is
one that reached term and was birthed normally, and adults will fiercely defend
it. One produced during combat is considered premature and will die a few
minutes after the fighting stops. Adults are less attached to those. In either
case it’s not yet hooked up to the hive mind and it’s recklessly hangry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polyps are Level 15 Minion Brutes. Their &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Rakes&lt;/strong&gt; do poison damage,
and when they die they let loose a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Scream&lt;/strong&gt; in a close burst 2, which
deals psychic damage and dazes for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are likely the most peaceful and sympathetic aberrant creatures you’re
likely to find anywhere. They’ll most likely be found just chilling and minding
their business, and will only become dangerous if the PCs strike the first
blow. The capybaras of the Far Realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their lore is both disturbingly biological and a breath of fresh air. The first
part is obvious (poor premature polyps!), and the second one is because here we
have an example of powerful Athasian wildlife that &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; so mindlessly
aggressive it thinks armed adventurers are a good meal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standard flying mantles need to either appear in pairs or have some other
opportunistic flanking buddy that will help them get their initial combat
advantage on a target. Other than that all of them have some interesting ways to
punish PCs that do &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; well against them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/10/wir-dscc-floating-mantle.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/10/wir-dscc-floating-mantle.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Elf</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-elf.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An elf running through the desert.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athasian elves are tall and long-legged, and their culture is almost entirely
nomadic. Elven communities roam the deserts of Athas accompanied by swift beasts
of burden and war, but none of those are mounts. An elf will only accept being
carried by a beast if they’re too sick or wounded to stand. Otherwise, they
prefer to run. And they’re very good at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike some of the other nomads we saw so far, such as brohgs, elves have
frequent interactions with Athasian settled peoples and city states. Their
overall reputation is not very good. They’re known as itinerant traders who
bring a lot of cool stuff to sell in the Elven Markets many towns have, but
they’re also known as swindlers, thieves, raiders, and occasionally
murderers. The cool stuff they sell you was probably stolen from someone else,
according to rumor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of reputation has a number of unplasant parallels with real-world
prejudices, so I find it off-putting that the book spends a lot of effort trying
to convince me it’s true. Even the PCs have “desert raider” and “market thief”
as their new custom background options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d prefer to portray elves as having a lot of solidarity for each other and not
a lot of sympathy for the outsiders who hate them so much. They drive hard
bargains at the Market and skip town en masse if it looks like someone’s going
to accuse one of them of a crime. The accusation is likely to be false most of
the time, as I interpret it. Some individuals might resemble the negative
stereotype, but then again that’s also true of city-dwellers, whose negative
stereotype is “servant to a slaving despot” or “slaver”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elves who are found guilty of crimes in their own communities are cast out, and
will often end up joining groups of actual raiders and bandits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their taller build elves remain Medium Fey Humanoids with a ground speed
of 7. The stat blocks here &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have low-light vision, though I think that’s
still a feature of PC elves. They do all have &lt;strong&gt;Wild Step&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Elven
Accuracy&lt;/strong&gt;, which work like their PC versions too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level range here is roughly comparable to that of standard elves from other
books, so you can mix-and-match a bit. All of the stat blocks here are Unaligned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elf-peddler&quot;&gt;Elf Peddler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical denizen of the Elven Markets. This could both represent a more or less
honest trader who knows how to defend themselves, or a cutthroat who looks for
particularly vulnerable customers to ambush after a sale. It’s a Level 2
Skirmisher with the Leader tag and 34 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical peddler’s goal in a fight will be to live to fight another day, so
they always hang around places with convenient escape routes and obstacles that
might deter pursuers, such as twisty alleys or clustered stalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peddler is armed with a &lt;strong&gt;bone longsword&lt;/strong&gt;, which does standard damage for
its level. It can use the &lt;strong&gt;Double Dealing&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver at will: this lets it make
a sword attack, shift half their speed, and then make another sword attack
against a different target if they end the shift flanking that target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Peddler’s Command&lt;/strong&gt;, which lets an ally
within 20 squares move half their speed as a free action. If that ally is
another elf, the move is instead a shift. This is useful to set up the flank for
that second Double Dealing attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elf-sniper&quot;&gt;Elf Sniper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another typical denizen of the markets, Snipers work security from shadowy
corners and rooftop perches. If trouble starts, they help cover their allies’
retreat with their thrown weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snipers are Level 3 Minion Lurkers armed with &lt;strong&gt;Bone Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; and a brace of 10
&lt;strong&gt;Chatkchas&lt;/strong&gt;, which are three-pronged sharpened boomerangs. Both of these
attacks deal a bit of extra damage if the sniper is hidden from the target when
they start the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an at-will Move action, the sniper can use &lt;strong&gt;Elven Misdirection&lt;/strong&gt; to move 2
squares and make a free Stealth check to become hidden if they end the movement
with cover or concealment. This check has an automatic result of 25, which means
they “take 15” on the roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat, they’ll try to pop out from cover, make a ranged attack, and hide
again. If someone tries to get close to them they will run. Like the peddler,
their goal in a “market fight” situation is to delay and distract pursuers
enough for their allies to flee, and then flee themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elf-dune-strider&quot;&gt;Elf Dune Strider&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This nomadic warrior is used to running through the wastes. This stat block can
represent a raider, or someone who’s just protecting their wandering band. It’s
a Level 4 Skirmisher with 52 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dune Strider can &lt;strong&gt;Move Like the Wind&lt;/strong&gt;, gaining +5 to all defenses against
opportunity attacks provoked by movement. They’re armed with a &lt;strong&gt;Bone
Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; that does extra damage on a charge, and a &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Shortsword&lt;/strong&gt;
that’s slightly better for static attacks. The &lt;strong&gt;Rushing Dervish&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver lets
them move their Speed + 2 and make one attack with each sword against a
different target during the movement. This recharges when they’re bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Striders acting as raiders will keep mobile and try to spread out their attacks
in an attempt to intimidate their targets into giving up their possessions. They
will flee if the fight turns against them. Their traits and abilities make it
easy for them to bounce around the battlefield like pinballs, making charge
attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elf-raid-leader&quot;&gt;Elf Raid Leader&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sort of veteran commander you might find leading a larger raid against a
settlement, either as revenge for mistreatment or as a plain old resource
grab. It’s level 6 Artillery with the Leader tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leader has a &lt;strong&gt;obsidian shortsword&lt;/strong&gt; for emergencies, whose strikes let it
shift 1 square on a hit. It will mostly fight with its &lt;strong&gt;Bone Bow&lt;/strong&gt;, which is
both more accurate and more damaging. It can fire &lt;strong&gt;Harrying Shots&lt;/strong&gt; that do the
same damage as a basic ranged attack, but also make the target grant combat
advantage to adjacent allies of the leader for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its leaderly action is a command to &lt;strong&gt;Focus on the Pain&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action,
recharge 6+) which deals 5 damage to an ally within 20 squares and allows that
ally to immediately roll a save with a +2 bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raid leaders obviously lead from the back, providing ranged support to their
skirmisher and lurker allies. It might be good to add a brute or soldier war
beast to help protect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already mentioned my opinion about the elven stereotypes here: I don’t like
them, and would probably change them a bit were I to run a campaign in this
setting. They would be less true than depicted in the book, and depending on the
tone I was going for might or might not be less prevalent in the setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks are good, and can make for an extremely mobile encounter group
when used together. As mentioned above, any brutes and soldiers who are part of
an all-elven group will likely be trained war beasts instead of more elves.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/08/wir-dscc-elf.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/08/wir-dscc-elf.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Eladrin</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-eladrin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An Eladrin Veiled Warrior stepping out of a mirage.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physically, Athasian eladrin are very similar to those of the core setting, but
the near-total loss of their home plane has done a number on their psychology
and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defiling magic didn’t just destroy Athasian ecosystems - they also dissolved its
Feywild. Now only a few rare pocket dimensions remain, scattered like oases
through the wastes. The fate of the Lands Within the Wind is still tied to that
of Athas, which means they’re slowly dying just like the world is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Athasian Eladrin are a traumatized and dying people. Most of the ones
that remain live in remote castles and settlements in the desert or inside
surviving pockets of Feywild, guarding the entrance to their realms with psychic
illusions and only venturing out when they must.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eladrin have the same common stats as always: they’re Medium Fey Humanoids with
a Speed of 6, Low-light vision and a +5 on saves vs. charm effects. They retain
their signature &lt;strong&gt;Fey Step&lt;/strong&gt; power, which lets them teleport 5 squares as a move
action once per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stat blocks occupies what would be the lower range of eladrin power levels
from the Monster Manuals and Monster Vault. There are no more epic-level ghaeles
and bralanis in Athas… probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eladrin-veiled-warriors&quot;&gt;Eladrin Veiled Warriors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veiled Warriors are spies and scouts that range far away from Eladrin
settlements to gather information and locate resources, thought hey can also be
found as part of their homes’ defense force. This is a great origin for PCs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPC Veiled Warriors are Level 5 Soldiers with 60 HP. They fight with
Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Longspears&lt;/strong&gt; that damage and mark for a turn on a hit. Once per
encounter they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Veiling Dart&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Will) which deals
psychic damage, blinds for a turn and slows (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eladrin-mirage-adept&quot;&gt;Eladrin Mirage Adept&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the psions responsible for hiding Eladrin settlements. They’re Level 7
Controllers with 80 HP and a focus on illusion powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; that deals psychic damage and slows for
a turn. They can attack at range with &lt;strong&gt;Deluding Whispers&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Will), a charm power that deals psychic damage, slides 3 squares and
prevents the target from seeing creatures not adjacent to it for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally they’ll strike with the &lt;strong&gt;Phantom Foes&lt;/strong&gt; power (recharge 6, area 2
within 20 vs. Will), which I guess projects the illusion that many additional
foes are attacking the targets. This “psychic fireball” deals psychic damage and
confuses (save ends). Confused characters roll a d20 whenever they’re about to
make a melee or ranged attack and an ally is also in reach of that attack. On a
10 or higher, they attack the ally instead of the intended target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirage adepts are very effective when combined with veiled warriors, because the
warriors use reach weapons and so don’t need to be adjacent to a target blinded
by Deluding Whispers in order to attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eladrin-windwalker&quot;&gt;Eladrin Windwalker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some eladrin indiscriminately blame all people of the natural world for the fate
of their homeland, and feel such overwhelming hatred towards them that they
offer themselves in ritual sacrifice. This causes their life essence to slowly
leak into the Feywild and be replaced with the raw magic of that plane. This
gives them great power for as long as their diminishing life lasts. They use
their remaining time to go out into the world and slay every humanoid they see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windwalkers are Level 8 Lurkers with 69 HP. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;sabers&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;blowguns&lt;/strong&gt; that ignore armor and target Reflex. Their damage is average, but
&lt;strong&gt;Unseen Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; lets the windwalker deal extra damage against targets that
can’t see it, and slow them for a turn on any hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Between the Winds&lt;/strong&gt; trait lets a windwalker become invisible and gain
phasing whenever it either spends a turn without attacking or uses its &lt;em&gt;fey
step&lt;/em&gt;. These conditions last for a turn or until the windwalker attacks. This
does mean they can stay continuously invisible if they don’t attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windwalkers will usually try to attack every other turn like most lurkers to
benefit from Unseen Advantage, but the presence of an ally who can make them
invisible or blind PCs (like a Mirage Adept) can let them strike every turn with
bonus damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eladrin-windwalker-mirage&quot;&gt;Eladrin Windwalker Mirage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windwalkers in the final stages of the process are little more than ghosts. They
become Level 8 Minion Lurkers with a ground speed of &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt;, a flight speed of 6
(hover, altitude limit 2), always-on phasing, and Resist 10 All. Despite
appearances they are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; undead, and are not especially vulnerable to radiant
damage and anti-undead powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Wisp on the Wind&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them partial concealment vs. enemies that
are 2 or 3 squares away, and total concealment against enemies 4 or more squares
away. Their melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Razor Wind&lt;/strong&gt; that does minion-tier damage. When
they hit 0 HP, their &lt;strong&gt;Dispersing Essence&lt;/strong&gt; attacks a Close Burst 3 and does the
same damage as Razor Wind to those it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mirage’s damage resistance means you can only get it to that point by
dealing 11 or more damage with a single attack - they’ll resist anything
weaker. On the bright side, this means Dispersing Essence cannot provoke a chain
reaction as it only deals 8 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirages love large battle maps that let them invisibly fly past the party’s
defenders and gang up on isolated squishies. PCs can counter this tactic by
sticking together, but Dispersing Essence makes that decision a bit tougher than
it would seem at first. Cruel GMs can make it even harder by including other
monsters capable of area attacks in the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Windwalker variants are evil, having succumbed to genocidal rage, but
everyone else is unaligned. And they’re all super tragic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think windwalkers would mix with other eladrin, though it’s easy
enough to reskin a standard Mirage Adept as another windwalker variant if you
want to mix them up. As noted above, this makes for a potent combination.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/03/wir-dscc-eladrin.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/06/03/wir-dscc-eladrin.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dune Reaper</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dune-reaper.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A dune reaper. This image is mirrored from the one in the book.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of other Athasian fauna, dune reapers are predatory
insectile/reptilian pack hunters. However, they lean a lot more towards the
“insectile” side, and their origins are clearly unnatural even to contemporary
inhabitants of Athas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book says they “came to existence through defiling magic”, though it doesn’t
specify whether they were an artificially engineered species or whether some
side effect of defiling brought them to the world. Their Aberrant origin kinda
hints at the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures have a complex social structure. They organize into large
familial groups known as prides, who build large hives from sand, rocks, and
organic secretions near a water source that becomes the center of their
territory. The pride then splits up into smaller packs, which roam that
territory looking for food. A pack is composed of a large female “warrior”,
accompanied by smaller male “drones” and “shrieks” who are her mates. The
pride’s dominant female is known as its “matron”, and it’s her who makes
decisions that affect the whole pack, like where to build the hive or when to
seek new territory. A matron rules the pride until her death, which is usually
in a duel with an up-and-coming warrior who challenges her for the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune reapers are a scourge on the local ecology. Their menu includes just about
everything they can reach: humanoids, animals, plants, wagons, buildings… they
even eat rocks to store in their gizzards and aid in the digestion of tougher
food. A humanoid settlement in dune reaper territory is only safe if they can
provide the creatures with an ample alternate source of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune reaper reproduction happens on an annual cycle, and they’re even more
dangerous during mating season. The pride’s females need to lay their eggs
inside the bodies of living creatures, you see. When the eggs hatch, the newborn
reapers eat their host, and then set upon each other. Only the strongest
hatchlings survive this process. After about two months they’re already as
dangerous as a fully grown adult. At this time, they’re driven from their birth
hive and must either join another pride or form a new one with other young
reapers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune Reapers are Aberrant Beasts with Darkvision. Their basic melee attack
always uses their &lt;strong&gt;Arm Blades&lt;/strong&gt;, which do standard damage for their level and
might have other effects depending on the stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-reaper-drone&quot;&gt;Dune Reaper Drone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These relatively small males are Medium and make up the dune reaper worker
caste. They build the hive and carry food back to it, but as Level 12
Skirmishers with 120 HP and Speed 8 they’re certainly strong enough to take part
in the hunt as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;arm blade&lt;/strong&gt; attack also lets them shift 1 square on a hit. They
can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping Slash&lt;/strong&gt; that lets them jump 4 squares without provoking
opportunity attacks and use Arm Blade at the end of the movement. This recharges
when they’re first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy grants Combat Advantage to the drone, it can use a minor action to
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, dealing light physical damage on a hit. If an enemy makes a melee
attack against the drone, it can &lt;strong&gt;Leap Away&lt;/strong&gt;, jumping 4 squares without
drawing OAs, as an immediate reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drones want to leap into melee at the start of the fight, and seek positions
where their chosen target grants them CA. They’ll leap away when attacked and
come back from an unexpected angle. When fighting drones, shoot them or surround
them. Don’t let them surround you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-reaper-shriek&quot;&gt;Dune Reaper Shriek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not a role you usuall find among mundane insects. The book considers them
specialized drones that can leap not just through the air, but through time and
space. When they do this, they emit an ear-splitting scream that gives them
their name. They’re Level 14 Lurkers with 106 HP and Speed 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;arm blades&lt;/strong&gt; are standard attacks with no riders, and are a lot more
dangerous when used in conjunction with the shriek’s freaky powers. A
&lt;strong&gt;Shrieking Reap&lt;/strong&gt; lets them make two arm blade attacks against the same
target. If one hits, it teleports the target 2 squares and inflicts 10 ongoing
damage (save ends). If both hit, the teleport distance increases to 5, and the
ongoing damage to 15. A &lt;strong&gt;Shrieking Warp&lt;/strong&gt; removes the shriek from play until
the start of its next turn, when it appears at a spot within 10 squares of its
previous position and makes a Close Burst 2 attack that deals thunder damage and
pushes 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shrieking Warp is an at-will ability, but it’s disabled for a turn when the
shriek takes force damage because of its &lt;strong&gt;Forceful Silence&lt;/strong&gt; trait. Shrieking
Reap recharges whenever the creature uses Shrieking Warp. Our lurker loop here
is Shrieking Reap -&amp;gt; Shrieking Warp -&amp;gt; Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book reminds us that forced movement is always voluntary for the attacker,
so shrieks arriving from a Warp will often choose to push all but one of the
enemies they hit with the attack, to isolate it from its allies. Clever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-reaper-warrior&quot;&gt;Dune Reaper Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Large female will lead a pack of drones and shrieks when hunting. She’s a
Level 15 Brute with 180 HP, Speed 7, and the Leader tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She exudes an aura (3) of &lt;strong&gt;Inciting Pheromones&lt;/strong&gt; that grants all dune reapers
inside a +2 bonus to Will, and makes them immune to the Dazed condition. She
also has the &lt;strong&gt;Unhindered&lt;/strong&gt; trait we saw before, which lets her drag grabbed
characters around when she moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her &lt;strong&gt;arm blade&lt;/strong&gt; is Reach 2 and extra-strong. She can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping
Slash&lt;/strong&gt; similar to the drone’s, which also inflicts 10 ongoing damage if either
attack hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her triggered actions make her even more dangerous. &lt;strong&gt;Snapping Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt;
triggers when someone hits the warrior with a melee attack. As a reaction, she
attacks their Fortitude and grabs them on a hit. Grabbed targets take 10 damage
when they fail an escape attempt. Her &lt;strong&gt;Compelling Musk&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is
triggered when she misses with an Arm Blade attack, and lets another dune reaper
within 3 squares make a melee basic attack as an opportunity action. I’m not
going to make a joke about that power name, it’s too easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune reaper packs number between 5 and 12 (!) individuals. Only one will be a
warrior, though you could say the PCs found more than one pack together if you
want there to be more of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reapers are impossible to train, but sapient humanoids still capture them for
use as arena beasts, and hunt them as a source of leather, organic armor plates,
and blades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These seem to me like yet another pack-based predator, the third or fourth we
saw in this reading. I do like the ominous aberrant touches in both their lore
and mechanics, though. The shriek in particular reminds me a lot of a Hound of
Tindalos.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/24/wir-dscc-dune-reaper.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/24/wir-dscc-dune-reaper.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dwarf</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dwarf.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A Dark Sun dwarf. This world is too hot for big beards.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s customary for Fourth Edition monster books to include entries for playable
species. After all, they may show up as enemies or allies. In this book, they
also serve to flesh out some of the Dark Sun-specific story of each species. As
you can see from the illustration, dwarves here are a little different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwarves probably had a pretty typical culture in Athas’ distant past, as the
book says they ruled “great mountain kingdoms”. However, the genocidal wars of
the Red Age pretty much destroyed their civilization. While modern-day dwarves
are still extremely resilient and dedicated workers, the knowledge of reading
and writing the Dwarven language has been lost. While you can still find Davek
runes in their ruins, no one alive knows how to read them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book kinda conflates this with dwarves not knowing how to read at all, and
therefore not knowing any magic, but that’s a giant leap that I think is
incorrect. Dwarven writing is a lost art, but Common and a lot of other
languages still have written forms and magic lore doesn’t have to be encoded in
Dwarven. I’d say dwarves are as likely to be literate and to know magic rituals
as any other person in this setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True, when you’re talking about typical civilians that’s still not very likely,
but Dwarven PCs and major NPCs will still be literate. And it does sound
flavorful for modern dwarven culture to include an element of pride about not
needing magic to do their work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwarves are a fairly common people. Every city state has hundreds or thousands
of dwarven laborers and artisans, both free and enslaved. They also live in
small communities in the wastes, some of which are also mining camps. Whether
your interaction with them is peaceful or violent depends entirely on the
behavior of the PCs and on the objectives of that specific group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the differences, Athasian dwarves are still Medium Natural Humanoids
with a ground speed of 5 and Low-Light Vision, just like the ones from the
PHB. They retain the PC traits that make them hard to move: &lt;strong&gt;Stand the Ground&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Steady-Footed&lt;/strong&gt;, which reduce forced movement by 1 and let them roll a
save against being knocked prone, respectively. They also have +5 to saves
against poison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier editions spent a lot of time describing how each dwarf had an obsessive
focus on one kind of task, to the point where it restricted their actions. That
makes an appearance here but it’s not as dominant as before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dwarf-conscript&quot;&gt;Dwarf Conscript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically a civilian, the conscript still has a body hardened by countless
hours of heavy labor, and will not hesitate to pick up weapons in defense of
their mine or their home. This is a Level 2 Brute with 47 HP, wearing hide armor
and wielding a Dark Sun polearm known as a “gouge”, which is basically a
sharpened shovel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;gouge&lt;/strong&gt; is a standard brute attack, but if it scores a critical hit it
also pushes the target 1 square and knocks it prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conscript also has a &lt;strong&gt;Singular Focus&lt;/strong&gt; minor action that’s the last vestige
of the 2e rules. This lets the conscript choose an enemy as the target of their
focus, and gain +5 damage against that enemy while they remain the conscript’s
focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power recharges when the chosen enemy drops to 0 HP, and it lasts until the
end of the encounter or until the conscript uses it again. It makes the
conscript punch &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; above their weight class when attacking their chosen
enemy, and is a very nice incentive to behave obsessively in a fight. Since they
can only switch focus when the previous enemy dies, targeted enemies should keep
away to make the conscript waste actions chasing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dwarf-sunpriest&quot;&gt;Dwarf Sunpriest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern dwarven religion venerates primal spirits and elementals, particularly
those associated with the sun. Sun priests are venerated spiritual and political
leaders among them, and often lead other dwarves into battle when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sunpriest is Level 5 Artillery with 52 HP and the Leader tag. They wear hide
armor and wield a mace in one hand and a totem in the other. Their basic melee
attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Burning Mace&lt;/strong&gt; that deals fire damage, and their main ranged
attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Bright Ray&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10) that deals radiant damage and inflicts a
-2 attack penalty on the target for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can apply a &lt;strong&gt;Sun Blessing&lt;/strong&gt; to an ally within 5
squares. That ally regains 10 HP, deals 5 extra fire damage with their attacks
for a turn, and any enemy that hits them in the same time span takes 5 fire
damage. Praise the sun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dwarf-war-chief&quot;&gt;Dwarf War Chief&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the name, not all war chiefs are commanders, but they’re all renowned
champions. They’re Level 6 Elite Soldiers with 144 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war chief fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; made from giant bone, and its basic
attacks grant them 5 temporary HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;Spinning Club&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge
5+) attacks enemies in a Close Burst 1. If it hits an enemy marked by the war
chief, that enemy is immobilized until the start of the warchief’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how do they mark enemies? Via &lt;strong&gt;Battlefield Focus&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action that
lets them automatically mark up to 2 enemies within 10 squares. It recharges
when one of these enemies drops to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a marked enemy adjacent to the war chief moves, shifts, or makes an attack,
&lt;strong&gt;Brutal Club&lt;/strong&gt; gives the dwarf a basic attack against them as an interrupt,
which also immobilizes for a turn on a hit. This triggers &lt;em&gt;even if the enemy
attacks the war chief&lt;/em&gt;, and even if the enemy makes one of those moves that
doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks. This means it’s more powerful than a PC
fighter’s Combat Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwarves can be part of any encounter group whose theme is “a bunch of people”,
be they villainous, allied, or bystanders. Dwarven communities, like everyone
else, also domesticate a number of Athasian beasts that might see use in a
fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these stat blocks! They’re low-level but each has some very interesting
tricks they can use. The “focus” powers ended up being more useful than I
thought at first.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/20/wir-dscc-dwarf.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/20/wir-dscc-dwarf.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Drake</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athas only has one dragon: The Dragon of Tyr. He’s the setting’s main bad guy,
over and above the Sorcerer-Kings. As such, he’s immensely powerful,
intelligent, and evil. Prime Final Boss material!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, you might not want to wait until your PCs are level 30 demigods before
they can fight a nasty giant lizard with elemental powers. That’s where Drakes
come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athas has a lot of things that would be called drakes in standard 4e, but here
the name refers to something else entirely. The things Athasians call “Drakes”
are, essentially, nonsapient dragons. They fulfill many of a dragon’s narrative
functions. They’re big and tough enemies that make splendid boss fights for
high-Paragon or low-Epic parties. There are several types associated with
different elements. They lair in areas dominated by their associated element and
possess psychic powers that let them summon and control orbs of that element
from the Elemental Chaos. They even have a hoarding instinct!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The roles they &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; fulfill are those of being a Machiavellian plotter or a
big player in regional politics, which are things you’d expect a powerful enough
dragon to be. They’re animals, not people. A text box informs us drakes were
written this way because the Dark Sun setting is very geographically limited,
and has a relatively small number of movers-and-shakers who are all accounted
for. Adding an arbitrary number of traditional sapient epic dragons to this mix
would wreck the setting’s delicate equilibrium, and that’s a job for the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of drakes not being sapient is that there’s no guarantee
their hoards will be &lt;em&gt;valuable&lt;/em&gt;. There might be some good loot there, but it’s
going to be mixed with a mountain of trinkets and souvenirs that are merely
shiny or pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All drakes presented here are Huge Elemental Beasts with the Reptile tag, and a
tag corresponding to their associated element. They all have a &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a
&lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that act as basic attacks, and the signature &lt;strong&gt;Drake’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; power
that lets them spend a single action to use two Claws against one target and a
Bite against a different target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their elemental orb powers are area attacks that create a hazardous zone in the
affected area, but their exact powers vary with each stat block. They always
have a &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; reaction that lets them immediately rechage and use
an elemental power when first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same text box that discusses why drakes are nonsapient tells us we can take
any dragon from other books and add them as drakes in Athas by declaring them
nonsapient. Good candidates include brown, gray and red dragons from the
chromatics; adamantine, iron, and orium dragons from the metallics; and any of
the catastrophic dragons. You might want to change the appearance of the
metallics too, since their default coloration stands out too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;water-drake&quot;&gt;Water Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-water.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A water drake ready to ambush you from its oasis hideout.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water drakes like to lair in oases. A possible sign of their presence is the
total &lt;em&gt;absence&lt;/em&gt; of the small animals that usually live in such an
environment. If you find such a place, you should either keep moving or be very,
very sneaky when filling your waterskin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This crocodile-looking beast is a Level 18 Solo Controller with 680 HP. It has
Resist 10 Cold, a ground speed of 8, and a swim speed of 12. It’s &lt;strong&gt;Aquatic&lt;/strong&gt;,
meaning it can breathe underwater and gets +2 to attacks against non-aquatic
creatures in underwater combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake’s elemental attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Water&lt;/strong&gt;,
which is a fireball-sized area attack (area 2 within 10, recharge 5+). It comes
in two versions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;boiling&lt;/strong&gt; orb deals fire damage despite being made of water, and creates
a damaging zone that lasts for the rest of the encounter or until the drake
uses another boiling orb.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;ice&lt;/strong&gt; orb deals no immediate damage, but inflicts ongoing 20 cold damage
and restrains (save ends both). It creates a zone that repeats the orb’s
attack against any creatures start their turn in the zone and are not
restrained. Again, this lasts until the end of the encounter or until the
drake uses another ice orb.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this means the drake can have both a boiling and a frozen zone in place
simultaneously, though I’d rule they can’t overlap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake’s other power is &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Clone&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action, recharge 4+), which
lets it create a duplicate of itself on a solid or liquid adjacent space in the
map. The copy can acts independently and can take a full turn on an initiative
count 10 lower than the original’s. It has all the original’s stats and powers
with the following exceptions: it only has 1 HP; and it shares the original’s
recharge roll for its powers instead of having its own. If the original has any
spent powers when it uses this power, the copy’s powers will also start out
spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water drake’s &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; recharges &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; the Orb and Psionic
Clone, letting the drake use both as a free action right then and
there. Double the orbs, double the fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-drake&quot;&gt;Fire Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-fire.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A fire drake roaring atop a patch of flaming ground.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flavor text here has a fire drake living inside an active volcano and
worshipped as a god by a halfling tribe, who try to sacrifice a human to it only
to be eaten along with the intended victim. Cliches aside, this shows us you can
find fire drakes in volcanos and other such places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire drakes are Level 20 Elite Lurkers with 298 HP, a Speed of 9, and Resist 15
Fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; does standard damage for its level. The &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; is a
little weaker but grabs on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Drake’s Fury&lt;/strong&gt; works as normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creature’s &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Fire&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is an Area Burst 1 within
10 that deals fire damage and creates a damaging fire zone that lasts until the
end of the encounter or until the drake casts another orb. While it waits for
the power to recharge, it can use minor actions to move the existing magma zone
4 squares. The drake’s &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; recharges this orb and lets the
beast use it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fire drake’s last power is not elemental: it’s &lt;strong&gt;Living Shield&lt;/strong&gt;, an
opportunity action that lets the beast use a grabbed victim as a shield if
anyone other than that victim damages it. This makes the victim take half of the
attack’s damage, with the other half still affecting the drake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing terribly lurkery about the fire drake. With that grab and the
mobile zone, you could have made it a controller instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;air-drake&quot;&gt;Air Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-air.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An air drake in a menacing stance.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air drakes live in tall mountains and canyons. They love to hunt animals and
people who try to walk the precarious passes of these places, knocking them down
with their wind powers and devouring the tenderized remains. They’re Level 22
Elite Skirmishers with 404 HP, a ground speed of 8, and a flight speed of 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures deal extra damage when they have CA on an enemy, and this bonus
increases when they’re bloodied. Their physical attacks are otherwise pretty
standard for a drake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Air&lt;/strong&gt; has a wider radius than usual (area burst 3
within 10), and deals untyped damage on a hit. On a hit it also slides the
targets 5 squares, and creates the usual damaging zone. The zone cannot be
moved, but slides targets 3 squares when it damages them. This recharges when
the drake is first bloodied, but it has to be used during the drake’s actions
after this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When pressured, the drake can use &lt;strong&gt;Wind Veil&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action (recharge
4+). This lets it shift its speed and gain concealment against non-adjacent
enemies until the end of its next turn. &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt; recharges this,
and lets the creature use it immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt odd for Bloodied Response to be such a defensive power here… but then
I saw that it’s because the drake can use &lt;strong&gt;Control the Wind&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction
when damaged. This is a Close Burst 5 vs. AC that deals the same damage as the
bite to the triggering enemy, and lets the monster slide the target 3
squares. Exceptionally, this slide can be &lt;em&gt;vertical&lt;/em&gt;, which means the target
will take a bit of fall damage when it falls back to the ground… or a lot of
fall damage if tossed diagonally into a chasm. A merciful GM could probably
still allow the usual save vs. hazardous terrain to let the victim cling to an
edge before being tossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;earth-drake&quot;&gt;Earth Drake&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-drake-earth.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An earth drake.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spicy bullette with earth control powers. Earth Drakes are Level 24 Elite
Controllers with 456 HP, a ground speed of 8, and a burrow speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their physical attaks work as usual. Their &lt;strong&gt;Orb of Elemental Earth&lt;/strong&gt; is an Area
1 within 10 attack vs. Fortitude. It damages and restrains (save ends) on a hit,
deals half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting zone is difficult terrain, and the drake can use minor actions to
make secondary attacks against anyone inside. This deals a tiny bit of physical
damage and knocks the target prone. This is what &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Response&lt;/strong&gt;
recharges, but it’s not the only thing that happens when the earth drake is
bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, when that happens the drake &lt;strong&gt;Expands&lt;/strong&gt;. It goes from Huge to
Gargantuan, pushing any targets that were adjacent to it out of its new occupied
space. While this lasts (until the end of the drake’s next turn), the drake’s
melee reach improves from 3 to 4, it gains +2 to AC, and anyone hit by its
attacks is immobilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone damages the drake it can use &lt;strong&gt;Immovable Stone&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction,
ignoring up to 4 squares of forced movement and using its bite against the
attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Athasian Drakes lack sapience, it’s harder to justify them being
accompanied by minions. However, all but the Water Drake are elites, which means
it’s very easy to set up an encounter against a mated pair of them. It might
also be possible to add elementals of an appropriate level to any drake
encounter as extra minions or regulars. The beasts wouldn’t be interested in
eating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I like their mechanics. Taking one of these drakes and turning them into
a sapient dragon for outside of Dark Sun is as easy as taking a foreign dragon
and turning it into an Athasian Drake.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/16/wir-dscc-drake.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/16/wir-dscc-drake.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Dragonborn (Dray)</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-dragonborn.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A dragonborn sorcerer in the Athasian desert.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the title of their entry, these Dragonborn are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a new
addition. Dark Sun is one of two 2e settings (that I know of) that had draconic
humanoids in it since its initial publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite using dragonborn stats for the PC version, these are not the same
dragonborn as the ones from the standard Points of Light setting. Athasian
dragonborn are known as Dray, are lankier than the standard variety, and have a
completely different origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dray species was created by the sorcerer-king Dregoth to be his perfect
servants and minions, but he was dissatisfied with the result and cast most
of them out of his city-state of Giustenal. Those he allowed to stay kept
serving him until the other sorcerer-kings banded together to destroy Dregoth
and his city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s Dray are descended both from the outcasts and from the survivors of
Giustenal’s destruction. Their total population is relatively small and few
people know of their existence. Their communities are either small scattered
tribes in the wastes or the rare enclave embedded in a larger settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their reputation among those who know about them is as slavers and
sorcerers. Not All Dray (TM) deserve this reputation… but a significant
majority of them do. They practice defiling magic and slavery, and frequently
act as mercenaries for other groups who are okay with this. In this, they
continue the cycle of abuse, inflicting on others what their creator inflicted
on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dray, like standard dragonborn, are Medium Natural Humanoids with a Speed
of 6. They can use a &lt;strong&gt;Dragon Breath&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter, a Close Blast 3
vs. Reflex that deals some sort of elemental damage and whose details vary with
the stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can easily use standard dragonborn stat blocks from the other monster books
as more dray varieties if you need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-slaver&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Slaver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These assholes roam the desert looking for easily taken captives that they can
sell to the sorcerer-kings in exchange for money and prestige. They’re
frequently found in mixed-species slaver parties as their rank-and-file muscle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slavers are Level 16 Minion Soldiers that fight with &lt;strong&gt;Bastard Swords&lt;/strong&gt; which
damage and mark for a turn on a hit. Their &lt;strong&gt;Dragon Breath&lt;/strong&gt; deals lightning
damage and marks (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re tougher than your average minion too - the first time they drop to 0 HP,
their &lt;strong&gt;Determined Defender&lt;/strong&gt; trait lets them recover, clear any effects on
them, and get back on at the start of their next turn. This makes them more
willing to risk harm when surrounding the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-scorned-champion&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Scorned Champion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few dray take pride in being scorned by their creator, making that part of
their identity. I’m guessing these are the nicer ones, since it would make sense
for them to reject the ways of the sorcerer-kings. The Scorned Champion is an
example of someone who might rise to lead a community of these Dray. Still, he’s
sensitive to anything he perceives as a challenge to his position, and is quick
to strike down the source of that challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scorned Champion is a Level 16 Skirmisher with 151 HP. This cocky fighter’s
&lt;strong&gt;Bravura Poise&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (1) that forces enemies inside to grant combat
advantage. He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; that damages the target and lets him
shift 1 square on a hit. The &lt;strong&gt;Dray Fury&lt;/strong&gt; special attack (recharge 4+) lets him
shift his speed and strike twice with the scimitar at any point during this
movement. His &lt;strong&gt;DragonBreath&lt;/strong&gt; can exclude one creature of his choice from the
blast, and deals fire-and-lightning damage. Finally, his &lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable Force&lt;/strong&gt;
power lets him immediately end any Slow or Immobilize effect on him once per
round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-defiler&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Defiler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drays like this one go in the other direction - they look fondly upon the past
when they could walk the streets unchallenged, openly displaying their arcane
might. They want the power to do that again, and see defiling as the quickest
way to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Defiler is Level 18 Artillery with 129 HP. They use &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; as weapons
and implements, and the damage roll on this attack has a funky format that mixes
physical and cold damage. Their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Dragonfear Ray&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 10 vs. Will) that deals psychic damage and causes the target to take 5
damage each time they damage the defiler or one of its allies, until the end of
the target’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their dragon breath has been corrupted into a &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5
vs. Reflex) that deals immediate and ongoing cold-and-necrotic damage (save
ends). While at least one target is taking this ongoing damage, the defiler has
+2 to all attacks and +5 to all damage rolls. This recharges if the defiler
misses every target with the power, so it will keep doing it until it hits
someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter the defiler can cast &lt;strong&gt;Flight of Dragons&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action,
allowing every ally within 5 squares to fly 5 squares, and flying 10 squares
itself. It doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks when it leaves its starting
square, but obeys the rules normally from that point on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action it can also use &lt;strong&gt;Hurled Dragon Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) to do
just that with a less corrupt form of its breath. This is either a Close Blast 5
or an Area 2 Within 10, both targetting Reflex. It deals cold damage on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dragonborn-atavist&quot;&gt;Dragonborn Atavist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dray like this one prefer to focus on the bestial nature of their dragon
heritage, using ritual techniques to tap into that inner beast and bring it
forth during combat. Why use weapons when you have the power of a dragon at your
disposal? This one’s a Level 19 Brute with 220 HP and Resist 10 Acid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attacks are a strong &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a slightly less strong &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;,
both of which deal ongoing acid damage on a hit (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Draconic Fury&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) lets them use both attacks with one action, or even engage in a
classic claw/claw/bite routine if they’re bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their dragon breath, as you might expect, does acid damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems the only stat block here that’s actively Evil is the Defiler - everyone
else is unaligned, even the slavers. I’m not sure I agree with that last part,
but I suppose you can use the slaver stat block for a more conventional non-evil
warrior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad the game gives us some tools to stat up a non-evil group of Dray. PCs
have to come from somewhere, and it’d get a little samey if all of them were
nonconformist rebels fleeing their evil upbringing.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/11/wir-dscc-dragonborn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/11/wir-dscc-dragonborn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read The Dark Sun Creature Catalog: (Not) The Dragon of Tyr</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At this point in our &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;read-through of the Dark Sun Creature Catalog&lt;/a&gt;, it the
next entry in the book would be the Dragon of Tyr. As I mentioned in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.rpg.net/index.php?threads/the-4e-dark-sun-creature-catalog.925701/post-25475185&quot;&gt;corresponding RPG.net thread&lt;/a&gt;, however, the Dragon’s touches upon the
setting’s deepest secrets. These only appear at the very end of the Dark Sun
Campaign Setting book, which forum user zedturtle is reading in another
thread. I don’t want to spoil him ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other reason for this is that the Dragon of Tyr is a singular character and
a very important one in the setting, so he should really be over on the
Personages section of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both of these reasons, I’m discussing the Dragon at the end of this Let’s
Read.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/08/wir-dscc-dragon-of-tyr-notice.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/04/08/wir-dscc-dragon-of-tyr-notice.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
