<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 20:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 20:07:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackaton: Shadowrun 4th Edition, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/sr4-cover.jpg&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Shadowrun 20th Anniversary's cover.
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After setting up our parameters in the previous post, we start the run here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually ran this one a couple of times, because it took me a bit to fully
internalize the rules. My main mistake was assuming I was familiar with them
already and only reading them superficially to “refresh my memory”. This made me
get some crucial basic facts wrong, causing my first run to be really fast but
incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I made an additional run where I tracked the die rolls accurately and got
detected in one of the hacks. Then I read the rules outside of the Matrix
chapter more closely and made another one where I spent Edge more wisely and
accomplished all goals without being detected. I’m referring to these as the
&lt;strong&gt;loud&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;silent&lt;/strong&gt; runs. They are recorded below as a single account with
notes on how they diverge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diff-merging-timelines&quot;&gt;Diff-merging Timelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hacker enters the building with is team. They get past the reception as
usual, receiving temporary badges. Once inside, he feels a “sudden” need to go
to the bathroom, and locks himself inside a stall. He spends a couple of turns
scanning for the badge’s wireless signal, and finds it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He then tries to hack into the badge, still using AR because it’s a fragging’
badge. He succeeds quickly. As expected the badge can’t do a lot, but it knows
how to talk to the security server and now so does the hacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hacker then switches to VR and goes hot, after bracing himself so he doesn’t
fall down in the stall. He tries to get himself security-level access because he
knows from examining the badge that user-level accounts do nothing in this
server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where our timelines diverge. In the &lt;strong&gt;loud&lt;/strong&gt; run, he gets in but also
gets detected. The server issues a restricted alert against his persona,
triggers the Blackout ice, and pings the guards. Restricted alert means the
server’s Firewall increases by +4 against the hacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hacker and the IC go into cybercombat, with the hacker winning
initiative. Cybercombat here resembles the SR1 version a bit, though the exact
things you roll are different. With the expenditure of a couple points of Edge,
our hacker manages to destroy the ice at the start of the second combat turn,
without suffering any trauma to his brain meats. Still, in this timeline the
guards are suspicious of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;strong&gt;silent&lt;/strong&gt; run, luckier rolls let the hacker in without being detected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both, the hacker manages to disable the camera and alarm, letting the team
move into the records room. While they perform a physical search for hard
copies, our hacker jacks into the secret isolated server and goes into hot sim
VR again. He manages to get in undetected, though in the &lt;strong&gt;silent&lt;/strong&gt; run he has
to spend the Edge he didn’t spend in combat to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rule that finding the files requires no tests, as this is only a single node
and the existing data search rules are for searching the Matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still in the records room, our hacker decides to be daring and hack the office
network in search of those drainable accounts. This network has a wireless
signal covering the whole office and is quite visible, so he gets right to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, our decker easily hacks himself a user account. From there he runs a
data search on the network’s user directory to find the one who has access to
the bank accounts, and then attempts to gain access to it. I give this a low
Threshold because it’s a small intranet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding the accountant’s profile, the hacker attempts to hack into it. That’s
like starting from scratch, this time going for a security account. Again the
hacker manages to get in undetected, and again in the &lt;strong&gt;silent&lt;/strong&gt; run he needs to
spend Edge to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draining the account requires no additional rolls. And since our hacker retained
his account at the security server, unlocking the back door requires no rolls
either. Of course, in the &lt;strong&gt;loud&lt;/strong&gt; timeline there’s a very high chance that
they’re doing this during a firefight, as the guards are extra-suspicious and
would have known to check the records room…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;loud&lt;/strong&gt; run that had cybercombat and an alert took 31 minutes. The
&lt;strong&gt;silent&lt;/strong&gt; one took 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-analysis-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Run Analysis and Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This system is my personal favorite so far, and I had to actively keep myself
from adding little cool bits that kept appearing in my imagination, because I’d
otherwise would have found myself running an entire solo adventure, controlling
the whole team and imagining dialogue in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having “my” character be present with the group certainly helped stir the
imagination, because he wasn’t sitting pretty at home. I had to think about how
he navigated the physical site with the rest of the group, and from where he’d
jack into VR to avoid suspicion, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do love that the system was very fast compared to the other ones so far, but I
wonder how much of that is down to the design of the target nodes. I’d love to
hear about how people design their own adventures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see how Shadowrun’s system still favors silent runs here. Cybercombat
against even a single instance of ICE takes a while to resolve, and the more of
it there is the longer the run will take. Careless hackers could easily find
themselves having to deal with multiple ICE cubes at once, perhaps even in
different hosts, and that will drastically lower their chances of success. More
advanced rules let hackers run their own agent programs, which helps fighting
the icy hordes but makes things take more real time to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, let’s see how our sample runs here fit with the physical team’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we again assume the physical part of the run takes 50 minutes for a perfectly
stealthy team and 90 minutes with a firefight on the way out, then it’s also
possible to correlate our diverging runs to each of these scenarios. The
perfectly sneaky run would mean a perfectly sneaky hack. The loud run would
almost certainly be caused by that alert we got, unless our talker was &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;
at their job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in the more common silent/silent and loud/loud scenarios, our hacker took up
around 25% of the total session time, which is pretty close to ideal in a
four-player party. In an anomalous loud hack/silent run scenario, they take up a
little under half the run time. And in a silent hack/loud run situation, they
take around 15% of the time hacking the objectives and can spend the rest of
their spotlight time helping out in physical combat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/31/hackaton-sr4-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/31/hackaton-sr4-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon: Shadowrun 4th Edition</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/sr4-cover.jpg&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Shadowrun 20th Anniversary's cover.
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this post we’ll be using Shadowrun 4th Edition, published in 2005. More
specifically, we’ll be using the 20th Anniversary core book published in 2009,
which uses the same base rules as 4th Edition but incorporates errata and some
material that was previously published in supplements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-overview&quot;&gt;Setting Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Shadowrun 1e’s Matrix was inspired by 80s mainframes, then 4th edition’s is
inspired by the Internet as it was in 2005, plus some reasonable extrapolations
of things that were in fashion among futurists then but didn’t necessarily pan
out in the following decades. It does end up looking a lot like what we actually
have here in 2023, with a few important differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of being built around high-speed cell towers, the mobile Matrix is a
ubiquitous wireless mesh network. Individual devices in a mesh cooperate to
route its network traffic without the need for central coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet of Things was also in fashion, so every object that could possibly
have a use for built-in computing and network capability has that
capability. Most of those devices are fairly limited, but computer hardware is
apparently so cheap and standardized that many of them have unused capacity that
could be repurposed by a clever hacker. One example is someone converting cheap
appliances into mesh routers to to bring connectivity to a “dead zone”. It’s
also easy to turn off a device’s wireless capability with a simple command or in
some cases a physical switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone carries a &lt;em&gt;commlink&lt;/em&gt;, a device that’s equivalent to a real-world
smartphone in form factor and usage. They often connect to a variety of
&lt;em&gt;peripherals&lt;/em&gt;, more limited devices that are built to talk to commlinks and not
to the wider Matrix. These range from augmented-reality glasses to that
smartlinked gun your character owns. A big server of the sort that’s the target
of a hacking run is called a &lt;em&gt;nexus&lt;/em&gt;. I will just say “server” instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Augmented Reality is a big deal here, with most things connected to a mesh
having some sort of AR presence, and general interaction with your commlink and
the Matrix happening through AR interfaces. If you can use AR to help with your
current task you gain a bonus to the roll. Examples include finding your way
around town with that handy videogame-style minimap, overlaying a blueprint and
instructions over the thing you’re fixing, firing a smarlinked gun, finding
someone in a crowd when you have a face-recognition database, and so on. One can
also choose to go “full VR”, which more useful for certain applications (mainly
hacking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secure facilities of the sort shadowrunners are hired to break into have
internal mesh networks. They use tactics like limited signal ranges and
radio-blocking paint to keep their signal contained to the physical space they
service, and might not be connected to the wider Matrix at all. In some the
paydata is going to be in a server that’s only accessible via wired connection
or even via its own terminal. While sometimes it’s still possible for a hacker
to work from home, they will most often have to hoof it alongside the rest of
the team and take on devices and intranets as they come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like it happens with Shadowrun 1e, a lot of criticism of this model comes
from a mismatch between the person’s understanding of the modern (2023) Internet
and the model they used to build the Matrix in the books. It’s a bit worse here
both because of the usual edition warrior shenanigans, and because the
differences are more obscure. On the bright side it’s a lot easier to change the
explanation behind the Matrix to a 2023-current one here than it would be to do
the same to Shadowrun 1e’s 80s extravaganza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics-overview&quot;&gt;Mechanics Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacker characters are called, well, hackers. They use powerful commlinks and a
suite of specialized software to hack mesh-connected devices. Most often this
means some peripheral or commlink-level device like a camera, alarm, door or
handy pieces of scenery like unattended cars and other things that can be used
to ruin an enemy’s day. It can also mean hacking into a big nexus to steal data
and generally do the same things you could do back in SR 1. All devices are
described by the same set of attributes, and use the same types of programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuff like memory, storage, file sizes, and download speeds are still
considerations in the fiction, but they don’t get detailed rules. Unless the GM
judges a given chunk of data is too large, you can download it in one turn and
store it in your commlink. Some really huge files might take multiple turns to
download or might not fit your storage at all, and the GM decides when that’s
the case based on common sense. You don’t need to worry about storing your run’s
paydata, but you also can’t try to get cute and download the entire public
Matrix into a talking teddy bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacking a device means obtaining illicit access to a user account inside it. If
you have set of legitimate credentials for your target account then you don’t
need to roll anything. Otherwise you can gain access by either &lt;em&gt;probing&lt;/em&gt; the
device over a period of hours or days, or by &lt;em&gt;hacking on the fly&lt;/em&gt;. The latter is
an aggressive approach that happens in combat time and carries a much higher
risk of detection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacking can be done in AR or VR. There are several advantages to doing it in VR,
and even more for doing it with the safety limiters turned off (a condition
known as “hot sim”). Hot sim is the preferred way to hack important nodes, but
it also leaves you vulnerable to lethal damage from Black Ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three types of user account. Standard accounts can view and mess with
their own data and perform basic functions of the device. Security accounts have
access to more sensitive functions and thus are more protected. And
administrator accounts are the most protected and have full control of
everything. Individual nodes in adventure descriptions should also include a
description of which account tiers they support and what those let users do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible to use a technique called “spoofing” to send single commands
to nearby devices by pretending to be someone who’s authorized to do so. This is
probably what you’re going to use for one-off environmental fuckery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no Hacking Pool here, but all characters can spend Edge to boost any
roll by doing things like rerolling failed dice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-parameters&quot;&gt;Run Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in this series our Hacker will be joining the physical team
on-site. In this game, it’s common for a site to have more than one server, and
for the really important ones to be isolated from the outside Matrix. This means
the servers containing our main mission objectives can’t be hacked remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual the core book provides us with a very handy sample Hacker which we can
use for our run. This one’s an ork dude with an implanted commlink with all
attributes at 5 and a full set of programs whose ratings vary between 2
and 5. His skills vary between 4 and 5 too. He’s better at sneaking around than
at cybercombat, so we should take care not to trigger any alerts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a ready-made target site for him to hack, but I found this &lt;a href=&quot;https://pavao.org/shadowrun/miscellany/example_matrix.pdf&quot;&gt;free
document&lt;/a&gt; with some example sites and I’m going to take inspiration from
this, from the SR1 mainframe, and from what little I know of real life to design
a target network. Here it goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This company has a public site but that doesn’t get stats here because it’s
hosted in some cloud provider elsewhere. It has an internal office network for
its day to day business, separated from the Matrix by a beefy firewall. The
firewall node is also not relevant to us because we’re hacking the site from the
inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll treat the entire office network as a single node: System 4, Response 4,
Firewall 3, Analyze 2. User-level accounts allow each user to perform their
daily work. The company’s accountant has a Security account that can access and
manipulate the company’s money, and we need to breach it in order to steal that
money. The network’s standard ice has Pilot 3, Analyze 3, Attack 3, Armor 3, and
triggers when the node detects any unauthorized access. There’s another piece of
ice here (Pilot 4, Analyze 4, Stealth 4, Track 4) that gets activated if the
system detects unauthorized access to the security-tier account. It tries to
trace the intruder’s connection and notifies the authorities when it succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separate from the internal network, there is a security server in charge of
alarms, cameras, badges and lockable doors. User accounts in this server let
employee badges open some doors, but not the one that leads to the record
room. Security accounts let their user operate alarms and cameras. The security
server has its own wireless signal that covers the entire office, but it doesn’t
connect to any other server and accounts on other hosts aren’t valid here. We
want at least a Security account to perform most of our objectives. If the
hacker is on site they might also try to spoof the individual devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security server has System 4, Response 4, Firewall 4, Analyze 4. Its ice,
which activates when an intruder is detected, has Pilot 4, Blackout 4,
Armor 4. Any guards currently connected might also be alerted to the
intruder. The server operates in hidden mode, so our hacker needs to find it
before trying to hack it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cameras, alarms and doors attached to the security server all have Device
Ratings of 3 and can be individually hacked or spoofed. Employee badges have
Device Ratings of 2. All are subscribed to the security server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secret file server containing the evidence is located in the records
room. It has no wireless interface at all, only a cable jack and a physical
terminal. It has the same stats as the Security server: all stats at 4 plus
Analyze 4. Its ice has Pilot 4, Black Hammer 4, and Armor 4, and is of course
illegal for the target to possess. It has only security and admin accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/30/hackaton-sr4-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/30/hackaton-sr4-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackaton: Cyberpunk 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/cp2020-cover.jpg&quot;
        alt=&quot;The cover of Cyberpunk 2020&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     I used to think this guy on the cover was so cool.
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this post, we’ll be using Cyberpunk 2020 Version 2.01, published in 1993 if
I understood the copyright notice correctly. The original edition of Cyberpunk
was from 1988. Cyberpunk 2020 came out in 1990, and this version only adds minor
corrections on top of that. I’m given to understand the rules themselves didn’t
change much from the original edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to own a physical copy of this corebook back when I was a teenager, so I
also get a bit of cozy nostalgia for looking at the PDF of it now, but I would
definitely not play it as written today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-overview&quot;&gt;Setting Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting’s global network is called the Net, or sometimes the NET in all
caps. I’ve heard claims that it doesn’t take inspiration from Neuromancer, but
the description I’m reading here leans as much into Neuromancer imagery as
Shadowrun’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacker characters are called Netrunners, and they use devices called cyberdecks
that range from the size of a desktop workstation to the size of a paperback
book, with a lot of plugs for neural interfaces and data lines but no built-in
keyboard or monitor. Decks all have the same starting stats, but smaller and
more portable models are more expensive. The most expensive deck is the only one
that has a built-in cellular modem. All the others need to jack into landlines
or directly into target devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most expensive decks are cheaper than a subcompact car, and they get much
more affordable if you give up that cellular modem. However netrunners are still
a specialized niche because Cyberpunk 2020 is a class-based system. Netrunner is
a specific class (or “Role”), and only they get the Interface skill that’s used
for hacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Shadowrun’s Matrix uses mainframes as the “backing” for its sci-fi chrome
flash, behind CP 2020’s flash is yet more flash with a dash of space magic. The
overall Net still works kinda like a phone grid, but the book works very hard to
make the reader see it as, effectively, a parallel dimension. Back in 2014 some
researchers effectively cast a spell over the telecom grid and turned it into a
“conceptual space” where each phone line and connected device is located in a
point analogous to its physical location. When you connect to the Net you form
an “ICON” (all caps) representing yourself at the point of entry, and accessing
other servers means making that ICON actually travel the distance between its
entry point and the destination. If you’re in Night City and your destination is
in Japan, there’s no way to reach it except hopping into a Long Distance Link
and flying over the entire Pacific Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are serious musings about how the “empty space” you fly over while
traversing these links is teeming with unindentified greeblies because every
computer is on the Net by simply being turned on. If it doesn’t have a
connection, it’s still on the Net, it’s just unreachable from the telecom
grid. Adding new connected systems “physically increases” the size of the Net,
and you could extend it to space by launching a server in a spaceship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics-overview&quot;&gt;Mechanics Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of talk about local and regional telecom grids, much like in
Shadowrun, and a big emphasis on paying your phone bill for your home landline
or cellular modem, because CP 2020 never loses an opportunity to joke about
militarized debt collection squads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reasons to run the Net are to provide support to a physical team, and
to recover data from a target server. We can surprisingly already see the image
of the netrunner who stays together with their team here and hacks a series of
remotely controlled devices, doing stuff like controlling robot cars or opening
doors without having to do a full run. However only some PCs will be able to do
this out of the gate, since they might not have the cash for that cellular
portable deck. Oh, and this is an 80s cell, so moving too fast will break your
link. No 5G for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who can, there’s a series of control programs designed for different
types of device. Anything that can be described as “computer controlled” can be
hacked this way if the PC has the appropriate program, since due to SPACE MAGIC,
everything computerized is automatically in the Net. There are also programs for
remaining hidden, getting past barriers, and attacking both other programs and
other people. Everyone is going to want these even if they’re using a desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The netrunner’s Interface class skill is required to run the Net at all, but is
not used for all netrunning tasks. Its main use is in combat against security
programs (IC, “ice”) or other netrunners. Due to the way the character creation
system works it also determines your starting money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of server you expect a netrunner to hack is called a Data Fortress. It
vaguely resembles a mainframe, but as the name implies it goes all in on the VR
Dungeon aesthetic, even harder than Shadowrun did. You’re not moving through an
abstract representation of a mainframe, you’re crawling an actual dungeon-like
structure drawn on a 10x10 square grid. It has walls, gates, and security
programs acting like wandering monsters, and memory banks that work like
treasure chests. They have CPUs that act like brains, and give them an INT score
and possibly skills that are useful both in its day-to-day operations and when
fighting netrunners.  A Fortress with an INT of 12 or higher (which requires 4
CPUs) is a sapient AI and has a personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security programs are drawn from the same master list as netrunner
programs. You place them like monsters in the dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-parameters&quot;&gt;Run Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly CP 2020 does not include sample characters, so we have to create
one. We’ll also need to create our target system, because the example there is a
bit too high level for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-netrunner-g0blin&quot;&gt;Our Netrunner: G0blin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So called because of his looks, he prefers to work from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/on-cyberpsychosis.html&quot;&gt;my Cyberware Capacity rules&lt;/a&gt; instead of Humanity, but that’s the only
tweak I did here. I lucked out on the starting stat and cash rolls and decided
to optimize my money by getting a desktop with expanded memory instead of a
portable deck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INT&lt;/strong&gt; 10 &lt;strong&gt;REF&lt;/strong&gt; 9 &lt;strong&gt;TECH&lt;/strong&gt; 7 &lt;strong&gt;LUCK&lt;/strong&gt; 6
&lt;strong&gt;EMP&lt;/strong&gt; 6  &lt;strong&gt;MA&lt;/strong&gt; 5  &lt;strong&gt;COOL&lt;/strong&gt; 4 &lt;strong&gt;BODY&lt;/strong&gt; 4
&lt;strong&gt;ATTR&lt;/strong&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cyberware Capacity&lt;/strong&gt;: 11/40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;career-skills&quot;&gt;Career Skills&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interface - 8&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Awareness/Notice - 5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic Tech - 4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Education - 3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System Knowledge - 4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CyberTech - 2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cyberdeck Design - 4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Composition - 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electronics - 4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming - 5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pickup-skills&quot;&gt;Pickup Skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handguns 6, Stealth 6, Persuasion 1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cyberware&quot;&gt;Cyberware&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neural Processor (1k, CC 6),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cybermodem Link (100, CC 1),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interface Plugs (200, CC 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;equipment&quot;&gt;Equipment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Desktop deck (20 MU, Speed 0, Data Wall 2, 6k)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Killer 6 (STR 6, 5 MU, 1480 eb),&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stealth (STR 4, 3 MU, 480)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wizard’s Book (STR 6, 2 MU, 400 eb)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Crystal Ball (STR 4, 1 MU, 140 eb)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Genie (STR 5, 1 MU, 150 eb)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-system&quot;&gt;Our System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackaton-cp2020-system.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By following the rules in the CP2020 core book, and with a little help from its
random generation system, I came up with the Data Fortress depicted above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the key to the numbers and symbols in the file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1: Watchdog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2: Bloodhound&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3: Stun&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4: Knockout&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M*: Financial File, where the money is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;M**: Grey Ops file, where the evidence is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Knockout was a originally a Hellhound, but I thought that might be a bit
excessive since the book keeps describing it as the scariest thing ever, only
employed by the richest and nastiest corporations. Still, there’s not much
difference for us, as one hit from the Knockout will still ensure a mission
failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-summary&quot;&gt;Run Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;G0blin arrived from the left side of the screen. The Watchdog next to the gate
spotted him when he got close despite the running Stealth program. He destroyed
it with one attack, and then proceeded to crack the gate. Inside, he first went
right to the remotes and got spotted by another Watchdog. As before, he won
initiative and destroyed it with one attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then he moved down, clipping through the CPU. He managed to stay hidden from
both the Bloodhound and the much more dangerous Stun, bushwhacking them with
sneak attacks. He examined the data stores there and drained the company’s
accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then he went into the little corner room for the final leg of the mission. The
Knockout program didn’t spot him at first, but also didn’t go down with the
sneak attack. They went to initiative, G0blin won, and finished the program
off. This left him free to finish the mission, as both the door and evidence
were right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The run succeeded and took a total of around 21 game turns and 32 minutes of
real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-analysis-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Run Analysis and Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this less enjoyable than Shadowrun’s system, I guess, but it’s mostly
because of me. I’m not a big fan of how this game views the Net, or of how much
a net run resembles a roguelike dungeon crawl. Nevertheless it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do wonder if the quick runtime might have been because this host was too
easy. How would it have gone if I used the Militech regional office that comes
as an example as my system for this run? Or maybe I got something wrong when
designing the fortress or running the session?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume I got things right and the physical team takes the same amount of
time from the SR1 post to do their part (50 minutes for a perfectly stealthy run
or 90 for one with a firefight). This means the hacker takes up anywhere from a
third to half the session. That’s still more than the theoretic “ideal” ratio of
25%, but perhaps it could be alleviated with a bit of proper scene management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as VR dungeon crawls go, CP 2020’s are much more like brutal raids than
Shadowrun’s careful sneaking missions. Non-combat programs add only their
Strength to the d10 roll, while attacks and defenses use the netrunner’s INT and
Interface skill as well. Attacks are also much more devastating, since most
programs have a Strength of less than 6, and that 1d6 damage Killer programs do
reduces Strength directly. Even if the target survives, it’s greatly weakened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if any of those anti-personnel programs had managed to act
and hit our runner, they’d instantly be put out of commission and the mission
would fail. That’s another way in which it resembles a roguelike: the key to
victory is to bump the monster before the monster bumps you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were several things that were unclear to me here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do detection rolls happen only once, or do they happen every turn? I went with
“every turn”, and this ended up making things more violent. Most ICE that
initially missed G0blin ended up spotting him on the second roll and forcing him
to enter combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you need control programs to operate those remote icons from a data fortress?
I went with “no” despite buying a couple of those for G0blin, because the
examples were all about netrunners controlling physical objects close to them
from meatspace. If I had went with “yes”, it would only have increased the
amount of turns the run took by a bit, since G0blin only tried to control these
remotes when all neighboring ICE had been killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also didn’t know what happened when a Watchdog spotted G0blin. Text said it
“alerts its owner”, but does that happen immediately or does the dog have to run
to where the owner is? I judged the program had to travel to the owner since the
setting places so much emphasis on the “physicality” of the Net. That would be
the terminal icon here in our map, but no dog ever made it there. If any had, we
might have seen an enemy netrunner here and the run would have perhaps been
harder.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/28/hackaton-cp2020.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/28/hackaton-cp2020.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackaton: Shadowrun 1st Edition Play Phase</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/sr1-cover.jpg&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-summary&quot;&gt;Run Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/10/26/hackaton-sr1-1.html&quot;&gt;deciding on the design parameters&lt;/a&gt; for our Shadowrun 1st Edition
Matrix run, I got my stopwatch and jumped right into it. I stopped it at the end
of every node to keep a running tally of the elapsed time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the system map we’re using, for reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackaton-sr1-system.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the account of events. As I mentioned before, the actual timed run was
written in a brief shorthand and the account below was expanded for readability
after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-1-san-red-3-trace-and-dump-4&quot;&gt;Node 1 (SAN): Red-3, Trace and Dump-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Decker enters through Node 1, dialing the mainframe’s modem. Security here
is unusually tight for a Shadowrun system - the target really doesn’t want
anyone sticking their noses in his business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t quite understood the rules here yet, thinking that you couldn’t use
your Hacking Pool outside of cybercombat for anything but improvising programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our decker arrives here at Sensor range, improvises Analyze-7 with her pool,
and runs that against the ICE, seeing that it’s a potentially dangerous
tracer. She moves into Contact range and I roll Initiative even though we’re not
in combat, just to have a sense of the flow of the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She runs Sleaze against the Tracer using only the program rating, beating the
ice but failing anyway because this is a Red node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that point on I learn that you can use Hacking Pool dice on any Computer or
program test even outside of combat, so I use some on the second attempt and
pass even though that has increased difficulty. Ice supressed, we get to whisper
“I’m in” into our comms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is where I realize there’s very little reason to be sparing with those
pool dice, and that I can use pool dice even for tests with improvised
programs. So my strategy for pretty much the rest of the run is to shout I AM
SPEED and drop my entire Hacking Pool on any test that doesn’t happen during
actual cybercombat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed so far: 1 turn, 13 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-2-spu-orange-5-access-6&quot;&gt;Node 2 (SPU): Orange-5, Access-6&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another beefy node, and our actual password prompt. Our Decker analyzes the Ice
like before, and this fails with a tie. I rule a tie doesn’t activate the
ICE. She decides not to try again and just tries Sleaze instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I AM SPEED gets us through this just fine - Sleaze works against everything, but
Deception would have worked here too. We can see two other nodes from this one,
but not what they are. I decide to flip a coin to see where we go next, and we
go right towards Node 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed so far: 2 turns, 28 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-3-spu-green-4-barrier-3&quot;&gt;Node 3: SPU, Green-4, Barrier-3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I arrive at my final interpretation for improvised
programs. Improvising them is part of the same action in which you run them, so
while this takes only 1 action total, the pool dice you use for the script
aren’t available for the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily Analyze’s rating doesn’t actually limit what it can discover, so we’re
better off improvising an Analyze-1 script and chucking our remaining 13 pool
dice into the test than going for Analyze-7 with 1 extra die. Having an actual
Analyze program would be even better, but this is pretty good still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our reckless Decker successfully analyzes the ICE and Sleazes past it using
the same actions and approach as before. I AM SPEED wins again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She sees there are two connected nodes, and it’s right here that I realize she’s
not actually in any danger at Sensor range and can back out after
reconnoitering. So Ms. Decker moves into Sensor range of the two connected nodes
in order to scout them all and see they’re an I/O Port and a Control node
without any ICE in them. She then decides to move on to Node 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 5 turns, 41 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-4-io-port-green-4&quot;&gt;Node 4: I/O Port, Green-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This node and Node 5 don’t actually have a security rating of their own, so I
gave them the same rating as the SPU that was linked to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We once again go with I AM SPEED, and our total of 21 dice easily takes care of
the system operation needed to disable the camera. Per the rules, after either
succeeding at a system operation or giving up after a number of failures, we
need to roll a d6. If the result is less than or equal to the number of
attempts, the system noticed something wrong and triggered an alert. We only had
one attempt before succeeding, and we roll a 3, so no alert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camera is off. First goal accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 6 turns, 47 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-5-control-green-4&quot;&gt;Node 5: Control, Green-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same deal as before, and same outcome. Alarm is off, second goal
accomplished. And we took less time because I already knew what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 7 turns, 50 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-6-spu-red-4-killer-4&quot;&gt;Node 6: SPU, Red-4, Killer-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have data to steal, so we go to the only unexplored path so far and try
to find data stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scouting the node, we follow your usual procedure of Improvised Analyze -&amp;gt;
close to Contact range -&amp;gt; Initiative -&amp;gt; Sleaze, always using our whole Hacking
Pool for each individual test. We suppress the ICE without issue. If you noticed
how reckless we’re being, take a cookie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further scouting reviews two data stores attached to this node. I flip another
coin to decide where to go, and we go down to Node 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 10 turns, 58 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-8-data-store-red-4-black-ice-5&quot;&gt;Node 8: Data Store, Red-4, Black Ice-5.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our usual Improvised Analyze routine shows us this data store is protected by
Black Ice! This is scary, but is also a very promising lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disregarding the danger, our Decker goes all in and chucks her whole Hacking
Pool into Sleaze again. She succeeds by exactly the needed amount and suppresses
the ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She then uses Browse to find any drainable accounts, because she doesn’t know
the full layout of the system like we do. The operation succeeds but she doesn’t
find anything. Boo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remembering the actual mission, she Browses for incriminating evidence and finds
it. She has enough disk space for the file, and no time pressure for the
download, so we just wait a couple more turns. Third objective accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She still wants to find that money, though, so she moves to the other data store
at Node 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 13 turns, 1 hour, 9 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-7-data-store-red-4-access-5&quot;&gt;Node 7: Data Store, Red-4, Access-5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same deal as usual. Improv Analyze reveals the ICE, Sleaze gets past it, Browse
confirms there’s nothing of value to the team in this node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is where I begin to notice that despite the different types of nodes and
the flowery descriptions of virtual dungeons, we’ve been performing more or less
the same sequence of tests in the same order, in a loop. So I guess a long
enough Matrix run might seem a bit boring for the decker as well. I’m still
having fun &lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;, because lucky rolls have given me a string of successes, but
I don’t feel like I’m in danger or having to make complex decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the only unexplored node left is the CPU. A cautious decker might decide
to cut their losses, perform the single remaining system operation they need,
and jack out. But we’ve already established our Decker is not cautious, SHE IS
SPEED!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total elapsed time: 14 turns, 1 hour, 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-9-cpu-red-5-trace-and-burn-6-black-ice-4&quot;&gt;Node 9: CPU, Red-5, Trace and Burn-6, Black Ice-4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup is a little unusual here. This CPU has all the standard system
operations available, and the Trace and Burn-6 is protecting those. It also has
a link to the target’s bank account, and draining it counts as a custom system
operation. There’s a piece of Black Ice protecting that operation only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Decker will have the run of the system if she neutralizes the Tracer, but
to get the money she must also get past the Black Ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She comes within Sensor Range, Improv-Analyzes both pieces of Ice, and sees what
they’re protecting. She decides to deal with the Tracer first. I roll Initiative
for everyone as she gets into Contact Range, but the ICE will only act if it
activates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the usual I AM SPEED approach giving us 19 dice to Sleaze past the
Tracer, the node’s high security level prevents us from succeeding. We try again
with increased difficulty, and this time a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; unlucky roll gives the ice
more successes, meaning it activates!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing Trace and Burn does upon activation is try to raise an Internal
Alert in the system. This causes the ratings of all ICE to increase by 50%, so
we’re actually dealing with Trace-and-Burn 9 now. The Black Ice also improves to
Rating 6, but it remains inactive since it’s only protecting the bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could have allocated dice from our Hacking Pool to an opposed test to “jam”
the ice and prevent the alert from going through… but we already used all of
them on the Sleaze attempt, and the pool hasn’t refreshed yet. This is why our
Decker has been very reckless so far, as every piece of ice she faced until now
could have done this on a failed test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its first actual action, Trace and Burn rolls its rating to determine how
long it will take to trace the Decker. We’re lucky here because this roll gets
only 1 success, meaning it will take a total of 10 of the IC’s actions to do
so. Once that time is up, though, her deck is toast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Decker switches to using the Attack program to destroy the Tracer before
that happens. This is proper cybercombat, which works a little differently. The
“to-hit” roll is an unopposed test with only with your Hacking Pool against the
Node’s security. The program’s rating is your base damage if you hit, and it
increases by 1 for every extra success past the minimum required to hit. Actual
damage is your net successes in an opposed test of the ICE’s rating versus your
damage pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I end up using my entire pool in the to-hit roll, since any less than that means
I won’t be beating the difficulty on average. It takes me 3 turns to destroy the
Tracer this way, but since everyone acts multiple times per turn I only had 3
actions left before the trace completed. This was still somewhat repetitive
since it was the same set of rolls every time, but it was also exciting since
this is the first time our Decker is in any actual danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the tracer gone, she uses a system operation to cancel the alert and
manages to Sleaze past the Black Ice and drain the target’s account. Bonus
objective completed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that done, she moves normally to the Control Modules and opens the final
door, completing the mission’s objective. She then jacks out. Mission Complete!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 19 turns, 2 hours and 4 minutes. This combat alone took 41
minutes to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-analysis-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Run Analysis and Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not gonna lie, I kinda feel like I completed an important life goal. I could
never understand this hacking system when I was 12, but now not only did I grok
it, I finished an entire Matrix run while using it. So I’m pretty happy, and I
had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I must also conclude that all the criticisms leveled at this system are
valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the intro, we’re assuming our physical team has an easy time
getting past the reception area. This would take some light roleplaying and a
roll or two from our talker. That plus walking to the restricted area might take
10 minutes of real time, but it takes the decker 50 minutes to complete the
goals that let them move forward from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next part of the physical mission will involve more tests and die rolls from
the physical team. The Decker takes around half an hour of real time to find the
electronic evidence, and it might be accurate to assume the physical team takes
about the same or a little bit longer to sneak past the guards and find the
physical documents. Let’s say 40 minutes for the physical team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the Decker decides to loot the server, and that takes 41 minutes. Unless
the physical team is having an epic shootout at the same time as they try to
leave the building, all they have to do is sit and wait. Otherwise they take
maybe 10 minutes total to reach the back door and walk out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a team that has a firefight on the way out might take up 90 minutes of real
time, and a team that doesn’t will take perhaps 50 with their part of the
mission. Our Decker is taking up &lt;em&gt;at best&lt;/em&gt; over half and at worst over
two-thirds of the session with her solo VR dungeon crawl. And this is all
assuming a 100% buttery smooth session with absolutely no digressions,
distractions, or rule arguments to make it longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also a point where I kinda felt that the decking run itself was
getting a little repetitive, because the “optimal” procedure to follow became
obvious: Improv Analyze -&amp;gt; Sleaze, always dumping the entire Hacking Pool into
each test. In actual cybercombat, I also ended up doing the same thing over and
over until the enemy died. It was still enjoyable, but I could see it eventually
overstaying its welcome even for the decker player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if it turns out that my rules interpretations were overly generous and
this was supposed to be way harder, then all the criticisms I made become even
stronger, because everything would take more time and more rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/27/hackaton-sr1-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/27/hackaton-sr1-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon: Shadowrun 1st Edition Design Phase</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/sr1-cover.jpg&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this run we’ll be using the original edition of Shadowrun, published
in 1989. I started with second edition, but that’s not a problem because I’m
equally unfamiliar with both edition’s hacking systems!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing and setting and even the rules of these two early editions give me a
sort of cozy nostalgic feeling when I read them, but these days I am well aware
of all their issues, mechanical and otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-overview&quot;&gt;Setting Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting’s global network is called the Matrix. Hackers are called Deckers
because they use &lt;em&gt;cyberdecks&lt;/em&gt;, devices the about the size of a full 104-key
keyboard that have cable jacks for connecting directly to the decker’s neural
interface and to either a computer terminal or a communications line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a cyberdeck to access the Matrix takes you to the full Gibsonian VR
Dungeon experience, where you zip through the infinite grid of the Matrix and
then crawl through the low-poly simulated environments of a server, treating its
security programs as monsters and its data as loot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beneath the chrome flash, we’re dealing with classic mainframes from the
Eighties. The Matrix isn’t the Internet, it’s the global phone grid. You access
your target mainframe by connecting to the phone grid yourself and dialing the
number of the mainframe’s modem. There are even rules for making long-distance
and international calls. Mainframe numbers are usually unlisted, but can be
found with diligent research by deckers or provided by whoever’s hiring them for
the run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cyberdeck is distinctly different from a mere “computer”, crammed full of
specialized electronics that allow it to be used for operating in VR and hacking
mainframes. Personal computers don’t do really do much other than letting you
store and view data files, and perhaps acting as dumb terminals to mainframes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberdecks cost a fortune! The one used by the sample starting characters in the
book costs more than a sports car. The most expensive one is about twice the
price of a fighter jet. And that’s just for the base hardware. If you want your
deck to be truly tubular, you’re probably going to spend around twice its base
price on software and optional extras. Deckers tend to be highly specialized at
character creation because they need to spend most of their points on money and
most of their money on a deck - there isn’t any “room” to be anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics-overview&quot;&gt;Mechanics Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mainframe is composed of a set of Nodes representing its different parts,
connected by Data Lines. The end result is a lot like a dungeon with rooms and
corridors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each node allows users to perform a different set of System Operations related
to its function. Authorized users can do this automatically. Our decker must
perform a Computer skill test to beat the node’s Security Rating, a color and
number combination that gives you both the difficulty of the roll and how many
successes you need. If you fail at performing a system operation, you might
trigger an alert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deckers can also run Utility Programs, which do things not listed in the system
operations menu. There are four program categories, and each has a slightly
different procedure that’s some variation of rolling the program rating against
the node’s security. Some programs degrade, losing effectiveness each time
they’re used. This resets when the decker jacks out. Failing at using a program
doesn’t raise an alert, but might trigger IC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is very concerned about how large programs are because there are rules
for loading them from disk to RAM and managing your free memory. Not having
enough RAM to run all you need at once is the quintessential 80s computing
experience after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Computer skill tests and Utility Programs can benefit from the decker’s
Hacking Pool, which is equal to the sum of their Computer Skill and Reaction
attribute, modified by stuff that increases Reaction. Like other dice pools in
this system, it refreshes at the start of every action. You can allocate dice
from it to benefit any Computer or Program tests while in the Matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use a program you don’t have, you can improvise a single-use
script version of it with your Hacking Pool. You can only improvise a degrading
program once per Matrix run, but if I understand the book correctly you can
improvise non-degrading programs multiple times. I’m interpreting the rules to
mean that an improvised program must be used in the same action, otherwise there
would be little reason to buy any programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most nodes are going to have some IC (Intrusion Countermeasures, “ice”) in
them. The mere presence of IC stops deckers from performing system operations or
moving past the node, and they must either destroy or fool the IC before they
can do these things. Most ice only triggers when it beats you in the opposed
test to fool it. If you beat it but fail to beat the node’s base security, they
remain inactive and still block your progress. Subsequent attempts are harder,
increasing your chances of triggering the ice. Attacking IC directly also
triggers it, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White ice is completely passive. It tries to raise an alarm but you can block it
with your Hacking Pool. Grey ice additionally tries to trace you or attack your
deck. Black Ice attacks the &lt;em&gt;decker&lt;/em&gt; directly, and might kill them. There’s a
little bestiary of different types within each category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matrix turns happen at the same speed as physical combat turns, using the same
initiative rules. Both types of turn last around 3 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-parameters&quot;&gt;Run Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Shadowrun 1st Edition version of our run, our decker is going to be
remote, and we will assume the team discovered the mainframe’s unlisted phone
number during their prep phase. I’m going to take a couple of shortcuts here
because those are available to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our decker, we’ll be using the &lt;strong&gt;Decker Archetype&lt;/strong&gt; from the SR1
corebook. She has Computer 6, the Fuchi-4 deck with a decent spread of mods and
programs, and a hacking pool of 15. I’m going to cheat a little bit and replace
her Deception 4 utility with Sleaze 4, because from what I understood of the
system there is no reason to ever take Deception when you can take Sleaze
instead. Let’s assume she has one run under her belt and used the payout from
that to upgrade her software a bit. Even with Sleaze’s larger size she can still
fit all her programs in RAM at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackaton-sr1-system.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our target system, we’ll be using the one from page 55 of the &lt;strong&gt;Mercurial&lt;/strong&gt;
adventure. Here’s a list of the ICE present in the system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 1: Trace and Dump-4.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 2 Access-6.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 3: Barrier-3.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 4: no ICE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 5: no ICE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 6: Killer-4.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 7: Access-5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 8: Black Ice-5.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 9: Trace and Burn-6, Black Ice-4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Node 4 will be connected to our security camera, Node 5 to the alarm and
door. Node 8 will contain the evidence we seek, and the CPU at Node 9 is where
we can drain their accounts because that’s how it is in the original
adventure. The other data store at Node 7 has nothing of value to our runners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/26/hackaton-sr1-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/26/hackaton-sr1-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon, part 00: Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackers-cast.jpg&quot;
       alt=&quot;The protagonists of the 1995 movie Hackers.&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Getting ready to hack the Gibson.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently got into a forum discussion about hacking in cyberpunk tabletop RPGs,
as one does. This one was mostly centered around Shadowrun, and it touched on a
lot of the reasons why one might want to &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html&quot;&gt;play without a hacker PC&lt;/a&gt; even when
you want to feature hacking in your game. It also got a bit into edition
arguments, as it often does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowrun’s problems are more or less universal to the genre, as mentioned in
the other post linked above. The first three editions go heavy into the whole
Gibsonian VR Dungeon aesthetic and suffer from the classic problems from that
approach. It’s also very inspired by how 80s mainframes worked, and rules aside
it all made so much more sense to me once I realized that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth has something that visually resembles Ghost in the Shell or Cyberpunk
2077, where the hacker follows along with the group and hacks a series of
smaller devices using an augmented reality interface. My recollection is that
this is supposed to be faster, but the discussion in question had people
complaining it wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk-the-game is similar, with CP 2020 going in fully for VR dungeons, and
CP RED going in for smaller localized servers that are also supposed to only
take a small series of rolls to solve instead of an hours-long minigame. They’re
are much less inspired by reality than Shadowrun’s (though this is of course not
a knock on them, merely an observation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also more recent games that try to either capture the nostalgic feel
of old-school cyberpunk or to express the same themes in a more modern way. I’m
thinking of Neon City Overdrive and Hard Wired Island, respectively. I’m not
very familiar with them yet but I intend to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you have GURPS, which has a few hacking systems of its own depending on
which genre you’re talking about. The ones I’m interested in are the one from
Pyramid #3/21, which emulates classic cyberdecks-and-mainframes hacking but
could also work for GitS-style shenanigans, and the more streamlined one from
GURPS Action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I kinda want to see if they all match the memories and impressions I have of
them. Let’s try them all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hackathon-scenario-and-rules&quot;&gt;Hackathon Scenario and Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture a team of flawed but stylish urban mercenaries composed of a hacker, a
sneaky talker, and a pair of sneaky bruisers. They’re on a mission to take down
a corrupt and racist businessman, and they learned a company he owns stores the
sort of evidence that can’t be ignored by the government: proof of rampant
embezzling and tax evasion, in both digital and hardcopy forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mercenaries are going to infiltrate a small, single-office company, one of
the many owned by the target. It does do legitimate business but also serves as
a “stash” for records about the target’s illegal activities. Secret ledgers,
blackmail material, and so on. Some of this lives in the company’s computer
system, some of it is stored in hardcopy in a “records room” whose access is
restricted to normal employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employees and other authorized personnel can wander the legitimate business area
of the office freely, but the “records room” can only be accessed by a small
group of people who work directly for the target and drop by occasionally to use
it. There’s a back entrance with an electronic lock so that these lieutenants
can get in and out outside of business hours and/or without bringing too much
employee attention to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The records room is watched by a camera and protected by an alarm that triggers
if a stranger or even a normal employee tries to get close to it. There’s a
small guard shift here during the day which increases at night. The guards know
who the lieutenants are, and their duties involve keeping everyone else away
from the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The office’s computer system will be different in every game. In all of them
it’s supposed to be small but with tighter than expected security, because of
what it hides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team’s mission is to infiltrate this office, steal all the evidence, and if
possible drain the company’s accounts on the way out, because at the end of the
day ya still gotta eat, chummer. Here’s how things are supposed to go, with a
greater focus on the hacker’s part since this is what I’m interested in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the team enters the building disguised as a maintenance crew. We’ll
assume this part succeeds, giving them limited freedom of movement inside the
office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next they must enter the records room. For them to be able to do this, the
hacker must turn off a security camera and an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the previous step succeeds, the hacker must locate and steal the target data
from the office’s computer system. Technically, the best strategy would be to
steal the evidence first and only then drain the accounts, but our hacker will
do things in the order in which they run into the corresponding locations. The
lure of money is strong when the account is right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the hacker must unlock the back door so the team can leave. Ideally
they will do so quietly and with no one the wiser, but this could happen in the
middle of a firefight. Possibly one caused by the hacker triggering an alert in
the computer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each of the following systems, I’m going to stat up a hacker character and a
computer system that conforms to that game’s paradigm and rules. And then I’ll
roll through the target session while timing how long it takes me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 1st Edition&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk 2020&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 4th Edition, 20th Anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk RED&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 5th Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neon City Overdrive&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hard Wired Island&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GURPS Action with the Pyramid #3/21 system, both in “classic” and “modern”
modes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GURPS Action with its own system. Not sure this can accommodate the scenario,
but we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using this particular list because those are the books I happen to own at
present. I’m not sure if I want to spend money to acquire the hacking systems
used in Shadowrun 2nd and 3rd Edition, though I do remember they are notably
different from SR1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hacker and their equipment will be at roughly starting character level for
each game, possibly with a slight tweak or two, and the challenges faced should
be challenging but not impossible for the hacker. Whether the target devices are
separate or part of the same single “target system”, and whether the hacker is
even with the physical team, will depend on the system in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have more practical experience with some of these systems than with others,
but I will be studying all of them to ensure I do each run “right”. Preliminary
study doesn’t count towards the timed session, but consultations that happen
during the actual run &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;, because I’ve never been in a session where people
didn’t have to consult the books for something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be writing a lot of stuff down during the actual run, but I’ll try to be as
brief as possible there. It’s still going to take a bit more time than doing it
verbally, but I think it evens out because there will be no table talk or extra
player questions getting in the way. I’ll write wordier summaries after the run
is done, and these are the ones that will see publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All rolls will be made on Orokos, but I’m not going to save them and will just
report the results in the article.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/hackaton-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/hackaton-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Evernight, part 02</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post concerns itself with specific landmarks in Evernight. A lot of them
are “coterminous” with Neverwinter landmarks, occupying the corresponding
location in space and having the exact same boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;black-mound&quot;&gt;Black Mound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The district of &lt;strong&gt;Black Mound&lt;/strong&gt; is named that because of the hill that dominates
it. It’s coterminous with the Protector’s Enclave in Neverwinter. The houses and
manors here are larger than in the rest of Evernight, but just as
dilapidated. Undead are not known for their tidiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the city’s relevant landmarks are here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;house-of-screams&quot;&gt;House of Screams&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Located in the same spot as Neverwinter’s Hall of Justice, the House of Screams
is the oldest manor in the city and the closest thing Evernight has to a
courthouse or city hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tribunal holds court in the upper levels. When it’s time to adjudicate a
dispute, they slam iron portcullises over all exits until the session is done,
because as mentioned in the previous post the ghouls eat the losers. They do
find vampires to be a particular pain in the neck to deal with, as they can
transform into mist and fly through the grates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The House’s wide open cellar works as an arena where citizens can work out their
problems without getting the Tribunal involved. There’s usually some bored
ghouls, wights and vampires hanging around hoping to watch a fight or three, and
they will gladly act as witnesses to confirm that the few rules of engagement
were obeyed by both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;temple-of-filth&quot;&gt;Temple of Filth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with the House of Knowledge in Neverweinter, the Temple of Filth
used to be dedicated to Bhaal and Myrkul, ancient gods of murder and death who
died during the switch-over from AD&amp;amp;D 1e to AD&amp;amp;D 2e. Now it’s dedicated to Orcus
and Dorensain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the temple’s decorations, including its altar and holy symbols, are built
from corpses and corpse bits. No special care is taken to &lt;em&gt;preserve&lt;/em&gt; these
bits. They’re just replaced with new ones when they rot away. Ewwww.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The undead of Evernight sometimes ask the priests here to resolve their
disputes, because they tend to demand services from both parties instead of
eating one of them like the Tribunal does. The temple’s chief priest is
Ursuntos, whose stats are those of an Adept of Orcus (Level 6 Controller, from
the MM3). He has a bunch of ghoul and vampire underlings, and his political
power in the city is second only to the Tribunal’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grounds of the Temple are considered both defiled and necrotic ground as per
the DMG2. Very cursed, but surprisingly not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; as cursed as the Dread Ring,
which has additional effects on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pool-of-daylight&quot;&gt;Pool of Daylight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep within the temple, behind a bunch of locked doors, traps and magical
darkness areas, is a literal pool of radiance (is this a name drop?) that shines
as bright as the world’s mid-day sun. Any undead entering its chamber suffers
terrible pain, and touching the pool can actually destroy the weaker among
them. This is here as the ultimate security measure, for the pool is said to
hide an artifact at its bottom that works as a weapon of mass destruction
against undead. The Temple doesn’t want anyone else getting a hold of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good thing living PCs don’t need to fear the light, huh? This could be just the
thing to use against those pesky Thayans and Shadovar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-graveyard&quot;&gt;The Graveyard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight’s Graveyard occupies the same area as the pauper section of
Neverwinter’s own graveyard. Despite the name, and despite being absolutely
filled with crypts and tombs and graves, from the point of view of the city’s
ghouls this place is a &lt;em&gt;restaurant&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, when an Evernight ghoul catches a living “tourist”, they don’t eat
right away. Instead, they take the paralyzed victim to a place called Lamantha’s
Mortuary, where the resident necromancer will inject them with longer-term
paralytics. Then the ghoul arranges for a “funeral procession” for the
still-living victim, who is buried alive in the Graveyard. Only after the victim
has died and “ripened” a bit does the ghoul crack open the coffin and eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;corpse-market&quot;&gt;Corpse Market&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with the “rich” section of Neverdeath in the world, this is exactly
what it says on the tin. A market where undead merchants sell meals to undead
customers who are too busy to catch their own. From preserved blood for vampires
to assorted corpse bits for ghouls to necromantic supplies, you can find all of
that here for affordable prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the place to go if you want to hire undead labor. Renting a zombie
laborer costs 10gp per day and requires leaving a chunk of your flesh as
collateral. The chunk is alchemically preserved, so it stays fresh and can be
reattached later. While it’s missing, you lose a healing surge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might also be able to hire undead guides for about 100gp per day. Some of
these guides might be able to smell specific “flavors” of death from a long
distance away, so they might be useful to an Uthgardt Barbarian who wants to
find their tribe’s missing thunderbeast skeleton, or to PCs looking for
Gauntlgrym. Undead guides charge a premium for going into particularly dangerous
places, refuse to fight for their clients and might in fact run away if a fight
breaks out. Other than that, though, they’re reliable as long as they’re getting
paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creepy old man known as the Resurrectionist wanders the Market every day,
looking for a piece of someone specific he wishes to bring back to life. He
never finds the right one, so he keeps coming back to continue searching. He’s
been at this long enough that most standard resurrection magic wouldn’t work any
more, but the man guarantees he can bring anyone back no matter how long it’s
been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a fenced off area here that contains warehouses and some of the
merchant’s residences. While anyone can walk through the market, unauthorized
people caught in this area are assumed to be prowling thieves and are killed on
sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dark-creeper-enclave&quot;&gt;Dark Creeper Enclave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This large manor close to the Graveyard is the Netherese consulate on
Evernight. The Netherese pay a family of Dark Ones, the Glumguts, to mind the
place. They don’t have any official authority - their job is to maintain the
house, serve any actual dignitaries in the rare occasions they stay here, and
receive any packages dropped off at the embassy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family members like to supplement their income with the occasional spot of
burglary or robbery, though they are careful to restrict their activities to
the living (who can do less about it). They also only target Thayans if they can
get one of them alone, to avoid reprisals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a proper gothic family too: their patriarch Blackclaw, a dark stalker
(level 10 lurker), rules them through fear. The only ones who have the courage
to defy him are his young cousins Thrax and Vinnia, and his son Blackcut. The
trio believes they’re protected by Blackcut’s relation to his father, and free
to do whatever they want. The truth is Blackclaw simply doesn’t know most of
what they’ve been up to, and will be livid when he finds out. Their shenanigans
have actually been quite detrimental to the family’s duties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thayan-outpost&quot;&gt;Thayan Outpost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Thayans are based out of a warehouse near one of the city’s haunted piers in
the Black Mound. They have a permanent garrison here commanded by Katrice Ansar
(stats as a human hexer from the MM2, Level 7 Controller). She’s convinced they
are being watched by Shadovar spies besides the obvious dark creepers, but has
yet to find them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near the warehouse, in an abandoned neighborhood, is an iron gate that acts as a
“dusk crevice” linked to Neverdeath cemetery. It’s guarded around the clock by a
unit that includes undead loyal to the Thayans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;locations-outside-black-mound&quot;&gt;Locations Outside Black Mound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only three of these described here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lamanthas-mortuary&quot;&gt;Lamantha’s Mortuary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentioned above in the Graveyard description, this is run by a living human
necromancer named Lamantha who works as a mortician and taxidermist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of her main jobs is preparing mortal victims for burial in the Graveyard,
which she does by injecting them with long-term paralytic drugs and dressing
them up. She can also disguise undead so they look like living people through
wardrobe and makeup adjustments, and she can turn bodies or bits of bodies into
trophies and tools (or &lt;em&gt;sporting equipment&lt;/em&gt;, as the book makes sure to mention).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since she provides valuable services, the rulers of Evernight gave Lamantha
citizenship and allow her conduct her research in peace. Only the necromancer
herself knows its precise nature - it’s something to do with observing the
nature of growth and change among undead. Maybe she’s a necro-sociologist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being completely amoral and quite unhinged, Lamantha is happy to receive
living visitors and get the latest gossip from the middle world. PCs who are
polite to her might be able to use the mortuary as a safe place to rest for a
couple of days, though she will become impatient with them if they overstay
their welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-demon-pit&quot;&gt;The Demon Pit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with Neverwinter’s Chasm, this opened up at the same time, though it
did not disrupt “life” in the cursed undead city nearly as much as it did on the
living one. Like in Neverwinter, the average civilian does not know why this
rift opened up, nor what’s down there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight’s inhabitants call their rift the Demon Pit because rumor has it that
it goes all the way down to Dorensain’s kingdom in the Abyss. No one tried to
explore it, but they sometimes throw living mortals into the Pit as sacrifices
to Orcus and Dorensain. That’s more of a folk ritual than established Temple
practice, mind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Temple of Filth, this area counts as both defiled and necrotic ground,
and is still not as cursed as the Dread Ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;castle-nowhere&quot;&gt;Castle Nowhere&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coterminous with Castle Never. It looks much more intact and much creepier than
its worldly counterpart, and not even the most ancient of Evernight’s undead
citizens can tell when it was built. Like a few other places we’ve seen in
previous posts, Castle Nowhere only exists &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt;, vanishing and appearing
in a ten-day cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one in Evernight knows much about what goes on inside the castle. They avoid
going in because, get this, they think it’s haunted. This is hilarious, but it
also makes you wonder what kind of haunting would scare an undead city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the legends about the place say that if you’re inside the castle when it
vanishes, you don’t come back when it does. Others say that the ghosts inside it
feed on &lt;em&gt;the hunger of others&lt;/em&gt;. This means they can cause the living to starve
to death, but they can also cause a ghoul or vampire to become trapped in a
state of eternal starvation and use them as permanent food sources. A fate worse
than a second death!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a box here with a power you can add to any incorporeal undead creature
to make it into a ghost of Castle Nowhere. &lt;strong&gt;Consume&lt;/strong&gt; is a melee attack vs. AC
that removes the target from play and inflicts 10 ongoing damage (save
ends both). The target reappears adjacent to the monster when they make their
save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living creatures reduced to 0 HP by this reappear normally and become immune to
the power for the rest of the encounter. They make death saves and can be healed
as normal. Undead reduced to 0 HP do not die, and remain trapped until willingly
released by the ghost, or until the ghost is destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a proper creepy city, yes indeed. There’s more than enough material to
fuel a whole horror-themed campaign, though I suspect most typical groups who
are focused on other stories wouldn’t want to linger here too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, there are good reasons to visit the place. That artifact hidden in the
Pool of Radiance would be extremely useful to wreck the Thayans, for example,
and if the PCs want to follow the Shadowfell Road to their home base they would
also need to start at the Thayan outpost in Evernight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castle Nowhere would make an awesome dungeon, but as written there’s barely any
reason for PCs to enter the place. Perhaps they could use it to lure and trap a
powerful undead foe like Valindra, or maybe the quickest way to access the Tomb
of the Nine is by entering Castle Nowhere and crossing to the world through a
dusk crevice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/neverwinter-evernight-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/neverwinter-evernight-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Cyberpsychosis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a number of tropes that are specific to Cyberpunk-the-game&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but
which many people end up thinking are integral to cyberpunk-the-genre. And
“cyberpsychosis” is the one that annoys me the most by far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpsychosis is Cyberpunk’s term for the general concept that cybernetic
implants make you less human. This concept made the way into the game because
its author Mike Pondsmith used the AD Police anime as one of his sources of
inspiration, and the anime goes heavily into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably already know how it works in the game, but here’s a refresher:
characters have an Empathy stat that determines how well they relate to other
people. This gives them a Humanity score that’s equal to Empathy x 10. Each
implant has a “Humanity cost” that gets deducted from that score when installed,
and for every 10 points of Humanity you lose you also lose 1 Empathy. This makes
it harder to succeed at social tasks. When both Humanity and Empathy reach 0,
you become a “cyberpsycho” and an NPC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with the &lt;em&gt;mechanical&lt;/em&gt; purpose of these rules, which is to limit how much
cyberware a character can have. But this is heavily entangled with the “this
stuff makes you less human” story concept, from the terms used to the in-fiction
justification to the setting elements built around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk 2020 was particularly bad about this. Cyberpunk RED is much better
about it due to thirty years of progress in popular thinking about mental
health, but I still have issues with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-which-i-talk-about-my-issues&quot;&gt;In Which I Talk About My Issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CP RED, Humanity loss is more or less equated with psychological trauma. You
can lose Humanity by experiencing traumatic events, and modifications that are
purely cosmetic or therapeutic in nature don’t cost Humanity. Therapy helps you
recover and restores your Humanity. And I’m happy to report it’s “merely”
difficult and expensive instead of the sinister tracker-injecting conspiracy it
was in CP 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the mechanics remain exactly the same as before for cyberware that has
game benefits. The explanation given is that the act of “going beyond the human
baseline” is traumatic. Cyberpsychosis is the dissociative disorder you get when
you do it too much, and makes you start seeing yourself and others as
collections of replaceable parts instead of living, thinking beings. You can use
therapy to partially recover the Humanity lost to cyberware, but to recover
those final points, you need to get rid of the implants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of “human baseline” isn’t examined very deeply here. You know it
when you see it, and your Empathy reduces when you move away from it. It’s the
act of implantation that causes harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feels really backward to me, because a theme I often see in literature or
media I like is that cybernetic implants are more like the &lt;em&gt;scars&lt;/em&gt; of trauma
than its &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Molly Millions from Neuromancer has implanted mirrorshades because her traumatic
past made her wary of opening herself up emotionally. The windows to her soul
are shuttered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burton and his ex-Haptic Recon buddies from The Peripheral have a number of
twitchy combat implants that mostly serve as symbols for the PTSD they got from
their time at war. Flynne, one of the main protagonists, has similar
psychological scars from her time playing realistic military simulations for
money, but she has no implants because her trauma comes through in her viewpoint
narration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Martinez from Edgerunners was already a reckless putz with a hero
complex&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; before getting his first implant. Each one he has installed is
either a reminder of someone he feels he failed to protect, or a reflection of
his desire to be strong enough to protect those who are left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard it said that someone who gets an implanted gun or blade is declaring
themselves the kind of person who needs to be ready to kill someone at all
times, and that erodes their humanity. But isn’t “feels the need to be ready to
fight and kill at all times” a common trait to all Cyberpunk PCs, chromed or
not? It’s a lot easier to find a PC with no implants than one with no weapons,
armor, or combat skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t really matter whether your gun is inside your coat or inside your
arm. And since I don’t think a Cyberpunk character should lose Humanity for
carrying a conventional gun, they also shouldn’t lose it for carrying an
implanted one&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-id-do-instead&quot;&gt;What I’d Do Instead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said above, I still agree that there must be some sort of rule limiting
the amount of cyberware Cyberpunk PCs can get. A lot of it gives powerful
abilities and you don’t want them to be able to install the whole catalog at
once. That would make the game less fun in a variety of ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to base it on some stat other than Empathy, though, and I’m going to pick
Body for that. I find it much easier to imagine that cyberware has concrete
impacts on your body than on your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this new rule, your maximum Cyberware Capacity (CC) is your natural Body
x 10. “Natural” here means the base stat value before any modifications from
cyberware. Cyberware’s “humanity loss” stat now represents its “capacity cost”
instead. Your current Cyberware Capacity is the cost of all your implants added
together. This represents both minor health issues caused by the implant’s
presence and the increased need for maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you exceed your maximum Cyberware Capacity, you die. The good news is there
are no other game penalties until you get to that point. Note that medical exams
to measure your CC values are standard pre-op procedures even at mall clinics.
No ethical ripperdoc will ever agree to perform an operation that would kill the
patient. Not all of them are ethical, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Body-scultping (including full gender transition), medical-grade replacements,
and cosmetic mods continue to have zero cost&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The implants involved in all
of these processes are designed to be minimally invasive and to require
near-zero maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cyberware-maintenance-optional&quot;&gt;Cyberware Maintenance (Optional)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GMs who wish to make a commentary on the cruelty of capitalism might institute
this optional rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it’s in effect, you need to pay a monthly cyberware maintenance cost equal
to your current CC x 10eb. This represents anything from periodic check-ups and
implant cleaning to a regime of targeted immunosuppressors at the high end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you skip a month, your current CC increases by 1d6. If you’re also living
under harsh and unsanitary conditions during that time, such as from being lost
in the desert or having to sleep in the gutter, it increases by 2d6 instead. If
it goes over your maximum, you die as above. And yeah, this extra CC also
increases your maintenance costs next month. Field-expedient maintenance and a
Medicine roll might reduce the increase from 2d6 to 1d6, at the GM’s discretion,
but there’s no reducing it to zero without making that monthly payment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excess CC from neglected maintenance can be removed through treatments that cost
and work the same as the psychological therapies from page 229 of the core book:
500eb (or 100eb and a DV15 Medicine roll) to restore 2d6, and 1000eb (or 500eb
and a DV17 Medicine roll) to restore 4d6. These consist of extensive drug
courses, therapeutic surgery, and physical rehabilitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a further optional rule, the GM could also use these stats for “tune-up”
treatments to reduce Cyberware Capacity to the minimum values described in the
book: 2 per piece of cyberware, 4 per piece of borgware. Gotta spend money to
save money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-humanity&quot;&gt;What About Humanity?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathy and Humanity continue to exist in a game where Cyberware Capacity rules
are in play. Since we’re renaming things anyway, let’s rename Humanity to
Stability because suffering from mental trauma doesn’t make you less human
either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can still suffer Stability and Empathy loss when you suffer actual mental
trauma, as described in the CP RED core book. The same therapy options are still
available and they can help you as described there. Reaching 0 EMP will cause a
breakdown that will leave the character unplayable until they can recover, but
this will not necessarily be violent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one case where cyberware still causes Stability loss is when a victim is
&lt;em&gt;forcibly implanted&lt;/em&gt;. The Maelstrom gang in CP 2077 loves doing that to random
civilians, and it definitely qualifies as a traumatic experience. In that case,
recovering from the trauma follows all standard core book rules, including the
one where you need to remove the offending implants for a complete recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-cyberpsychosis&quot;&gt;What About Cyberpsychosis?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again we follow CP 2077’s example here. Cyberpsychosis is a myth, a label
without any science behind it that gets thrown around by corps and media as an
easy explanation for a number of tragedies. Corporate strike team shoots an
activist, well, that was a cyberpsycho who had it coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can have real mental breakdowns, and these can get ugly when the victim
has a predisposition towards violence and a few combat implants and/or some
weapons on hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, violent breakdowns are never &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; by implants. They’re always a
consequence of the inherently traumatic nature of life in the shit future of
Cyberpunk. I bet a lot of “cyberpsychos” turn out to have very few or even no
implants. Just easy access to guns and no access to mental healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The original edition was named “Cyberpunk”, and it was followed by
Cyberpunk 2020 and Cyberpunk RED, with a couple of extra editions that were
considered “non-canon” between those last two. If I capitalize the word I’m
talking about this game line. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A condition also known as “Shonen Protagonist Syndrome”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A game where owning a weapon brings you closer to becoming a monster is a
perfectly valid concept, but if that’s what you want to play you’re better
off moving away from action-oriented systems like Cyberpunk RED. I suggest
Wanderhome, which does implement that very concept in one of its archetypes
and is otherwise a non-violent game. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This also applies to stuff that has no &lt;em&gt;tangible&lt;/em&gt; game benefits but still
causes Humanity Loss in the core book, like the “sex booster” implants or
the color shift cybereye option (which is purely cosmetic like shift-tacts
but costs Humanity in the book). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/on-cyberpsychosis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/on-cyberpsychosis.html</guid>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Evernight Overview</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Evernight is Neverwinter’s reflection on the Shadowfell, but it’s also a city in
its own right, inhabited by a large number of undead and undead-adjacent people
(cultists, necromancers, and the like). This book doesn’t go too deep into its
history, but it does give me the impression Evernight has existed for a long
time. It was probably described in a previous edition when the Shadowfell was
called “the plane of Shadow”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight is ruled by a Tribunal composed by its most influent citizens, all of
whom are ghouls and ghasts who worship Orcus and his exarch Dorensain. The
Tribunal makes the laws and settles disputes. It does the latter by deciding who
is right and eating the loser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is very dangerous for living mortals who aren’t citizens, though it’s a
bit &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; dangerous than you’d think. Only its vampire and ghoul inhabitants
feel the need to feed on the living, and since the ambient energies of the
Shadowfell help sustain them this happens much less often than it would in the
world. Mortals and undead alike can apply for citizenship. Mortal citizens gain
legal protection from random attacks on the street, though they should probably
keep their token of citizenship within easy reach at all times. Living merchants
who pass through the city on the way to other locations can also acquire tokens
of safe passage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legal status of a mortal who doesn’t have any of that can best be summed up
as “fresh meat”, but even that isn’t an automatic death sentence. Undead who see
the living brazenly walking down the streets of Evernight tend to assume they
belong there, and will only challenge that assumption if given reason to be
suspicious. Such as when the “tourists” make horrified faces at the deeply
fucked up stuff that happens in the city’s routine unlife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no official portals between Evernight and Neverwinter, but the planar
membrane separating the two is awfully thin and becomes fully permeable in
certain places known as “dusk crevices”. These crossings link a place in
Evernight to its corresponding worldly location, which is always in dim light or
darkness. Some are fixed, some temporary or mobile. They’re the true cause of
most spooky stories about disappearances in Neverwinter since before the
Spellplague. Mortals who fall through these crevices into Evernight make up a
significant portion of the diet of its ghoul and vampire population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its (literally!) ghoulish culture and society, Evernight is a major
Shadowfell trade hub, so it often sees passing caravans that link it to other
settlements in the plane. One of the trade routes passing through here is the
Shadowfell Road, a mystical path that has a ritual component. It only exists if
approached and traversed in a very specific way. The Thayans use it to supply
the Dread Ring, and the Tribunal allows them to use it for that purpose because
the Thayans pay them in &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;. A similar arrangement allows the Netherese to
maintain an embassy in the city and use their own share of trade and supply
routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason the Tribunal accepts these deals is that both factions
represent powerful nations who are very adept at necromancy, but the ghouls
still draw the line at permitting hostilities within city limits. Evernight is
neutral territory, and violating this edict is one of the things that would
cause the Tribunal to take drastic action against the rule-breaker. In practice
that means conflict within the city takes the form of sordid spy stories of
intrigue and assassination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city did suffer some changes during the cataclysm. A reflection of the
Chasm, known locally as the Demon Pit, opened up in the corresponding Shadowfell
coordinates. And while the eruption of mount Hotenow was a quick affair in the
world, its shadowy counterpart continues to expel a slow and steady stream of
lava that flows through the equivalent of the Neverwinter River’s bed. Sometimes
you can see crew-less ghost ships sailing the lava, docking in abandoned piers,
and leaving after a few days. All of the other horrific stuff we’ll see in the
following posts was already there before that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evernight comes as a bit of a surprise to me, since I think it was only
mentioned in one place in the book before this section and that mention didn’t
hint at the full scope of the thing. I’m guessing old FR hands already know all
about it, though.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/neverwinter-evernight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/23/neverwinter-evernight.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Gauntlgrym, Part 02</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here we cover the lower strata of Gauntlgrym, where the place’s greatest dangers
live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-mines&quot;&gt;Duergar Mines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duergar of Gauntlgrym live in this sector, which lies deeper than most of
Gauntlgrym. The book says they’ve been here for “a few generations”, which is a
lot longer than I thought before even if these are human generations. Their
situation, however, still matches: they’ve taken over old mining tunnels and dug
new ones under the direction of their leader Kholzourl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ve unearthed several veins of useful metal, including iron, silver, mithral
and hellthorn (the one that likes infernal enchantments). Their work is
ceaseless, grueling, and mostly done by slaves, which they replenish by
capturing any non-duergar they lay eyes on down here. Tunnels built by the
original dwarves show their characteristic sloped walls and tend to be both safe
and clean. Duergar tunnels are slapdash and hazardous, sometimes nearly vertical
due to their leader’s need to go ever deeper. Some of these shafts are so deep
that they contain semi-permanent work camps where duergar and enslaved workers
live instead of going back to the city at the end of every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duergar don’t care about the big mithral gates. They got here from below,
via tunnels that link their camps to the deep Underdark. Some of these tunnels
have since been taken over by plaguechanged mind flayers, which are as much a
cause of injury and death as the work itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the mines is also a temple to Asmodeus built from desecrated
material taken from the Iron Tabernacle, which Kholzourl uses to commune with
his god and summon the occasional devil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And why exactly are the duergar so intent on digging ever deeper? Only Kholzourl
and the GM really now. The book gives us several possible reasons - GMs can
either pick one or use them as inspiration for a bespoke sinister plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hellthorn comes from a meteorite that fell here in primeval times, and the
main body of the thing contains far more power than the mere shards that have
been found so far. Maybe it contains an alien diabolic entity, millions of
years old, waiting for the moment when it is found and awakened.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The duergar want to drain the magma from Maegera’s resting place and transport
her slumbering form to some place where she can wake up and destroy an enemy
of Asmodeus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mining is just a cover and their actual goal is to observe the mind
flayers and track down their aboleth masters. The duergar suspect they want to
open a permanent portal to the Far Realm and want to hijack the procedure so
the portal leads to Hell instead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Or maybe the interaction of all the different types of bad magic that bathe
this region (infernal, aberrant, necromantic, oh my!) has created something
terrible underground that they wish to claim for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fiery-pit&quot;&gt;The Fiery Pit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lowest halls of Gauntlgrym are occupied by this enormous lake of magma, at
the center of which spins a white-hot whirlpool that marks Maegera’s resting
place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prison devised by the ancient mages if Illusk used bound water elementals
fed by a continuous stream of sea water pumped here by magical means. The system
could only be turned off by a true heir of Delzoun. The cataclysm happened when
Valindra found one to pull the lever, causing Maegera to nearly awaken. Drizzt
and his buddies prevented a full awakening back then, but the partial one was
still enough to ruin Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately one of the channels had been destroyed, and so was not reactivated
when the rest of them were. This caused the binding to become imperfect and to
slowly fade over time. Now Maegera is dangerously close to another awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maegera is meant to be used as a looming threat - the bad guys want to wake her,
the PCs want to stop that from happening. PCs could fix the broken arcane pump
by using the notes found in the Waterclock Crypt in Neverwinter, which would
make the whole thing stable once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless of course the Heir of Delzoun PC is foolish enough to pull the “off”
switch again, causing another cataclysm. Then the whole Sword Coast is due for a
TPK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-great-forge&quot;&gt;The Great Forge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the water elemental-based restraints, the structure around
Maegera also contains a complex network of pipes and wires made from all sorts
of enchanted and rune-carved metal, from copper to adamantine. These act as
conduits for the primordial’s power, which was siphoned to this sector of the
city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heat arrived at a great adamantine pyramid known as the Burning Heart, which
collected it and distributed it to the various forges and manufactories in the
sector. This heat could melt through any metal in short order, making it
extremely easy to shape and ensuring the resulting products would carry a little
of Maegera’s power with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs investigating the Forge can find remains of an ancient battle here, and will
find with the appropriate skill tests that the bones of the invading force
belong to legion devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Heart itself can also be investigated by characters competent in
Arcana. Beating a DC of 11 reveals the obvious (lots of fire magic!); beating a
16 reveals this fire magic is being moderated by water magic; and beating a 23
reveals that the energy is being drained by a third party (the aboleths, which
use it in their research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Normal” areas of the Forge are subject to the Unearthly Heat terrain effect,
and since Maegera is partially unbound some terrain here can display more
overtly supernatural fire features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaching one of the conduits from the Heart or the Forge will bathe the
offending character in primordial fire magic, making them resistant to fire and
better at using fire attacks, but vulnerable to and worse at using some other
element of the GM’s choice. Also, they get a bonus to Diplomacy with elemental
creatures and a corresponding penalty when dealing with immortal ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The character loses three healing surges when this happens, and it wasn’t clear
to me whether they could be recovered normally. The mutations are permanent
until cured by Remove Affliction or an equivalent power. A cure removes all
effects - there’s no way to keep just the beneficial ones!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-deepest-depths&quot;&gt;The Deepest Depths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part of Gauntlgrym that connects to the Underdark. The duergar
originally came in through here, but the place has since become very
inhospitable even to them. Many species of aberrant creature dwell in these dark
passages, chief among them the plaguechanged mind flayers that are giving the
duergar trouble. Their mission is to prevent anyone from messing with Maegera,
and thus from getting in the way of the AbSov’s remote experiment with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means they fight the duergar, but they aren’t any less evil than their
foes. Like most Underdark villains mind flayers are fond of slavery, and they
keep their captives here as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This region is also where the dwarves built secure vaults to store a variety of
horrors they found in their delves. Most are still secure, but some have been
opened over the centuries. One of the vaults that are already open is the one
that housed the original population of dire corbies, and which has become their
largest nest. They keep a lot of treasure there that no other faction has
managed to claim yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beneath even this, you get into tunnels that aren’t part of Gauntlgrym, and
which snake their way downwards to the Underdark. Whatever is down there is out
of scope of the campaign. It could perhaps be an interesting segue into Paragon
Tier when the PCs do finish it, should the group be willing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The areas detailed in this post have a definite “endgame” feeling. Whatever your
reasons for coming to Gauntlgrym, if you’re here you’ll need to deal with the
mess of adversarial factions described in this post, finish what Drizzt and
company could not, and make sure Maegera stays asleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be a fitting end to a campaign centered on the Heirs of Delzoun, but
others might go from here to the bottom of the Chasm as they follow the clues
left by the mind flayers to their real masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, if the group doesn’t include any heirs or anyone else who’d be
interested in the lost city, Gauntlgrym can be safely and entirely removed from
the campaign. Just say that Maegera is in no danger of waking up, and focus on
those elements that are relevant to your players.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/16/neverwinter-gauntlgrym-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/16/neverwinter-gauntlgrym-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
