<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 15:42:49 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 15:42:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Giants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual and the Monster Vault contained plenty of giants, whose
lore in 4e is pretty awesome. I covered their basic lore &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/30/giants.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and also had
individual posts for &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/01/earth-giants.html&quot;&gt;hill&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/04/frost-giants.html&quot;&gt;frost&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/06/fire-giants.html&quot;&gt;fire&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/07/death-giants.html&quot;&gt;death&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/10/storm-giants.html&quot;&gt;storm&lt;/a&gt;
giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 added more giants, and it’s actually where Frost Giants
made their first appearance in this edition. We already covered them in the
corresponding post linked above. In this one, we’ll cover the two other
varieties introduced in the same entry: Eldritch and Stone giants. The latter
are old standbys, and I had never heard of the former until now. If they existed
in a previous edition, it was in one of the more out-of-the-way supplements or
Dragon articles for 3e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eldritch-giants&quot;&gt;Eldritch Giants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-giant-eldritch.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the basic lore post, the primordials made the first Giants from
the same elements they used in the world, to help them shape and understand
it. Well, it turns out &lt;em&gt;raw magic&lt;/em&gt; is as much a basic building block of the
world as the more classical elements of earth, fire, air, and water. Therefore,
it got its own Giant type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eldritch giants were among the most powerful creations of the Primordials, and
they helped a lot with shaping the flow of magical energies in the still-cooling
world. Today their power is much diminished from what it was at the dawn of
time, and most of them dedicate their lives to accumulating magical power and
knowledge in hopes of returning to those lofty heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both eldritch giants and titans are still well-versed in magic. They know how to
form weapons out of pure force, and they tattoo their bodies with symbols that
allow them to absorb the magic of others and teleport at will. They live near
sources of arcane power, and jealously hoard knowledge and artifacts. Eldritch
giant social hierarchy is based on how much power individuals managed to
accumulate - Eldritch Titans tend to be at the top. An individual eldritch giant
or titan might have more abilities than what is depicted in the “typical” stat
blocks of this entry, and they’ll certainly have access to lots and lots of
magic rituals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most interactions between mortals and eldritch giants as written here are likely
to be hostile, since the giants don’t have much reason to be friendly. They love
binding and enslaving other creatures with magic, though, so they might be
encountered alongside powerful elementals, slaads, and other such creatures. A
more reasonable group of them would make valuable allies against powerful
incorporeal enemies, though, since they specialize in force magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eldritch-giant&quot;&gt;Eldritch Giant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Standard” eldritch giants are Large Fey Humanoids with the “giant”
keyword, and Level 18 Skirmishers with 171 HP. They have low-light vision, 10
force resistance, and a +5 bonus to saves vs. charm effects. Their ground speed
is 8 and they also have a teleport speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These giants fight in melee with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Blades&lt;/strong&gt; that target Reflex
and deal force damage, and at range with Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;Force Missiles&lt;/strong&gt; that do the
same. Being so large, they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Sweeping Sword&lt;/strong&gt; attacks to target
everyone in a Close Blast 2 instead of a single victim, and they can do that
even when charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, they can deploy an &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Field&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5; recharge
5+) that counts as difficult terrain and makes enemies inside take extra damage
from the their attacks. Also as a minor action, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Consume Magic&lt;/strong&gt;
to absorb a magic zone created by a PC. This requires them to hit the caster’s
Will with an attack, and if they succeed their own attacks get a big damage
boost until the end of their next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eldritch-titan&quot;&gt;Eldritch Titan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eldritch Titans are Huge, and Level 21 Elite Skirmishers with 394 HP. They have
the same passive traits as their smaller cousins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Hammers&lt;/strong&gt; deal more damage, and they can make two
attacks per action, even on a charge. Their ranged force attack is also stronger
and pushes the target 5 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can cast a &lt;strong&gt;Force Hammer&lt;/strong&gt; that damages everyone on a
close blast 3, pushes then 3 squares and knocks them prone. On a miss the
targets still take half damage and are pushed. They have the same Consume Magic
and Eldritch Field abilities as eldritch giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stone-giants&quot;&gt;Stone Giants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other type of classic earth giant, Stone Giants are among the most
reasonable people among all giantkind. They usually don’t care about raiding or
conquest, and just want to be left alone in their mountain homes. Discrete and
contemplative sorts, they can stay immobile for years while lost in thought, and
are surprisingly adept at hiding themselves in their home terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone passing throug stone giant territory might never spot them at all, and
ill-intentioned travelers might find themselves ambushed before they can do any
harm. The exception to all of this is when the giants are feeling rowdy and want
to have some fun: their favorite game is basically dodgeball with enormous
boulders, and when they’re in the middle of it they don’t usually pay attention
to any smaller creatures who might be in the path of those boulders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone giants are one of the few Giants who are actually on friendly terms with
communities of galeb duhrs and azers. They have a long and proud tradition of
stone carving, and their magic is based on carved runes. It’s possible the
dwarves originally learned their own rune-magic from stone giants, though modern
dwarf scholars dispute this notion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friendly giants of other types, unable to stand their generally unpleasant
societies, often move in with stone giants. Conversely, evil stone giants tend
to move out of their ancestral homes and throw their lot with their more
villainous relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stone-giant&quot;&gt;Stone Giant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-giant-stone.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Giants are Large Elemental Humanoids with the Earth and Giant
keywords. They’re Level 14 Soldiers with 140 HP, immune to petrification, and
have a ground speed of 8 with Earth Walk. This lets them ignore difficult
terrain with a “geological” origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use giant-sized &lt;strong&gt;stone greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt;. As usual for soldiers, their basic
attacks mark on a hit and they can make opportunity attacks marked creatures in
reach that move or shift. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Staggering Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; that works
like an area attack, pushes targets 2 squares, and marks them. At range, they
can &lt;strong&gt;hurl rocks&lt;/strong&gt; like you’d expect out of an old-school giant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While they’re unbloodied, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Stone Bones&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt when hit
by an attack, gaining 5 resistance do its damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stone-giant-runecarver&quot;&gt;Stone Giant Runecarver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spellcaster is a Level 16 Controller with 155 HP and the Leader
keyword. Their magic is partly about slowing and immobilizing enemies, and
partly about doing unpleasant things to enemies suffering from those conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight in melee with &lt;strong&gt;Enruned Picks&lt;/strong&gt;, which are High-Crit weapons and have
a slow (save ends) rider. &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Stone&lt;/strong&gt; ensures that any enemy slowed by
the giant is also immobilized for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magic-wise, their &lt;strong&gt;Rune of Thundering Echo&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) deals thunder damage
over an area and inflicts ongoing thunder damage (save ends) on targets who are
slowed or immobilized. The &lt;strong&gt;Rune of Stony Sleep&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) affects a
similar area, deals physical damage and slows (save ends). After the first
failed save, slowed enemies become petrified instead (save still ends). That
rune also creates a zone within its affected area that inflicts a -2 penalty
against saves vs. slowness or immobilization effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Save ends” petrification might not sound so bad, but runecarvers also have a
&lt;strong&gt;Hardened Focus&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that makes all petrified enemies inside lose any
damage resistance they have &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; gain Vulnerable 5 to all damage. An evil
runecarver is a good counter to a group of PCs who thought a fight against frost
or fire giants was going to be easy just because they packed the right elemental
resistances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stone-titan&quot;&gt;Stone Titan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Titans are basically Stone Giants Plus, being Huge in size and Level 18
Elite Soldiers with 348 HP. They fight unarmed and throw rocks, but there are
some important differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, their marking ability is a &lt;strong&gt;Slipstone Distortion&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) that marks
any enemy who starts their turn inside. Their &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; deal extra damage to
marked enemies, and they can make opportunity attacks against marked enemies
like stone giants can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they can use an &lt;strong&gt;Avalanche Stomp&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) to attack everyone in a
Close Burst 3, with a hit doing heavy damage and causing the very earth to grab
the targets. The escape DC is 28, and the giant doesn’t need to spend actions to
sustain the grab. A miss still does half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And third, they can “charge” a thrown rock and turn it into a &lt;strong&gt;Quakestone&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+), making it into an area attack that does light damage, knocks
prone, and dazes (save ends) on a hit. A miss does half damage and knocks prone
without the daze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eldritch giants have a somewhat unusual name and appearance when compared to the
traditional types, but they’re a lot closer to them than it seems at first. I
guess calling them “Force Giants” would have been a little too on the nose, but
this is basically what they are. They use Force attacks in the same way a frost
giant would use Cold, or a fire giant would use Fire. Their fighting style is
similar, aside from the “I eat magic!” thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone giants on the other hand are one of the traditional types that have been
there since the beginning. I’m happy to see them here because your average stone
giant fits the “Earth Giant” mold a lot more readily than a hill giant, who’s
just a big human-looking person. I also like that the book doesn’t consider all
of them evil, and even mentioned that they partner up with non-evil individuals
of the other giant types. I often ponder how to make sapient monsters less evil
and hostile when I discuss them, so it’s nice to see an entry that does that as
written.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/31/giants.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/31/giants.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Ghost Legionnaire</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-ghost-legionnaire.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual already includes a bunch of &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/18/ghost.html&quot;&gt;ghosts&lt;/a&gt;, and it even
has a basic Phantom Warrior. Here we have a more specific implementation of that
concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are the ghosts of soldiers who died in battle more or less at
the same time as the entire rest of their units. The emotional bonds between
them and the trauma of their violent massed deaths causes their spirits to fuse
and to rise as undead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legionnaires always appear as a unit, and they look like individuals acting in
concert, but they’re all part of the same collective ghost. So it might have
been more accurate to title this entry “Ghost &lt;em&gt;Legion&lt;/em&gt;”. Members of the legion
can possess the living and make them experience the soldiers’ last moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a ghost legionnaire is damaged, it always displays the wounds it suffered
in its final battle rather than the ones that were actually inflicted on it. So
a squad killed by some wizard’s acid-infused fireball would grow progressively
more burned and melted as the PC paladin stabs them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ghost legion might be endlessly reliving its last battle when found, seeing
any living intruders as their enemies. It might also be following the orders of
a more powerful undead being, particularly if that being was one of its
commanders in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual legionnaire is a Medium Natural Humanoid with the Undead keyword,
and a Level 13 Soldier with 100 HP. Despite being a ghost, it’s not considered
insubstantial, but it has 10 necrotic resistance and isn’t especially vulnerable
to radiant damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legionnaires fight with the same weapons they had in life, making &lt;strong&gt;devastating
cuts&lt;/strong&gt; with their melee weapons or shooting &lt;strong&gt;ghost arrows&lt;/strong&gt; that do necrotic
damage. They can also use their &lt;strong&gt;Battle Visions&lt;/strong&gt; power to possess a
target. This has range 20, targets Will and deals psychic damage with a Dominate
(save ends) rider. While the target is dominated, the ghost is removed from the
map. When the target finally makes their save, the ghost reappears in an
adjacent space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ghost’s main weakness takes the form of a trait named &lt;strong&gt;Call to
History&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows a PC to make a DC 25 History check as a minor action to
recall details about the legionnaire’s original unit. A success here makes the
PC’s next attack against that ghost deal 10 extra damage. I don’t think you can
stack multiple checks in a single attack, but you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make a check every turn
before you attack. Someone who was possessed and made their save has a +5 bonus
to these tests for the rest of the fight, as those horrifying battle visions act
as extra reference material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collective nature of a ghost legion is expressed by the &lt;strong&gt;Soul Link&lt;/strong&gt;
trait. Basically, you combine the HP totals of all legionnaires present in the
fight into a single pool. Damage to any individual legionnaire is subtracted
from this combined pool. The whole unit is destroyed when this pool is reduced
to 0, but until that happens all legionnaires remain in the fight! This makes
the usual “focus fire” strategy considerably less effective against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 15, and quite straightforward: a 5-ghost unit and
a human lich wizard from the MM. A Nerathi squad plus their former commanding
officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the “collective HP” gimmick! It shouldn’t be too hard to add or
subtract levels from the stat block given here, either, meaning you can bring
the Fun (TM) of ghost legions to the party no matter what their
level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t much of a story difference between a ghost legionnaire and a phantom
warrior, as you can see by their names. This suggests that one way to get a
level 4 legionnaire would be to remove Insubstantial from the warrior and add
Soul Link in its place. You can likely do the same with any other thesaurus
buddies that might come along (banshee battlers, figment fighters, spectral
soldiers, wraith warriors…).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/29/ghost-legionnaire.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/29/ghost-legionnaire.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Genasi</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-genasi.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of “people touched by the elements” is a 3e thing, but genasi as
presented in Fourth Edition are slightly different than what came before
them. They debuted in the Forgotten Realm Player’s Guide as a playable option,
and would later appear in the MM2 in “monster” format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In previous editions genasi were humans with “genie blood”, but in Fourth
they’re simply humanoid sapients from the Elemental Chaos. They’re given no
cosmically significant origin story like tieflings or daeva, so I must assume
they simply evolved naturally in that plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi look more or less human and have human proportions, but each of them also
has an &lt;em&gt;elemental manifestation&lt;/em&gt;. The five known manifestations are “firesoul”,
“watersoul”, “windsoul”, “stormsoul”, and “earthsoul”. Each genasi is born with
one of these and an individual’s manifestation has more to do with their
environment than with genetics. A genasi community built inside a volcano is
going to have a lot of firesouls, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A genasi’s manifestation accents their physical appearance and defines some of
their inborn powers and resistances. It’s an always active part of their being,
not something they can turn off. Some of them train to acquire additional
manifestations. PCs can have two at most, but some NPCs can have more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi live primarily in the Elemental Chaos. They have an easier time of it
than most other mortals but still must step lightly around efreeti and the
like. They can also be found in the world or in the Feywild, since they don’t
have any more difficulty living there than a human would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi are Medium Elemental Humanoids, with a ground speed of 6. They tend to
have keywords corresponding to their elemental manifestations: a fire genasi
will have the Fire keyword, and so on. Their manifestation also determines what
elements they are resistant to, if any, and the themes of their powers. What
those powers are is mostly a function of training, so varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-elemental-dervish&quot;&gt;Genasi Elemental Dervish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m the Avatar, and you’re gonna have to deal with it!” This is a genasi
warrior who has learned to manifest multiple elements, and trained extensively
with the double sword. They can move equally well on the ground, in the water,
or in the air. Their sword attacks can cause several different types of
elemental damage, as can their magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elemental dervishes are Level 18 Elite Controllers with 344 HP and keywords for
the four “classic” elements (air, earth, fire, water). They have ground, swim,
and fly speeds of 6, and 10 resistance to cold, fire, and lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of its turn, the Dervish chooses an between fire, lightning and
thunder. Their &lt;strong&gt;double sword&lt;/strong&gt; attacks will deal both immediate and ongoing
damage of that type. They can make two of those per action, being elites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a dervish is hit by an adjacent enemy, it can use its reaction to respond
with a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Riposte&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex and inflicts 10 ongoing fire
damage (save ends). If the enemy was already on fire, their existing ongoing
fire damage increases by 10 instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Primordial Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which allows them to
shift 6 squares and perform three attacks in order against different targets at
any point along the movement. The first is &lt;strong&gt;Promise of Storm&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals
thunder damage and makes the target Vulnerable 5 to thunder (save ends). The
second is &lt;strong&gt;Earth Shock&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals physical damage and stuns for a turn. The
third and last one is &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Cut&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals lightning damage and
inflicts 10 ongoing lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elemental dervish is flashy and awesome, and given enough time or
well-selected comrades they can set up some interesting elemental damage combos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-fireblade&quot;&gt;Genasi Fireblade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very straightfoward hot-headed warrior who charges into combat with a flaming
falchion. It’s a Level 11 Brute with 139 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;falchion&lt;/strong&gt; it wields is a High-Crit weapon and inflicts ongoing fire
damage. It has the same Fiery Riposte as the dervish, dealing 5 ongoing damage
instead of 10. Its other power is &lt;strong&gt;Fan The Flames&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 1 vs. Reflex;
recharge 5+), which sets people on fire and gives them a -2 penalty to saves
against ongoing fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fireblades are going to charge into combat, Fan the Flames, and then get to work
on cutting people up and setting them on fire at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasy-hydromancer&quot;&gt;Genasy Hydromancer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AKA, a waterbender that’s also partially made of water. This Level 8 Controller
has 91 HP, a swim speed of 8, and fights with a high-crit &lt;strong&gt;Scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; and lots
of water powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic &lt;strong&gt;Wave Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5) deals physical damage and slides targets 3
squares; &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Vortex&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) does the same in a burst around the
hydromancer that affects only enemies; &lt;strong&gt;Drowning Touch&lt;/strong&gt; inflicts ongoing
damage on a single target (save ends), but only recharges once the target saves
or drops to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “partially made of water” bit is expressed by two other abilities: &lt;strong&gt;Liquid
Body&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that allows them to take half damage from the triggering
attack, and &lt;strong&gt;Swift Current&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) allows them to shift their speed with
the ability to move through enemy spaces and basically ignore all terrain
effects while doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-skyspy&quot;&gt;Genasi Skyspy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A windsoul genasi that fights with paired shortswords and uses their mobility
powers to enhance their hit and run tactics. They’re a Level 7 Skirmisher with
78 HP and 5 cold resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; attack allows them to shift 1 square on a hit, and
they can make two of those against an opponent granting them combat
advantage. &lt;strong&gt;Feather-Footed&lt;/strong&gt; gives them an AC bonus against opportunity
attacks, and &lt;strong&gt;Sky Jaunt&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) allows them to fly until the end of
their current turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should the PCs manage to surround the skyspy, the genasi can use &lt;strong&gt;Manifest
Whirlwind&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2; encounter) to do some damage, push them 1 square,
and knock them prone. This should help clear some space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-stoneshield&quot;&gt;Genasi Stoneshield&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A heavily armored earthsoul warrior wielding a heavy pick in battle. It’s a
Level 10 Soldier with 106 HP. Stoneshields are difficult to push around - any
forced movement applied to them is reduced by 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;war pick&lt;/strong&gt; is a High Crit weapon, and it also marks on a hit. This mark is
remarkable for being (save ends) instead of only lasting a turn. Marked targets
take a -5 penalty to damage against the stoneshield’s allies. They can also
attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Mighty Bull Rush&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage as the pick and
pushes the target 1 square. It also allows the stoneshield to move into the
target’s previous position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they can stomp really hard and cause a non-damaging &lt;strong&gt;Earth Shock&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor action; encounter) that covers a Close Burst 2 and knocks enemies prone
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi can be found alongside a large variety of other creatures, particularly
elementals. They’re as morally varied as humans, so a villain could certainly
employ genasi henchpeople. We have three example encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: 3 genasi skyspies riding hipogriff dreadmounts, accompanied by their
pet shardstorm vortex elemental.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: 2 fireblades, 2 stoneshields, and a trained magma strider.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: Two storm archons (a squallshield and a tempest weaver) and two
elemental dervish mercs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about genasi doesn’t give me the sort of instant adventure inspiration
that some of the other monsters do, but I like that they exist. Their presence
in the Elemental Chaos gives you an excuse to place “normal everyday
communities” in that plane for your PCs to interact with. Not every EC
settlement is a githzerai monastery or the City of Brass.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/26/genasi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/26/genasi.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Fomorian</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Fomorians first appeared in the first Monster Manual, and we covered them
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/07/fomorian.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This entry gives us more fomorian stat blocks, and a few more bits of
lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we have a bit of general lore, which is really a logical extension of the
fact that Fomorians believe themselves the most important creatures in the
universe. They hate all other fey, but that hate manifests as a desire to
subjugate rather than exterminate them. Their perfect world is one where
fomorians rule absolute over the Feywild and have all its other inhabitants
forever toiling to please their masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this obsession, fomorians are eternally at war with the other fey
civilizations. It’s likely they’ll never succeed in conquering all of the
Feywild, but they’ll never stop trying either. I suppose there must also be some
level of internecine strife among them, because it seems to be they’re very
likely to fight over who gets to be supreme ruler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining bits of lore concern the individual stat blocks here, and so will
be covered in those stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numbers-wise, fomorians still retain their common traits from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/07/fomorian.html&quot;&gt;first
article&lt;/a&gt;: they’re Huge Fey Humanoids with the Giant keyword; they’re
extremely perceptive (trained Perception, Truesight 6); and they have some sort
of “evil eye” ability that varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-ghost-shaman&quot;&gt;Fomorian Ghost Shaman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-ghost-shaman.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost shamans are necromancers who enslave the spirits of those they kill. They
command these spirits as if they were puppets, enacting sadistic plays for their
own amusement. They also use enslaved spirits as weapons in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost shamans are Level 16 Elite Controllers with 312 HP. They have darkvision
in addition to the other fomorian traits. All of their attacks are magical in
nature and, except for the Evil Eye, target Fortitude. Their basic melee attack
is &lt;strong&gt;Death’s Touch&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals necrotic damage and slows (save ends). Their
&lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; is a minor-action ranged attack that inflicts ongoing necrotic
damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At will, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Spirits of Possession&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3), which targets
people taking ongoing necrotic damage and dominates them on a hit (save ends). A
bit less often they can use &lt;strong&gt;Darksoul Mist&lt;/strong&gt;, which is like a necrotic fireball
that leaves a zone of darkness in the affected area. This blocks line of sight
for anyone without darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-cackler&quot;&gt;Fomorian Cackler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-cackler.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cacklers are sly but unhinged assassins who get their name because they
constantly laugh a disturbing laugh. They can be silent when they want to be,
though, and are amazingly stealthy for someone the size of a house. They can
also use magic to shrink down to Medium size, which helps a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cacklers are also excellent at disguising themselves, since their minds can
easily construct entire fake personalities to aid in that. It’s possible for
previously discarded personalities to momentarily come to the fore again,
though, which is part of why they’re so unstable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; bigger than the average human greatsword, which they
can use in melee or throw out to range 10. The thrown dagger attack can target
one or two enemies, and they return after it resolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; makes them invisible to the affected enemy, and they get a
big bonus to damage against targets that can’t see them. &lt;strong&gt;Size Alteration&lt;/strong&gt;
lets them switch between Huge and Medium as a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-totemist&quot;&gt;Fomorian Totemist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-totemist.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totemists are fomorian spellcasters that collect the heads of those they kill
and build chains out of them. Each head in the chain is imbued with necromantic
power, and can channel a different curse. Most totemists have a preference for a
particular type of head - one might favor eladrin heads, another dwarves, and so
on. Some of them select prospective additions to their chains year in advance,
following the lives of their future victims until the time is right for the
“harvest”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totemists are Level 18 Elite Skirmishers with 352 HP. They fight with the
afore-mentioned &lt;strong&gt;Chain of Heads&lt;/strong&gt;, which is Reach 4, does physical damage and
inflicts ongoing necrotic damage. They can also channel curses through the chain
as a minor action, with an ability with the very unfortunate name of
&lt;strong&gt;Voodoo&lt;/strong&gt;. There are three possible effects: the &lt;strong&gt;Glorious Head&lt;/strong&gt; blinds, the
&lt;strong&gt;Wasting Head&lt;/strong&gt; weakens, and the &lt;strong&gt;Bewildering Head&lt;/strong&gt; forces the target to make
a melee basic attack against an ally in reach. After attacking, the totemist can
shift 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; does light necrotic damage and inflicts a -2 penalty to
saves, which helps that blindness or weakness last longer. And finally we have
&lt;strong&gt;Fresh Rage&lt;/strong&gt;, a passive trait that makes their first succesfful attack in
their turn deal extra damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-blinder&quot;&gt;Fomorian Blinder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-blinder.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blinders have more specialized and discerning tastes than totemists. They
collect &lt;em&gt;eyes&lt;/em&gt; instead of lugging whole heads around. Blinders are the scholars
and sages of fomorian-kind, acting as repositories of their civilization’s
lore. They’re also very good at eye-based magic - if anyone knows how to make a
defense against the Evil Eye, it’s them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blinders are Level 20 Elite Artillery with 296 HP. They use &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaffs&lt;/strong&gt;
for melee combat but their forte is eye magic. &lt;strong&gt;Acid Eye&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack
that deals acid and necrotic damage, and whose enervating properties prevent the
use of encounter or daily powers for a turn. &lt;strong&gt;Shower of Ichor&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter)
deals the same damage over a wider area, and also inflicts ongoing acid and
necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blinder’s actual &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; is quite powerful: it does no damage by
itself, but someone cursed by it will take the same damage the fomorian inflicts
on other enemies with their other attacks. It ends when the victim saves
successfully, or when the fomorian uses this on someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, blinders have no abilities that actually blind people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-butcher&quot;&gt;Fomorian Butcher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-butcher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Butchers are big fomorians with big blades who like to cut people up for
fun. Such simplicity is a bit disappointing after we saw all those esoterically
evil fomorian casters and assassins, but they’re still very dangerous and just
as ambitious. In fact, they go to absurd lengths to fulfill their serial-killer
urges, and will often trade their souls to devils and make other dangerous deals
in exchange for more power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Butchers are Level 22 Elite Brutes with 514 HP. They use titan-sized
&lt;strong&gt;falchions&lt;/strong&gt;, which are High-Crit weapons. They’re all about focusing on a
single victim and hacking them apart with repeated strikes: when they score a
critical, they can make another free attack with the falchion against the same
victim, and their attacks deal a bunch of extra damage against a victim they
already hit earlier in the same turn. Their &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; restrains (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways they can get that extra damage from a “subsequent” hit:
the bonus attack from a critical, spending an action point to attack again, and
I’d say hitting with the Evil Eye also counts for this. So they’ll always try
that before swinging their blades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the sample encounters here are “Assorted Fomorians” from this book and
the MM. One of them also involves drow and Lolthbound Goblins. Generally
speaking you can also frequently find fomorians accompanied by cyclops slaves,
or by other evil fey they’ve enslaved or allied with. Devils could also make an
appearance, since it seems Fomorian diabolists are somewhat common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lot is quite a bit more flavorful than the fomorians in the MM, and the
extra lore does justice to the basics laid down by the first book. “Voodoo” is a
very unfortunate name for an ability, but it’s easy enough to change.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/25/fomorian.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/25/fomorian.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Firbolg</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-firbolg.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firbolgs are inspired by Celtic myth, and I’m sure they must have appeared in
earlier editions in some form. I think their 4e presentation in this book is
new, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firbolgs are giants (not Giants) native to the Feywild. Their culture values
independence and courage, and their religion is a variant of the
Maiden-Mother-Crone triumvirate. This variant has a different goddess in each
role: Sehanine is the Maiden, Melora is the Mother, and the Raven Queen is the
Crone. This generally results in a religion that’s themed around the night, the
moon, autumn and winter, instead of the more balanced “classical” version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firbolgs live in and protect the deep wilderness of the Feywild, building their
settlements on precarious peaks, floating earth motes, and other such hazardous
heights. Leadership positions are occupied by their mightiest warriors and their
moon seers (priestesses), both of whom wear masks or helmets styled after one of
their deities. They place great value on clan and family ties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back when I discussed the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/05/30/hound.html&quot;&gt;Hounds of the Wild Hunt&lt;/a&gt;, I speculated that the
hunters would be high-powered eladrin. Well, I was wrong! Turns out the Wild
Hunt is a Firbolg tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, while firbolgs are fond of treasure, they place even greater value in
oaths and promises. And when someone breaks an oath made to the firbolgs, they
convene a Wild Hunt to track and punish the infractor. Even people who didn’t
betray the firbolgs directly still have reason to fear them, as there’s a ritual
that allows someone to sic a Wild Hunt on an oathbreaker. And I imagine they
might also ride out to fulfill sacred missions revealed in the moon seers’
visions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wild Hunts vary in size and composition, and might include allied sapients whose
goals and temperament are close to those of the firbolgs themselves. The
mightiest and scariest hunts are led by firbolgs with the oficial title of
Master of the Wild Hunt, who usually act as community leaders while not
fulfilling that role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs might find themselves fighting firbolgs when they stumble on their
territory, since a firbolg attack will likely be the first sign that they did
it. They could also find themselves on the path of a Wild Hunt, or even as their
main target if they manage to piss off someone who can convince the Hunt the PCs
are oathbreakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it’s possible to negotiate with firbolgs and even approach them
peacefully. The Wild Hunt is harder to parley with, but it’s still not
impossible unless the PCs really are oathbreakers. Of course, should their
interests align, the PCs might find themselves riding alongside the hunters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firbolgs are Large Fey Humanoids, and all the ones we see here are
Unaligned. They all have low-light vision and a natural ground speed of 8. They
also have Regeneration 5 (10 at Epic tier), which can be shut down for a turn by
necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a +2 bonus on saves against charm effects, and the immobilized,
slowed and restrained conditions. For elite firbolgs, this stacks with the +2 on
all saves elites get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature power is &lt;strong&gt;Moonfire&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Will; minor action;
recharge 4+), which prevents the target from benefitting from cover or
concealment for a turn. It also has additional effects that vary per stat block,
but all generally make the target more vulnerable to that firbolg’s attacks. All
of their other powers come from martial or magic training, and their magic has
the same themes as their religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firbolg-hounder&quot;&gt;Firbolg Hounder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hounders are members of firbolg hunting parties whose job is to attack and drive
prey into a position that makes them vulnerable to the other hunters. They wear
scale and wield axes and shields. They’re Level 11 Soldiers with 113 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Battleaxe&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can use it in a
&lt;strong&gt;Hounding Strike&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that has the same basic stats and also slides the
target 2 squares on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Drive Prey&lt;/strong&gt; is an even more powerful version of
that, doing more damage and allowing a secondary attack vs. Will. If that hits,
the target must move or shift away from the hounder with its first action on its
next turn, or become dazed until the end of that turn. This ability recharges
when the hounder is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range, the hounder can throw &lt;strong&gt;Handaxes&lt;/strong&gt;, which do light physical damage and
knock the target prone. Their &lt;strong&gt;Moonfire&lt;/strong&gt; power also marks the target for a
turn. Finally, the &lt;strong&gt;Hunter’s Leap&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait makes them immune to
opportunity attacks while jumping. They use the standard jumping rules for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it looks like these firbolgs will use Hounding Strike and Drive Prey to slide
enemies into a vulnerable position, and then either stay away and throw
handaxes, or move into melee to try and keep the enemy pinned in place while the
other hunters do their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firbolg-hunter&quot;&gt;Firbolg Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the people the hounder (above) works with. They’re level 12
Skirmishers with 123 HP, wear light armor and bring &lt;strong&gt;spears&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt;
to bear agains their prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their powers enhance their weapon attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Crippling Strike&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharges when first bloodied) adds extra damage to an attack and makes it
immobilize the target (save ends) with a Slow after-effect. &lt;strong&gt;Mobile Attack&lt;/strong&gt;
allows them to move 8 squares and make a basic attack without provoking
opportunity attacks from the target, or from making ranged attacks. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Moonfire&lt;/strong&gt; also makes their weapon attacks do +1d6 damage to the affected
target for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, they also have Hunter’s Leap. It’s really hard to run from them,
particularly when there hounders pinning you down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firbolg-moon-seer&quot;&gt;Firbolg Moon Seer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moon Seers are those priestesses I talked about. They’re Level 14 Controllers
with 141 HP. They wear masks and light armor, and fight with moon- and
fate-themed magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A seer’s basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Moon Mace&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex, deals
Radiant damage, and blinds the target until the start of its next turn. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Moonfire&lt;/strong&gt; has the additional effect of making targets grand combat advantage
to the seer for a turn. After hitting someone with Moonfire, the seer can use
&lt;strong&gt;Moonstrike&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Will) to deal psychic damage to that victim and dominate
them until the end of the seer’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s two other spells &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Hounds&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Ban of the Raven&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spirit Hounds is a blast that targets Reflex and only affects enemies. It deals
psychic damage, slows, and prevents the target from teleporting (save ends),
which is handy when hunting down eladrin or other fey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ban of the Raven is the big gun, an encounter power that’s a Ranged 10
vs. Fortitude attack. It deals heavy necrotic damage and worsens critical hits!
The affected victim takes critical hits on a natural 18-20 instead of only a 20,
and each such hit deals an extra 10 necrotic damage on top of whatever it would
normally deal. Once the victim saves against that there’s still a weaker
aftereffect that makes the victim suffer crits on a 19-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firbolg-bloodbear&quot;&gt;Firbolg Bloodbear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bloodbears mix in a bit of viking into their Celtic trappings, being able to
turn into bear hybrids. They’re Level 15 Elite Brutes with 240 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight unarmed, and start out in firbolg form. Once bloodied, they assume
&lt;strong&gt;Bloodbear Form&lt;/strong&gt;, recover &lt;em&gt;all of their HP&lt;/em&gt;, and double their
regeneration. This also upgrades all of their attacks. This transformation lasts
until they’re bloodied again, and then it reverts. So in effect they have 360
HP, and will become bears for the middle third of that health bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In firbolg form, they fight unarmed with &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can slam twice with
&lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. If they hit both attacks, they can also try to grab the
target. &lt;strong&gt;Bloodbear Maul&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to automatically deal heavy physical
damage against the grabbed victim. They have Moonfire, but it’s only the basic
version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In bloodbear form their slams turn into &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks that gain increased
damage, they gain a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does even more damage and deals ongoing damage
if the target is granting AC, and Bloodbear Maul also allows them to make a free
bite attack against the grabbed target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firbolg-ghostraven&quot;&gt;Firbolg Ghostraven&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Raven Queen themed assassins. They fight with heavy war picks, which
are not the kind of weapon you’d expect an assassin to use. They can assume the
form of a ghostly raven, which allows them to better hide in shadows and ambush
their intended victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghostravens are Level 16 Elite Lurkers with 238 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;picks&lt;/strong&gt; are
High-Crit weapons, and they can attack twice with them. If both attacks hit the
victim is blinded (save ends). Assuming &lt;strong&gt;Ghostraven Form&lt;/strong&gt; is a minor action
that makes them intangible, gives them a fly speed of 8, and gives them
concealment while in dim light or darkness. When a ghostraven attacks someone
who can’t see it, it deals increased damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firbolg-master-of-the-wild-hunt&quot;&gt;Firbolg Master of The Wild Hunt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it says on the tin. These hunt masters usually serve as leaders of firbolg
communities when they’re not heading a Wild Hunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunt Masters are Level 22 Elite Skirmishers with 404 HP. They wear the classic
stag helmet and fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Spear of the Hunt&lt;/strong&gt; that can make both melee and
ranged attacks (it returns when thrown). Being elites, they can attack twice per
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Moonfire&lt;/strong&gt; also marks and makes the target grant combat advantage until
the end of the master’s next turn. They deal increased damage to targets
affected by Moonfire (from &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; firbolg, not just their own).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Mortal Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to make a basic
attack against a bloodied enemy that’s an automatic critical and deals 6d6
additional damage. If this reduces the target to 0 HP, it gives an extra action
point to the huntmaster. Action Points, as a reminder, can be spent to give
their owner a whole extra standard action on their turn. All elites start out
with one, and the hunt master is one of the few who can gain more during a
fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is Level 13, a moon seer, a hunter and two hounders plus 2 centaur
hunters. This is either a “lesser” Wild Hunt or just a normal hunting
party/patrol. It hints that there’s likely a joint Centaur/Firbolg culture out
there somehwer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is a proper scary Wild Hunt: the Master of the Wild Hunt along with
two Wild Hunt hounds, a bloodbear, and 2 ghostravens. It’s level 22, which means
relatively few things in the setting can really stand up to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like firbolgs more than I though I would! There’s plenty of information on
them here, and it does plenty to differentiate them from the more standard
giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I found a bit awkward are the bits of text in the book that say they
value “the middle path between good and evil”. This is derived from one of
Sehanine’s commandments, which is equally awkward. What does this mean? Are they
supposed to feed a puppy one day and kick it on the next to keep things
balanced? A more charitable interpretation might be that they’re not any more
inclined to trust people who claim to be champions of good than they are anyone
else, and try to stay out of those particular cosmic struggles.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/17/firbolg.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/17/firbolg.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Fey Lingerer</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fey-lingerer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s fair to say that eladrins can be overachievers. Their societies
produce a lot of gallant knights and powerful spellcasters, who go on to
accumulate glory and renown to their name. They’ll be the first to say the world
is a better place due to their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, though, things go wrong. A knight perishes with a quest unfulfilled,
or a mage dies just before making that one crucial breakthrough that would get
him tenure at Lórien Polytechnic. Whether from violence, accident or natural
causes, such deaths are incredibly frustrating for the eladrin in question, so
they simply refuse to go. The entity that results from this is known as a Fey
Lingerer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fey lingerers resemble the people they were in life, but the book describes then
as “withdrawn from elven grace”. In other words, they look clearly dead, their
formerly shiny countenances now decomposed or dessicated. They’re also quite
cruel and anti-social, their personalities now dominated by the frustration and
anger that kept them from passing on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lingerers generally try to accomplish whatever it is they were trying to do when
they died, and can linger on even after that, looking for ways to gain the glory
and fame they feel were due to them while they lived. They might employ other
undead in this, and sometimes they also gather living eladrin followers who are
willing to help their fallen heroes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a fey lingerer is destroyed in combat, its spirit emerges angrier than
ever. This &lt;em&gt;vestige&lt;/em&gt; knows it can never complete its objectives now that its
body has been destroyed, and becomes obsessed with taking revenge on those
responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fey lingerers are corporeal undead, and since they used to be overachieving
eladrin luminaries, they’re usually mid-to-late Paragon-tier. As is standard for
undead, they have Darkvision plus some level of Necrotic resistance and Radiant
Vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lingerers retain the eladrin Fey Step power, and add an aura of &lt;strong&gt;Spiraling
Despair&lt;/strong&gt; (radius 3) which inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks and saves to enemies
caught inside. They also have an extra bonus on saves against charm effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re Elite monsters, but this is implemented in a novel and very interesting
way. Normally an Elite would have double HP, but Fey Lingerers have the normal
amount. However, when they hit 0 HP they become Vestiges, incorporeal undead
with their own stat blocks. They start in the same position as the original
lingerer, and act on the same initiative order, but are otherwise treated as if
they had just entered the fight: full HP, all abilities unused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vestiges aren’t worth any additional XP when fought as part of a lingerer fight
since the lingerer’s XP total accounts for them. You can design encounters
with vestiges directly, though, and in that case they’re worth XP as normal for
a regular monster of their level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lingerer-knight&quot;&gt;Lingerer Knight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These knights usually died when trying to fulfill an important mission or quest,
and are driven to complete it. They might have been honorable sorts before their
deaths, but now they’re just desperate. Bearing the same weapons they did in
life, they can infuse their strikes with necrotic energy and force enemies to
experience their rather unhealthy mental state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lingerer Knights are Level 16 Elite Soldiers with 152 HP. They have all standard
lingerer traits and a speed of 6. Their necrotic resistance is 10, and their
radiant vulnerability 5. The one in the book fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; that
also inflicts ongoing necrotic damage (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows it
to perform two sword attacks in a single action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also perform a spell called &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Sword Circle&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a
Close Burst 1 vs. Reflex that does slightly less damage than a double attack and
also inflicts ongoing necrotic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That unhealthy mental state manifests as two different powers: &lt;strong&gt;Desperate
Challenge&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10; Encounter) allows the knight to mark a target until the
end of the fight or until the knight discorporates, whichever comes
first. Marked targets take some automatic necrotic damage when they make an
attack that doesn’t target the knight. &lt;strong&gt;Spiritual Despondence&lt;/strong&gt; triggers when
the knight is first bloodied and deals automatic necrotic damage in a Close
Burst 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fey-knight-vestige&quot;&gt;Fey-Knight Vestige&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A destroyed lingerer knight becomes one of these. It’s a Level 16 Lurker with 75
HP. It has all standard lingerer traits, a ground speed of 6, and a fly speed
of 6. Its resistances and vulnerabilities increase by 5 each, and it’s also
insubstantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vestige fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Ghostsword&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude instead of AC,
does necrotic damage, and makes the target grant combat advantage to the vestige
(save ends). This means it can do its “Lurker thing” while staying in the front
lines, which is a bit unusual but matches the “knight” flavor. &lt;strong&gt;Desperate
Dash&lt;/strong&gt; (move; recharge 5+) allows it to shift 6 squares and possibly escape
being surrounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lingerer-fell-incanter&quot;&gt;Lingerer Fell Incanter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fell Incanters hang around for more open-ended reasons than knights, and are
usually obsessed with obtaining more arcane knowledge and power in order to Show
Them All. Their magic is tinted with their hatred, so all of it does necrotic
damage. So they’re kind of Lich-Lite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fell Incanters are Level 18 Elite Artillery with 130 HP and all standard
lingerer traits. They’re armed with a &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaff&lt;/strong&gt; that also inflicts
ongoing necrotic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range they can fire &lt;strong&gt;Soul Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that deal
necrotic damage and immobilize (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to
shoot two of these in one action. After they’re bloodied, they can also use a
&lt;strong&gt;Soul Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3 vs. Fortitude; recharge 5+) that does necrotic
damage and weakens until the end of the incanter’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fey-incanter-vestige&quot;&gt;Fey-Incanter Vestige&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a fell incanter is destroyed, it becomes one of these. It’s a Level 18
Lurker with 91 HP. Its resistances and vulnerabilities are increased by 5 each,
it gains a fly speed, and becomes insubstantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incanter vestiges have no melee attacks. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Ray of
Humility&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 5 vs. Will) doing both immediate and ongoing necrotic
damage. It also inflicts 5e disadvantage (roll 2d20 and take the lowest die) on
the victim’s saves, with a successful save ending both this and the ongoing
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also &lt;strong&gt;Ray of Spring’s Rejection&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Will; recharge 5+),
which does more damage and makes the target grant combat advantage to the
vestige (save ends). And, like the knight vestige, this one deals increased
damage to people granting CA to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This results in an enemy that’s a bit similar to the knight vestige but with a
ranged focus. It’s also a lot harder to save against its CA-granting effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 18: two lingerer knights, 1 fell incanter, and a
living bralani of autumn winds who is probably one of the incanter’s fan-elves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think fey lingerers are really interesting! Though I described them as “Lich
Lite”, I actually think they’re a bit more flavorful than standard liches, what
with the whole “become a vengeful ghost” mechanic. I always felt D&amp;amp;D 4 could
have done a lot more with such multi-stage enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/15/fey-lingerer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/15/fey-lingerer.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Fell Taint</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fell-taint.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; fell taints are new to 4e - at least, this book is where I first heard
of them. If they showed up in previous editions, it was probably in 3e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess the name made me think of something you might find staining an ogre’s
underwear, but that’s not the case. Fell Taints are small predators from the Far
Realm, where they occupy a niche more or less equivalent to that of our
foxes. However, they’re quite a bit more dangerous when they cross into the
world, which they can do rather easily in places where the border between it and
the Far Realm is even a little bit thinner than usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their presence acts as a beacon for more powerful and dangerous Far Realm
denizens, and slowly erodes the barrier between dimensions. So if you have fell
taints in a place, you’ll soon get bigger horrors from beyond popping up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The taints themselves are also dangerous on their own, since they hunt by
destroying the mind of their intended prey with their psychic powers. This is
not exactly something most mortal creatures have a strong defense against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the bizarre things about Fell Taints is that they’re only half real. The
other half is formed by the minds of those who see them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fell Taints are Baby’s First Elder Things, with levels in the early-to-mid
Heroic tier. If you’re starting an aberrant-themed campaign from Level 1,
they’re going to be the first genuine Far Realm denizens your party meets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fell Taints can fly quite well with a speed of 6 and hover capability, or crawl
along the ground at speed 1 if they must. They’re insubstantial due to that
half-real thing, but vulnerable to psychic damage. The touch of their
&lt;strong&gt;tendrils&lt;/strong&gt; causes psychic damage, and they usually have mind-affecting special
attacks as well. They’re all Aberrant Magical Beasts, and most are Small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ability they all share is &lt;strong&gt;Fell Taint Feeding&lt;/strong&gt;: when they manage to get a
victim helpless or unconscious, they can begin to feed. This causes them to lose
their fly speed and become substantial until the end of their next turn, but
allows them to perform a &lt;em&gt;coup de grace&lt;/em&gt; against the victim. If this kills the
victim, the fell taint immediately recovers all of its hit points. Yeah, they’ll
absolutely attempt to kill any PC that drops to 0 HP during the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-lasher&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Lasher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lashers are Level 1 Soldiers with 20 HP and all standard traits outlined
above. Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Tendrils of Stasis&lt;/strong&gt;, which does a bit less
damage than the basic tendril slap and immobilizes the target for a turn. When
making an opportunity attack, they can shift as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-pulsar&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Pulsar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pulsars are Level 1 Artillery with 18 HP and all common traits. Their special
attacks are a Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;tendril pulse&lt;/strong&gt; that does psychic damage, and a Ranged
10 &lt;strong&gt;tendril flurry&lt;/strong&gt; that makes a slightly weaker attack against up to three
targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-tought-eater&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Tought Eater&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 2 Controllers with 26 HP and all standard traits. They have two
special attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit Haze&lt;/strong&gt; is a Range 10 attack that does psychic damage and dazes for a
turn. &lt;strong&gt;Tought Fog&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a Close Burst 5 that only targets enemies,
does no damage, and slows. This worsens to immobilization after the first failed
save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-taint-warp-wender&quot;&gt;Fell Taint Warp Wender&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 4 Controller is Medium, and has 38 HP. Its single special attack is
&lt;strong&gt;Psychic Transposition&lt;/strong&gt;, which does light psychic damage, dazes (save ends)
and makes the taint and the victim teleport to exchange places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are mostly mixed fell taint groups, because they rarely
work with anyone else. Still, they might be coincidentally found alongside
undead or oozes, creatures they find unapettizing. I imagine some cultists and
such might also know how to bind them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a party’s first contact with the Far Realm, I think these creatures are quite
nifty. They look weird enough to unsettle, and each has a single distinctive
mechanical trick.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/13/fell-taint.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/13/fell-taint.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Elemental</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, any creature with the “elemental” origin is an elemental, but as we
saw in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/16/elemental.html&quot;&gt;Elemental&lt;/a&gt; entry from the first monster manual the name is also
used for a particularly wild subset of that plane’s denizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in that earlier post, Elementals proper are some of the “basest”
life forms of the Elemental Chaos, with bodies that share a lot more with their
constituent elements than with any sort of living organism. Unlike demons
they’re not actively malicious, but they’re mercurial and easy to provoke into a
rampage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As magical beasts, they’re technically sapient, but their intellects tend to be
rather limited. These creatures are also often bound by elementally-inclined
ritual casters such as mortal wizards, efreets, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM2 presents us with more elementals ranging from the mid-Heroic to the
early Epic tier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chillfire-destroyer&quot;&gt;Chillfire Destroyer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-chillfire-destroyer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Large humanoid made of ice wrapped around a fiery core, which means it has
zero chill. It’s a Level 14 Brute with 173 HP, lumbering about at Speed 5. It
has 10 resistance to cold and fire, and is immune to disease and poison. Its
&lt;strong&gt;fists&lt;/strong&gt; do a mix of fire and cold damage, and it can also move its speed and
&lt;strong&gt;trample&lt;/strong&gt; anyone it comes into contact with during this movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this elemental gets damaged, its shell begins to crack. Once it’s bloodied,
its &lt;strong&gt;Leaking Firecore&lt;/strong&gt; acts as an aura (radius 2) that deals fire damage to
anyone caught inside. Once it reaches 0 HP, a &lt;strong&gt;Firecore Breach&lt;/strong&gt; causes it to
explode! This explosion is a Close Burst 3 vs. Reflex, dealing heavy fire
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dust-devil&quot;&gt;Dust Devil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-dust-devil.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A being or air and earth, this capricious living whirlwind has a tendency to
sandblast anyone who makes it angry. It’s Small, and a Level 3 Skirmisher with
47 HP and a ground speed of 8. No, they can’t fly. It’s immune to disease and
poison, and it suffers a -2 penalty to all of its defenses if slowed or
immobilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Winds&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex, does some physical
damage and slides the target 3 squares. &lt;strong&gt;Gale Blast&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to shift 5
squares by moving really fast, and try to knock anyone in the way prone (attack
vs. Fortitude).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can do that sandblasting trick with &lt;strong&gt;Stinging Sands&lt;/strong&gt;
(close burst 3 vs. Fortitude), which does heavy damage and blinds for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flamespiker&quot;&gt;Flamespiker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-flamespiker.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a triple combination of air, earth, and fire, taking the form of a
Medium stony humanoid who can use high-pressure air to fire red-hot spikes from
its fiery core. They’re more like people than wildlife, and often end up hired
as front-line muscle by other sapient elementals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flamespikers are level 5 soldiers with 66 HP and a ground speed of 7. Their
immunities include disease, poison, and petrification, and they also have 10
fire resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flamespiker fights with its Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Stonespikes&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and can also
fire them at out to range 10 as &lt;strong&gt;Spikebolts&lt;/strong&gt;. Both attacks do physical damage,
and the melee one also makes the target vulnerable to fire damage until the end
of the spiker’s next turn. So it pairs really well with fire elementals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy within reach shifts, the stonespiker can react with a &lt;strong&gt;Thunderfire
Thrust&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which is a basic melee attack with an extra follow-up
against Fortitude that does 5 thunder damage and stuns (save ends). This makes
slipping past them a difficult proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;geonid&quot;&gt;Geonid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-geonid.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Large creature has more of a metabolism than most elementals, and needs to
hunt. A stony oyster-like creature, the geonid is extremely hard to tell apart
from a boulder when its shell is closed. When it reveals itself, we can see that
it’s yet another tentacular ambush predator that lives in the shallow Underdark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were initially created to guard the secret pathways of the world, and the
secret caches of weapons, dormant war-beasts, and treasure hidden there by the
forces of the primordials. Some of those caches are still out there, as are
their guardians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geonids are Level 6 Lurkers with 56 HP. They’re immune to disease, petrification
and poison, and cal roll around at speed 4. With its shell closed, potential
victims must pass a DC 28 Perception check to realize it’s not a harmless
boulder. At level 6, this is hard even for the party’s “radar”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the geonid strikes, it fights with &lt;strong&gt;tentacle&lt;/strong&gt; slaps that do standard
physical damage. It can also use a &lt;strong&gt;capturing grab&lt;/strong&gt; that consists of two
weaker tentacle attacks. If both hit, it grabs the target (escape DC 17).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it’s grabbed someone, the geonid will close itself with &lt;strong&gt;Shell Slam&lt;/strong&gt;,
which does a lot of things at once. It slides a grabbed victim to the geonid’s
space, and it tries to knock everyone in a close burst 2 prone (vs. Fortitude).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the shell is closed, the geonid has a ground speed of 0 and a +5 to all of
its defenses, and it can’t target anyone other than the grabbed victim it pulled
inside its shell. The victim can also only target the geonid, but on the bright
side it won’t have to contend with the defense bonus. If the victim escapes, it
gets spit out and appears adjacent to the geonid, who can open its shell with a
minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mudlasher&quot;&gt;Mudlasher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-mudlasher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another sapient elemental predator, mudlashers are made of well, mud. They slam
and drown their victims, and then sit atop the corpse as a puddle to slowly
digest it. They’re Medium Level 4 Brutes with 63 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; do physical damage, and once per fight they can upgrade
that to a &lt;strong&gt;Drowning Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude and adds an ongoing damage
follow-up (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also fling &lt;strong&gt;mud balls&lt;/strong&gt; at range (vs. Reflex), which do no damage but
slow their targets. If a target is already slowed, it’s immobilized
instead. This is good because the mudlasher gets a +2 to attacks against slowed
or immobilized targets. A save will end either condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rockfist-smasher&quot;&gt;Rockfist Smasher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-rockfist-smasher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name says it all: they’re humanoid rocks that like to smash with their
fists. Smashers don’t need to eat, so they do that for fun. People who build
elemental themed dungeons like to gather a bunch of these and lock them in
chambers and at the bottom of pits as living traps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hooligans are Large, Level 10 Brutes with 125 HP, the standard suite of
earth-creature immunities, and a speed of 5. Their &lt;strong&gt;Granite Punches&lt;/strong&gt; do good
damage and knock bloodied targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a smasher gets bloodied itself, its &lt;strong&gt;Internal Avalanche&lt;/strong&gt; triggers and
begins accumulating kinetic energy. This gives the smasher 20 temporary HP. If
it still has any temp HP at the start of its next turn, it gains an action point
that must be used in that turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shardstorm-vortex&quot;&gt;Shardstorm Vortex&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-rockfist-smasher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are living blizzards made of stone instead of ice. Despite this impressive
description, they’re just Medium in size and are the scavengers of the Elemental
Chaos. Shardstorms follow in the wake of more impressive beings and feed on what
remains of their battles. In battle they work like slightly stronger dust
devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re level 7 skirmishers with 80 HP. Their ground speed is 0, but they fly at
speed 8 with hover capability and project a &lt;strong&gt;Sandblast&lt;/strong&gt; aura (radius 1) that
inflicts a -2 to all defenses of anyone caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Abrasive Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude and does
physical damage. They can also perform &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Blasts&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that
allow them to shift 4 squares and an attack at the end. This does heavy damage
and pushes 1 square on a hit. It does half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also get two variant stat blocks for them as minions at levels 13
and 23. They still have the aura and the basic attack, but instead of the Blast
they get a &lt;strong&gt;Vortex Step&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will 4-square shift with no built-in attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stormstone-fury&quot;&gt;Stormstone Fury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-stormstone-fury.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Medium stone humanoid infused with the power of a storm. It can throw
explosive stones, cause shrapnel to fly outward from its body, and meld into the
ground for a quick escape. When fighting as part of a team they don’t really
care about catching allies in their blasts, so if you find yourself on the same
side as one of these, bring some thunder protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furies are Level 14 Artillery with 113 HP and Speed 6. They have the usual
immunity suite, and 10 thunder resistance. Its &lt;strong&gt;Grinding Stones&lt;/strong&gt; melee basic
attack is terrible, but its &lt;strong&gt;Hurtling Thunderstones&lt;/strong&gt; have Range 20 and do half
damage on a miss. Hit or miss, they also cause a follow-up explosion (burst 2
vs. Fortitude) that does thunder damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shrapnel Burst&lt;/strong&gt; is their “keep away from me” power, sending shrapnel that
pushes 2 squares and does physical and thunder damage in a close burst 2
(vs. AC). If that fails, &lt;strong&gt;Meld to Ground&lt;/strong&gt; removes them from the map for a
turn, after which they reappear up to 10 squares away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tempest-wisp&quot;&gt;Tempest Wisp&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-tempest-wisp.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gaseous creature is a bit smarter than your average elemental, and actively
seeks to either ally with or coerce other creatures to form groups that
cooperate against threats. It uses its wind powers to push enemies around the
battlefield, and hides behind its allies to avoid damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tempest Wisps are Level 13 Controllers with 134 HP. They’re immune to disease
and poison, and are insubstantial while not bloodied (i.e, while at over 50%
HP). They have a flight speed of 7 with hover capability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Air Slash&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex) that does physical damage,
and they can attack at range with &lt;strong&gt;Whistling Wind&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex) for
about the same damage and a 1-square slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their limited special attack is hilarious! Named &lt;strong&gt;Tumbling Updraft&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Fortitude; recharge 5+), it does no immediate damage but instead lifts the
target 20 feet up on a hit and restrains them (save ends). Each failed save
causes the victim to be tossed up another 20 feet. On a successful save, the
victim falls! That’s a minimum of 2d10 fall damage, plus another 2d10 for every
failed save. It’s all subject to the standard rules for falls, though, so you
might be able to reduce or avoid this damage in the usual ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;windfiend-fury&quot;&gt;Windfiend Fury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-windfiend-fury.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another Angry Tornado, this one more purely “stormy” than the others. These
Large beings like to hang around elemental storms, and so tend to get swept away
into other planes. Sometimes archons will capture them and bind them to their
flying ships as a power source and as a means to travel to other planes. You can
also say these are the beings trapped at the core of those Eberron flying ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 12 Controllers with 123 HP and a flight speed of 8. Aside from
the usual immunities to disease and poison they have 15 resistance to lightning
and thunder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They attack in melee with &lt;strong&gt;Flying Debris&lt;/strong&gt;, and toss &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; at
range that do lightning damage and daze for a turn. Their “keep away!” power is
a &lt;strong&gt;Storm Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that does thunder damage and teleports them to just outside
the area of effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;windstriker&quot;&gt;Windstriker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-elemental-windstriker.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final Angry Tornado is Medium, and a Level 9 Lurker with 56 HP. They have
the usual immunities and full-time insubstantiality, along with a flight speed
of 8. It attacks unpredictably, though apparently not to feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their attacks do “cold and thunder” damage. They’re probably going to
open up with &lt;strong&gt;Searching Wind&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Will), which knocks prone on a
hit and marks the target as the windstriker’s quarry as an effect. Then they’ll
follow that up with &lt;strong&gt;Lethal Windstrike&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. AC), which hits hard but
only works against the quarry. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Windstrike&lt;/strong&gt; is a lot weaker, so
it’s for emergencies only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the windstriker takes damage, it activates &lt;strong&gt;Shifting Wind&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction,
which gives it the ability to ignore opportunity attacks and pass through enemy
spaces during its next turn. So it’s going to be flitting back and forth to
alternate marking someone as a quarry and attempting to assassinate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a whole bunch of sample encounters here, but they’re all easily to
described: assorted elementals of similar level, occasionally with someone who
might be the spellcaster binding them, like a tiefling heretic or a beholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the lore of elementals in 4e on principle, and we have lots of
mechanically varied stat blocks here… but there’s &lt;em&gt;so many&lt;/em&gt; of them that they
all kinda started blurring together by the end. I almost wish we had gotten an
elemental “plug-in” module for the 4e monster design system rather than this
long list full of angry rock giants and angry living tornadoes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/10/elemental.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/10/elemental.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Eladrin</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-eladrin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already discussed the lore of the Eladrin &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/13/eladrin.html&quot;&gt;over here&lt;/a&gt;, along with how they
differ from your standard elves and from the celestials of 3e. I recommend
reading that post again for those basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 contains three more eladrin stat blocks, along with a bit
of additional lore on their society. I find it very funny that two of them
correspond to very popular elfy classes of editions past, debuting in 4e in the
form of monster entries. It would be some time before playable versions of them
were published, which I imagine must have made their fans quite anxious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eladrin-arcane-archer&quot;&gt;Eladrin Arcane Archer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arcane Archers are more than just wizards who can shoot a bow. They practice an
art that’s seamless fusion of the two disciplines, and whose secrets are
jealously kept by certain eladrin societies. The Bow Mage minions we saw in the
MM1 are likely to practice the same style. This entry would represent a more
advanced, experienced, or narratively important practitioner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think we ever explicitly got an Arcane Archer class in 4e. The Seeker
tries to implement the concept using primal magic but ends up not being very
effective. I think there’s also a way to build a Bard specializing in magic
ranged attacks with a bow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arcane Archers are Level 5 Artillery with 51 HP. Their speed is 6 and they have
low-light vision, along with the standard Fey Step power all eladrin get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight, they stay at range and repeatedly fire &lt;strong&gt;Scorching Arrows&lt;/strong&gt; from
their bows. This ability is kinda like a better version of the PC Ranger’s Twin
Strike, allowing them to make two attacks that target the lower of AC and
Reflex. The arrows have the same range as mundane ones, and individually deal a
low-ish mix of physical and fire damage. This adds up, though: an arcane archer
that consistently hits with both attacks punches a fair bit above its weight
class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also fire an arrow that explodes into an &lt;strong&gt;Eldricht Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst
1 within 20 vs Fortitude; recharge 4+). This deals force damage and knocks
enemies prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eladrin-bladesingers&quot;&gt;Eladrin Bladesingers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, bladesingers. I first heard of them in 2e and I can’t remember a more
controversial class from that edition, at least here in the Brazilian fan
community. People either really loved them or really hated them. While I was
eventually convinced that their highly cinematic combat style was cool, I never
liked that they were an elf-only option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, 4e bladesingers are eladrin practitioners of an ancient martial art that
joins swordplay and magic. The resulting style resembles something a Jedi knight
or wuxia hero might use, employing lots of empowered sword strikes and
magic-assisted acrobatic maneuvers. Their code of conduct has elegance as an
important principle, so they put real effort into making their combat techniques
both graceful and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same code also compels them to behave honorably, so they tend to treat
opponents with respect and despise those who slaughter the weak and
defenseless. Despite this, there are many possible reasons for even a party of
good-aligned PCs to come into conflict with bladesingers: they might have
offended the eladrin’s liege, or a given group of bladesingers might have fallen
to the Dark Side of the Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get pretty close to a playable bladesinger by playing a Swordmage, and
apparently there was also a “bladesinger” class published late in the
edition. More obliquely, a Blade Pact Fey Warlock could also fit the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM2 bladesinger is a Level 11 Skirmisher with 114 HP. They have a very nice
ground speed of 8, in addition to the low-light vision and Fey Step power all
eladrin get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wear mail and wield a longsword, both of which are probably magical or at
least very high quality. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Brilliant Blade&lt;/strong&gt; strike,
which deals radiant damage and gives the target a -3 penalty to attack the
bladesinger during the target’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dance of Brilliance&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will combination that allows them to make an
attack dealing light radiant damage, shift 3 squares, and make a basic Brilliant
Blade attack against another target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have two encounter powers. &lt;strong&gt;Crippling Strike&lt;/strong&gt; targets Fortitude and deals
no damage, but is guaranteed to slow the target even on a miss. On a hit it also
weakens them. In both cases the conditions are “save ends”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wyvern Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is much better, allowing the bladesinger to fly 8 squares
without provoking opportunity attacks and perform a strike at any poing along
the movement. This targets Fortitude, deals light physical damage, and 10
ongoing poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally there’s &lt;strong&gt;Combat Shift&lt;/strong&gt;. This allows them to shift 1 square as a minor
action, ending up adjacent to an enemy against which they have combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coure-of-mischief-and-strife&quot;&gt;Coure of Mischief and Strife&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time for more surreal fey nobility! Like “bralani” and “ghaele”, “coure” is a
noble title whose meaning can be a little confusing to mortals. One of the
reasons for this is that while most eladrin societies use the same names for the
titles, the actual rank they confer, and the amount of influence attached to
them, varies from culture to culture. So in this city state ghaeles might be the
rulers, but on that kingdom over there they’re just minor provincial nobles and
it’s the coures who call the shots. Attaining a noble title is rarely a matter
of inheritance - there’s a lot of mystery and mystycism involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever their rank, though, these titles always have some natural phenomenon or
abstract concept attached to them, like “autumn winds”, “winter”, or “mischef
and strife” in this entry. The noble in question will always have powers
relating to this area of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, a coure of mischief and strife is a pointy-eared Loki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This coure is a Level 17 Lurker with 129 HP. It has the usual low-light vision
and Fey Step ability, which in this case is completely redundant because the
coure also has a teleport speed of 6 to complement its ground speed of 6. It
wears leathers and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;rapier&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coure can become &lt;strong&gt;invisible&lt;/strong&gt; at will as a standard action, and this lasts
until it takes damage or &lt;em&gt;misses&lt;/em&gt; with an attack. If it attacks and hits, it
stays invisible! If for some reason the eladrin doesn’t already starts the fight
invisible, this is going to be its very first action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the invisible trickster is close to the party, &lt;strong&gt;Winds of Luck’s Mischief&lt;/strong&gt;
is a good fight opener: a Close Burst 3 vs. Will that does no damage, but makes
everyone it affects miss all attacks whose attack rolls were odd. This is a
“save ends” condition, so it might stick around for a while! Good luck trying to
damage an invisible enemy when half of your blows veer off course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While invisible the coure can also use &lt;strong&gt;Spark of Strife&lt;/strong&gt;, a Ranged 10 attack
vs. Will that deals psychic damage and is stronger than the rapier. A hit also
forces the target to charge its nearest ally, or make a melee basic attack if
it’s already close. This compelled attack is a free action, so it doesn’t eat
into the PC’s turn. However, if the compelled attack hits, the coure gets to use
Spark of Strife against the ally that was hit by it as a free action as well! A
series of lucky rolls is going to rapidly turn the party’s well-tuned battle
formation into a Three Stooges skit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter here is level 10: 3 bladesingers, an eladrin twilight
incanter from the first MM, and a will-o’-wisp which I guess might be the
incanter’s familiar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how the different eladrin celestial types from 3e became a bizarre system
of nobility ranks with a lot of that good faerie flavor. As one rises in rank,
one becomes less tied to the mortal world.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/07/eladrin.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/07/eladrin.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Duergar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-duergar.webp&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chronologically, the first appearance of Duergar in 4e is in the Monster Manual
2, but they were also in the Monster Vault so we covered their basic lore
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In this post, we’ll covered the duergar that appeared in the MM2 but
weren’t updated in the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;previously-on-octopus-carnival&quot;&gt;Previously on Octopus Carnival…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For your information, these are the duergar entries we covered &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;:
Scout, Guard, Thug, Raid Leader, Infernal Consort, and Devil-Bred Duergar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This still leaves us with a sizable selection of stat blocks that didn’t make it
into the Monster Vault. They include some elite warrior types, and several
Hell-themed spellcasters that resemble either warlocks or clerics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in that earlier post, all duergar share two signature traits:
resistance to fire and poison that increases with their level, and the ability
to shoot out their Infernal Quills at someone, once per fight as a minor
action. This has a Range of 3, does light physical damage and a tiny bit of
ongoing poison damage. It also inflicts a -2 penalty to attack rolls. A single
save ends both the ongoing damage and the attack penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-theurge&quot;&gt;Duergar Theurge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weakest of the spellcasters we’re going to look at here. Theurges wear robes
and wield warhammers in melee. At range they fight with a number of spells
themed around fire, smoke, and despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the name they feel a bit more wizardly than the others, who are more
clearly priests of some kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theurges are Level 5 Controllers with 63 HP. They wear robes and fight with
&lt;strong&gt;warhammers&lt;/strong&gt; in melee. Their basic ranged attacks are &lt;strong&gt;Hellbolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Reflex) that do fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a few more powerful spells. &lt;strong&gt;Brimstone Hail&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5-6)
does fire damage over a fireball-sized area and knocks targets prone on a
hit. &lt;strong&gt;Vile Fumes&lt;/strong&gt; (recharges when first bloodied) does poison damage over the
same area and blinds for a turn on a hit. And &lt;strong&gt;Wave of Despair&lt;/strong&gt; is a daily
blast 5 vs. Will and does psychic damage, slows, and dazes (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-shock-trooper&quot;&gt;Duergar Shock Trooper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shock troopers are somewhat similar to the guards we saw in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;the first
article&lt;/a&gt;, but stronger and more suited to open warfare. They wield mauls
instead of puny warhammers and have the ability to grow bigger when the fight
grows more intense!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troopers are Level 6 Brutes with 84 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;mauls&lt;/strong&gt; have no special effects
aside from hitting hard, and their &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Quills&lt;/strong&gt; attack works as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When first bloodied, they can &lt;strong&gt;Expand&lt;/strong&gt; as a free action, growing to size
Large. This makes them take up 4 squares and pushes anyone who was adjacent to
make room for their new bulk. It also gives them a +2 attack bonus and a +5
damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-fleshtearer&quot;&gt;Duergar Fleshtearer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a name “Fleshtearer”, you’d expect this duergar to be a mindless berserker,
but it’s actually a sneaky magical assassin that fights with claws made of smoke
and can become invisible to better slice you with them and make your wounds
bleed faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-number&quot;&gt;The Number&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleshtearers are Level 11 Lurkers with 89 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; also do ongoing
damage. If they have combat advantage they can instead attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Quill
Stab&lt;/strong&gt; that has the same effect as the signature Infernal Quills power as a
melee attack. This one recharges whenever the duergar hits with the basic claw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Underdark Sneak&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action) requires them to be in dim light or darkness,
or adjacent to some cover. It makes them invisible for a turn or until right
after they attack. &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Scourge&lt;/strong&gt; is a passive trait that builds on this by
doubling the ongoing damage the duergar causes if it attacks from invisibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-hellcaller&quot;&gt;Duergar Hellcaller&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This caster-type has focused their infernal magic on having the most fabulous
set of quills in the Underdark. They can fire quills all day long, unlike their
less well-endowed compatriots. Rounding out their arsenal is a small set of
diabolic curses and summoning spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellcallers are Level 12 Artillery with 96 HP. They wield &lt;strong&gt;maces&lt;/strong&gt; for
emergency, but as usual for artillery monsters the real interesting bits are the
ranged attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Quills&lt;/strong&gt; are an at-will Ranged 10 attack, and have the same
effects as the encounter version for other duergar. They can momentarily
increase their rate of fire to make this attack as a minor action, and to fire
off a &lt;strong&gt;Quill Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (area 2 within 10 vs. Reflex) that covers an area and
deals more ongoing damage than usual. Both of these special uses are encounter
powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can also conjure &lt;strong&gt;Asmodeus’s Ruby Curse&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast
5 vs. Will; enemies only) that deals psychic damage and slides those hits to the
outside of the affected area. This movement &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; provoke opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone manages to get close enough to make a melee attack against the
hellcaller, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Devilish Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt. This causes the
duergar to shift beyond the attack’s reach, and to summon a legion devil
hellguard into its former position. The attack targets the new minion, and if it
misses the devil gets to act right after the hellcaller in the initiative order
from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-blackguard&quot;&gt;Duergar Blackguard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evil paladin-type uses its martial skills and magic powers to isolate and
pursue individual PCs across the battlefield. It wears plate and wields both a
shield and a warhammer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-3&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 13 Elite Soldier with 260 HP. Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Blighted
Warhammer&lt;/strong&gt; that deals damage as usual and triggers a secondary attack against
Fortitude with similar effects to the standard Infernal Quills power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blackguard’s own quills are a bit stronger than usual, replacing the
standard power with a &lt;strong&gt;Quill Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage in a Close Burst
3 around the duergar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “isolate and pursue” part comes from a pair of abilities: &lt;strong&gt;Darkfire Mark&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor action 1/round) marks an enemy and compels it to approach and attack the
blackguard - if the enemy fails to do both in its next turn, it takes 10 fire
and necrotic damage. &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Footwork&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that allows the
blackguard to shift 2 squares in pursuit of an adjacent enemy who tries to get
away from it. If that enemy is marked, the blackguard also gets to make a hammer
attack against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar-blasphemer&quot;&gt;Duergar Blasphemer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strongest priest-type we’ll see here, weaker only than the Infernal Consort
from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/10/duergar.html&quot;&gt;Monster Vault article&lt;/a&gt;. Like the Hellcaller, the Blasphemer also
has Big Quill Energy, though its other magic is more focused on disruptive mind
control effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-4&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blasphemers are Level 14 Controllers (Leaders) with 140 HP who wield
&lt;strong&gt;greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt; in battle. Like Hellcallers, they can fire &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Quills&lt;/strong&gt; at
will and use a Quick Quill Strike once per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the quills, they have three spells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preach Submission&lt;/strong&gt; (Close burst 10 vs. Will; minor action 1/round) does no
damage but marks on a hit (save ends). An already-marked target is instead
knocked prone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eyes of Asmodeus&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) also does no damage, but
weakens and marks for a turn on a hit. On a miss, or as an after-effect on a
hit, the target is slowed (save ends). This combos nicely with Preach
Submission to knock someone prone immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sinner’s Slip&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt that redirects an attack made against the
blasphemer to the attacker’s closest ally. If no allies can be targeted in
this way the attacker is instead knocked prone and takes some psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one sample encounter here. It’s Level 4, consisting of 2 guards, 1
scout, 1 theurge, and 4 orc drudges that are probably their slaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sure is a lot of duergar, and it further increases the variety and level
range of the available opposition if you want your PCs to go up against a whole
fortress full of them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/06/duergar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/06/duergar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
