<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 01:28:30 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 01:28:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merging GURPS Weapon Skills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Peter V. Dell’Orto made a post in his blog Dungeon Fantastic about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/07/possible-weapon-skill-mergers-for-gurps.html&quot;&gt;merging GURPS weapon skills&lt;/a&gt;. I really, really like the idea, so I thought
about writing about how I’d do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dell’Orto’s post is specific to Dungeon Fantasy and to his own Felltower
campaign. Mine is a bit more generic since I don’t have an active campaign
going, and I tend to kind of mix up Dungeon Fantasy and default GURPS rules in
my head. Consider it an addition to my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/12/18/house-style.html&quot;&gt;House Style&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for doing this is also pretty well-covered by this &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/08/why-all-merging.html&quot;&gt;follow-up Dungeon
Fantastic Post&lt;/a&gt;: having too many fine distinctions between spells and skills
in a cinematic campaign can serve as a bit of a damper on the pacing and
excitement of the campaign. My usual players tend to have a certain resistance
to trying stuff that’s not on their character sheets, especially in a complex
system like GURPS, so having broader traits would allow them to experiment a bit
more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-skills&quot;&gt;The Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns where this post is in effect, I’m going to use the following list
of weapon skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Axe/Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This skill is a combination of the original &lt;strong&gt;Axe/Mace&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt;. When
using a flail, the character suffers a -1 skill penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games that use Techniques, &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt; is a new Hard technique that defaults to
Skill-1 and has a maximum level equal to Skill. This means you can buy the -1
penalty off for 2 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fencing-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Fencing (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new skill merges &lt;strong&gt;Rapier&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Saber&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Smallsword&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows you to
use not only these three “titular” weapons, but also any other weapon that would
fall under those skills, such as the jian (Rapier) or the light stick
(Smallsword).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the normal rules for fencing weapons apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;force-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Force Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-3, One-Handed Sword-3, Two-handed Sword-3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should I ever play a science fiction game with force swords, this gets merged
with &lt;strong&gt;Force Saber&lt;/strong&gt;. Whether you get fencing parries or not depends on the stat
line of the weapon you’re using. The “Fencing parries for everyone!” option is
also valid in a more explicitly Star Warsy game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;knife-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Knife (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges the original &lt;strong&gt;Knife&lt;/strong&gt; skill with &lt;strong&gt;Jitte/Sai&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Main-Gauche&lt;/strong&gt;. Any weapon that could be used with either of these can be used
with the new skill. Weapons use their Main-Gauche profiles for this, meaning
there’s no penalty for using the off hand and the user gets fencing parries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, “knife expert” PCs always went for Main-Gauche anyway. People
who dropped a point in Knife as a back-up skill almost never ende up using it,
so they can just drop a point in this one instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jutte and the Sai get both a +2 for disarm attempts and fencing parries
without any special stance switches required. They are rare enough in my games
that I don’t believe it will be a problem. And by “rare” I mean no one has taken
these weapons and no one has tried a disarm yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;One-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4, Two-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the skill used for all one-handed swords, merging both &lt;strong&gt;Broadsword&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Shortsword&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blade length is an important consideration in real life, but it’s below the
level of granularity I prefer. This also broadens the range of really cool magic
swords your sword-wielding players can find and immediately use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pole-weapons-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Pole Weapons (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Sword-5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges &lt;strong&gt;Polearm&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Staff&lt;/strong&gt;. The Form Mastery perk is
redundant for these weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about that sweet Staff parry bonus? If it’s in your weapon’s stat line
under Staff, you get it. If it’s not, you don’t. The only exception to this are
balanced two-handed spears, which I feel should have the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Axe-Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Axe/Mace, but for two-handed weapons. The same rules apply for two-handed
flails, including the existence of a Hard technique to buy the -1 penalty off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much the same skill as the original, with a suitably altered list
of defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-all-the-other-skills&quot;&gt;What about all the other skills?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the more exotic weapon skills, like Whip, Kusari, and Tonfa, remain the
same. I might change my mind in the future and come back to this, but I haven’t
actually used any of them in my games, so it makes no difference for them to
stay as-is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-rule-weapon-familiarity&quot;&gt;Optional Rule: Weapon Familiarity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like how these skills are merged, but still feel a staff user shouldn’t
be able to pick up a halberd and wield it just as proficiently right away, then
you can use a version of the Familiarity rules from the GURPS core book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs are considered familiar with any weapons they acquire during character
creation. If they pick up a weapon that would be used with a different skill
under the standard rules, they have a -2 penalty to use that weapon until they
can spend a few hours practicing with it. This takes time but costs no money or
points. In effect, it can only happen when the PCs have a significant amount of
downtime (such as when returning to town from a dungeon in DF). After this, the
PC is considered familiar with that weapon type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this up as an option, but it’s not one I’ll use myself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Star Wars RPGs and The Force: A Thought</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/Princess-Leia-Shirt.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heruniverse.com/product/star-wars-princess-leia-self-rescuing-princess-t-shirt/10920417.html&quot;&gt;
     Image source.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t part of a series or anything, but it’s a random though I’ve been
having and I feel it’s worth turning into a post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-thought&quot;&gt;The Thought&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I ever to a Star Wars adaptation, it’s going to be one where everybody is
Force-sensitive. Let’s do away with the absolutist “magic/no-magic” divide
inspired by D&amp;amp;D that all the official RPGs so far have used. If the Force is
described in the source material as being in everyone, then it should &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; in in
everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players would not be forced to play Jedi - rather, the badassitude of their PCs
would be explained by their connection to the Force. No more of that nonsense
about how “you can still be cool even though you’re blind to the Force”. No,
you’re cool because you opened yourself to it. It’s everywhere, and getting past
a certain threshold of skill at any endeavor means becoming attuned to the
Force. By definition, any character who is PC material in the sort of heroic
story Star Wars favors is past that threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, yeah, you can still be a Jedi who throws stuff around telekinetically and
parries blaster bolts with a lightsaber, but you can also be an amazing
gunfighter from the slums of Coruscant who can &lt;em&gt;dodge&lt;/em&gt; blasters, react to stuff
before it happens, and make shots that ricochet from five different surfaces
before hitting some impossibly small target. And maybe both of you can jump
really high because that’s always useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a set of Force-based mechanics that all PCs gets access to, even if they
have the least mystical background possible. They can use it to perform
impossible feats of skill and luck. They can have intuitions and
premonitions. Maybe they can study a mystical tradition to do more overtly
supernatural stuff, but that’s not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe one of the reasons the Dark Side and the Empire are evil is that
they’re the ones who believe that only a select few elites should be given
access to the Force.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/14/star-wars.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/14/star-wars.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>star-wars</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Post Cyberpunk!</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/800517c403ee40194b3e22356dfe823a.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=https://www.deviantart.com/hidrico/art/Style-Over-Substance-Cyberpunk-2077-802599843&gt;
      By Hidrico on DeviantArt
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned back in my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/05/19/cp-red-review.html&quot;&gt;Cyberpunk RED review&lt;/a&gt;, I felt the game didn’t
quite clear my “Threshold of GURPS”. This particular term is new but the idea
itself is almost exactly 5 years old now. I first mentioned it in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/21/to-gurps-or-not-to-gurps.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;, where I discussed what makes me want to reach for GURPS in an
adaptation and what makes me look for other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CP RED’s native system is fine! The reason I say it didn’t “clear the threshold”
is that it’s exactly the sort of system and setting described in the “When to
GURPS” section of that 2017 post. It worries about modeling specific concrete
actions, and it worries about the details of how they’re executed. In addition
to this, the system itself doesn’t have any mechanical novelties that aren’t
reproducible in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, while I’d happily play the native system in a one-shot or something
like that, given enough time to prepare I’d prefer to adapt its setting to
GURPS. Talking about how I’d do it is an excellent excuse for an Octopus
Carnival post. It helps that “Cyberpunk” has been one of the genres GURPS set
out to support since its beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-1-high-concept&quot;&gt;Part 1: High Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk-the-setting is actually a fairly broad place that supports a large
variety of campaigns… but most people seem to be fans of that fairly narrow
slice of stylish street mercs pulling heists for money and/or personal
reasons. I’m not gonna lie, I’m like most people in that regard and so I’m going
to focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the setting has three distinct “eras” now, they all look and feel mostly
the same. The main changes are to the map of Night City and the specific reason
why Johnny Silverhand is raiding Arasaka Tower this time. I think we might be
able to condense that long timeline down a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to mix in my personal preferences: I believe cyberpunk doesn’t
&lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be a dystopia. This is something you might have gathered from my
previous posts on the subject. I find a lot of cyberpunk settings tend to
confuse “things are bad” with “things can never get better”, and I don’t want to
do that here. For Cyberpunk Red specifically, this ends up resulting into a game
that tells players simple survival is the most they can expect in the same book
where it touts the epic exploits of Bartmoss and Silverhand. I want to treat
them as “iconic” characters in the modern sense, which means that if those
clowns can do all this, so can the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we are: a game about stylish street mercs in the neon-lit future, living
in the fictional Night City. They get into noir-ish situations for money, and
see them through for personal reasons. Hostile factions are mostly corporations,
crime syndicates, or violent themed gangs with corporate ties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though PCs often fight for personal stakes they can still end up having a big
impact in the setting&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. PCs who are smart about it and make use of collective
action can make big, lasting, positive change, but even more traditional “band
of badasses” actions will still do something. Not every campaign has to be about
this, but the play style should be possible and supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-2-time-and-place&quot;&gt;Part 2: Time and Place&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, it’s Night City in the neon-lit cyber future. Feel free to
use the present date that suits you best. Set it in one of the official dates of
the original game. Set it in 2100 just to spite Transhuman Space. Make it 20XX,
21XX, 22XX, whatever. Or be like William Gibson and never even mention calendar
years. The backstory follows the same general lines of the original, using
relative dates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifty-something years ago the US government descended further into fascist
stupidity than ever before&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Over the next few decades its economy and
environment crashed big time, the entire West Coast seceded, and the government
was either powerless to stop the rise of the megacorps or was actively helping
them along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-something years ago Johhny Silverhand performed his one and only raid on
Arasaka Tower, which is more or less a combination of the events from the 2013
and 2023 raids in the original chronology. Arasaka’s nuke blows up, and the
political and literal fallout from this causes heavy backlash against megacorps
in general all over the world. Though many are still around, they can no longer
do whatever the fuck they want without fear of consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our narrative present is a blend of CP RED and 2077. Night city rebuilt enough
to leave “survival mode”, but it’s still something of a crime capital where the
corps have lots of influence and habitually pay those themed gangs to do their
dirty work. It also has a relatively large “edgerunner” culture with its own
honor codes and a surprisingly large propensity to take jobs from people who are
neither corp- nor gang- affiliated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of past wars to be a veteran of. The most recent one was
the Corp War that finally died down let’s say 5 years ago. It featured lots of
big corps going at each other, and lots of governments cracking down on them for
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberware is common enough that most people sport at least a bit of
“fashionware” from their late teens onwards. Most people won’t cut off healthy
limbs in order to replace them, but there are plenty of maimed veterans and
victims of disease for whom cybernetic replacements are an appealing
prospect. Implanted augmentations are somewhat more common, with the most
popular by far being a GitS-style “cyberbrain” implanted computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guns and armored clothing are common and relatively easy to get in Night
City. This is not generally a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; thing, and contributes to the city’s still
dismal violence statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertisements are nowhere near as aggressive and explicit as they are in
CP 2077. The real world is bad enough on that front that you don’t need to
further “enhance” it to make a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rache Bartmoss did not “destroy” the NET, because we don’t need to justify rules
changes with an in-setting event. Feral AI gods running on mutated data centers
is too good an image to pass up, though, so those are still there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-3-characters-and-their-stuff&quot;&gt;Part 3: Characters and Their Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of our rules is going to be GURPS Action, because this is a game about
action heroes. The default is that players get to build their PCs using the
250-point archetypes from GURPS Action 1. This makes them experienced
edgerunners. Greenhorns would use the lower-point templates from Specialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our default ruleset is the one from GURPS Action 2, with the main changes to
that being due to the science fiction elements we’re introducing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gear-and-cyberware&quot;&gt;Gear and Cyberware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base tech level is 9, though TL8 gear is still widely available. We’re
either not that far into the future or it’s simply easier to print at home than
the more advanced stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers and biotech are at TL10. You can run a mind emulation from a
portable system, and miraculous speed-healing drugs are available. Implants are
drawn from Ultra-Tech and Bio-Tech and are mostly TL9, though some TL10 things
that appear in the CP books would also be available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberware &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; inherently erode your humanity. Not even if you replace
your healthy bits with chrome that’s better than human standard. We use the
usual GURPS mechanics of making implants cost character points at character
creation and both points and money afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any template can spend its discretionary points on cyberware from Ultra-Tech or
implants from Bio-Tech. This means most PCs might have one or two implants to
start with, though having none is also a valid choice. Campaigns where the PCs
are meant to start out chromed to the gills might give them 25 or 50 extra
points to spend on starting cyberware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;netrunning&quot;&gt;Netrunning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hacking, I want a streamlined system. The one from Pyramid #3/21 is a good
start, since one of its goals is to prevent the isolation from the classic
“dungeon crawl” system of CP 2020. However, I want to rely even less on virtual
reality and be more like Ghost in the Shell or CP 2077.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prospective hacker needs a Neural Interface Implant of some sort (UT,
p. 216). A &lt;em&gt;cyberdeck&lt;/em&gt; is either a Computer Implant (Complexity 5, UT p. 215) or
a small computer (Complexity 6, UT p. 22) with a cable jack and a tiny radio
communicator, but without any built-in terminal. The “default” interface tier is
“Augmented Reality”, where the hacker sees the necessary interfaces alongside
the physical world. It’s possible to go “Full Immersion”, which is faster but
leaves the character effectively unconscious in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters running AR have a -2 penalty in opposed tests against characters
running Full Immersion. This is the only game effect, so it’s only worth giving
up your physical senses when you run into an immersed enemy hacker or an enemy
AI (which always counts as immersed). Programs and skills are the same as in the
Pyramid article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest change from the Pyramid article is in level design. Generally
speaking, “interesting” hackable servers and networks are not directly connected
to the public Internet, and the hacker PC must be on-site to access them. The
smallest and most common target is a single device with a basic firewall,
usually something like a security camera or an automatic door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sites with better security link their devices into a slightly larger
network. This is a bit more similar to the design examples of the Pyramid
article, but remember not to make them too large. Such a network might encompass
all security devices in a given floor. No connecting through a megacorp’s
top-secret research server through the vending machines in the lobby!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;People&lt;/em&gt; might also be a valid target for hacking, if they have those
nearly-ubiquitous computer implants. The implant can have any defenses that
could be installed in a computer of the same Complexity and usually contains at
least a basic firewall. Overcoming those defenses might allow netrunners to
“jam” the target’s senses with spurious sensory data or even run the Damage
program. Savvier opposition might link their internal computers into a more
secure network overseen by a friendly hacker, or just turn the their wi-fi off
entirely if it doesn’t confer any combat benefit to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. That’s enough to play your classic edgerunners in the
Cyberpunk 2020/RED/2077 setting. Any of the Screamsheets from 2020 or RED should
be readily adaptable, since they have little in the way of stats to begin
with. The gigs and side jobs from 2077 also provide plentiful inspiration and
material for tabletop adventures, and that game’s main plot gives you an idea of
what the sort of “high impact” adventure that leaves a crater looks like. You
might need a bit more thought to devise adventures about organizing collective
action, but they’re also quite possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Possibly leaving a big crater. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you’re using a 2077 date, that’s Trump’s thankfully fictional second
mandate starting in 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/23/one-post-cyberpunk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/23/one-post-cyberpunk.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Exalted Martial Arts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s this post on Mailanka’s Musings that talks about two different ways of
modeling martial arts in RPGs. The first is something he calls “Move-Based”, and
the second “Skill-Based”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based martial arts is how most RPGs in the 90’s did it. You bought a style,
and that gave you access to a series of “moves” that were essentially special
powers with individual rules for what they did. Some systems made you buy each
individual move as well, usually as a way to model your progression in the
style - advanced practitioners know more moves. Your move set is as or more
important than your raw skill level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skill-based martial arts are what GURPS does. Everyone uses the same skills to
fight, and knowing one style or another is mostly a matter of flavor with a few
minor mechanical bonuses thrown in. What really matters are your skill levels:
people with different style familiarities but similar skill levels are equally
effective. The same applies to someone who “knows” a style and someone who just
has the combat skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based rules might allow you to emulate some classic kung-fu stories that
are all about how some styles are objectively superior to others, or how there’s
a secret style or ultimate technique that’s jealously guarded by a cranky old
master. Skill-based rules are closer to Bruce Lee’s philosophy, or modern views
of martial arts in general, where individual skill is more important and the
“ultimate power” is learning from multiple sources and combining everything into
something that works for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer skill-based rules, largely due to my exposure to GURPS
Martial Arts for Fourth edition. Everything it introduces can be done by someone
who isn’t using the style rules. It covers styles from the whole world without
treating any of them as inherently superior, and it acknowledges that basically
any organized system of fighting counts as a “style”. The “generic swings” other
systems describe as the standard form of fighting only happen if you’re
completely untrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this preference, it comes as no surprise that I have a few weirdly
specific hangups about how Exalted handles its martial arts. Let’s talk about
them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exalteds-martial-arts&quot;&gt;Exalted’s Martial Arts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exalted’s &lt;em&gt;whole system&lt;/em&gt; is entirely move-based. Every PC has a large set
of “Charms” that are usually linked to skills, and represent magic techniques
they can use to enhance uses of that skill. Getting to the maximum possible
skill level is trivial, and it’s your Charms that make the difference when going
against similarly supernatural opposition. This goes even for non-combat skills,
though the fighty bits tend to take up a lot of attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martial Arts are part of this system, but the game still takes pains to make
them extra-special, even as it struggles to explain what makes them different
from standard combat powers. Exalted First Edition had a separate Martial Arts
skill, whose associated Charms were structured as “Martial Arts Styles”. They
didn’t really “mix” with charms of other skills. As a result, a lot of each
style’s Charms end up duplicating the effect of basic combat Charms in different
ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second Edition merged “standard” unarmed combat and Martial Arts, and made it a
little easier to mix and match charms from a few different styles. Third Edition
doubled down on the original position and made it so each style had its own
separate skill, thus coming full circle on the ‘martial arts cost more because
they are exotic and special’ trope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-id-do-it&quot;&gt;How I’d Do It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had I been writing these rules, I’d probably take them in a different direction
entirely, and more towards the way GURPS sees things. There would be no Martial
Arts skill. Each style is associated with a single standard combat skill, and
consists of exactly three Charms representing its advanced or iconic
techniques. The basic stuff is already covered by the standard skill and
standard Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Charms I’d reuse the “lotus” metaphor, so they would be the Root, Bulb
and Blossom Charms. You learn them in this order. Each has the previous one as a
prerequisite, and probably an increasing Essence score. They’re meant to be
combined with the standard Charms for that skill, relying on them for the basic
dice-adding mechanics and such. If you know Charms of multiple styles you can
explicitly combine them as long as the combination is otherwise rules-legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who learns to fight is a martial artist, even if they never pick up
style Charms. Every martial artist ultimately develops their own personal style
by learning from as many sources as possible and keeping what works for
them. And you can certainly describe the way your kung-fu looks as being a
certain style even if you don’t have the Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example-snake-style&quot;&gt;Example: Snake Style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t originally plan on doing this, but what the heck, let’s go! Snake Style
has traditionally been the main corebook style, so let’s see how it would look
in this format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what the lore says about it: it’s a style focused on speed and
precision, aiming to take down better armed and armored opponents before they
have time to act. It uses two-fingered strikes to hit pressure points and
exposed tendons. Masters of the style can “pierce through armor”, “paralyze
opponents with pressure point strikes”, and “deliver poisonous Essence through
their fingertips”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of what to keep in our new format is pretty easy - each of the things
masters of the style can do references a specific Charm. We want those. All the
others increase basic numbers in different ways and can be replaced by standard
charms from Brawl and other trees. Want to dodge like a snake? Take Dodge
Charms. Want the “tough scales” effect? Take Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our new Snake Style is an unarmed style linked to Brawl. Our Root Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Crippling Pressure Point Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (Ex3 p. 428). Our Bulb Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Armor-Penetrating Fang Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Our Blossom Charm is &lt;strong&gt;Essence Venom
Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Their skill level and Essence prerequisites remain the same, but read
Brawl in place of Martial Arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quick and dirty sketch, and some additional work would be
required. Essence Venom Strike needs to be rewritten a bit, since half of its
effects reference Charms we’ve eliminated. We might also want to rewrite some of
the base Brawl charms, though I haven’t looked at them in much depth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>exalted</category>
        
        <category>martial-arts</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nordlond Bestiary Kickstarter Campaign</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit late to the promotion bandwagon for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;Nordlond Bestiary&lt;/a&gt;, since
there’s only a few days left in the project. But I’m still going to say it: go
back the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;Nordlond Bestiary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is already funded. If you back the project, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get your
reward, and you’ll be contributing to possibly making it &lt;em&gt;bigger&lt;/em&gt;. There’s a
chance it might make the first stretch goal, which means 16 extra pages full of
undead abominations for use in any GURPS campaign that needs monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the classic complaints of many new and veteran GURPS players is the lack
of a “proper monster book” for GURPS 4th Edition. Lots of books include a small
sample selection and tips on making more yourself, but there’s no official
“one-stop-shop” for ready-made critter stat blocks. And of course, this being
GURPS it’s kinda hard to make a truly generic monster book, since whether a
given monster is an impossible challenge or a mere speedbump depends on who your
PCs are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nordlond Bestiary is probably the closest we can get to that mythic book - a
chunky selection of creatures suitable for Dungeon Fantasy campaigns. DF has a
well-known starting point total and a known set of PC templates, you can easily
know how the monsters are callibrated. And it’s also the genre that’s more
likely to need a “monster book” anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book will be made for use with the DFRPG boxed set, but it’s also perfectly
usable with the GURPS core books if that’s what you have. And since you know
what sort of PC these monsters were made to fight, you can also adjust them for
your specific campaign more easily.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/02/nordlond-bestiary.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/02/nordlond-bestiary.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nordlond Bestiary Kickstarter!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gaming Ballistic is about to launch a campaign for the Nordlond Bestiary, and
you can go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; to click a button and be notified of when that
happens. Everyone always says GURPS really needs a good bestiary. Well, here’s
one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributing to Kickstarter campaigns is a bit hard for me, as my bank dislikes
it and tries to cancel my credit card whenever I do it. But if that’s not a
problem for you, by all means click that button. I’ll be here waiting for the
book’s final launch to buy myself a copy in the traditional way :).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/05/nordlond-bestiary.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/05/nordlond-bestiary.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>kickstarter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on LANCER Against the Giants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember reading a few play reports about a campaign titled “Mecha Against the
Giants” a few years ago. It was run by Mark Langsdorf, using GURPS as a rule
system, and it was vaguely inspired by the Against the Giants modules for AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these days, I really want to run something like that using LANCER. As of
this writing I definitely don’t have the bandwidth for it, but I just thought it
would be nice to write it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lancer-against-the-giants&quot;&gt;LANCER: Against the Giants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armies of Giants invade, out of nowhere and for seemingly no reason!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their relentless assaults threaten to destroy “smallfolk” civilization!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The realm’s bravest heroes have fallen against their foe’s overwhelming strength
and numbers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desperate, the King’s wizards and priests spend the last of their power in a
rituat. It purpose: to summon someone, &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; from across the vastness of
existance that has the power to stop the destruction!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They succeed in bringing the 2021st Union Auxiliary Squadron. Your squadron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount up, Lancer, and end this war!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fight off attacking giants and their pet giant monsters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discover the mystery behind these invasions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find a way to end this war that &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; involve genocide, because we’re better
than Gygax!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, at the end of it all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ATTACK AND DETHRONE LOLTH&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/25/musings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/25/musings.html</guid>
        
        <category>lancer</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>De-monk-ifying Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/marching-fire.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Is this guy a Martial Artist? A Swashbuckler? A Knight? Yes.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy has the Swashbuckler template. Swashbucklers are physical
combatants who prioritize mobility and precision over heavy armor and brute
strength. They use a specialized set of weapons, are obsessed with improving
their skill, and strive to learn secret techniques of legendary reputation and
effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy also has the Martial Artist template. Martial artists are
physical combatants who prioritize mobility and precision over heavy armor and
brute strength. They use a specialized set of weapons, are obsessed with
improving their skill, and strive to learn secret techniques of legendary
reputation and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, those descriptions use most of the same words. When you look at these two
professional templates from a large enough distance, they really are two takes
on the same concept. They could, in theory, be represented by the same
template. The reason Martial Artist is a separate archetype in Dungeon Fantasy
is because Monk is a separate class in D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the reason Monk is a separate class in D&amp;amp;D, as far as I can tell, is because
of a particular set of media cliches that have surrounded the words “martial
arts” in a lot of media contemporary with earlier editions of D&amp;amp;D. I guess you
could call it a form of orientalism&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some of these media sources, “martial arts” are this mysterious and exotic
secret from the mysterious and exotic East, much more sophisticated than the
crude flailings of Western barbarians. Knowing it makes you more “enlightened”
and gives you superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In others, they’re this fancy dance for pansies that’s totally ineffective in a
“true” fight, because a Real Man knows he just has to punch the other guy. The
Real Man in this scenario is of course always a man, and always Western too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D monks were originally based on this character named Remo Williams, the
protagonist of the Destroyer series of novels. These novels came out in the 70s,
and they were very much in the “exotic secret that gives you superpowers”
camp. Williams learned a fictional martial art from an exotic foreign master and
proceeded to use it to defeat a string of (usually Asian) bad guys. D&amp;amp;D writers
applied a “shaolin” veneer to the class in later editions but many monk
abilities are still based on stuff Williams did in the novels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS replicated this in Dungeon Fantasy because it tries to replicate D&amp;amp;D, but
its “default” approach to martial arts turns out to be a lot better in my
opinion. It has a supplement named GURPS Martial Arts that treats historical
styles from all over the world with the same level of respect. The message
contained in its rules seems to be that these styles are all different
expressions of the same thing&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. How good an individual combatant is matters a
lot more than where his techniques come from. I really liked that when I first
read it, and I’ve only grown to like it more over the years. It kinda bothers me
to see a game that still treats the subject in that older “Destroyer” way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every character who practices a fighting style and trains to improve their skill
at it is a martial artist by definition, no matter &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; that fighting style
comes from. Whether that training gives you superpowers has always been more of
a genre or campaign “setting” than something that should be assigned to
individual character types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the dungeon fantasy genre, that particular setting is obviously
stuck on “yes”. Every PC can perform impossible feats of badassery, that has
been a given since the very beginning&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Someone who comes from a culture that
talks about things in terms of Chi will likely describe any such character as
possessing “strong chi”. Someone who doesn’t will just describe them as being
really good at fighting. This in no way changes the fundamentals of how their
abilities work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s what I’m going to do in my campaigns from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demonkified-dungeon-fantasy&quot;&gt;Demonkified Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chi Mastery no longer exists as a specific power. There is no Chi Talent, and
all its component abilities lose the power modifier along with the associated
discounts and drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only have access to the DFRPG, do this instead: if a former Chi ability
is described as “working like” another trait, you can buy that trait
instead. For example, Tough Skin instead of Dragon Skin, and Striking ST instead
of Mantis Strike. For abilities that have no parallel… keep the same cost,
it’s simpler. In all cases you no longer get a bonus for Chi Talent, but you
also no longer need Disciplines of Faith: Chi Rituals to keep them either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Swashbuckler and Martial Artist become related templates. A Swashbuckler
gains access to the Martial Artist’s abilities and power-ups, and
vice-versa. Characters of each template might still look and behave very
differently on a role-playing level, but there isn’t any fundamental difference
in their mechanics any more. The 30 points that would go to Chi Talent in the
Martial Artist template are instead avaialble to be spent on any template
advantages or skills. And there you go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re also using &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html&quot;&gt;Streamlined Mastery&lt;/a&gt;, this means that a PC built using
the Martial Artist template could start off with True Master and Iron Limbs for
the same cost as the official Trained By a Master and Chi Talent 2 advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-knights&quot;&gt;What about Knights?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything I said about monks and swashbucklers in my introduction applies
equally well to Knights and the other “fighty” templates. However, I still want
to keep it as a separate template because it’s good to still have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt;
guidance when building characters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Combatant who prefers strength and heavy gear” is different enough from
“combatant who prefers precision and speed” to remain a useful distinction. I’d
still allow some judicious cross-aisle shopping for traits that make sense for a
specific PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, combining this with some form of &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/08/30/agnostic-dungeon-fantasy.html&quot;&gt;Agnostic Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; (where
either no spellcaster is a priest or they all are) would leave us very close to
ditching templates entirely, or at least having a collection of “classes” that’s
much closer to that of the oldest of old D&amp;amp;Ds: “warrior” and “magic user”. Maybe
I’ll try that some day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-about-the-path&quot;&gt;What About the Path?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the side-boxes in the Dungeon Fantasy Companion 2 introduces the notion
of The Path, an alternate progression scheme that a Martial Artist PC can opt
into at character creation. Basically, it makes your Chi Talent levels limit how
many levels you can have in certain traits. As a result those limits are lower
to start with, but with enough time and points they can end up much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think The Path is more appropriate for a campaign that does the reverse of
what I’m trying to do here, where &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; uses chi mechanics. I’ll leave it
out of my games for now and maybe write about it at a future date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though of course I’m not an expert on the subject and will gladly defer to
people who are. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, Bruce Lee said this, and yes, the book does talk about him with great
admiration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Don’t even try to bring the Guy at the Gym fallacy into this. The guy at
the gym will never have 200 HP or be able to fight 50 goblins without
breaking a sweat. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/20/demonkification.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/20/demonkification.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Streamlined Melee Mastery for GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In GURPS, the Trained by a Master advantage allows a character to perform
martial feats on par with those seen in kung fu movies and other similar
stories. The Weapon Master advantage does basically the same in a slightly
different way. They overlap so much that I’m not sure if they were meant to
exist in the same campaign!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think both advantages are fairly priced on their own, but I don’t think both
of them combined are worth 75 points. Choosing to only allow one of them in your
campaign is a fairly simple matter, but what if you want to allow both,
potentially on the same character?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the differences between the two traits are fiddly matters of skill
coverage. Sweeping those aside leaves us with the remaining elephant in the
room, the Weapon Master damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elephant-examination-the-damage-bonus&quot;&gt;Elephant Examination: The Damage Bonus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the damage bonus is the biggest game changer in the entire WM
package. Even if a Weapon Master never learns a supernatural skill and never
attacks or parries more than once per turn, they’re still going to feel like an
entirely different character from someone who has the exact same stats but lacks
the advantage. It feels a bit unfair to me that this bonus is not available to
characters that focus on unarmed strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS uses realistic assumptions as a base for its rules, and under those
assumptions a combatant with a weapon always has a big advantage over one
without. The unarmed fighter risks limb injury on every parry and strike. The
armed one has greater reach and much better damage from using swing attacks or
simply from doing a better damage type than crushing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unarmed fighter with Trained By a Master can approach that by taking other
traits… But then they’ve spent 60 points and bought a Hard combat skill to be
on par with someone who bought an Average skill and took Weapon Master (single
weapon) for 20 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t feel a need to keep this “effectiveness gap” between armed and unarmed
skills when we’re dealing with a campaign that allows “mastery” advantages in
the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-traits&quot;&gt;New Traits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solution to the above situation is to rejigger the existing traits. The new
and altered traits below are available in any campaign that also allows both
Trained by a Master and Weapon Master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;true-master-50-points&quot;&gt;True Master (50 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through either decades of dedication or being some sort of war god, you have
mastered all forms of “archaic” combat. You gain &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the benefits from having
both Trained by a Master and the full version of Weapon Master. Your unarmed
strikes enjoy the same damage bonus described under Weapon Master. This bonus
&lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; stack with other bonuses from high striking skills and from traits like
Claws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those two advantages still exist, and represent a slightly less comprehensive
form of mastery. You can upgrade from any of them to True Master by spending the
difference between their point value and 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iron-limbs-10-points&quot;&gt;Iron Limbs (10 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your limbs are immune to incidental injury during unarmed combat. Enemies can’t
damage your limbs when they parry your unarmed attacks with a weapon, nor can
they switch targets and damage your limbs when you fail to parry their
attacks. You also don’t hurt yourself when hitting armored opponents with
unarmed strikes. Your limbs can still be deliberately targeted by enemy attacks,
however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trait replaces Unarmed Master, as it is basically Unarmed Master without
the damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like those two traits, though as of this writing I still need to actually
field-test them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns that use these two new advantages, an unarmed specialist &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt;
turn their limbs into Strikers. That’s what Unarmed Master did, and we did away
with it. IF the specialist in question happens to belong to a non-human species
that has natural Strikers, though, &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; would stack with True Master. Beware
of boxing crab-people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron Limbs doesn’t have any prerequisites: you could buy it without having any
of the “mastery” advantages. This allows it to be used to represent an extremely
focused blessing, or a creature whose limbs are naturally hard to hurt or even
naturally made of metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you feel 10 points for Iron Limbs is too expensive for someone who
is already a True Master, you could try rolling it into True Master at no extra
cost, and eliminating the separate Iron Limbs advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a GURPS Spaceplane: The Second Iteration</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/mac-rebisz-20150220-esa-spaceplane-001.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fictional ESA spaceplane.
    Illustration by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/3q14v&quot;&gt;Maciej Rebisz.&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/03/06/spaceplane.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we used GURPS Spaceships rules to build a “minimum
viable spaceplane” at TL8, with no superscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company, Octopus Aerospace, builds one of those and sells it to the
Kerbal Space Program for close to a billion GURPS dollars&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and after using
it for a few launches Director Kerbman comes back to us with a few change
requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His astronauts have complained that the Mark I Spaceplane handles very poorly
for its size. They’re entering a phase of their program where future missions
will require a lot of precise orbital maneuvers, like docking and such, so they
need a ship that can do better at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to satisfy KSP’s requests because we want a slice of their inifinte
budget, but we’re also committed to making only Single Stage To Orbit craft. How
can we satisfy both of these requirements?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-mark-ii&quot;&gt;Building the Mark II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still using “realistic” TL 8 for our Mark II, and it’s still streamlined
and winged just like its predecessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw in our previous post, a TL8 craft capable of reaching orbit can only
spare 10% of its mass to systems that are not fuel tanks or chemical engines. We
achieved that in the Mark I by shrinking our control systems and cargo bay,
filling the freed space with additional fuel tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want a full size control system for the second iteration, but having that
means we’ll be short on delta-V and can’t make an orbital insertion. We have to
shrink something else to compensate. We’re already shrunk the cargo bay, and I
don’t want to shrink the armor because I’m envisioning as the craft’s heat
shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about the engine?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our resulting configuration is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x Metallic Laminate Armor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x SM +8 control room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x 15-ton cargo bay&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;17.33 x Fuel Tanks (865 tons rocket fuel)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 x SM +7 Chemical Rocket Engine (1G Acceleration)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One lone G of acceleration is useless for leaving Earth… in a traditional
rocket. We have wings! According to GURPS Spaceships p. 37, a winged craft can
take off and reach Earth orbit even if its acceleration doesn’t exceed 1G.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That leaves us with the following stat line for our Mark II space plane:
&lt;strong&gt;dST/dHP&lt;/strong&gt; 70; &lt;strong&gt;Air Hnd/SR&lt;/strong&gt; +3/4; &lt;strong&gt;Space Hnd/SR&lt;/strong&gt; -2/4; &lt;strong&gt;Move&lt;/strong&gt; 1G/6.05mps;
&lt;strong&gt;LWt&lt;/strong&gt; 1000; &lt;strong&gt;Load&lt;/strong&gt; 15.3; &lt;strong&gt;SM&lt;/strong&gt; +8; &lt;strong&gt;Occ&lt;/strong&gt; 4; &lt;strong&gt;dDR&lt;/strong&gt; 0/2/0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model’s Air Handling and Stability is pretty awesome when compared to that
of most contemporary airplanes. Its space handling is still not exactly
spectacular, but it’s the best we can do for a ship of this size at TL 8, and
should help with those delicate maneuvers. It takes longer to reach orbit due to
its lower acceleration, but it still has the same Delta-V. Finally, it has space
for one additional crew member, allowing KSP to bring extra scientists or other
mission specialists along with the payload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheaper engine and more expensive control room balance themselves out. The
Mark II costs the same as the Mark I: a nominal $8.8M for the craft and $693,200
for a full load of rocket fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-notessales-pitch&quot;&gt;Bonus Notes/Sales Pitch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I forgot to mention in the previous post: both the Mark I and
Mark II Octopus Carnival Spaceplanes can take off from conventional runways,
dispensing with the need for an expensive launch pad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mark I would probably require a launchpad if you want to use those 3Gs of
acceleration right away, but if I remember correctly liquid fuel engines can be
throttled. So you can take off using a jet-engine-equivalent 1G and throttle up
when you reach a higher altitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you multiply their nominal cost by 100 for the extremely limited
production run, you still end up with a cost-effective system. SpaceX’s
semi-reusable rockets cost between $50M and $150M &lt;em&gt;per launch&lt;/em&gt;. The real-world
Space Shuttle cost between $500M and $1.5B per launch. The Saturn V cost about
$1.6B per launch in modern dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our fictional spaceplane would cost little more than the cost of a load of
fuel. Sure, it’d need to undergo maintenance between flights, but it probably
wouldn’t need to be practically rebuilt like the real-world systems. So perhaps
we’re looking at $2M per launch or so? It practically pays for itself in six
launches or so when compared to the “competition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, that’s a very optimistic assumption. In your games you’re always free
to assume Octopus Aerospace is full of shit and this thing is a lemon in all its
incarnations. It’s what prevented all those real world spaceplane projects from
going forward, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;$880M, or its nominal cost multiplied by 100 because it’s a production
run of one. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/10/spaceplane.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/03/10/spaceplane.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>spaceships</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
