<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 01:13:14 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 01:13:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Wilderness Hazards</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing our read of the Hazards section, we’ll now see a few Wilderness
hazards. These are all naturally occurring, and most are extra-dangerous
versions of the terrain we saw earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wilderness-hazards&quot;&gt;Wilderness Hazards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chokedust-cloud-level-2-lurker&quot;&gt;Chokedust Cloud (Level 2 Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more dangerous version of the stuff you might find in ash wastes, silt pools,
and deserts with particularly fine sand. This is a 3-by-3 area of particularly
fine and powdery stuff, and the slightest disturbance will cause it to form a
cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can roll Perception to notice the area is different, and if they pass
that first test they can roll an easier Nature one to learn exactly why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hazard triggers when someone steps into the area, or when a portion of it is
included in a blast or burst attack. The entire area erupts into a choking cloud
that attacks the Fortitude of those standing on it. On a hit it blinds and
inflicts ongoing 5 damage (save ends). The cloud stays around after this -
victims cannot save against its effects while they remain inside. I imagine it
also attacks anyone who steps into it after this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can roll Acrobatics when moving into the area to avoid disturbing it,
and they can roll Endurance to steel themselves and gain a +2 to Fortitude
against the cloud’s next attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;badlands-tremor-level-5-lurker&quot;&gt;Badlands Tremor (Level 5 Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small localized earthquake. It has four epicenter squares scattered through
the encounter area. The GM can either roll randomly or place them for maximum
inconvenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can roll Perception to listen for the groaning noise that precedes
the tremor, and then Nature to identify it as an incoming earthquake and (with a
good enough roll) where the epicenters are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tremor starts when the encounter does - roll initiative for it. On its
initiative count, a random epicenter makes a Close Burst 5 attack vs. Reflex
that damages and knocks prone on a hit, half on a miss, and makes its area
difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only countermeasure is an Acrobatics check on your turn to brace yourself
for the next tremor. Staying away from the tremor areas also works, but it might
not be feasible depending on the map’s layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silt-sink-level-8-lurker&quot;&gt;Silt Sink (Level 8 Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A much more dangerous version of the Silt Pool terrain from before. This is a
4-by-4 squares wide, 30-foot deep hole filled with silt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a Perception roll to notice the ground is different, and then a Nature
check to realize this is a deep pit that could bury someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone steps onto the pit’s area, they suffer an attack against their
Reflex. On a hit they take fall damage (3d10, as if the pit was empty), and then
get immobilized and begin to take ongoing 5 damage until they escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An escape attempt requires a series of Athletics or Acrobatics check against the
pit’s escape DC. Each success causes the victm to rise 10 feet towards the
surface. If they’re still in the pit at the end of their turn, they remain
immobilized however. So it takes 3 successes for someone to fully escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another character can try to help the victim if they can find a way to reach
them (such as with a long branch or pole), using a move action to automatically
pull them up by 10 feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;devil-dune-level-9-obstacle&quot;&gt;Devil Dune (Level 9 Obstacle)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge pile of loose sand that is currently being pushed by the winds and moving
at a surprisingly high speed. This could be a natural phenomenon, or it could be
the work of an angry spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be automatically noticed, and there’s a Nature check to realize it’s
dangerous. The dune rolls Initiative, and on its turn it shifts 4 square towards
the nearest creature. When it enters a creature’s space, it can attack their
Reflex to try to engulf them. This damages, slows, inflicts ongoing 5 damage,
and obscures vision beyond 2 squares (save ends all). On a miss, it just slows
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who starts their turn entirely inside the dune takes an attack against
their Fortitude, which deals heavy damage and restrains. It takes an escape
roll, not a save, to get out of the sand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only countermeasure, other than staying the heck away, is the option to roll
Acrobatics as an interrupt before the dune attacks your Reflex. The result of
the roll becomes your new defense against that attack, even if it was lower than
your Reflex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;false-oasis-level-13-elite-lurker&quot;&gt;False Oasis (Level 13 Elite Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 6-by-6 square area looks like an oasis, but it’s actually an
illusion. Behind it is a 2-by-2 area filled with blood-sucking creeper plants,
which counts as blocking terrain. Sounds like just the kind of thing a group of
sand brides would set up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Insight check might let someone recognize the oasis as an illusion, but not
identify what it hides. A harder Arcana test can do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone gets to within 3 squares of the illusion’s borders, the hazard rolls
initiative. On its turn, the creepers reach out and try to pull the victim, an
attack against AC that deals no damage and pulls the target 2 squares. This can
target up to three creatures, so it not being an opportunity attack is actually
an advantage. There’s enough time for multiple victims to approach the sweet,
sweet illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a character starts their turn adjacent to the actual creeper squares, they’re
targetted by an opportunity action that attacks their Fortitude and, on a hit,
weakens and inflicts ongoing 10 necrotic damage (save ends). On a miss, it deals
5 necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t pierce the illusion or staying away is not an option, you can
destroy the false oasis with violence (105 HP, vulnerable 15 radiant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dust-funnel-level-15-blaster&quot;&gt;Dust Funnel (Level 15 Blaster)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tornado, more or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roll Initiative for the hazard when combat starts, and choose a square on the
battle map. On its first turn, the dust funnel manifests in a Close Burst 2
around that square, and takes up that much space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Perception or an easier Nature test can identify this spot as the forces build
up, before the funnel manifests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its turns, the funnel moves 1d10 squares and makes an attack against anyone
who happens to be in its area. On a hit, it damages, knocks prone, and
immobilizes its targets (save ends). Until the target passes a save, they get
dragged along with the funnel whenever it moves. Of course, targets who get
dragged along will suffer the attack again next turn, since they will be in
reach of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine if this thing manages to grab &lt;em&gt;every other combatant&lt;/em&gt;, monsters and PCs
alike. That’d be hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can make a hard Nature check to figure out where the funnel will move
in its next turn, and if they can’t escape its path they can spend a standard
action to grab onto something and get +4 to all defenses against its next
attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;desert-glass-level-17-obstacle&quot;&gt;Desert Glass (Level 17 Obstacle)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already saw what an even mix of sand and powdered glass can do. This is a
stretch of ground that’s mostly pure glass, in much bigger chunks. It’s super
slippery and cuts you to ribbons if you fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hazard covers 20 contiguous squares, in any configuration the GM wants. All
of them are difficult terrain. If they’re not obvious, such as if there’s a
thin layer of sand over them, they can be identified with a Perception test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who enters, starts their turn, or stands up from prone on one of these
squares takes an attack against Reflex that damages, knocks prone, and inflicts
ongoing 10 damage (save ends). It the target was already prone, they are dazed
for a turn instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one or more squares of the glass are included in an area attack that has the
cold, thunder, or force keywords, the affected squares make a Close Burst 1
attack that deals the same amount of immediate and ongoing damage as the other
one, and then disappear. They got shattered and blew up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venomous-spines-level-21-blaster&quot;&gt;Venomous Spines (Level 21 Blaster)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are from a species of tree that grows on some of the rare jungle biomes of
Athas. When someone gets near, the tree forcibly ejects an omni-directional
cloud of venomous spines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Perception check can notice there’s something funny about that tree. A Nature
check can identify it before the PCs enter its range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack hits a Close Burst 5 around the tree, dealing heavy poison damage and
making a secondary attack that on a hit blinds and inflicts ongoing 5 poison
damage (save ends). On a miss, it deals half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who knows the tree is dangerous can close in without triggering it with
an Acrobatics or Stealth check. They can then use hard Nature checks to reduce
the size of the burst by 2 per successful check, entirely “disarming” the tree
with the third success. I’m guessing they’re plucking the spines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defiled-plain-level-24-obstacle&quot;&gt;Defiled Plain (Level 24 Obstacle)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A patch of ground so thoroughly defiled it’s not just dead, it’s
“undead”. Anyone stepping on it will have their life force drained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Perception check can tell the ground is unnatural, and an Arcana check can
identify its danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack deals heavy necrotic damage and inflicts vulnerable 10 to all damage
(save ends). The first failed save causes the target to lose a healing surge,
and the second one makes the vulnerability &lt;em&gt;permanent&lt;/em&gt; until cured by a ritual
like Remove Affliction. A miss deals half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A character near or on the affected area can make a hard Arcana check to
neutralize it for a turn. Characters without Arcane Defiling powers or abilities
have a +2 on this test. Those who have these take a -2 instead. A preserver
(which I assume means someone without those abilities) can choose to spend 2
healing surges to destroy the hazard, which I guess means they can restore some
of the place’s lost life. The book says those healing surges can only be
regained through an extended rest, which feels redundant but I guess means no
other trick that would normally allow an early recovery can do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hazards are generally scarier versions of the terrain we saw earlier, so
they’re certainly appropriate for inclusion in battles taking place in that
terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it for the book! I hope you enjoyed the reading. I’m trying to think
of what to do next, so any suggestions are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/12/wir-dscc-wilderness-hazards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/12/wir-dscc-wilderness-hazards.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels: A Decision</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in a &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2025/12/22/lphr-background-change.html&quot;&gt;post back in December&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve been actually playing this
solo game in a sporadic fashion for years. And as I said back when I started, I
planned to post it here. So why didn’t I?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it was anxiety over art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I was going to do was to post the stats for my player
characters, and since these were going to be “proper blog posts”, I decided I
wanted to have illustrations for them just like I have for all the other
characters I posted before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My method of procuring them was going to be the same. I’d use search indexes and
trawl some specific art sites for published images I could add to the post, with
proper credit and a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For certain characters, that’s dead easy. But for a couple of others I ended up
never finding an image that &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; matched what I wanted. Or when I did find
one that had the right vibe, it turned out the artist explicitly forbade this
kind of usage, even with proper credit. Also one of my sources was Pinterest and
I had just learned that one site had a serious “proper credit” issue. Whoops!
What to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know exactly what suggestion is already forming in a lot of your brains right
now, and I’m gonna stop y’all right there and say “no”. I’m not using AI for
this, or anything else. Not now, not ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after way too long you’ll get those posts without illustrations at all. I
can’t draw, but I can write, so you’re getting verbal descriptions. And maybe
then I can finally proceed with publishing this.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/11/lets-play-hells-rebels-announcement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/11/lets-play-hells-rebels-announcement.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Hazards</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if the stuff we saw on our previous post was pretty hazardous, none of it
counts as a “hazard” in mechanical terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference is that Terrain is entirely passive. It might do something
when you step on it, or it might allow a character to perform some special
action when next to it, but it never &lt;em&gt;initiates&lt;/em&gt; any interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hazards, on the other hand, have enough “agency” to count as a monster for
encounter building purposes. They can make attacks, and can also be disabled by
the methods outlined in its description. Traps are the most popular example of
hazards, but these rules can also model dangerous terrain features that weren’t
built to do harm on purpose. Obviously, unlike real monsters, traps and hazards
don’t use tactics. They just follow their “programming”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traps and hazards have their own set of roles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blasters&lt;/strong&gt; make ranged or area attacks. A crossbow trap is the most popular
example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lurkers&lt;/strong&gt; can disappear for a while after making their attacks, so dealing
with them is harder. A blade trap that retracts into the wall is a good
example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obstacles&lt;/strong&gt; impede movement, both by their presence and with attacks that
slow the target down. They might block passage entirely or require characters
to make tricky movement or puzzle-solving skill checks to pass.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warders&lt;/strong&gt; are alarm systems. They can have damaging attacks too, and will
make them as soon as they detect intruders, but their main function is to warn
others about the presence of those intruders. The alarm might only sound once,
or keep sounding while the hazard persists. In truth, this seems to be kind of
a catch-all category. If the hazard can’t conceal itself after attacking and
doesn’t really impede movement, it’s a warder. A shrieker mushroom is a
non-damaging example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summarized descriptions below, I always start with a description of the
hazard’s nature and appearance, what it does when triggered, and how to avoid or
disable it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arena-hazards&quot;&gt;Arena Hazards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This subsection details hazards that might be found in the many gladiatorial
arenas of Athas. They’re placed on purpose to make things more “interesting”,
but they’re not really &lt;em&gt;traps&lt;/em&gt; per se.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worthy-sacrifices-of-draj&quot;&gt;Worthy Sacrifices of Draj&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a 3-by-6 square pile or corpses with their hearts torn out. &lt;em&gt;Animated&lt;/em&gt;
corpses, that will try to grab, pull, and gnaw on anyone they sense nearby. It’s
a Level 8 Obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs can notice the corpses are animated with Perception or Religion. The pile
makes opportunity attacks that damage and grab against any character who steps
adjacent to it. Roll Initiative for it after the first such attack. On its
turn, it will try to pull any grabbed victims into itself, dealing the same
damage as the initial attack and inflicting ongoing 10 necrotic damage while the
victims remain inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PC can choose to make an Acrobatics test when they step adjacent to the pile
to avoid the opportunity attack. They can disable it either by good old
fashioned violence (70 HP, resist necrotic, vulnerable radiant), or by
improvising an exorcism with Nature and Religion. This is a complexiy 1 skill
challenge where each failure deals 5 necrotic damage to the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blood-trees-of-gulg&quot;&gt;Blood Trees of Gulg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are large trees with red leaves. The main arena in Gulg has about a dozen
of these planted in a semi-random arrangement. Their trunks completely fill a
square and count as blocking terrain. Their branches stretch 3 squares in every
direction from the trunk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rumor that these trees have red leaves because they feed on blood is
false. The leaves are naturally red, and the trees are mostly harmless. They
only turn carnivorous when they’re about to bloom, you see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no fixed blooming season - the timing for that is rather random. For
this specific arena, at most 3 trees might be dangerous at a time. The rest are
still blocking terrain, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood Trees are level 9 Warders. Their presence is obvious, and a Nature or
Perception check can allow a PC to notice that a given tree is “primed” and what
its reach is (it’s 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone steps into that reach, the tree makes an opportunity attack that
damages and knocks prone on a hit. On its turn, it apparently uses another set
of branches to make attacks against Fortitude to damage, poison and fling away
anyone it hits with those. That’s ongoing 5 poison (save ends), plus a secondary
attack that makes a 5-square push on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood trees can be destroyed by violence (100 HP, resist 10 poison); and a PC
can succeed at a Nature check when stepping into their reach to avoid the
opportunity attack and be ignored by the tree for the rest of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;obsidian-façades-of-urik&quot;&gt;Obsidian Façades of Urik&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arena in Urik is a former pit from an obsidian mine. Its walls are wickedly
sharp and good enough at absorbing heat that by noon the arena resembles a huge
natural air fryer. Guess when fights take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters inside the arena are exposed to Sun Sickness, a disease detailed in
the Dark Sun Campaign Setting that probably represents heat stroke and
dehydration. The walls are a variable level Obstacle, and moving adjacent to
them subjects the character to an attack that deals mixed physical and fire
damage that rises with tier. Characters doing so on purpose can attempt an
Acrobatics check to avoid this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-up&quot;&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilderness hazards! Because the world itself is also out to get you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/10/wir-dscc-hazards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/10/wir-dscc-hazards.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Athasian Terrain</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re done with monsters for now, and we’re getting into a section about
terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrain is as important a building block for a fun encounters as the monsters
that make it up, and this section has some uniquely Dark and Sunny examples for
you to add to your battlemaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;barbed-cacti&quot;&gt;Barbed Cacti&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when they don’t uproot themselves to hunt you down, Athasian cacti can
still be dangerous. These specimens have sharp spines that break off and stay
stuck to you. Lines of barbed cactus squares can be used to cordon off some
areas of the battlefield, and provide an excellent barrier for artillery
monsters to hide behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering a square of barbed cacti deals 3 damage and inflices -2 to attack rolls
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brambleweed&quot;&gt;Brambleweed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like barbed cacti, but worse. Brambleweed grows in sprawling thickets that can
thrive even in defiled areas, because they can use the blood or corpses of
captured creatures as nourishment. Some defilers plant them intentionally as
defensive measures in their lairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creature that ends their turn in a brambleweed square is restrained until the
end of their next turn. A creature that &lt;em&gt;starts&lt;/em&gt; their turn there (which they
will if they were restrained) takes 5/tier damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;defiled-terrain&quot;&gt;Defiled Terrain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a more varied category describing several possibilities for what might
remain behind after a major act of defiling. It can be used as pre-existing
terrain in an area what was subject to defiling in the past, or you can place it
in the middle of the fight after someone uses Arcane Defiling or an equivalent
power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ash-field&quot;&gt;Ash Field&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the remains of plant life caught in a defiling field. Sometimes the
wind causes them to pool in terrain depressions to form areas of Settled Ash,
which can act as a terrain feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who’s adjacent to a square of settled ash can make an Athletics test to
raise a cloud of it, which functions as a blast attack vs. Fortitude that blinds
for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;black-sand&quot;&gt;Black Sand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The residue of defiling mixed in with the local soil. People standing on black
sand only regain half the normal amount of HP from healing effects. Wasn’t there
an entire geographical region covered in the stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dead-magic&quot;&gt;Dead Magic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas that have lost so much to defiling that they have nothing left to
give. Anyone standing on dead magic squares takes a -5 penalty to attack with
arcane or primal powers, and is barred from using Arcane Defiling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book recommends being careful with dead magic areas, particularly if there
are a lot of arcane and primal PCs in the party. Usually only very powerful
defilers are capable of creating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sickening-heat&quot;&gt;Sickening Heat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is either a mystical side effect of defiling, or it could just be a natural
consequence of killing all that plant cover. Creatures ending their turn on
these squares are weakened for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This terrain can do a number on your party’s strikers, and monsters who have the
ability to inflict forced movement simply love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;glimmering-mirage&quot;&gt;Glimmering Mirage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mundane mirages are the effect of heat haze in the distance. These ones are more
than that: they’re illusions crafted by malicious primal spirits. In addition to
luring travelers, they persist once they get closer, and can conceal all kinds
of danger behinds their alluring façades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glimmering mirages form walls 4 or more squares long. They block line of sight,
and give concealment against ranged attacks to anyone standing adjacent to
them. At the end of every turn, you roll a d6 for each mirage. A 1 means it’s
gone, a 6 means it moves 5 squares, and other results mean it stays put.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lightning-pillar&quot;&gt;Lightning Pillar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally a pillar of congealed lightning, probably created due to the area’s
proximity to an “electric” region of the Elemental Chaos. PCs and enemies might
be able to use their Arcana, Nature, or Religion skills to “hack” such a pillar
and make it deliver a lightning strike to a chosen target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mudflats&quot;&gt;Mudflats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are natural areas where underground water surfaces a bit and mixes with
the soil, creating an area that is both dusty and sludgy at the same
time. Inland mudflats are the next best thing to oases, and draw many animals
and people who learn to extract water from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly thick mud flats are difficult terrain, and can contain &lt;strong&gt;mud sink&lt;/strong&gt;
squares representing deeper areas. Creatures standing adjacent to those can be
pushed into them, which will immobilize them (save ends), with a slow
after-effect due to the clinging mud (also save ends). Voluntarily or
accidentally stepping into one would have the same effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;psychic-reservoirs&quot;&gt;Psychic Reservoirs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fragile purple crystals that grow in psychically charged areas sheltered from
the winds, these can be tapped by psionic characters to boost their attacks. It
takes a minor action to tap into an adjacent crystal, which makes it crumble to
dust. If the character uses power points, they gain 1 bonus point that lasts
until the end of the encounter. Otherwise they gain +5 to their next damage roll
from a psionic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rocky-badlands&quot;&gt;Rocky Badlands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regions are too rough to support permanent settlements, so they’ll mostly
feature as ambush sites. They’re filled with &lt;strong&gt;teetering stone pillars&lt;/strong&gt; that
can be pushed onto enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;salt-flats&quot;&gt;Salt Flats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bone-dry regions are a hassle to fight in, as salt will inevitably get in
the wounds and make them sting like hell. They’re also filled with loose &lt;strong&gt;salt
piles&lt;/strong&gt; that work a lot like the Settled Ash hazard above, except that they also
slow the target if it was bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sandy-wastes&quot;&gt;Sandy Wastes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What most people think of when they hear “desert”. They can contain 3x3-square
&lt;strong&gt;Small Dunes&lt;/strong&gt; that anyone might use as a hiding or ambush spot, even if they
can’t normally burrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;silt-pools&quot;&gt;Silt Pools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They work a lot like mud flats, except there’s no water, just very fine
dust. Usually filled with difficult terrain, and with &lt;strong&gt;deep silt spots&lt;/strong&gt; that
restrain (save ends) anyone who falls or gets pushed into them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slipsand&quot;&gt;Slipsand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandy areas where some magical or psionic effect caused a significant amount of
tiny glass crystals to be mixed in with the sand. They’re slippery &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; sharp,
requiring an Athletics check from any who enters them to avoid falling prone and
taking damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tree-of-life&quot;&gt;Tree of Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These extremely rare plants are imbued with a much greater than usual amount of
vital energy, which enables them to resist and even recover from defiling
attempts given enough time. Ironically, this makes them extremely valued by
sorcerer-kings and other powerful and rich defilers, which cultivate them for
use as batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think earlier editions kept a more or less precise list of the remaining trees
of life in Athas - they were &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; rare. In this edition, I believe their
number is less restricted, but the most likely place you’re going to find one is
still in the “boss room” for these defilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees of life emit a 5-square aura. Creatures within always regain the maximum
possible HP from variable healing effects, and have a +5 to perform divination
rituals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever someone performs Arcane Defiling inside the aura, or use some other
necrotic power that damages one of their allies, the tree takes the damage
instead. Trees have 500 HP and Vulnerable 10 Necrotic, and die when they
hit 0. They regenerate 5 HP per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ztal-horde&quot;&gt;Z’Tal Horde&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A much funnier and more mundane piece of terrain! Z’tals are tiny, slimy, stinky
lizard-bug-things that gather in very large swarms. They’re relatively harmless,
but still a bother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A z’tall horde fills one or more squares, which are difficult terrain. Someone
who ends their movement in such a square takes 5/tier poison damage from the
stink. Someone who starts their turn in a horde square must roll a save before
taking any other actions. A failure means they fall prone because of the
slippery slime. A close or area attack that deals at least 1 point of damage
will automatically disperse a horde square with no roll required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re sometimes bred as living security measures, but a horde of these
annoying scavengers might naturally form around the corpse of any large
creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-up&quot;&gt;Next Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hazards! What, you thought these were the hazards?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/09/wir-dscc-athasian-terrain.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/09/wir-dscc-athasian-terrain.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Sunwarped Monster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is your one stop shop for generating horribly mutated varieties of standard
monsters. The name “Sunwarped” comes from the belief that these mutations are
caused by Athas’ scorching sun, but there are many different causes. These
creatures might have been exposed to concentrated psionic energy, lived for too
long in defiled areas, or been victims of terrible experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pristine Tower is also a prime source of mutated monstrosities, altering any
who linger near it for too long. To hear people talk about it, it was the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt;
such source in previous editions, but now it’s just one more among many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunwarped creatures are obviously misshapen when compared to typical
specimens. They might be exceedingly assymetrical, have extra limbs or eyes, and
so on. These descriptors give me a kind of “science fantasy” vibe, because they
match what you would expect radiation to do in 50s-style atomic horror tales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, sunwarped creatures get a +2 to Endurance, and might also get one or two
&lt;strong&gt;Sunwarped Traits&lt;/strong&gt; in addition to their extra theme powers. These traits
usually give it an extra bonus in one area and a small penalty in another. There
is a table here with some examples, but the GM is free to come up with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a creature might get digging claws that give it climb and burrow speeds equal
to its base speed, but also reduce that base speed by 1. Or uneven eyes that
give it all-around vision but inflict a -3 penalty to ranged and area
attacks. Or something that gives +1 to one defense and -1 to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these changes are situational, and their effectiveness depends entirely
on the monster they get applied to. A Brute with no ranged attacks will find
those uneven eyes to be a pure bonus, while an extra limb that aids in grappling
would be wasted on an artillery monster. While you can min-max and only give
monsters traits that increase their power, you can also do the opposite to show
how random these mutations can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The split is pretty clear in this theme - attack powers either deal damage or
apply debuffs to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breath of the Blazing Sun&lt;/strong&gt; probably has this name because almost no one in
Athas would know what radiation is. It’s a Close Blast 4 vs. Fortitude that
blinds its targets and makes them vulnerable to radiant and fire damage (save
ends both).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burning Blood&lt;/strong&gt; will make xenomorph fans happy, as it represents a
high-pressure jet of hazardous blood spraying out when the creature is
hit. This is a reaction that makes a Close Blast 3 attack vs. Reflex, and
inflicts ongoing acid + fire damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ravaging Fury&lt;/strong&gt; is a free action encounter power, meaning it can be used in
the creature’s own turn without spending actions. Once this is used, if the
creature hits with its next attack it will immediately gain an action point
that it can use before the end of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sticky Hide&lt;/strong&gt; makes the monster be constantly covered in goo. Any enemy that
hits the creature with a melee attack is subject to an attack vs. their
Reflex, and if that hits the weapon used on the attack gets yanked out of
their hands and and sticks to the monster’s slimy coating. Recovery is
automatic but requires staying adjacent to the monster and spending a standard
action.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These heal of buff the creature itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enraged Growth&lt;/strong&gt; makes the monster grow one size category when first
bloodied! It pushes anyone adjacent to make room, and gains 10 temporary
HP/tier. This gets more awesome when you apply it to a monster that is already
big.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feast on Flesh&lt;/strong&gt; causes the creature’s melee basic attack to give it 5/tier
temporary HP on a hit as it consumes some of the target’s flesh. The book
itself says that while you’d expect to see this only for bite attacks, you can
add it to any attack and come up with a suitably freaky explanation for why it
works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misshapen Body&lt;/strong&gt; means the creature’s important anatomical bits are not
where you’d expect them to be, so it can roll a d20 when it takes a critical
hit, downgrading it to a normal hit on a result of 10+. These are the same
mechanics of a normal save, but since they’re written out in full I guess it
means it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;count&lt;/em&gt; as a save, so wouldn’t get general save bonuses such
as those of an elite or solo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also make such misshapen creatures &lt;strong&gt;Steady-Footed&lt;/strong&gt;, letting them
also roll actual saves against falling prone because their weird shape ends up
being more stable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get a very strong “atomic horror” vibe from this theme, except it’s happening
in a setting where people don’t know about radiation, and so the mutations get
blamed on other causes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/28/wir-dscc-sunwarped-monster.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/28/wir-dscc-sunwarped-monster.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Psionic Adept</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As we all know by now, psychic powers are very common in Athas. Anyone might
have some, even if that’s not their main specialty. For PCs, this is implemented
as a couple of character themes (Noble Adept and Wilder).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For NPCs and monsters, we have the Psionic Adept theme presented here. You can
add this to a non-psionic monster to make it more controller-ish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psionic Adepts gain a +2 to either either Diplomacy and Intimidate (force of
personality!) or to Insight and Perception (sixth sense!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the usual design strategy of adding new abilities that work “around”
established attacks, we get a collection of powers that hinder and debuff
enemies. All of the ones that require attack rolls target Will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blind the Mind’s Eye&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a ranged attack that makes the
creature invisible to the target (save ends). This ends when the creature
attacks the target. Lurkers can use this to enable their big attacks, while
others can use it as a way to ease pressure on themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empathic Wall&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) creates a 12-square wall that lasts a turn. It
blocks line of sight. People can cross it, but its squares are difficult
terrain, and anyone inside them is lightly obscured.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mantle of the Mind&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a close burst 4 that attacks will and
prevents affected targets from targeting the creature with their attacks (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Marionette&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a sustainable domination power. It
dominates for a turn on a hit, but can be sustained with standard actions to
let the creature repeat the attack against the same target, potentially
prolonging the domination. On a miss, it dazes for a turn. It’s a little
weaker than a fire-and-forget (save ends) power, because it eats up standard
actions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three variants of &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augmentation&lt;/strong&gt; that add a little extra something
when the creature hits with a melee basic attack. One deals extra psychic
damage, the other dazes for a turn, and the third one inflicts ongoing psychic
damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a lot more clearly “utilities” than the ones for elemental
creatures. They’re all encounter powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Bastion&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt that gives a +4 to Will, potentially
turning a hit into a miss.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open the Mind’s Eye&lt;/strong&gt; gives blindsight 5 and all-around vision for a
turn. The latter means the creature cannot be flanked.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oracular Empathy&lt;/strong&gt; is a weird one. When an nearby ally of the creature is
hit by an attack, the creature can use a reaction to switch its initiative
order to be just after the attacker’s.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psionic Flight&lt;/strong&gt; automatically pushes each adjacent enemy 1 square and lets
the creature fly its speed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty cool! It seems more thematically tight to me than Elementally
Infused. Adding these powers to someone like an ogre would be a nice/nasty
surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/22/wir-dscc-theme-psionic-adept.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/22/wir-dscc-theme-psionic-adept.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Elementally-Infused Monster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Athas is a world particularly close to the Elemental Chaos, and so there are
lots of places in it that are soaked in elemental energies of some kind. The
creatures that inhabit these areas often end up elementally-infused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book suggests changing the creature’s origin to elemental if its mutations
end up being inheritable, though that just affects the lore and so it’s just
necessary if it will affect the game’s stories in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main mechanical thing you must decided about an elementally-infused creature
is its element. All of its powers that deal damage have it written as “[damage
type]” in the book, and you’re meant to replace that lacuna with a type
corresponding to the creature’s associated elements: one of fire, acid, cold,
thunder, or lightning (very very frightening!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of its attacks need to do the same type of damage. Multi-element
elementals are a thing now, after all. And you might decide to make one or more
of these attacks untyped, which would be common for an earth elemental whose
rock-based attacks deal physical damage for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementally-infused creatures get +2 to Intimidate and Athletics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these powers deal damage of the type you chose above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Auras&lt;/strong&gt;, one that triggers when the monster is
bloodied and damages enemies inside, and one that is always active and makes
enemies vulnerable to your chosen element.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Eruption&lt;/strong&gt; causes an explosion when the monster is first bloodied,
a close burst 2 that targets Reflex and deals elemental damage equal to the
monster’s best basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Manifestation&lt;/strong&gt; converts the damage of all of the monster’s
attacks to your chosen element.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Persistence&lt;/strong&gt; is recharge 5+ and inflicts 5/tier ongoing damage of
the chosen type when the monster hits with a melee attack. It’s said to
increase “damage output and entertainment value”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious here is &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Damage Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;, which should be high
enough for the monster to resist its own attacks (or I guess 5/tier if you don’t
want to do math). If a monster’s attacks are untyped, you could give it
variable resistance instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all of the others deal damage, proving that the “attack”/”utility” split
is more of a guideline here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Dissipation&lt;/strong&gt; lets the monster vanish from play for a turn and
reform next to an enemy, dealing a bit of damage and making them grant combat
advantage for another turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Ground&lt;/strong&gt; is a third aura variant, this time meant to keep enemies
close. The aura’s radius becomes difficult terrain and enemies take damage
when they leave it, instead of when they enter it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Step&lt;/strong&gt; deals elemental damage to anyone who hits the monster with
an opportunity attack while it moves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Transport&lt;/strong&gt; lets the monster teleport between patches of hazardous
terrain that deal damage of the chosen type. Clever!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mutable Body&lt;/strong&gt; is appropriate for water-based or otherwise gooey monsters,
and lets the creature count as one size smaller when squeezing through narrow
openings.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want elemental damage? We got elemental damage! I like the design strategy
of additional attack powers that modify and work around the monster’s usual
attacks, and it works particularly well here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/20/wir-dscc-themes-elemental.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/20/wir-dscc-themes-elemental.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Arena Bred Monster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What’s a Monster Theme? The concept was first introduced in Dungeon Master’s
Guide 2, and it’s a way to give a set of monsters a shared look and feel. This
involves changes to their mechanics and lore, but unlike monster &lt;em&gt;templates&lt;/em&gt;
from the DMG 1, it doesn’t change their “quality”. Regulars remain regulars,
elites remain elites, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monster themes end up being more flexible than templates, since the monster
creation rules are good enough to handle any level or quality changes by
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anatomy-of-a-monster-theme&quot;&gt;Anatomy of a Monster Theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each theme has a fairly involved presentation. You get some explanation for the
lore attached to that theme and how it might modify a monster. Then a line about
skill changes that might apply, and finally a big list of powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those powers are divided between Attack Powers and Utility Powers - you pick one
of each category to add to the monster’s stat block. Nothing else about its
basic stats changes, unlike with a template. If you want those to change, you
can use the standard monster creation and “editing” rules to change the
monster’s level or quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-first-theme-arena-bred-monster&quot;&gt;Our First Theme: Arena Bred Monster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood sport arenas are the most popular entertainment in all city states, and
monster fighting is one of its most popular modalities. It’s common to throw
recently captured wild animals into the ring, but a monster that was
specifically prepared for the spectacle is a much bigger draw. Animals are
specifically bred for the role; people receive special training. And both might
be further modified by magic or psionics, all in the service of providing a more
brutal and spectacular fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monsters with this theme get a +2 to Intimidate and a +2 to either Athletics or
Acrobatics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the name of this category, the powers here tend to avoid having specific
attack or damage figures, to better enable them to apply to monsters of any
level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berserk Passage&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) lets a monster make two basic attacks and
shift half its speed at any moment in this sequence, passing through enemy
spaces. It usually goes on monsters that have been made mad with hunger and
pain before being dropped into the arena, though I supposed it could also be
used to represent an agile duelist humanoid.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bleeding Attack&lt;/strong&gt; is a triggered power that inficst 5/tier ongoing damage
(save ends) when the monster bloodies a target. It might represent serrated
weapons or claws. The book recommends making it (recharge 5+) for elites or
solos; by default, it’s at-will.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brutal Flourish&lt;/strong&gt; lets the monster make a free melee basic attack whenever
it bloodies or defeats an enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Death Burst&lt;/strong&gt; means the monster has been rigged to explode! This is visible
to the PCs and should be described appropriately. This power is common for
monsters that have received some sort of combat implant, but could be applied
even without that. By default this happens when the monster hits 0 HP, but for
elites and solos it could also happen when the monster is first bloodied,
where it might be combined with some other change in its stats as those
implanted bits fall off. The explosion is a Close Burst 2 with attack and
damage figures appropriate to the monster’s level.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retaliating Stride&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a move action that lets the monster
move its speed and deal damage to any creature that hits it with an
opportunity attack during this move. It can represent showy counterstrikes, or
maybe something like implanted spikes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attached Weapons&lt;/strong&gt; are not written up like a power, but discussed in general
terms inside a text box. Many arena monster handlers like to implant extra
weapons on their charges through magic. This is an excuse for your to add
extra attack powers that monsters of that type don’t normally have. For
example, an artillery monster could receive implanted melee weapons that give
it a stronger than usual melee attack, or a brute could get an unusually
accurate ranged weapon. It’s common for these weapons to break or fall off
when the monster is bloodied - and this can also be combined with Death Burst
variants.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are generally the fruit of long experience in the arena, representing
cunning, resilience, and luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intervening Armor&lt;/strong&gt; represents an ability to leverage the normally useless
piecemeal armor that covers gladiators by shifting so enemy attacks hit the
tiny plates. It’s an Interrupt that gives +2 to AC or Reflex when the monster
is hit by an attack targetting one of these defenses.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Necessary Betrayal&lt;/strong&gt; is for treacherous gits who developed the habit of
abusing their teammates’ trust. If the monster is hit by a melee or ranged
attack while adjacent to an ally, it can swap places with the ally as an
interrupt, and have the ally take damage from the attack instead. You don’t
compare the attack roll against the ally’s defenses - just apply the damage
directly. This power cannot be nice even by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shake it Off&lt;/strong&gt; represents the ability to quickly recover one’s wits in a
bout. Whenever subject to an effect that a save could possibly end, the
monster can roll a save to end it as a reaction, even if this specific
application cannot be ended with a save. (So it works against “dazed until the
end of the next turn”, but not against “dead”).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turn the Tables&lt;/strong&gt; is a defense against forced movement. If pushed, pulled,
slid, or knocked prone, the creature can trigger this reaction to stand up (if
prone) and shift 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s interesting how many of the powers here can be either applied to a
berserk beast of a flashy humanoid fighter that uses finesse and agility, with
the final mechanical result being the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/14/wir-dscc-themes-arena-bred.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/14/wir-dscc-themes-arena-bred.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Customizing Monsters</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re past the monster lists, but there’s still a fair amount of book to
cover. Its final third is dedicated to Encounter Options, and the first
subsection of that is a small lesson on Customizing Monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of it is that when you want to bring a “generic” D&amp;amp;D monster to Athas,
you should change them a little to make them fit the more brutal and desperate
tone of the setting. In other words, you should make them Darker and Sunnier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next page has a few tips on how to do that. First, you should keep the
monster recognizable, since it both keeps things a little familiar and makes
the differences stand out that much more. And then you can apply one or more of
the customization guidelines they suggest, each with an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No change&lt;/strong&gt;: Some monsters already fit the aesthetic and could just be
dropped in where you need them. Gnolls and bullettes, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altered Appearance&lt;/strong&gt;: Some monsters need a little extra make-up to fit the
visual style of Athas. You’ll rarely find traditional mammals here for
example, but you could have equivalent creatures that have carapaces, scales,
and bony plates instead of soft fur. Hill giants might look more rocky, with
skin matching the colors of the surrounding terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altered Environment&lt;/strong&gt;: Creatures that live in frozen or aquatic biomes in
their original forms could be changed to live in the desert wastelands of
Athas instead. Sure, the aquatic ones could live in oases, but turning them
into sand-burrowers can be a “nice” surprise for the players.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternative Lore&lt;/strong&gt;: This most important for creatures whose lore has
extensive ties to the Astral Sea and divine magic, both of which are mostly
inaccessible in Athas. Eidolons are one example, and they’d need to be changed
to be tied to arcane or primal magic instead unless they’re relics from when
the gods were still around. Angels and the like should also be reskinned
unless your entire game revolves around the mystery of why they appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Powers&lt;/strong&gt;: New mechanical abilities might be just the thing to make a
given creature Darker and Sunnier. This should mostly be handled through
Monster Themes, which are discussed in the next page.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-converted-monsters&quot;&gt;Sample Converted Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two are given as examples, and in some cases are also stealth updates to
the originals, using the new Monster Manual 3 math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silt-shark&quot;&gt;Silt Shark&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the Fleshtearer Shark from the Monster Manual 2, this creature occupies
a similar niche to the bullette, with slightly different abilities. Its
water-based traits were replaced with sand-themed equivalents, and it’s been
given training in Athletics to make higher jumps. It “swims” through sand and
loose soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silt Shark is a Large Natural Beast and a Level 10 Brute with 128 HP. It has
a ground speed of 5, and a burrow speed of 8, with low-light vision and
Tremorsense 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original shark’s Aquatic trait has been replaced with &lt;strong&gt;Silt Swimmer&lt;/strong&gt;,
which lets the shark shift and charge while burrowing, and gives it a +2 damage
bonus while burrowing against any creature without a burrow speed. It cannot
burrow through solid stone, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shark has a basic &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt;, and a &lt;strong&gt;Lockjaw Charge&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that deals the
same damage and grabs on a hit. While the shark has a grabbed victim, it can
automatically deal damage to them with &lt;strong&gt;Shredding Teeth&lt;/strong&gt;. And once the grab
ends, the victim takes ongoing 5 damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the shark starts its turn within 5 squares of a bloodied creature, it enters
a &lt;strong&gt;Feeding Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt;, and makes a free attack against a creature adjacent to
it. If it was grabbing someone, it releases them first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ssurran-dune-mystic&quot;&gt;Ssurran Dune Mystic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Greenscale Marsh Mystic from the Monster Manual, modified into a
Ssurran version. The swamp theme of the original’s abilities has been switched
to a sand and desert theme, its Constitution was increased a little, and its
basic attack has been given a push rider to match the Ssurran Shaman from that
entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We end up with a Level 6 Controller (Leader) with 72 HP and a ground speed of 6
with Earth Walk. It has a &lt;strong&gt;Sun Blessing&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that heals 3 HP to any ally
that stats their turn inside, and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and
pushes 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystic also has a couple of fireball-style combat spells: &lt;strong&gt;Salt Cloud&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) deals poison damage and dazes for a turn; &lt;strong&gt;Sand’s Grasp&lt;/strong&gt;
(encounter) is non-damaging, but it immobilizes (save ends) and creates a zone
of difficult terrain that lasts for the rest of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite likely that anyone who still actively plays D&amp;amp;D 4th Edition is
experienced enough at reskinning monsters that they don’t really need this
advice. Nevertheless, it’s still good to see it printed, and with worked
examples to boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up: Monster Themes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/11/wir-dscc-customizing-monsters.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/11/wir-dscc-customizing-monsters.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Creature Catalog: Zeburon, the Iron Rider</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-zeburon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Zeburon
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeburon is the leader of the Black Sands Raiders, a brutal and feared bandit
gang that hides out in the Black Sands. According to rumor they always number a
hundred, and ride war-trained kanks to assault caravans and settlements around
the Black Sands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iron Rider got this title because of his signature metal helmet, which has a
pair of prominent horns and completely conceals his face. Not even most of the
Raiders have ever seen it - only his most trusted lieutenants (such as the
defiler Fevik) know what he looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is because Zeburon’s big secret is that he’s a tiefling. The book lists
reasons why no one has figured it out yet, and they’re actually a little
funny. He lacks a tail because he cut it off himself years ago. People tend to
mistake the reddish tone of his skin for sunburns instead of natural
pigmentation. And they think the horns are part of the helmet, when in fact
they’re poking through a pair of holes in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeburon hides his true nature from the rank and file of his gang because he’s
afraid of how they’d react if they found out. Given bigotry is never in short
supply around Athas, I’m guessing the answer is “not well”. And being a fearsome
individual warrior is not very helpful if about ninety guys on war kanks decide
they want you dead and charge you all at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeburon is a Level 12 Elite Soldier with 246 HP. He has a ground speed of 6,
low-light vision, and Resist Fire 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of his attacks deal bonus damage against bloodied targets due to his
&lt;strong&gt;Bloody Violence&lt;/strong&gt; trait. He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Bastard Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that can make
standard basic attacks and be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Wild Bloodletting&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver,
attacking a Close Burst 1. A hit deals damage, slows the target, and inflicts
ongoing 10 damage (save ends both). This recharges when he’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action he can use his &lt;strong&gt;Iron Fist&lt;/strong&gt; (metal gauntlet!) to make another
attack, which does the same damage as the sword, and immobilizes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, he has the tiefling &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; power which, when used, gives
him a bonus to attacks and damage against any enemy that hit him since the end
of his last turn. This lasts for a turn or until he hits an enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fight against Zeburon will also include a sizable contingent of Black Sands
Raiders, as well as his best buddy and top lieutenant Fevik the Defiler. Plus
any amount of kank mounts you deem necessary. It will likely come after the PCs
have fought multiple encounters against the raiders, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure I’ve seen someone a lot like Zeburon in one of the many Brom
illustrations for DS: muscles, leather straps, face-concealing horned helmet,
menacing pose.  I haven’t read any older DS material to know whether he’s
someone from the old days, or if he’s new and just likes following local
fashions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/24/wir-dscc-zeburon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/12/24/wir-dscc-zeburon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
