<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 13:29:26 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 13:29:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackaton: Shadowrun 1st Edition Play Phase</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/sr1-cover.jpg&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-summary&quot;&gt;Run Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/10/26/hackaton-sr1-1.html&quot;&gt;deciding on the design parameters&lt;/a&gt; for our Shadowrun 1st Edition
Matrix run, I got my stopwatch and jumped right into it. I stopped it at the end
of every node to keep a running tally of the elapsed time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the system map we’re using, for reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackaton-sr1-system.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the account of events. As I mentioned before, the actual timed run was
written in a brief shorthand and the account below was expanded for readability
after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-1-san-red-3-trace-and-dump-4&quot;&gt;Node 1 (SAN): Red-3, Trace and Dump-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Decker enters through Node 1, dialing the mainframe’s modem. Security here
is unusually tight for a Shadowrun system - the target really doesn’t want
anyone sticking their noses in his business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t quite understood the rules here yet, thinking that you couldn’t use
your Hacking Pool outside of cybercombat for anything but improvising programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our decker arrives here at Sensor range, improvises Analyze-7 with her pool,
and runs that against the ICE, seeing that it’s a potentially dangerous
tracer. She moves into Contact range and I roll Initiative even though we’re not
in combat, just to have a sense of the flow of the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She runs Sleaze against the Tracer using only the program rating, beating the
ice but failing anyway because this is a Red node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that point on I learn that you can use Hacking Pool dice on any Computer or
program test even outside of combat, so I use some on the second attempt and
pass even though that has increased difficulty. Ice supressed, we get to whisper
“I’m in” into our comms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is where I realize there’s very little reason to be sparing with those
pool dice, and that I can use pool dice even for tests with improvised
programs. So my strategy for pretty much the rest of the run is to shout I AM
SPEED and drop my entire Hacking Pool on any test that doesn’t happen during
actual cybercombat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed so far: 1 turn, 13 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-2-spu-orange-5-access-6&quot;&gt;Node 2 (SPU): Orange-5, Access-6&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another beefy node, and our actual password prompt. Our Decker analyzes the Ice
like before, and this fails with a tie. I rule a tie doesn’t activate the
ICE. She decides not to try again and just tries Sleaze instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I AM SPEED gets us through this just fine - Sleaze works against everything, but
Deception would have worked here too. We can see two other nodes from this one,
but not what they are. I decide to flip a coin to see where we go next, and we
go right towards Node 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed so far: 2 turns, 28 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-3-spu-green-4-barrier-3&quot;&gt;Node 3: SPU, Green-4, Barrier-3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I arrive at my final interpretation for improvised
programs. Improvising them is part of the same action in which you run them, so
while this takes only 1 action total, the pool dice you use for the script
aren’t available for the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily Analyze’s rating doesn’t actually limit what it can discover, so we’re
better off improvising an Analyze-1 script and chucking our remaining 13 pool
dice into the test than going for Analyze-7 with 1 extra die. Having an actual
Analyze program would be even better, but this is pretty good still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our reckless Decker successfully analyzes the ICE and Sleazes past it using
the same actions and approach as before. I AM SPEED wins again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She sees there are two connected nodes, and it’s right here that I realize she’s
not actually in any danger at Sensor range and can back out after
reconnoitering. So Ms. Decker moves into Sensor range of the two connected nodes
in order to scout them all and see they’re an I/O Port and a Control node
without any ICE in them. She then decides to move on to Node 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 5 turns, 41 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-4-io-port-green-4&quot;&gt;Node 4: I/O Port, Green-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This node and Node 5 don’t actually have a security rating of their own, so I
gave them the same rating as the SPU that was linked to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We once again go with I AM SPEED, and our total of 21 dice easily takes care of
the system operation needed to disable the camera. Per the rules, after either
succeeding at a system operation or giving up after a number of failures, we
need to roll a d6. If the result is less than or equal to the number of
attempts, the system noticed something wrong and triggered an alert. We only had
one attempt before succeeding, and we roll a 3, so no alert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camera is off. First goal accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 6 turns, 47 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-5-control-green-4&quot;&gt;Node 5: Control, Green-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same deal as before, and same outcome. Alarm is off, second goal
accomplished. And we took less time because I already knew what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 7 turns, 50 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-6-spu-red-4-killer-4&quot;&gt;Node 6: SPU, Red-4, Killer-4.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still have data to steal, so we go to the only unexplored path so far and try
to find data stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scouting the node, we follow your usual procedure of Improvised Analyze -&amp;gt;
close to Contact range -&amp;gt; Initiative -&amp;gt; Sleaze, always using our whole Hacking
Pool for each individual test. We suppress the ICE without issue. If you noticed
how reckless we’re being, take a cookie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further scouting reviews two data stores attached to this node. I flip another
coin to decide where to go, and we go down to Node 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 10 turns, 58 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-8-data-store-red-4-black-ice-5&quot;&gt;Node 8: Data Store, Red-4, Black Ice-5.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our usual Improvised Analyze routine shows us this data store is protected by
Black Ice! This is scary, but is also a very promising lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disregarding the danger, our Decker goes all in and chucks her whole Hacking
Pool into Sleaze again. She succeeds by exactly the needed amount and suppresses
the ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She then uses Browse to find any drainable accounts, because she doesn’t know
the full layout of the system like we do. The operation succeeds but she doesn’t
find anything. Boo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remembering the actual mission, she Browses for incriminating evidence and finds
it. She has enough disk space for the file, and no time pressure for the
download, so we just wait a couple more turns. Third objective accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She still wants to find that money, though, so she moves to the other data store
at Node 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 13 turns, 1 hour, 9 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-7-data-store-red-4-access-5&quot;&gt;Node 7: Data Store, Red-4, Access-5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same deal as usual. Improv Analyze reveals the ICE, Sleaze gets past it, Browse
confirms there’s nothing of value to the team in this node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is where I begin to notice that despite the different types of nodes and
the flowery descriptions of virtual dungeons, we’ve been performing more or less
the same sequence of tests in the same order, in a loop. So I guess a long
enough Matrix run might seem a bit boring for the decker as well. I’m still
having fun &lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt;, because lucky rolls have given me a string of successes, but
I don’t feel like I’m in danger or having to make complex decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the only unexplored node left is the CPU. A cautious decker might decide
to cut their losses, perform the single remaining system operation they need,
and jack out. But we’ve already established our Decker is not cautious, SHE IS
SPEED!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total elapsed time: 14 turns, 1 hour, 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;node-9-cpu-red-5-trace-and-burn-6-black-ice-4&quot;&gt;Node 9: CPU, Red-5, Trace and Burn-6, Black Ice-4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup is a little unusual here. This CPU has all the standard system
operations available, and the Trace and Burn-6 is protecting those. It also has
a link to the target’s bank account, and draining it counts as a custom system
operation. There’s a piece of Black Ice protecting that operation only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our Decker will have the run of the system if she neutralizes the Tracer, but
to get the money she must also get past the Black Ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She comes within Sensor Range, Improv-Analyzes both pieces of Ice, and sees what
they’re protecting. She decides to deal with the Tracer first. I roll Initiative
for everyone as she gets into Contact Range, but the ICE will only act if it
activates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the usual I AM SPEED approach giving us 19 dice to Sleaze past the
Tracer, the node’s high security level prevents us from succeeding. We try again
with increased difficulty, and this time a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; unlucky roll gives the ice
more successes, meaning it activates!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing Trace and Burn does upon activation is try to raise an Internal
Alert in the system. This causes the ratings of all ICE to increase by 50%, so
we’re actually dealing with Trace-and-Burn 9 now. The Black Ice also improves to
Rating 6, but it remains inactive since it’s only protecting the bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could have allocated dice from our Hacking Pool to an opposed test to “jam”
the ice and prevent the alert from going through… but we already used all of
them on the Sleaze attempt, and the pool hasn’t refreshed yet. This is why our
Decker has been very reckless so far, as every piece of ice she faced until now
could have done this on a failed test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its first actual action, Trace and Burn rolls its rating to determine how
long it will take to trace the Decker. We’re lucky here because this roll gets
only 1 success, meaning it will take a total of 10 of the IC’s actions to do
so. Once that time is up, though, her deck is toast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Decker switches to using the Attack program to destroy the Tracer before
that happens. This is proper cybercombat, which works a little differently. The
“to-hit” roll is an unopposed test with only with your Hacking Pool against the
Node’s security. The program’s rating is your base damage if you hit, and it
increases by 1 for every extra success past the minimum required to hit. Actual
damage is your net successes in an opposed test of the ICE’s rating versus your
damage pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I end up using my entire pool in the to-hit roll, since any less than that means
I won’t be beating the difficulty on average. It takes me 3 turns to destroy the
Tracer this way, but since everyone acts multiple times per turn I only had 3
actions left before the trace completed. This was still somewhat repetitive
since it was the same set of rolls every time, but it was also exciting since
this is the first time our Decker is in any actual danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the tracer gone, she uses a system operation to cancel the alert and
manages to Sleaze past the Black Ice and drain the target’s account. Bonus
objective completed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that done, she moves normally to the Control Modules and opens the final
door, completing the mission’s objective. She then jacks out. Mission Complete!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time elapsed: 19 turns, 2 hours and 4 minutes. This combat alone took 41
minutes to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-analysis-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Run Analysis and Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not gonna lie, I kinda feel like I completed an important life goal. I could
never understand this hacking system when I was 12, but now not only did I grok
it, I finished an entire Matrix run while using it. So I’m pretty happy, and I
had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I must also conclude that all the criticisms leveled at this system are
valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the intro, we’re assuming our physical team has an easy time
getting past the reception area. This would take some light roleplaying and a
roll or two from our talker. That plus walking to the restricted area might take
10 minutes of real time, but it takes the decker 50 minutes to complete the
goals that let them move forward from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next part of the physical mission will involve more tests and die rolls from
the physical team. The Decker takes around half an hour of real time to find the
electronic evidence, and it might be accurate to assume the physical team takes
about the same or a little bit longer to sneak past the guards and find the
physical documents. Let’s say 40 minutes for the physical team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the Decker decides to loot the server, and that takes 41 minutes. Unless
the physical team is having an epic shootout at the same time as they try to
leave the building, all they have to do is sit and wait. Otherwise they take
maybe 10 minutes total to reach the back door and walk out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a team that has a firefight on the way out might take up 90 minutes of real
time, and a team that doesn’t will take perhaps 50 with their part of the
mission. Our Decker is taking up &lt;em&gt;at best&lt;/em&gt; over half and at worst over
two-thirds of the session with her solo VR dungeon crawl. And this is all
assuming a 100% buttery smooth session with absolutely no digressions,
distractions, or rule arguments to make it longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also a point where I kinda felt that the decking run itself was
getting a little repetitive, because the “optimal” procedure to follow became
obvious: Improv Analyze -&amp;gt; Sleaze, always dumping the entire Hacking Pool into
each test. In actual cybercombat, I also ended up doing the same thing over and
over until the enemy died. It was still enjoyable, but I could see it eventually
overstaying its welcome even for the decker player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if it turns out that my rules interpretations were overly generous and
this was supposed to be way harder, then all the criticisms I made become even
stronger, because everything would take more time and more rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/27/hackaton-sr1-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/27/hackaton-sr1-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon: Shadowrun 1st Edition Design Phase</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/sr1-cover.jpg&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this run we’ll be using the original edition of Shadowrun, published
in 1989. I started with second edition, but that’s not a problem because I’m
equally unfamiliar with both edition’s hacking systems!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The writing and setting and even the rules of these two early editions give me a
sort of cozy nostalgic feeling when I read them, but these days I am well aware
of all their issues, mechanical and otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-overview&quot;&gt;Setting Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting’s global network is called the Matrix. Hackers are called Deckers
because they use &lt;em&gt;cyberdecks&lt;/em&gt;, devices the about the size of a full 104-key
keyboard that have cable jacks for connecting directly to the decker’s neural
interface and to either a computer terminal or a communications line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a cyberdeck to access the Matrix takes you to the full Gibsonian VR
Dungeon experience, where you zip through the infinite grid of the Matrix and
then crawl through the low-poly simulated environments of a server, treating its
security programs as monsters and its data as loot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beneath the chrome flash, we’re dealing with classic mainframes from the
Eighties. The Matrix isn’t the Internet, it’s the global phone grid. You access
your target mainframe by connecting to the phone grid yourself and dialing the
number of the mainframe’s modem. There are even rules for making long-distance
and international calls. Mainframe numbers are usually unlisted, but can be
found with diligent research by deckers or provided by whoever’s hiring them for
the run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cyberdeck is distinctly different from a mere “computer”, crammed full of
specialized electronics that allow it to be used for operating in VR and hacking
mainframes. Personal computers don’t do really do much other than letting you
store and view data files, and perhaps acting as dumb terminals to mainframes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberdecks cost a fortune! The one used by the sample starting characters in the
book costs more than a sports car. The most expensive one is about twice the
price of a fighter jet. And that’s just for the base hardware. If you want your
deck to be truly tubular, you’re probably going to spend around twice its base
price on software and optional extras. Deckers tend to be highly specialized at
character creation because they need to spend most of their points on money and
most of their money on a deck - there isn’t any “room” to be anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics-overview&quot;&gt;Mechanics Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mainframe is composed of a set of Nodes representing its different parts,
connected by Data Lines. The end result is a lot like a dungeon with rooms and
corridors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each node allows users to perform a different set of System Operations related
to its function. Authorized users can do this automatically. Our decker must
perform a Computer skill test to beat the node’s Security Rating, a color and
number combination that gives you both the difficulty of the roll and how many
successes you need. If you fail at performing a system operation, you might
trigger an alert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deckers can also run Utility Programs, which do things not listed in the system
operations menu. There are four program categories, and each has a slightly
different procedure that’s some variation of rolling the program rating against
the node’s security. Some programs degrade, losing effectiveness each time
they’re used. This resets when the decker jacks out. Failing at using a program
doesn’t raise an alert, but might trigger IC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is very concerned about how large programs are because there are rules
for loading them from disk to RAM and managing your free memory. Not having
enough RAM to run all you need at once is the quintessential 80s computing
experience after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Computer skill tests and Utility Programs can benefit from the decker’s
Hacking Pool, which is equal to the sum of their Computer Skill and Reaction
attribute, modified by stuff that increases Reaction. Like other dice pools in
this system, it refreshes at the start of every action. You can allocate dice
from it to benefit any Computer or Program tests while in the Matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use a program you don’t have, you can improvise a single-use
script version of it with your Hacking Pool. You can only improvise a degrading
program once per Matrix run, but if I understand the book correctly you can
improvise non-degrading programs multiple times. I’m interpreting the rules to
mean that an improvised program must be used in the same action, otherwise there
would be little reason to buy any programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most nodes are going to have some IC (Intrusion Countermeasures, “ice”) in
them. The mere presence of IC stops deckers from performing system operations or
moving past the node, and they must either destroy or fool the IC before they
can do these things. Most ice only triggers when it beats you in the opposed
test to fool it. If you beat it but fail to beat the node’s base security, they
remain inactive and still block your progress. Subsequent attempts are harder,
increasing your chances of triggering the ice. Attacking IC directly also
triggers it, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White ice is completely passive. It tries to raise an alarm but you can block it
with your Hacking Pool. Grey ice additionally tries to trace you or attack your
deck. Black Ice attacks the &lt;em&gt;decker&lt;/em&gt; directly, and might kill them. There’s a
little bestiary of different types within each category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matrix turns happen at the same speed as physical combat turns, using the same
initiative rules. Both types of turn last around 3 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-parameters&quot;&gt;Run Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Shadowrun 1st Edition version of our run, our decker is going to be
remote, and we will assume the team discovered the mainframe’s unlisted phone
number during their prep phase. I’m going to take a couple of shortcuts here
because those are available to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our decker, we’ll be using the &lt;strong&gt;Decker Archetype&lt;/strong&gt; from the SR1
corebook. She has Computer 6, the Fuchi-4 deck with a decent spread of mods and
programs, and a hacking pool of 15. I’m going to cheat a little bit and replace
her Deception 4 utility with Sleaze 4, because from what I understood of the
system there is no reason to ever take Deception when you can take Sleaze
instead. Let’s assume she has one run under her belt and used the payout from
that to upgrade her software a bit. Even with Sleaze’s larger size she can still
fit all her programs in RAM at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackaton-sr1-system.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Our target system
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our target system, we’ll be using the one from page 55 of the &lt;strong&gt;Mercurial&lt;/strong&gt;
adventure. Here’s a list of the ICE present in the system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 1: Trace and Dump-4.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 2 Access-6.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 3: Barrier-3.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 4: no ICE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 5: no ICE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 6: Killer-4.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 7: Access-5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 8: Black Ice-5.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node 9: Trace and Burn-6, Black Ice-4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Node 4 will be connected to our security camera, Node 5 to the alarm and
door. Node 8 will contain the evidence we seek, and the CPU at Node 9 is where
we can drain their accounts because that’s how it is in the original
adventure. The other data store at Node 7 has nothing of value to our runners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/26/hackaton-sr1-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/26/hackaton-sr1-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon, part 00: Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hackers-cast.jpg&quot;
       alt=&quot;The protagonists of the 1995 movie Hackers.&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Getting ready to hack the Gibson.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently got into a forum discussion about hacking in cyberpunk tabletop RPGs,
as one does. This one was mostly centered around Shadowrun, and it touched on a
lot of the reasons why one might want to &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html&quot;&gt;play without a hacker PC&lt;/a&gt; even when
you want to feature hacking in your game. It also got a bit into edition
arguments, as it often does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowrun’s problems are more or less universal to the genre, as mentioned in
the other post linked above. The first three editions go heavy into the whole
Gibsonian VR Dungeon aesthetic and suffer from the classic problems from that
approach. It’s also very inspired by how 80s mainframes worked, and rules aside
it all made so much more sense to me once I realized that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth has something that visually resembles Ghost in the Shell or Cyberpunk
2077, where the hacker follows along with the group and hacks a series of
smaller devices using an augmented reality interface. My recollection is that
this is supposed to be faster, but the discussion in question had people
complaining it wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk-the-game is similar, with CP 2020 going in fully for VR dungeons, and
CP RED going in for smaller localized servers that are also supposed to only
take a small series of rolls to solve instead of an hours-long minigame. They’re
are much less inspired by reality than Shadowrun’s (though this is of course not
a knock on them, merely an observation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also more recent games that try to either capture the nostalgic feel
of old-school cyberpunk or to express the same themes in a more modern way. I’m
thinking of Neon City Overdrive and Hard Wired Island, respectively. I’m not
very familiar with them yet but I intend to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you have GURPS, which has a few hacking systems of its own depending on
which genre you’re talking about. The ones I’m interested in are the one from
Pyramid #3/21, which emulates classic cyberdecks-and-mainframes hacking but
could also work for GitS-style shenanigans, and the more streamlined one from
GURPS Action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I kinda want to see if they all match the memories and impressions I have of
them. Let’s try them all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hackathon-scenario-and-rules&quot;&gt;Hackathon Scenario and Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture a team of flawed but stylish urban mercenaries composed of a hacker, a
sneaky talker, and a pair of sneaky bruisers. They’re on a mission to take down
a corrupt and racist businessman, and they learned a company he owns stores the
sort of evidence that can’t be ignored by the government: proof of rampant
embezzling and tax evasion, in both digital and hardcopy forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mercenaries are going to infiltrate a small, single-office company, one of
the many owned by the target. It does do legitimate business but also serves as
a “stash” for records about the target’s illegal activities. Secret ledgers,
blackmail material, and so on. Some of this lives in the company’s computer
system, some of it is stored in hardcopy in a “records room” whose access is
restricted to normal employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employees and other authorized personnel can wander the legitimate business area
of the office freely, but the “records room” can only be accessed by a small
group of people who work directly for the target and drop by occasionally to use
it. There’s a back entrance with an electronic lock so that these lieutenants
can get in and out outside of business hours and/or without bringing too much
employee attention to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The records room is watched by a camera and protected by an alarm that triggers
if a stranger or even a normal employee tries to get close to it. There’s a
small guard shift here during the day which increases at night. The guards know
who the lieutenants are, and their duties involve keeping everyone else away
from the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The office’s computer system will be different in every game. In all of them
it’s supposed to be small but with tighter than expected security, because of
what it hides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team’s mission is to infiltrate this office, steal all the evidence, and if
possible drain the company’s accounts on the way out, because at the end of the
day ya still gotta eat, chummer. Here’s how things are supposed to go, with a
greater focus on the hacker’s part since this is what I’m interested in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the team enters the building disguised as a maintenance crew. We’ll
assume this part succeeds, giving them limited freedom of movement inside the
office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next they must enter the records room. For them to be able to do this, the
hacker must turn off a security camera and an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the previous step succeeds, the hacker must locate and steal the target data
from the office’s computer system. Technically, the best strategy would be to
steal the evidence first and only then drain the accounts, but our hacker will
do things in the order in which they run into the corresponding locations. The
lure of money is strong when the account is right there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the hacker must unlock the back door so the team can leave. Ideally
they will do so quietly and with no one the wiser, but this could happen in the
middle of a firefight. Possibly one caused by the hacker triggering an alert in
the computer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each of the following systems, I’m going to stat up a hacker character and a
computer system that conforms to that game’s paradigm and rules. And then I’ll
roll through the target session while timing how long it takes me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 1st Edition&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk 2020&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 4th Edition, 20th Anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk RED&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shadowrun 5th Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Neon City Overdrive&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hard Wired Island&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GURPS Action with the Pyramid #3/21 system, both in “classic” and “modern”
modes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GURPS Action with its own system. Not sure this can accommodate the scenario,
but we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using this particular list because those are the books I happen to own at
present. I’m not sure if I want to spend money to acquire the hacking systems
used in Shadowrun 2nd and 3rd Edition, though I do remember they are notably
different from SR1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hacker and their equipment will be at roughly starting character level for
each game, possibly with a slight tweak or two, and the challenges faced should
be challenging but not impossible for the hacker. Whether the target devices are
separate or part of the same single “target system”, and whether the hacker is
even with the physical team, will depend on the system in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have more practical experience with some of these systems than with others,
but I will be studying all of them to ensure I do each run “right”. Preliminary
study doesn’t count towards the timed session, but consultations that happen
during the actual run &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;, because I’ve never been in a session where people
didn’t have to consult the books for something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be writing a lot of stuff down during the actual run, but I’ll try to be as
brief as possible there. It’s still going to take a bit more time than doing it
verbally, but I think it evens out because there will be no table talk or extra
player questions getting in the way. I’ll write wordier summaries after the run
is done, and these are the ones that will see publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All rolls will be made on Orokos, but I’m not going to save them and will just
report the results in the article.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 19:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/hackaton-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/25/hackaton-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Coiled Spring</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/coiled-spring.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Image source: &lt;a
  href=&quot;https://www.deviantart.com/eveyd/art/Antique-Vintage-Pocket-Watch-png-268108244&quot;&gt;EveyD
  on DeviantArt&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coiled Spring is an amulet made of brass. It’s disc shaped and about an inch
thick. On its front, there is a relief of a snake eating its own tail, the
classic Ouroboros. The inside of the ring formed by the snake is a clear crystal
panel, through which can be seen a spring like that of a watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That spring can store up to ten Fatigue Points which can be used to enable
bursts of extra effort - most often &lt;em&gt;Extra Effort in Combat&lt;/em&gt; (p. B357), but also
other athletic feats. The stored FP can only be used for those purposes, and is
not affected by negative effects that would sap the user’s own FP. In other
words, it works just like the Heroic Reserves advantage from &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Dungeon
Fantasy 20: Slayers&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; like a power item for martial characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference between the Coiled Spring and a normal Power Item is that it
hijacks the natural recovery processes of the wearer’s body in order to “wind”
itself, and cannot be recharged by the usual methods for power items. While the
Spring is not at full capacity, its wearer is unable to recover their own
Fatigue Points, and the amulet gains 1 FP every 10 minutes. This is a constant
rate - traits which speed up FP recovery for the wearer have no effect on the
amulet. The wearer regains their usual ability to rest when the amulet is fully
charged, or when it’s removed (which stops the charging process).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this does mean recharging the Coiled Spring in town is effectively free,
it can make dungeon delving more complicated for martial characters,
particularly if the GM enforces rules like fatigue costs for fighting a battle
(p. B426 or DF Exploits p. 60). Characters who normally can’t use Fatigue Points
can wear the Coiled Spring and use it to benefit from the Extra Effort rules in
and out of combat, though they can’t recharge it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholars who know of the Spring speculate that it was originally meant  to allow
golems and other constructs to surpass their limits. In an adventure, it will
most likely be found worn by such a construct, or by an elite warrior who
figured out it works just as well for organics. If found in a chest or hoard,
though, it will always start out empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the delvers try to sell the Coiled Spring, or if you decide it’s available in
shops, its monetary value is twice that of a Power Item of the same
capacity. That’s $3400 for the 10 FP version described here, though you could
have versions with greater or smaller capacity. Note that you &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; double-dip
and use the Coiled Spring as a Power Item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variant Springs are possible. Maybe the Flywheel of Faith can power divine
magic, the Arcane Array wizardly spells, and the Goddess Gyre druidic ones. The
recharging mechanics and all other restrictions are the same. They could allow a
construct who can’t normally cast spells or use casting magical items due to a
lack of FP to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/10/coiled-spring.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/10/coiled-spring.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>artifact</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hacking Without a Hacker</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/lancer-horus.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    NPC hackers waiting for the PCs to arrive at the jackpoint.
    Illustration by Tom Parkinson Morgan.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether called a hacker, a decker, or a netrunner, the person who invades
computer systems and makes them do things features prominently in the stories
most cyberpunk RPGs take inspiration from, and so often ends up being a vitally
important archetype in those games. However, they tend to have a very mixed
track record when it comes to actually presenting you with a hacking system
that’s fun and bug-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means there are many possible reasons for why you might find yourself
planning a cyberpunk game but have no cause or wish to use its hacking
rules. Maybe none of the players wants to be a hacker, or maybe the group just
doesn’t like the rules of the game in question. In those cases, a popular
suggestion is to include a NPC hacker, and in this post we’ll discuss a way to
do so that keeps the rest of the group reasonably involved in the hacking. Rules
are for GURPS, but the concepts can be easily translated to other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-from-home&quot;&gt;Work From Home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current best practice in games that include hacker PCs is to devise ways to
keep the hacker together with the rest of the party, so that they can fully
participate in the game even when it’s not hacking time. When your group’s
hacker is an NPC, however, the best thing to do is the opposite. Hacker NPCs
should always do their thing remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing NPCs who constantly accompany the party is a tricky affair. A character
who’s much weaker than the party runs the risk of turning the adventure into a
video-game-style escort quest, one of the most reviled types of mission in
existence. One who is strong enough to protect themselves can end up becoming a
GMPC, a label reserved for annoying characters who overshadow the players and
make them feel like the support cast of someone else’s story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is subjective, which makes it even trickier. Your group’s fun will
be hurt if they &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; either of those scenarios is happening, even if the math
is well-balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remote hacker removes most of the risk. They’re in communication with the
group, and they can do the jobs covered by their niche, but any other challenge
that can be handled by the PC’s own skills &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be, even if it’s
technological in nature. And there are things the hacker can only do with
on-site support from the PCs, which keeps them involved in the actual hack even
if you’re not engaging with those rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact nature of these support tasks depends on how your specific setting
handles computers and hacking. Most games either go the same Retro way of early
Shadowrun and CP2020, or a more “Modern” way that uses more recent tropes such
as the ones employed by Shadowrun 4th Edition or CP2077. We’ll look at how you
can accommodate a remote NPC hacker in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-future-of-another-timeline&quot;&gt;The Future of Another Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not immediately obvious to us here in 2023, but the earliest iterations of
Shadowrun’s Matrix and CP2020’s NET were based on a pre-Internet model of
networked computing. Strip all the futuristic terms from their description and
you’ll find out you’re dealing with 80s mainframes. This lies at the root of a
lot of things there that can look a bit weird or silly to modern
readers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Here’s a short and approximately correct explanation for how that
works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainframes are huge (and hugely expensive) computers that are usually
responsible for handling all data processing for an entire company or
organization. They were the dominant form of institutional computing from around
the 1950s to at least the early 1990s, and never really went away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mainframe is operated through remote terminals, which can be in the same
building or even off-site. Therefore, it must be ready to receive connections
and requests from these terminals. And the way you do that in the 80s is through
phone lines and modems. They do have &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; security measures to
authenticate users and prevent one user from seeing or changing other users’
data, but there is no such thing as a firewall because permanent Internet
connections are not yet a thing for mainframes. The most security you can add to
the connection step is to keep the numbers for your mainframe’s phone lines
unlisted&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is why both Shadowrun’s and CP2020’s descriptions of their “global
nets” are so concerned about splitting them into geographical regions and
assigning codes to them and the servers within them. That net is not the
&lt;em&gt;Internet&lt;/em&gt;, but a world-spanning phone circuit. The first step to hacking
into that corporate mainframe is to dial the unlisted number of its modem&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-school-remote-hacking&quot;&gt;Old-School Remote Hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have a PC hacker in these more “retro” games, the number of the
target’s modem line might be included with the mission briefing, letting them
hack removely. It’s more likely that no number is included, then the hacker has
to go in with the group and find an terminal in the target facility through
which they could connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a hacker NPC and they have the number, the reason the adventure is
happening at all is because the mission objectives have a physical component
that must happen at the same time. The typical setup is that you need to steal
the physical prototype while the hacker grabs the research files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they don’t have the number, then &lt;em&gt;discovering&lt;/em&gt; the number becomes one of the
physical mission objectives! The place the PCs are infiltrating might not even
have any direct relation to the real, final objective, but it could be a place
that also uses the same mainframe remotely. The number is going to be written
down somewhere in there, either in an official manual, some employee’s personal
notes or even a scrap of paper that was carelessly thrown away&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Some
non-VR-dungeon hacking of a physical terminal to peek at its configuration might
be necessary, which might be resolved by a couple of rolls since dumb terminals
are less secure than the mainframe they talk to. Or you might need to find a way
to scam the info out of an someone who works there (“social engineering”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fact-finding expedition could be a whole adventure in itself, or it might
just be an intermediate step in a more complex operation where the group must
also infiltrate the final target facility at the same time as the hacker does
their thing, as outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twenty-minutes-from-now&quot;&gt;Twenty Minutes From Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent cyberpunk games tend to base their networks on the real-world
Internet and the technologies that support it. This means that every individual
device attached to a network is effectively a full-feature computer, be it an
employee’s workstation, a security camera, or a guard’s smartphone. Different
departments have their own private servers and their own internal network that
doesn’t necessarily connect to the others or to the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less sensitive facilities might allow employees to work remotely from their
homes or from other buildings by letting them connect via &lt;em&gt;virtual private
networks&lt;/em&gt;. These connections to happen over the Internet, but they’re encrypted
and protected from general snooping. Realistically, our dastardly hacker would
need to steal valid credentials to be able to access a VPN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other extreme, a top-secret secure facility might be &lt;em&gt;air-gapped&lt;/em&gt;, which
means it’s isolated and sealed in such a way that no signal can enter or leave
the building. None of its internal networks are connected to the outside world,
and they are not connected to each other either unless this is absolutely
necessary. The servers controlling the security system are isolated from the
servers housing sensitive data. Each has its own independent set of protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is both realistic according to our contemporary understanding of network
security, and an excellent way to make sure PC hackers stick with the group and
have plenty to do once inside. Individual hacking attempts tend to be shorter
but more numerous, and made against devices that are within the hacker’s
immediate reach&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Shadowrun 4th Edition goes deep into this (5th and onwards
go back to the retro model), and it’s also more or less how things work in
Cyberpunk 2077.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-school-remote-hacking&quot;&gt;New-School Remote Hacking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an environment so full of incentives for the hacker to stick with the party,
how can you accommodate a remote NPC hacker?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the target facility has a VPN that contains the data you want, then many of
the same “classic” techniques for acquiring those old-school mainframe phone
numbers might also work to acquire valid VPN credentials, allowing the NPC to
hack the place remotely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it doesn’t have a VPN or is completely isolated, then we need to resort to
quantum bullshit. Below we’ll see GURPS stats for the bullshit in question,
imported directly from Warframe. It’s easily usable in other systems, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/CorpusDatamass.webp&quot; width=200/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A datamass.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;datamass&lt;/strong&gt; is a device similar in concept to the causality communicator in
Ultra-Tech page 45, but &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; cheaper. It consists of an armored,
briefcase-sized device that incorporates several kinds of data cable plus laser
and IR micro-communicators and a small radio (GURPS Ultratech pages 43-44). All
of these are connected to a sizable amount of quantum-entangled matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Datamasses are made in entangled pairs that allow high-bandwidth communication
and data transfer between elements of the pair through any amount of barriers or
interference. They have DR 10, HP 8, cost $5000 for the pair, weight 5kg (10 lb)
each, and are LC1 (AKA &lt;em&gt;super illegal&lt;/em&gt;). They also include an emergency
self-destruct switch that melts the internals of both elements of the pair and
can be triggered from either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your typical cyberpunk setting, datamasses were first invented as
super-secret espionage tools by a major government or computer-focused megacorp,
and initially gave them a major leg up in one of the many ongoing cold wars
between such entities. The secret of their existence soon leaked, however, and
an enterprising independent engineer figured out they were quite easy to make
with a properly modified home 3d printer. Yes, even the entangled matter. The
plans for a home-baked datamasses were soon made widely available on the Net,
and they keep popping up no matter how much effort the corps spend to squash
them. That’s why they’re relatively cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Datamass technology is going to be really revolutionary when FTL travel is
invented in the distant future, but for now it’s mostly used for its original
purpose, and allows teams of plucky street mercs like the PCs to operate at the
same level as crack corporate commandos when it comes to high-level
espionage. If the PCs are hired to do a hacking mission, they will usually be
provided a datamass pair. PCs can also buy their own through the usual illegal
channels available to PCs in these games. It should be difficult, but not
impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a setting that has datamasses, hacking missions look a lot like the Warframe
“mobile defense” missions these devices come from. The PCs need to sneak into
the target facility carrying a datamass, and find a place where to connect it. A
direct cable connection to a machine in the target network is best. A wi-fi
connection will do in a pinch, but will make everything that follows take
longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the hacker is an NPC, you don’t need to roll anything for the actual
hack - you just need to give the PCs a time frame for when it will be done. And
then they must stay near the datamass and guard it until that much time has
elapsed. If they snuck in, they need to find a way to maintain stealth and
divert security attention from their access point. If they’re found out, it
turns into a fight, but they still must stay until the hack is done or it will
fail. For added Fun(TM), a difficult mission might require the party to do this
several times from different access points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The self-destruct switch is useful for when the hack is done, as it allows the
party to leave without having to lug the datamass back out. It can also prevent
the hacker from being traced if the device is captured. Or it can be used in a
double-cross that leaves the team stranded in enemy territory without network
support. Use that last one sparingly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Alas, it’s not related to the whole VR Dungeon thing. That’s weird and
silly for other reasons. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The real-world practice of &lt;em&gt;wardialing&lt;/em&gt; consisted of dialing every number
in a big list or an entire area code looking for accessible modems. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And you can absolutely go wardialiing there. The Genesis version of
Shadowrun even implements it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The real world hacking practice of &lt;em&gt;dumpster diving&lt;/em&gt; consists in searching
a company’s trash for discarded papers with valid passwords and credentials
written down on them. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Anywhere from “directly plugged in” to “in the same local wi-fi network”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/10/08/hacking-without-hackers.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Play Hell's Rebels: Devils and other Fiends</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My recent adaptation efforts for that Hell’s Rebels campaign had me going on a
spelunking expedition about fiend stats in D&amp;amp;D. Here’s what I found out, and
what I intend to do about it on this GURPS adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our purposes here, “fiend” refers to all of the monsters that originate from
the “evil planes” of the D&amp;amp;D universe: demons, devils, daemons, and
others. “Fiend” was the only general term left, so we’re using it in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fiends-in-dd&quot;&gt;Fiends in D&amp;amp;D&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D’s fiend situation is one of the most egregious examples of its tendency
towards overly-complicated taxonomies&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Every synonym becomes the name of a
distinct type of monster with stats that differ from those of the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real purpose of the divide here seems to be mechanical: in most editions
each type has a different lengthy list of weaknesses and resistances that seems
calculated to confuse players. Things that are good against devils are bad
against demons and vice-versa - if the PCs guess wrong, they’re in trouble. The
specifics here change from edition to edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, early editions made a big deal out of the fact that devils were
Lawful Evil and demons Chaotic Evil. Later ones tried to elaborate on it and
find more ways to explain that the two alignments were different at a
fundamental cosmic level. Pathfinder really doubles down on that, trying to find
additional themes for every fiend type it presents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathfinder 1e, which is what we’re interested in, has this configuration for the
mechanical bits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Demons are immune to lightning; Devils take normal damage from it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Devils are immune to fire; Most demons are merely resistant to it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They’re equally resistant to acid and cold.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They’re both immune to poison.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They’re resistant to weapon attacks unless the weapon is Good-aligned &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;
made from a special material. For demons, that’s cold iron; for devils,
silver. Powerful specimens have resistance that can only be bypassed by
weapons fulfilling both the alignment and material requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about as complex to describe as it was in previous editions, but it’s
actually much easier to completely bypass due to the combinatorial explosion in
spells and magical effects available to players compared to AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first couple of levels you can forget about the materials requirement
entirely, because you’ll have access to Align Weapon or the Holy enchantment. By
the time you’re fighting those stronger fiends, you’ll probably have a +3 weapon
in hand, which also bypasses both material requirements. And as for elemental
damage types, this is the edition that introduces sonic damage, which damages
both demons and devils normally. It also makes it quite easy for a character to
swap all of their spells’ damage to sonic&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fiends-in-dungeon-fantasy&quot;&gt;Fiends In Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy is a lot simpler. Demon is one of the big monster categories in
the game, and all demons come from the area colloquially known as Hell. The
specifics are left as an exercise to the GM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belonging to the Demon category makes them immune to magic that affects the
minds of natural creatures and susceptible to magic that affects spirits in
general or demons in particular. They don’t count as “alive” for spells that
strictly require living targets but always count as “evil” for spells and
abilities that affect evil creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most notably, they do not have any universal resistances to elemental damage or
mundane weapons. Each demon “species”, other than the very weakest ones, does
have additional defenses. Most take damage as normal but can only &lt;em&gt;die&lt;/em&gt; if a
specific condition is met. They also often lack some or all of the weak points
of natural creatures, such as blood and vital organs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaming Ballistic’s &lt;em&gt;Nordlond Bestiary&lt;/em&gt; does include some demons that are direct
adaptations of D&amp;amp;D fiends, but only the most powerful of them (the Balor and Pit
Fiend equivalents) have resistances that resemble Pathfinder’s to any degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-will-i-do-in-hells-rebels&quot;&gt;What Will I Do in Hell’s Rebels?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was starting this project way back in 2017, I’d probably be gearing up to
convert every devil that appeared in Hell’s Rebels to GURPS. But since this is
2023, I don’t have to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;em&gt;plenty&lt;/em&gt; of first- and third-party Dungeon Fantasy books now, and between
them I have more than enough stat blocks available that I can just pick whatever
looks closer to the original monster and use that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does mean that I’m going to end up ignoring a lot of the default D&amp;amp;D
cosmology and lore when picking my monsters. “Demon” and “devil” are once again
synonyms - there is no fundamental cosmic difference between them. They all come
from the same place. Any differences, if they ever become relevant, are
political rather than taxonomical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also ignoring the difference between Lawful Evil and Chaotic Evil because
1) there is no alignment in GURPS DF and 2) it’s a bit nonsensical anyway. In
fact, &lt;em&gt;Pathfinder itself&lt;/em&gt; is going to get rid of alignment in its upcoming
revised second edition, which was motivated by an attempt to rid itself of all
remaining ties to the OGL after this January’s brouhaha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game’s existing rules should suffice to determine whether something counts
as “holy”/”good” or “unholy”/”evil” for game purposes. This is a similar
approach to what I hear PF 2.5 is going to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Another famous one is incorporeal undead. Is that thing a wraith, a
specter, a shade, or a ghost? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;That’s assuming they want to fight fair in the first place instead of
casting one of this edition’s many instant fight-enders. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/22/lphr-fiends.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/22/lphr-fiends.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>gm-hat</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Underwater Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/geoffrey-ernault-skeletonpirateslq.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a
  href=&quot;https://www.artstation.com/artwork/3dvodY&quot;&gt;Illustration by Geoffrey Ernault&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Underwater adventuring is one of those things that older editions of Dungeons
and Dragons seemed to like more than their players did. Lots of monster books
included a selection of monsters that could only be encountered under the sea,
but every bit of commentary I read on those was always about how no one ever
bothered to include submarine delves in their campaigns. If a sea monster
couldn’t go up to the surface to attack a ship or climb on its deck, it was
usually ignored by GMs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dungeon Fantasy lines learned this lesson well, and don’t spend a lot of ink
on support for underwater adventures. This was a big problem for me when I was
GMing Hell’s Rebels to a group of friends. This particular adventure path
follows the old tradition of making PCs spend a chunk of levels 5-8
underwater. When I got to that part in my GURPS conversion, I had no idea what
to do and got a bit stressed out trying to figure this out on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frantically researching rules in real time is no fun at all even when I am the
only player, so for the benefit of my solo Hell’s Rebels game and any future
run-throughs with actual players, I’m going to collect everything I know about
fighting underwater in GURPS right here in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit I don’t have all the officially published primary sources that discuss
underwater adventuring. The ones I’m using are &lt;strong&gt;DF: Exploits&lt;/strong&gt; and the
simplified rules that can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2019/01/simplified-df-underwater-combat-revised.html&quot;&gt;Dungeon Fantastic&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
reference the sources I don’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;underwater-fighting-for-land-lubbers&quot;&gt;Underwater Fighting For Land-Lubbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not an aquatic creature, you use these rules when fighting underwater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your Move is limited to your Swimming move: Basic Speed/5, minimum 1.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All of your skills are capped at the level of your DX-based &lt;strong&gt;Swimming&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thrusting and unarmed strikes receive no penalties.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some grappling techniques won’t work. Others work as normal. GM adjudicates.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swinging attacks with Reach 1+ weapons are impossible. This does cover pretty
much every weapon listed in DF: Adventurers, as even small knives have a Reach
of “C, 1” when swung.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shield bashes are -2 x DB to hit and do half damage. Don’t bother trying.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Blocks are impossible but you still get your shield’s DB.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Parries with Reach 1+ weapons are impossible. Parries with close-combat-only
weapons like daggers, and unarmed parries, are allowed and suffer no
penalties.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dodge is possible and not penalized, but you can’t Retreat.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No thrown ranged attacks, even from Missile spells. Special underwater ranged
weapons exist and use specific stats.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ranged attacks into our out of water have -4 to hit, 1/10 range, and do half
damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All through this, you’ll be holding your breath under Heavy Exertion (DF:
Exploits p. 21)!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;underwater-fighting-for-fish-and-fish-people&quot;&gt;Underwater Fighting for Fish and Fish-People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water adaptation in GURPS has two main components. One is the ability to
&lt;em&gt;breathe&lt;/em&gt; underwater. The other is the ability to &lt;em&gt;move freely&lt;/em&gt; while
submerged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In monsters, the first is handled by traits such as &lt;strong&gt;Gills&lt;/strong&gt;, some variety of
&lt;strong&gt;Doesn’t Breathe&lt;/strong&gt;, or the ability to hold their breath for a really long time
even in combat. A combatant with one of these traits doesn’t need to worry about
the standard Breath Holding rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is handled by the &lt;strong&gt;Amphibious&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Aquatic&lt;/strong&gt; traits. If you have
one of these traits, you get a lot of advantages over land-lubbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your get to use your full Move and skills, not limited by your Swimming.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are exempt from most skill penalties from being underwater and from many
Swimming tests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can Retreat!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your other attacks and defenses are limited as for land-lubbers. This is
important for weapon users, not so much for aquatic beasts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-delver-to-diver&quot;&gt;From Delver to Diver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a typical delver belonging to one of DFRPG’s standard ancestries, then
you fall squarely in the “land-lubber” category, and you have to solve a couple
of problems before you can dive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breathing&quot;&gt;Breathing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want your underwater life expectancy to be measured in seconds, you
need to find a way to breathe in there. In most typical DF settings, that means
magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;spells&quot;&gt;Spells&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DFRPG boxed set includes two main drowning-prevention measures: the
&lt;strong&gt;Breathe Water&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Hold Breath&lt;/strong&gt; spells. They have different
prerequisite chains but work the same, letting you ignore that part of the rules
for as long as they last. Both have a base duration of 1 minute and an energy
cost of 4 to cast and 2 to maintain, reduced by skill as normal. Hold Breath
is a little better because it also let you survive in non-watery environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main disadvantage is that their duration is relatively short. Unless the
PC casting these spells has a skill of 20 or more with them, the affected
character is only going to be able to remain underwater for a few minutes at a
time. That’s nowhere near enough for a full delve, and it’s an even shorter time
if you need to maintain this spell for multiple PCs. If the caster &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have
skill 20 then things get a lot easier, but that costs a lot of points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;items&quot;&gt;Items&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we expand our scope a little to look at DF supplements, then we see that
Dungeon Fantasy Magic Items 1 has an alchemical &lt;strong&gt;Water-Breathing Amulet&lt;/strong&gt;. You
can breathe underwater as long as you wear it… but it costs an amazing
$23.400. Outfitting a party of 5 with that is a very expensive proposition,
unless you find them as treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A reusable casting item like a wand or ring with the Breathe Water spell would
cost at least $8200. This basic version would be powered by the user, so it has
the same duration limits as the spell. Doubling the price would halve the energy
cost, which is better but not perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if we expand our scope even further and break out of the DFRPG bubble,
we can go to GURPS Magic and find an alchemical &lt;strong&gt;water-breathing elixir&lt;/strong&gt; that
costs $600 in a setting with common magic and gives you the ability to breathe
water for 1d hours! Even a minimal roll gives you a nice amount of time to
explore, and per that book’s rules you’ll know the duration is about to expire 5
minutes in advance, which is better than nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That elixir is clearly the best approach for campaigns where underwater delves
are a sometimes thing. They’re a little less convenient than the amulet, but the
price can’t be beat. I’m definitely including this in my campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving&quot;&gt;Moving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless your delvers are willing to spend the time and points to become
better-than-Olympic swimmers, solving their underwater movement issues also
means resorting to magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;spells-1&quot;&gt;Spells&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DF: Spells gives us two options here: &lt;strong&gt;Swim&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Ethereal Body&lt;/strong&gt;. The first
makes the subject effectively Amphibious, the second makes them intangible and
thus able to ignore all that water. GURPS Magic additionally gives us &lt;strong&gt;Walk
Through Water&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes the user intangible only to water and ice. This
means you don’t enjoy 3D movement while underwater… but your maneuvers in
combat are unrestricted! I think I can kinda see why this one didn’t make the
cut to the DFRPG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with water-breathing, our biggest limitation here are spell maintenance
costs, which limit our unimpeded movement to a few minutes at most. These are
also harder to completely eliminate, since Ethereal Body costs 4 energy per
minute to maintain and the others cost 3. Still, a caster could conceivably save
these for when a fight is about to start, and only cast it on the group’s
physical fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;magic-items&quot;&gt;Magic Items&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find an always-on item with a Swim enchantment in the books I own. A
basic casting item for Swim will cost at least $20500, almost as expensive as
the always-on water breathing amulet. Lowering its casting/maintenance cost from
6/3 to 3/2 doubles the price, lowering it to 2/1 quadruples it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might built this as a charged item instead, with each charge giving you 2
minutes of Swim time and costing 9 energy. A non-rechargeable item would cost
$1350 per charge, a rechargeable one $2700 (plus $180 per charge to reload).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Walk Through Water is allowed in the campaign, an item with the same duration
per charge would be a tad cheaper: $910/$1820/$140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any of these cases, the item is best used sparingly, in the same manner as
the spell. You activate it when it’s time for a big fight or a crucial skill
test, and rely on your Swimming lessons the rest of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optimal-strategies&quot;&gt;Optimal Strategies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all of the above, I think we can pretty easily arrive at an “optimal”
strategy for underwater expeditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your group is about to embark in a &lt;strong&gt;campaign centered around underwater
delving&lt;/strong&gt;, your PC party should include a caster who can use Breathe Water at
Skill-20, and also someone who can use Swim at Skill-15. A druid or wizard could
do both, a cleric can use Breathe Water and leave Swim to someone else. This is
a hefty investment, but worth it for the amount of use they’ll get out of
it. Every PC, caster or not, should also consider investing points into the
Swimming skill, because it can help conserve spell energy and is pretty useful
in itself. You might want to give them extra points for these purposes depending
on your desired power level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative here is for you to allow players to make PCs from ancestries that
have an easy time underwater. Both Sea Elves from GURPS DF 3 and &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/10/10/elder-scrolls-others.html&quot;&gt;Argonians&lt;/a&gt;
from this blog have Gills and are Amphibious. &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/09/17/dfrpg-warforged.html&quot;&gt;Warforged&lt;/a&gt; are a bit less
nimble but don’t need to breathe at all. Each delver who is a natural-born diver
will make the rest of the party’s life that much easier. For those who aren’t,
Water-Breathing Amulets make excellent treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re planning a standard campaign that features a &lt;strong&gt;one-off underwater
dungeon&lt;/strong&gt;, Water-Breathing Elixirs are the way to go, possibly supplemented by
one or two rechargeable Wands of Swimming. The elixirs should definitely be
easily available in a nearby town (perhaps it’s a coastal fishing village?). The
wands might be for sale as well, or might be found as treasure either before or
during the delve. Proper safety procedure is to carry two elixirs per
PC, saving the second one for the return trip if the first one wears off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only have &lt;strong&gt;isolated underwater encounters&lt;/strong&gt;, we’re back to learned
spells, but they don’t need to have high levels. The submerged environment
becomes an additional challenge, but no one is going to spend too long inside
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell’s Rebels in particular fits the second category, so I’ll be using that
solution.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>gm-hat</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Play Hell's Rebels!</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started a Let’s Read of Hell’s Rebels way back when it was new, in 2017. I had
gotten the campaign’s first three volumes with alongside a huge pile of other
Pathfinder PDFs in one of Humble Bundle’s offerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to publish articles about the first three of those books here, though
I kinda stalled out between volumes 2 and 3. I still want to “Let’s Read” the
rest one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post, and the series it starts, are about something a bit different. You
see, ever since I got those books I also had a desire to &lt;em&gt;run&lt;/em&gt; this campaign,
but I didn’t want to do so using Pathfinder 1e’s default system. No, I wanted,
and still want, to use the Dungeon Fantasy RPG for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually did it, too! This was during the thick of the pandemic here in
Brazil, so I ran it on Roll20 with a group of friends. We got through the first
two adventures, but I ended up stopping that campaign because the combined
workload became a bit too heavy for me. I had to convert everything, prepare
battle maps and tokens for Roll20, adjudicate setting developments in response
to PC actions, and do all of that on time for the next session in two weeks
while juggling all the other stress sources those interesting times produced for
me and my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still wanted to go through the whole thing, whether as a GM or as a player. As
a GM, I no longer had any confidence I could prepare everything I needed on
schedule. As a player, I had that peculiar problem where the only person I knew
who wanted to run that adventure in the exact way I wanted to play it was
me. Clearly, there was only one solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;running-this-thing-as-a-solo-campaign&quot;&gt;Running this thing as a solo campaign&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually decided to run Hell’s Rebels for myself as a solo campaign way back
at the beginning of 2023, but it took until the start of June for me to finally
find the inspiration I was lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This won’t be my first “solo” campaign: I ran through the first two Zeitgeist
adventures that way between 2015 and 2017, give or take a year. That attempt
lost steam due to the issues I’m about to discuss, but it was pretty fun while
it lasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solo campaign attempts don’t have much in common with others I’ve seen
online. Those games tend to be quite minimalistic, with a single protagonist run
by the solo player, a setting sketched in broad strokes, and some sort of
“divination engine” taking the place of the GM. There is no pre-defined plot at
all - it’s entirely decided by asking questions to the engine and interpreting
its answers. The protagonist might have a starting goal, but how hard that is to
reach and what happens on the way are determined randomly. Note-taking seems
pretty minimal, unless the player in question wants to post actual play reports
online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, there is absolutely nothing wrong with that approach and it is in
fact the one I would recommend to most people who want to do a solo game. All of
the solo game products out there support it, and it is excellent at replicating
the experience of being a player in a game and not knowing what will happen
next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also not the approach I’m going to use for myself. I guess I’m built
different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest difference between this game and one using the “best practice”
approach outlined above is that I have a pre-defined module I want to run: the
Hell’s Rebels Adventure Path. Not only do I want to play that, I’ve already read
the first four volumes quite closely. While I find it easy to “forget” this
stuff when I’m just a player, here I’m also the GM, which makes separating this
knowledge impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I have this weird desire to run it in a way that mirrors a
standard party-based campaign with multiple players as closely as possible. I
want a &lt;em&gt;party&lt;/em&gt; of heroes, and I want to be both player and GM at the same
time. I want it to be GURPS, and I want to interact with the mechanical widgets
of that system because I find them fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I don’t want to just keep a minimal set of notes. I’m not gonna
write things as a novel or anything, but I kinda want to see the game’s events
rendered as a reasonably comprehensive actual play report of the sort I see in
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Dungeon Fantastic&lt;/a&gt; blog. I’d do that even if I &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; intend to post
them publicly - it’s what I did for Zeitgeist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-im-doing-this&quot;&gt;How I’m doing this&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My strange preferences bring two big risks to this endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is the lack of an “information barrier” between player and
GM. This barrier and the dramatic tension it brings do not exist when player and
GM are the same person. The usual strategies for separating in-character
knowledge from out-of-character information do not work here, at least for
me. This gives me the strange simultaneous feeling that I’m “cheating” (as a
player) and “going too easy on the PCs” (as a GM). This is obviously an obstacle
to fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other issue is with preparing maps and tokens. Sure, this would be much
easier on me if I ran everything in the theater of the mind, but I like moving
figures around on a battle map. The problem on my earlier attempts was that I
would usually leave the &lt;em&gt;building&lt;/em&gt; of those battle maps to the very last second,
when I’d be in a rush to get on with the action. This also means I never took
the necessary time to familiarize myself with the software I was using. So I’d
stall, and procrastinate, and take two months to finish something that could
have been done in a couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve both of these issues, I’m going to make a resolution to never wear the
GM and player hats at the same time. The GM hat is for preparation. The player
hat is for “actual play”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gm-hat&quot;&gt;The GM Hat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During preparation, I’m going to consider myself a mix of GM and designer and
I’m going to lean on my newly-discovered feelings of Miniature Envy. You see, a
lot of the online friends I’ve made in the past year and a half are very much
into tabletop wargaming. They have extensive miniature collections and extremely
well-organized workspaces for assembling and painting them. They often post the
results of their work online and it always looks awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have neither the space, skill, nor the budget to do the same thing, but I
&lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; look at the process of building battle maps and actor tokens in GCS,
TokenTool and Foundry with the same sort of perspective. Learning how to use the
software and actually building the things, then, becomes a hobby in itself. And
there’s no time or schedule pressure, so there’s no problem if I take a bit
longer in this part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will also be when I actually convert enemy stats, tests, and treasure from
the adventure’s original Pathfinder 1e to GURPS Dungeon Fantasy. I’ll try to
make them useful to others who want to try running the adventure in a more
traditional manner, but I won’t bother converting rules material for those paths
my PCs never take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also perform some significant “condensation” in the campaign. Like all
Pathfinder adventure paths, Hell’s Rebels includes a lot of filler fights
placed to give your PCs enough XP for them to hit the expected character levels
at the right times. It also features lots of elements that get added only on
later books but which could be relevant from the start. Neither of these things
are necessary in a Dungeon Fantasy campaign where the PCs already start out
powerful and advance in a completely different manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I have a large enough chunk of unplayed material, I’m going to take
off my GM hat and become a player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-player-hat&quot;&gt;The Player Hat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve the information barrier issue, I’m going to just learn to stop worrying
and love the cheese. When I’m wearing my player hat, it will be like I’m playing
a computer game with a walkthrough open. Sure, I might know what’s coming, and I
might even have a party custom-tailored to overcome those challenges, but the
&lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of overcoming those challenges can still be quite fun. It can even
still be surprising, depending on what the dice tell me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps that this is the campaign whose main goal is punching fantasy
Nazis. Even if I know what’s coming, the actual process of going through it can
still be fun. Let us make awesome heroes tailored to the challenge and
completely stomp those fascist fuckers into the fucking ground! Let’s kick their
asses all the way to the Hell they came from! I want catharsis, dangit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also try to pay special attention to my characters’ disadvantages and
other traits, and obey the dictates of those self-control rolls. And when some
kind of question appears during the “actual play” part, I’m going to use
the Mythic GM Emulator to answer it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-in-this-for-you&quot;&gt;What’s in this for you?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This effort is going to generate a lot of material for this blog! I expect
readers will get some use out of my premade PCs, and out of the enemy stat
blocks I generate. Everything from those stats to the “actual play” reports and
design commentary is going to be published here.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/08/lets-play-hells-rebels.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/07/08/lets-play-hells-rebels.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>solo-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wealth in D&amp;D and Dungeon Fantasy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One thing I’ve done pretty often these past few years is converting D&amp;amp;D and
Pathfinder adventures for use with Dungeon Fantasy (either version). These
conversions didn’t have nowhere near the level of rigor of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/projects/dragons-dogma/&quot;&gt;Dragon’s
Dogma&lt;/a&gt; adaptation, but that larger project did give me a solid grounding on
the basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Converting from one tabletop system to the other is fairly easy, for the most
part, but there are some aspects of it that I found harder to do, especially on
the fly. One of these is converting wealth between the two systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I’ll be comparing the Dungeon Fantasy RPG and Pathfinder 1st
Edition and trying to come up with a way to convert monetary amounts from the
latter to the former. I chose the DFRPG because I use its monetary system in my
games, and I chose Pathfinder 1e because I want to convert Hell’s
Rebels. Pathfinder 1e, of course, shares most of its base assumptions with D&amp;amp;D
3.5, the system from which it is derived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-money-looks-like&quot;&gt;What Money Looks Like&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy purposefully makes its coins have the exact same dimensions as
those of D&amp;amp;D, and therefore Pathfinder. They both use chunky standardized coins
that weight 1/50th of a pound (around 10 grams). These come in copper, silver,
gold, and a few other exotic materials that we don’t need to look at right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dimensions are apparently universal standards, and their value comes from
their precious metal content. If you find a chest of thousand-year-old gold
coins in an ancient dungeon, you can carry them back to town and spend them on
the market right away. Finding “non-standard” coins is usually a rare special
case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, though their physical dimensions are identical, their values seem
to be derived from completely different assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-money-buys&quot;&gt;What Money Buys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all variants of GURPS, Dungeon Fantasy expresses its prices and values in
“GURPS dollars”, or “$”. The exact value of this unit of currency varies with
the setting. Here, $1 is the worth of a copper piece. Silver pieces are worth 20
copper pieces each ($20). Gold pieces are worth 20 silver pieces each
($400). This means GURPS is effectively on a copper standard. The vast majority
of Dungeon Fantasy characters gets $1000 to buy their starting gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Pathfinder we have the classic decimal setup where 1gp == 10sp == 100cp. The
most common coin is the gold piece, and nearly everything in the core book’s
gear chapter has its price expressed in gp. So here we’re on a &lt;em&gt;gold&lt;/em&gt;
standard. Starting money is determined by a random roll that varies per
class. Fighter-types start with an average of 175gp, others start with less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases, this starting money is meant to let you buy your main weapon,
perhaps a backup or shield, a suit of armor, and the miscellaneous sundries that
make up your typical adventurer’s kit: a pouch or pack, some camping supplies
and rations, and maybe some tools like the thief’s lockpick set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there on out, things start to diverge quite sharply, and the way I see it
it’s mainly the fault of Pathfinder’s Wealth By Level table. It subjects PCs to
the tyranny of inflation. This plus the difference in base value means that
while a haul of a thousand gold pieces is a fantastic fortune for even veteran
Dungeon Fantasy delvers, it starts out at “pretty nice” for low-level Pathfinder
adventurers and quickly becomes “pocket change” for high-level ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-our-exchange-rate&quot;&gt;So What’s Our Exchange Rate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can start with the guidelines presented in the Exploits book: an adventure
should pay at least enough for the party to recoup their expenses with
consumables, power item recharge, and the cost of staying in town during
downtime. It’s perfectly OK for it to pay more than that, even &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more than
that, because it’s relatively easy to get rid of “excess” money by giving them
opportunities to spend it. Maybe a weird old man has a treasure map to sell, or
a mystical artifact or something. Magic items don’t count as part of character
wealth for this, as the game’s attitude to them is more similar to early D&amp;amp;D
than modern Pathfinder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after all of that I think we can safely say that a Pathfinder 1e gold piece
should be worth around &lt;strong&gt;$5&lt;/strong&gt; in Dungeon Fantasy. This leads to amounts of money
that are sufficient to cover expenses with a little left over in low-level
adventures, and to increasingly bigger hauls in higher-level ones, but as we
established that’s OK. Some of those Pathfinder adventures even helpfully
provide us with domain mini-games of their own that can soak up that extra cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;performing-the-actual-conversion&quot;&gt;Performing the Actual Conversion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that basic exchange rate in mind, we can think about how that affects the
actual treasure our delvers find in the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coins&quot;&gt;Coins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piles of coins change to reflect their new value. The two main approaches you
could take here are to prioritize keeping the same value, or prioritize keeping
the same weight (which means keeping the same number of coins). Getting &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt;
value and weight to match is very hard, so I strongly recommend sticking to only
one unless you like solving &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knapsack_problem&quot;&gt;multi-dimensional knapsack problems&lt;/a&gt; in your
spare time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prioritizing &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; means those coin piles will end up smaller and lighter
than the originals. This will make hauling them off easier. I recommend against
condensing the pile as much as possible, because you don’t want to make
logistics &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; easy. Also, finding a single gold coin can be a bit of a letdown
even if it is worth a lot. This is the easiest approach to take on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prioritizing &lt;strong&gt;the number of coins&lt;/strong&gt; means the pile will have exactly the same
size and weight, but it will be made of a smaller denomination coins. Its actual
value will probably be a little higher or lower than that of the original, but
that’s OK as long as the value remains close. This could lead to a situation
where the group only takes the most valuable portions of the pile, but I guess
that’s true to how it was done in Old D&amp;amp;D too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;: A chest containing 100gp in Pathfinder should contain $500 in coins
when converted to DF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prioritizing value might give us a bag containing 25 silvers. That’s a
satisfying number of coins that still has a non-negligible weight.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Prioritizing weight might give us a chest containing 80 coppers and 20
silvers, with a total worth of $480.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gems-jewelry-and-art-objects&quot;&gt;Gems, Jewelry, and Art Objects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things tend to have pretty arbitrary values in both systems! The biggest
difference in how they handle selling this stuff in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Pathfinder, you can generally exchange them for their full listed value in
cash, making them perfectly efficient forms of portable wealth. PF adventurers
are quite likely to convert their coins into fancy jewelry when they need to
travel long distances, since it’s much lighter for its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dungeon Fantasy, the only thing that fetches its full value is coin or bulk
precious metals. Everything else, including gems, jewelry, and art objects, is
subject to the rules for appraisal and haggling. This means typical delvers are
likely to get less than full value for this stuff back in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My recommendation here is to use a doubled exchange rate: each gp of gems,
jewelry and treasure is worth $10. That’s the treasure’s &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; value, which
means a typical party will get half of that on average when they sell it back in
town. I feel this preserves the “original intention” of the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;magic-items&quot;&gt;Magic Items&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both systems have a lot to say about magic item pricing, so my strategy here is
to not attempt a conversion of the price at all. I convert the &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt; of the
item and figure out how much that would cost in Dungeon Fantasy if it was a new
item. Saying it like this makes it sound easy, but this can be complex enough to
warrant its own post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an item can be replicated with the standard enchantments from DF, it has
those enchantments and is priced accordingly. Items with unique functions might
be a bit harder, but I always have the “easy escape” there of just not assigning
a fixed price to these. Like DF Artifacts, they’re either impossible to sell in
the first place, or will be worth some arbitrary amount that matches what I want
the PCs to have at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/25/dungeon-fantasy-wealth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/25/dungeon-fantasy-wealth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Hell's Rebels Adventure 3, Part 3</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we come to the final part of our Let’s Read of the third Hell’s Rebels
adventure, “Dance of the Damned”. With the “regional support” missions complete,
the Rebellion’s stats can grow to their maximum values. We’re almost at the
point where things get real serious in Kintargo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution starts with a party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-5-the-ruby-masquerade&quot;&gt;Part 5: The Ruby Masquerade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barzilai Thrune has been organizing a grand masquerade ball to be hosted at the
Opera House ever since the start of this adventure. He advertises it as a way to
reconcile with his critics and to show everything is fine in Kintargo, but of
course it’s a dastardly trap. After the PCs close the Menador Gap he steps up
his time table and announces a date for the event. He might also end up doing it
on his original schedule if the PCs take too long to complete that key mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His plan is to use a troop of dottari and disguised devils to massacre the
ball’s attendants at the party’s climax, and doctor the evidence to blame the
Silver Ravens. This will give him an official excuse to begin hunting them down
in earnest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barzilai sends invitations to every noble or other prominent citizen he knows
does not support him. He’s not stupid enough to believe the PCs would attend if
he invited them directly, so he makes invitations relatively easy to acquire by
other means as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s at this point that the private investigator Tayacet Tiora makes contact
with the PCs. Barzilai had hired her to look into the Silver Ravens, and it’s
even possible they ran into her in previous adventures if the GM decided to use
that scene. This time, she’s found out enough to become convinced the PCs are in
the right, and she comes to warn them that the Masquerade is a trap. Her
recommendation is for the PCs to not attend, but she promises to help if they
insist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply not going is certainly an option. It ensures the safety of the PCs but
lets the trap spring on the innocent guests unopposed. The book also
contemplates the possibility that the PCs will want to break into the Opera
House early, which is actually a good call. The same security forces will be
present and they will be patrolling more aggresively, but there will be no
bystanders. The PCs would miss out on a few extra hob-nobbing opportunities but
would be in a much better tactical position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the adventure assumes the PCs do attend, however. It should be
fairly easy to get invitations for the whole party plus any allies they wish to
take. Tiora will also attend in this case, and be ready to help if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masquerade starts at 9 PM, and whatever day is most convenient for the
GM. The PCs should have ample time to prepare for this one, growing the
rebellion and aiming their NPC teams at the Opera House to provide
information. It’s even possible to plant an infiltrated saboteur among the
guards. With good rolls they should have a pretty good idea of the security
inside the place, and an extra ally on the inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;party-mechanics&quot;&gt;Party Mechanics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual ball is a bit of a skill challenge in the same vein as the Vyre
banquet. There’s an official dress code: outfits should include the color red,
everyone must wear a mask, and both should be fancy. Fortunately they can pass
anything up to medium armor and shields as part of the costume, but it’s
definitely worth it to have it adorned and to splurge on extravagant
masks. These give bonuses to social skills during the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like we had Banquet Points in Vyre, here we have Masque Points. PCs start
with an amount between 4 and 16 depending on how fancy their costumes are. NPC
allies they bring with them also affect this total. The ball is split into
half-hour segments, and each PC can perform one of several available actions
during this span of time. Some of these actions cost Masque Points, some can be
used to acquire more with good skill rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless the PCs have been making an effort to ingratiate themselves with the
noble houses during “strategic” play, this is their last real chance to do so
before things heat up. The Kintargo-aligned house heads should all be here, so
the party’s socialites can identify them and chat them up. Having to do this now
does add a layer of complication to the procedures, which is why I like the idea
of introducing this element early in the campaign instead and let players make
their own interaction opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;opera-house-layout-and-security&quot;&gt;Opera House Layout and Security&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Opera House has three floors and an extensive basement. The main seating
areas had all of their seats removed to host the ball. Most guests stay on the
ground floor, but the nobles gravitate towards the second floor balcony because
they like to look down on commoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two floors have a lot of backstage areas off to the sides, and the
third floor and basement are all “backstage”. Many of these areas were converted
in living spaces for Barzilai and his staff. All backstage areas are off-limits
to party guests, so PCs need to be sneaky when exploring them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a total of 22 dottari in the house, half of which attend to the guests
while wearing smiley masks. The other half stands in reserve, waiting for the
trap to spring. The dottari here use the same stats as the Menador soldiers,
with slightly different gear. This means the PCs should be able to handle small
groups of them just fine - the challenge is doing so without raising an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a troop of devils in here: two bone, six bearded, and a single
erinyes. One of the bone devils, Crizmerkis, has a few class levels on him and
is wearing an illusory disguise to look like Barzilai. The real Thrune has
relocated to the temple of Asmodeus, and does not appear in this adventure. The
other bone devil is in the orchestra pit, using his illusion magic to provide
the music for the ball. The remaining monsters are scattered through several
side rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the rooms also contains suspended cages for Barzilai’s pet cockatrices,
which can be released at the press of a switch. Unless the PCs or an ally break
the switch, these creatures will be released when the trap is sprung.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are a bunch of secret rooms in a sub-basement that used to belong
to the original Silver Ravens. Barzilai is using them to stash his treasures and
house his “prize” henchthings. Former Mayor Jilia Bailinus sleeps here as a
vampire, and the long-missing singer Shensen is also here as a statue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of additional secret chambers Thrune’s lackeys haven’t been
able to find, and which contain valuable Silver Ravens stuff. This includes the
crypts for the original Ravens, which confirm their fates and the fact that
Jackdaw, the last remaining member, might still be alive. And it also includes
the musical score for the Song of Silver, a potent ritual that will greatly help
the PCs in the climax of the rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using rebellion actions the PCs can arm themselves with plenty of information
before going in: a Covert Action can give them the map to the whole building,
even the secret-secret chambers with a good enough roll. And a Sabotage action
can place an infiltrator among the dottari. Once the PCs link up with the
infiltrator during the party, they can learn the composition and location of the
place’s entire security detail, devils included. The saboteur can also break the
cockatrice release switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several rooms that are noted as being rarely visited by both guests
and patrols, which makes them perfect places to hide bodies. So yup, time to
Assassin’s Creed it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;delving-the-masquerade&quot;&gt;“Delving” the Masquerade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say those covert actions are so vital that the GM should push for them
to happen if the players have been neglecting that aspect of the game. The PCs
are on the clock here and every little advantage helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party starts at 9PM. At 10PM, they have a special “Dance of the Damned”
event that takes up half an hour. At midnight an unmasking ceremony happens and
Crizmerkis springs the ambush with the aim of killing every single guest in the
house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs should carefully manage their masque points, with some of the party making
an effort to mingle and gain more while the rest spend them on exploration
actions. It’s important that the minglers manage to maintain the point total
above 0, and that the explorers avoid raising a general alarm. Either of these
things will cause Crizmerkis to spring the trap immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participation on the dance is optional, but winning the contest gives a ton of
Masque Points so the minglers will want to participate. This leaves them with 5
other segments on which to decide their actions before the trap is sprung.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explorers who refuse to take part in the contest have 6 segments on which to
act. Their priority target here should be taking out the dottari, because
they’re weaker and have less means of raising the alarm (several of the devils
are telepathic and can do so instantly). The less enemies there are at midnight,
the easier the final fight will be. Looting and detailed exploration of the
basement should wait until after the main ambush force is defeated. There are a
few extra monsters down there that will not take part in the ambush, so they can
be safely ignored for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-stroke-of-midnight&quot;&gt;The Stroke of Midnight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At midnight, Crizmerkis (disguised as Barzilai) will stop the music and make an
ominous speech. During the speech, the dottari will split into 11 pairs and
stand guard over every one of the building’s exits, locking those doors in the
process. Attacking them before the speech is done will cost the party a bunch of
Masque Points but will give them a surprise round and a tactical advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of the speech is that the guests present here have graciously
volunteered themselves to help maintain public order, by being massacred so the
blame can fall on the Silver Ravens and Barzilai can go after them. As soon as
it ends, the devils attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 300 guests in the house, not counting the PCs. The “spare” bone devil
and the erinyes will focus on slaughering them, while the bearded devils and
Crizmerkis will come for the PC directly. Most of them will be disguised as good
outsiders using illusions, but additional summoned devils and such will not have
disguises on. The PCs can draw the attention of the bone devil and erinyes by
engaging them in combat. If cornered, Crizmerkis might summon the vampire Jillia
Bailinus to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why killing the dottari early helps: if there are less of them, they’re
going to leave some of those exits unlocked and unprotected. The PCs &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; open
the exits so guests can leave: 1d6 guests escape every round for every unlocked
exit. With no open exits, 2d6 of them die every round to sheer crushing crowd
pressure. Those two devils kill even more per round if left alone. If you’re
using GURPS, read “every round” as “every six seconds”, otherwise things might
get a little impossible here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results-and-consequences&quot;&gt;Results and Consequences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event will go down in history as the Ruby Massacre. Whether the PCs or
Thrune are blamed for it depends on how well they do in this final fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs win the big fight they should have plenty of time to explore the rest
of the opera house. They’ll get to fight a pack of hellhounds being used as
guard animals in the basement, find Vampire Jilia’s coffing and stake her, and
find Shensen and the Song of Silver. There’s also a lot of other cool loot to be
had, including a scroll of resurrection that can be used to bring the former
Mayor back to life after she’s destroyed as a vampire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs loose, they’ll find themselves waking up inside a cell in Castle
Kintargo. Either way as soon as they leave the opera house we transition
directly to Volume 04, where we go full Assassin’s Creed: Brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Notes and Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book makes that final battle sound quite difficult, particularly if the PCs
didn’t prepare for it by coming into the party armed and taking out some of the
opposition ahead of time. Even if they did, it’s going to be hard to save all
the bystanders. Dungeon Fantasy delvers should have it a bit easier because
the GURPS version of these opponents won’t have HP in the triple digits, but
it’s going to be tough even for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same emphasis on etiquette from the Vyre banquet is present here, but here
it makes less sense given the surrounding context. The Silver Ravens only get
diplomatic/strategic benefits from thwarting the ambush if they have more than
20 Masque Points by the time the ambush starts. I guess this is supposed to
represent the final impression left on the survivors about who is to blame for
the massacre, but it feels odd to have the party save these people in a very
obvious manner and not be recognized for it. I’d say that saving the heads of
the noble houses at least should be more than enough to get them on-side for the
next adventure, if that hasn’t happened yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs have been buttering up the nobles on their own initiative prior to
this point, then the best strategic decision they can make is to break into the
opera house days before the ball, preferrably during daylight hours so the
vampire isn’t a factor. All the same enemies will still be there, but the whole
party can focus on exploring the area and taking them out. They’ll completely
forfeit the possible diplomatic rewards from the Masquerade, but not having to
split their focus between delving and socializing or rescuing bystanders is more
than worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 18:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/24/hells-rebels-3-part-3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/06/24/hells-rebels-3-part-3.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
