<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 14:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 14:39:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Neverwinter Woods</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Neverwinter Wood dominates the northern half of our regional map and is much
larger than the city that gives it its name. It’s a classic Creepy Forest, where
the canopies block out all sunlight and even in the safer trails it seems like
someone is always watching you from the shadows. And that’s just the baseline
mood - the Wood is also currently full of ill-intentioned outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters in a Neverwinter campaign might need to trek through this place for
any number of reasons. This section of the chapter covers some of the Wood’s
most notable places, but it’s large enough that you could run a full
hex-crawling campaign on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book actually includes rules for a “Creepy Woods” hazardous terrain type
that can be included in exploration or combat maps. Anyone on this terrain when
a fight starts must roll a save before rolling Initiative - if they fail,
they’re surprised during the first round. They also gain a -2 to Will while on
Creepy spaces and when they fail a Perception check there they always think they
heard something that’s not there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first post covers the “smaller” areas and “standard” geographical features
of the Woods. It also contains several faction strongholds that will each get
their own post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-crags&quot;&gt;The Crags&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a large mountain range that splits the Wood in two, running from NE to
SW. Mount Hotenow is the most notable place in the Crags, as it’s where the
Neverwinter River starts and also the source of the eruption that caused the
cataclysm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more besides the volcano though - this is a typical D&amp;amp;D mountain
range full of monsters, caves, and hidden valleys and is also rumored to contain
paths to lost Gauntlgrym. Whether those exist or not, the range does definitely
contain a lot of old Delzoun outposts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those outposts will give the Heir of Delzoun something to marvel at even if they
don’t find a path to the lost city here. They’re also targets for Netherese
plundering in their unceasing quest for magic items to burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iceless-waterways&quot;&gt;Iceless Waterways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Wood’s rivers are warmed by Hotenow’s heat, so they never freeze even
during winter, and generally act to keep the forest warm and untouched by the
seasons. They teem with non-monstrous aquatic wildlife but never gave rise to
monsters - except for the River Morgur, the northernmost tributary of the
Neverwinter. It’s still iceless, but also has river monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bones-of-thundertree&quot;&gt;Bones of Thundertree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thundertree used to be a logging village that produced a lot of quality
timber. It was completely destroyed by the eruption, and all of its surviving
inhabitants fled to never return. The place is now haunted by possessed plant
monsters (take plant monster stat blocks of your choice and give them undead
traits). Aside from them, only the dwarf Favria, leader of the more violent
faction of the Ashmadai, calls this place home. She lives in an underground wine
cellar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was given to understand her whole Ashmadai sub-faction used this place as a
base, so it looks like there was a miscommunication between different authors
here. I’d probably add them here if I ran a Neverwinter campaign. Maybe say
those plant monsters are possessed by &lt;em&gt;devils&lt;/em&gt; instead of undead. How do you
like evil treants with 20 fire resistance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tower-of-twilight&quot;&gt;The Tower of Twilight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There used to be a wizard’s tower built in the middle of a lake island. It, and
the bridge leading to it, only appeared at night, becoming more solid as the sun
set and fading out again when it rose. During the Spellplague, the tower
vanished entirely and did not return until after the cataclysm. Now, it appears
sporadically with no set schedule, and no one knows what goes on in there
anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One suggestion from the book is that the tower fades out of &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; when it’s not
visible in the physical world, and the people inside only experience the passage
of time when it appears. This mean that the tower’s wizard and their apprentices
and staff might still be there, either absorbed in their studies as if this was
still 3e or struggling with what is to them a very recent bout of “original
strain” Spellplague.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/22/neverwinter-woods.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/22/neverwinter-woods.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Helm's Hold</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re getting outside of the city proper now! Helm’s Hold is a small town
located on the edge of the Neverwinter Wood, built around a monastery and
cathedral dedicated to the god Helm. It’s about a day’s travel northeast of
Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The town’s proximity to the Wood and its traditions of rugged individualism give
it big “American frontier” vibes, tempered a bit by the monastery’s own
culture. Helm used to be the god of guardians, and the monastery’s purpose since
its ancient founding is to give sanctuary to those who have none. The monastery
came first, and the town slowly grew around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year before the Spellplague, when the inhabitants had just laid the
foundation for the cathedral, Helm died. The grieving priests and citizens
finished the huge building as a monument in his honor, and kept its purpose as a
sanctuary, welcoming people of all faiths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience of Helm’s Hold from the computer games and reading this book is
that the place’s narrative purpose is to be infiltrated and secretly taken over
by the current campaign’s Big Bads. It happened in the first computer game
(ancient underground civilization), it happened again shortly before the
Spellplague (Netherese), and now it’s happening once more (the aboleths). We’re
headed for a plot pileup here because the Netherese are also trying to
infiltrate the town anew, via their werewolf minions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lurking-threats&quot;&gt;Lurking Threats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those mysterious disappearances and murders are caused not by the spellscarred,
but by the Grey Wolf Uthgardt, who have been ordered by their Netherese masters
to infiltrate the town and cause chaos. They’re proficient at disguising
themselves as locals or pilgrims, which lets them get into position to wolf out
at night and go hunting. The core of their force hides out in the Wood. The
Netherese don’t think the Hold is strategically valuable, they just want to keep
the barbarians occupied until they’re needed in their true function as
expendable muscle to throw against the Thayans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two barbarian-themed PCs are quite likely to end up here, and a peaceful
resolution to the Grey Wolf plot would involve convincing them the Netherese are
both evil and not interested in the tribe’s well-being. This has to be done
subtly, though, as they are likely to attack the Pack Outcast on sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course there’s also the cathedral itself, which is currently being run by
Rohini’s group and thus is a secret aboleth center of power. No one else knows
about this currently, though ironically the AbSov is also interested in solving
the murders because it will reduce the suspicion currently directed at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hold-and-environs&quot;&gt;The Hold and Environs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hold’s mission as a sanctuary turned into the region’s premier treatment
center for Spellplague victims, a duty which only became heavier about a year
ago when Lord Neverember made it his official policy to send any such victims he
finds in Neverwinter to the cathedral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the region tends to see the spellscarred as dangerous freaks, but
the inhabitants of the Hold see them as unfortunate victims affected by a
horrible curse. Still, the overwhelming influx of new patients has been testing
their open stance, as the city had to do a lot of rush construction to
accommodate them all, with limited success. You can find newer buildings
haphazardly constructed between older structures, their quality dubious due to
the Hold’s chronic labor shortage. Most skilled builders are over on
Neverwinter, where the work pays better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hold’s citizens are further stressed out by the recent spate of mysterious
murders and disappearances, which the more conservative among them have started
blaming on the spellscarred. A group of spellscarred activists calling
themselves the Heirs of Azure has sprung up to try to counter the distrust
heaped upon their community. However, the Mintarn detachment sent by Neverember
to help keep the peace isn’t having much success tracking down the real
culprits, tensions keep increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city is governed by a council of elected Speakers who meet at a former
tavern named The Dragon’s Gauntlet. They’re also split on the issue of the
spellscarred, though the official stance is still receptive since current Chief
Speaker is in that camp. The council’s collective power is waning, as there are
enough mercs in town that they could declare martial law unopposed. Their
commander, however, is uncharacteristically responsible and dutiful, so the
order won’t come from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heartward&quot;&gt;Heartward&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market plaza, so named because there’s a shrine to Sune here. Fights are
frequent because resources are scarce and prices high. Every now and then, at
night, a major haunting happens here and a bunch of ghosts goes through the
motions of market life. Some crew the stalls, some walk around making purchase
and talk to each other. Most of their words are gibberish, but some are
prophetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-dirty-dwarf&quot;&gt;Old Dirty Dwarf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And old, respected, and dirty tavern, with a reputation as the place for new
arrivals to go in order to get the lay of the land and hear the latest news from
the Hold. The owner is friendly to the spellscarred, but some of the staff
aren’t. Agents of the Prophet keep an eye here at all times and report news to
their boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scar-alley&quot;&gt;Scar Alley&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ground under this neighborhood softened during the Spellplague, causing many
of its buildings to sink and crack. Nowadays it’s a barely-standing,
precariously-patrolled slum that is home to the most deformed of the
spellscarred, those even the Hold shuns. It’s also filled with shady characters
and the occasional monster hiding out in an abandoned ruin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;helms-cathedral&quot;&gt;Helm’s Cathedral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aging faithful of Helm’s Cathedral now share it with a contingent of Oghma’s
priests who arrived to set up a sanatorium for spellscarred patients. Brother
Satarin commands the former: he’s a 160 year old dwarf who was an acolyte before
Helm’s death. Rohini the Prophet officially commands the latter, and is the de
facto boss of the whole place. As we learned a few posts ago, she’s a former
succubus turned aberrant creature, and serves the Abolethic Sovereignity, as do
all her subordinates. She holds the loyalty of Helm’s old priests because some
of her (fake) prophecies hint at his return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface levels of the cathedral are airy and well-lit. The underground is
far less pleasant and houses the sanatorium for the most “severe” cases. Rohini
spends a lot of time down there “treating” them (i.e, turning them into
foulspawn). They go out for exercise every day, and the foulspawn among them are
only detectable as such by people specifically looking for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-warrens&quot;&gt;The Warrens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a failed attempt to expand the city’s drainage system, abandoned when
the dig broke into the monastery’s old crypts and was overwhelmed by
monsters. It became a kind of unofficial sanatorium for monstrous humanoids
afflicted by the plague, who find no acceptance even in a tolerant city such as
this. Goblins, kobolds and others venture into the city to steal food for
themselves, and this has given rise to rumors of fey hauntings. I think it still
connects to the rest of the crypts, described below, and would be a good
alternate route for parties who want to sneak in. I’d probably run that as a
negotiation focused adventure rather than a classic murdery crawl, at least
until the PCs get to the crypts where the actual bad guys are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crypts-of-the-vigilant-eye&quot;&gt;Crypts of the Vigilant Eye&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These crypts lie beneath the Cathedral, and predate its construction. Though the
levels closer to the surface were clearly used by priests of Helm from the older
monastery, things get more ancient and mysterious the deeper you go. There’s a
big vertical pit full of side niches that could only be reached by flight or
teleportation, and is now full of gargoyles. There’s a hallway full of gigantic
robed skeleton statues that don’t resemble any sort of Helmite iconography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all that is without counting the twisting of the place by Spellplague
energies and its current occupation by AbSov agents and foulspawn. Or the
trapped Grey Wolf recon force that still hasn’t managed to find a way out
through all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deepest levels turn into caverns that were excavated and mutated by the
Symphony of Madness, turning into a fungal underground swamp. These are
Chartilifax’s hunting grounds, so they probably contain all sorts of creatures
that are tasty to dragons and dangerous to adventurers. From here you can enter
a pulsating tunnel to the brain-like chamber containing the Hex Locus, a bronze
coffer that acts as a repeater for the Symphony of Madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Locus chamber can also be reached via a teleportation circle somewhere in
the crypt levels, and Rohini will use that as soon as she learns someone is
inside. She is linked to the artifact and can feel when someone enters its
room. This is likely where any final confrontation against her and her pet
dragon will occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot-hooks&quot;&gt;Plot Hooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spellscarred Harbinger will most likely be told to go here soon after the
campaign starts. The Pack Outcast and Uthgardt Barbarian’s pursuit of the Grey
Wolf might also bring them here early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s werewolf problem and the creepy happenings at the cathedral should be
obvious enough to get the PCs investigating, and the growing tension between
locals and refugees would make a fine secondary plot line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rohini herself would not appear immediately villainous - she would instead
attempt to coopt the PCs and get them to help with her goals. By default that’s
serving the AbSov, but the book offers a few alternatives. Perhaps she wants to
break free of them and would secretly help them destroy the Hex Locus instead of
protecting it. She is of course still a devil, so she might double-cross the PCs
once she has what she wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent of that, Mordai Vell is working hard to woo her, aware that she’s a
devil in disguise but unaware of all the rest. So &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; might hire the PCs as
go-betweens in his courtship efforts. That’d be a fun way to introduce the AbSov
and Ashmadai to the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to be fair and write a complete summary of the material in the book, but
the truth is that I have a hard time caring about what’s going on in the town of
Helm’s Hold proper. The original Neverwinter Nights computer game colors my
perceptions here - it skipped the “town” bit entirely and placed you directly
inside the monastery, which it treated as a dungeon. I only learned the Hold was
an actual town once I read this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like most campaigns will go a similar route, focusing all of their “urban
intrigue” creative energy on Neverwinter itself and treating the Hold as a
mostly-skipped prelude to the big delve into the cathedral and the crypts
beneath. On the other hand, it would also be possible to do the reverse and
ignore the big city depending on your party composition. There are several
themes that have more reason to start at the Hold than at Neverwinter, like the
Spellscarred Harbinger, the Uthgardt Barbarian, and the Pack Outcast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/18/neverwinter-helms-hold.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/18/neverwinter-helms-hold.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New project page!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been reading this blog for a while you’ll know that I’ve been doing a
Let’s Read of the Neverwinter Campaign Setting for D&amp;amp;D 4e. This has been
generally less organized than the ones I did for the monster manuals, and it
didn’t have a project page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, now it does! If you want to see all the Let’s Read Neverwinter posts
collected and neatly linked in one single place, then you can &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/neverwinter/&quot;&gt;head over
there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/new-project-page.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/new-project-page.html</guid>
        
        <category>meta</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Underground</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We already saw several underground danger spots in the city. Neverdeath
Cemetery, the dungeons of Castle Never, and of course the Chasm. But there are
even more beyond those. The Mintarn mercs usually stay on the surface, so every
one of these places can be considered “dungeon-like”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shattered-sewers&quot;&gt;Shattered Sewers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverwinter had an extensive sewer system that’s still largely ruined. It makes
for a great way to move about the entire city undetected, but it’s hazardous to
navigate and filled with both monsters and other people who don’t want to be
discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kraken-tunnels&quot;&gt;Kraken Tunnels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an underground complex with a floor plan that vaguely resembles an
octopus. It used to be the former headquarters of the Kraken Society, a criminal
syndicate specializing in slavery. Now it’s the headquarters for the Nashers
faction of the Sons of Alagondar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complex is build right above an underground canal that links to the sea, and
this canal is the home of an actual kraken. The Spellplague reduced the monster
to bestial intelligence. The Society used to feed it and keep it as a guardian
beast, and the Nashers have continued the practice. The complex has several
floor openings through which the creature can attack intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kraken was trained by the Society to recognize anyone bearing an amulet with
its symbol as a friend - it attacks all who &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have this amulet on
them. The Nashers know this and carry Kraken Society amulets with them when
inside the complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a tunnel here that links the Kraken Tunnels to the Dead Rats’ HQ through
the sewers, which the Nashers use to talk and trade with them. The Rats don’t
yet know the trick to avoiding the Kraken, but it’s just a matter of time until
they find out and attempt to take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible the Nashers might end up releasing the kraken into the river or
the docks as a sort of weapon of mass destruction if they become desperate
enough. The aboleths could also try to get to it in order to search its mind for
secrets from back when it was sapient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dead-rat-hole&quot;&gt;Dead Rat Hole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a section of the sewers that has been taken over by the Neverwinter
chapter of the Dead Rats. It’s marked with gang signs gouged into the sewer
walls, and packed with both loot and trash collected by the gangers. Their
leader, Rsolk, holds court at a set of caves near the shores of
Blacklake. There’s a trap here that can let the waters of the lake in and
“flush” the whole complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Dead Rats are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; familiar with the Dead Rat Deserter PC, contrary to
what I thought before. Looks like word hasn’t got to them yet. A bold Deserter
might try to infiltrate the gang and perhaps even challenge Rsolk for
leadership. This starts as a one-on-one duel but turns into a standard mass
fight once he’s bloodied. And of course he flushes the lair if it looks like his
side will lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tunnels-and-trenches&quot;&gt;Tunnels and Trenches&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sewers around the Chasm area are partly collapsed, forming trenches where
the street above was destroyed and tunnels where it hasn’t. This and the influx
of non-sapient monsters provides good cover for the AbSov’s smarter agents to
infiltrate the River District or to escape the city and head to Helm’s Hold and
other places.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 10:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/neverwinter-underground.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/14/neverwinter-underground.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: The Chasm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The southeast quadrant of Neverwinter is where a huge chasm opened during the
cataclysm, a chasm which has been disgorging a constant stream of mutant
monsters ever since. As if that wasn’t enough, staying near the rift for too
long also makes people go mad. The other quadrants of the city only survive
because they managed to isolate themselves from this one somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ruined-city&quot;&gt;The Ruined City&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a “bad part of town” like the River District. There’s nothing
“town-like” about this expanse of ruined buildings and twisted streets. By
setting foot in here you’re already on a proper dungeon delve. No one does this
much any more, since few who try ever return and those who do come back changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs might be hired to search for someone who vanished here. Or they might end up
sleepwalking here due to the Chasm’s influence and need to fight their way
out. If they have a Spellscarred Harbinger, that character is going to feel an
odd connection to the Chasm and a desire to explore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already learned from the faction descriptions, the Chasm goes all the way
down to the Underdark, where it opens on an underground lake whose bottom houses
a Spellplague pocket and the AbSov research base built around it. The
Plaguechanged monsters are projects and rejects created by the aboleths - they
have been growing more powerful and “efficient” as of late, as the creatures
improve their designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if no other reason draws the characters to explore the Chasm region, they
will eventually have to come here in a campaign where the AbSov is the greatest
threat. Getting to them requires not only traversing the ruined city on the
surface, but also going down the Chasm itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-upper-reach&quot;&gt;The Upper Reach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When descending the Chasm, the first few hundred feet might seem fairly mundane,
but after that the landscape starts resembling the Elemental Chaos or Abyss more
and more. Elemental energies surge up from the depths at irregular
intervals. The walls are harder to climb, with handholds appearing and vanishing
at random and occasional blasts of fire or wind erupting from them. Earthmotes
abound, some drifting slowly and others bashing against the walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monsters can be found climbing the walls or flying from the depths. Even those
who have no flying ability can be seen floating up in bolts of chaos magic,
particularly if they were sent to attack the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creeping-madness&quot;&gt;Creeping Madness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the Spellplague radiation is already so intense that characters
are already at risk of contracting Creeping Madness, a magical disease
similar to the plague itself. They must make a DC 10 Endurance check on every
short or long rest to avoid contracting it. Further resistance rolls also use
Endurance, with a Maintain DC of 10 and an Improve DC of 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stage 1 inflicts a -2 penalty to Will and Initiative, and a +1 bonus to psychic
attacks. Stage 2 eats a healing surge and inflicts -4 to Perception and
Insight. Stage 3 inflicts a -2 penalty to all skill checks, and makes the
victim’s attacks deal +1d6 psychic damage. Stage 4 drives you mad and makes you
permanently dazed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most diseases I think it’s possible to recover from the final stage
through Endurance rolls. If a character fully recovers from stage 3 or later,
they also gain a spellscar. The Spellscarred Harbinger has a +2 on all Endurance
checks against this disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-twisted-fane&quot;&gt;The Twisted Fane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the apparent bottom of the chasm, a broken wasteland whose rock pulses
as if it was alive. There’s an alien-looking black fortress here, the Twisted
Fane, which is built around an eerily shining crystal. The Fane is guarded by a
colony of fouslpawn which will fight to repel any intruders they detect. The
monsters attack on sight and fight to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is a ruse put in place by the Aboleths to stall any would-be
heroes. They expect these interlopers to slay the disposable foulspawn, destroy
the useless crystal, and go back home thinking they solved the problem of the
Chasm. PCs can make several different skill tests to notice the crystal doesn’t
have any actual power, the foulspawn are acting strangely because of mental
domination, and that there are tunnels hidden in the area around the fortress,
leading deeper underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plaguechanged-warrens&quot;&gt;Plaguechanged Warrens&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an enormous chunk of rock wedged between the two walls of the Chasm. It
could be moved by sufficient force, but only has room to go up. The top surface
is where the Twisted Fane was built, and the inside is a maze of twisty passages
that end in gross “breeding pits” where creatures are stuffed into fleshy
cocoons and mutated by Spellplague magic directed by the Symphony of
Madness. This is where all the plaguechanged monsters that attack the surface
come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This deep into the chasm, characters have a -2 penalty to Endurance to resist
creeping madness. At the bottom levels of the rock, they also start to hear the
physical sounds of the Symphony of Madness, which inflicts a -2 penalty to Will
on all non-aberrant creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-blue-cauldron&quot;&gt;The Blue Cauldron&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underside of the Warrens opens into a large cavern mostly filled by an
underground lake. The water glows blue and bubbles as if boiling due to the
Spellplague pocket at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no physical way to safely climb down to the water; characters must
either fly or fall down the 60-foot drop. There is an “unfettered travel”
magical effect put in place by the aboleths that lets them swim in the air
inside this cave. Characters trained in Arcana might be able to hijack that and
be able to swim through the air as if it was water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a depth of 20 feet, the PCs can find bubbles holding particularly interesting
prisoners. At the bottom of the lake, is the research lab itself. Any characters
who get to this cave will immediately draw the attention of the aboleths, both
because they proved themselves a major threat and because they might make
excellent research subjects. The aboleths themselves are quite powerful and
might also be plaguechanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this depth, characters have a -4 penalty to resist creeping madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface of the Chasm could make for a decent hex- or point-crawling map as
characters try to find a safe path to the rift itself. As described, it seems
the Chasm itself is a very meaty dungeon delve. None of its separate areas
described above get maps, so the GM can make maps that suit their
purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, once you’re here you know you need to go &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt;, but depending on how long
the GM wants you to spend inside each of the named areas could vary in
complexity from the equivalent of a single “room” with a big battle in it to an
entire labyrinthine dungeon level where finding the way down is a significant
challenge in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/10/neverwinter-chasm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/10/neverwinter-chasm.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: River District</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The River District occupies the city’s northeastern quadrant and was where most
of the city’s merchant class lived, and also the location of a couple of wizard
towers. These homes were not as nice as those of the Blacklake nobles, but they
were still sturdy and are still mostly standing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s River District is much more dangerous and hostile than Blacklake. The
many guardhouses and security walls here now act as prime ambush spots. It’s
protected from the Chasm by the river, but monsters from the wilderness outside
can freely wander in. The main source of danger, however, are the Many-Arrows
Orcs. Neverember has so far failed to dislodge them, and maintains an uneasy
truce punctuated by skirmishes while he thinks of a way to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mintarn mercs mostly stay away from the River District, making it a good
place for shady deals if one can dodge the orcs. Hot-blooded youngsters also
love to go here on dares, despite their parents’ protestations. And while
scavengers have long taken all of the most obvious treasure, there’s still some
left in secret stashes all over those merchant mansions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fallen-tower&quot;&gt;The Fallen Tower&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This used to be a wizard’s tower, but it was destroyed during the
Spellplague. Some time later, its ruins became a tavern whose main attraction is
the nightly haunt showing the deaths of the wizards as they fall from a great
height into what is now the tavern’s cookfire at the center of the common
room. Charming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The place was vacant when the orcs found it but it still contained a lot of
stored food and drink, so they reopened it for their own use. Lord Neverember
and Commander Vansi have declated The Fallen Tower to be neutral ground, and
their envoys meet here when they have cause to talk. Non-orcs deemed worthy to
share a drink with the Many-Arrows are also allowed to frequent the Tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-cloak-tower&quot;&gt;The Cloak Tower&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cloak Tower was once the headquarters of a mage guild called The
Many-Starred Cloaks. It vanished into thin air at the height of the Spellplague
and rematerialized six months later at a different address, without its
wizards. People who have tried to explore it in the past were turned away or
killed by its magical wards and traps, and everyone thought the same would
happen to the orcs. However, for some reason, they had absolutely no trouble
moving in and making this tower their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-shard-of-night&quot;&gt;The Shard of Night&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This black stone tower appeared high above the River District during the
Spellplague and has floated there ever since. It looks like it was cut off from
its base, with an opening at the bottom. It casts no shadow during the day, and
when people walk under it their own shadows vanish as well. It does cast a
shadow by the light of the moon, and even though no one was ever seen to enter
or leave the place, eerie sounds sometimes echo from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tower used to be part of a distant temple of Selûne, but it was cut off and
banished to the Shadowfell during a Netherese assault on that temple. After the
battle, they found out they could control where the tower appeared in the world,
so they sent it to Neverwinter during the Spellplague and left it there until
the day when it was needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it is needed, and they’re using it. The Shard’s enchantments allow it to
absorb shadows during the day and use them to power a teleportation circle
inside that links it to Xinlenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creatures infused with shadow power, such as the Scion of Shadow, are immune to
the absorption effect and still cast shadows while under the Tower. They also
feel a comforting pull from it, which might help clue them in to what lies
inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This&lt;/em&gt; is the “bad” part of town. I imagine most who live here are either
Many-Arrows, allied with them, or sneaky enough to go undetected. I also think
envoys who want to go to the Fallen Tower for diplomacy with the orcs might need
some sort of token of safe passage, since it’s actually quite far from the
district’s borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profit-oriented parties could have some interesting adventures following up on
rumors of a big treasure cache still hidden in the River District, but most of
the hooks here involve dealing with the Many-Arrows somehow. Raiding the Shard
of Night is an interesting way to get to Xinlenal without a long and arduous
overland trek into the Woods, but that place is only approachable by “endgame”
parties.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/04/neverwinter-river-district.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/09/04/neverwinter-river-district.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Castle Never</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Castle Never sits on the northern bank of the river, in the Blacklake District
that takes up Neverwinter’s nortwestern quadrant. It used to be the seat of its
government, and home to its ruling family. The cataclysm wrecked it and killed
almost everyone inside. The surviving servants decided to seal its crypts,
vaults and grounds, hoping that a worthy heir might make use of them one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle’s ruins are still a towering landmark, and its foundations are still
solid. While many interior chambers were destroyed, some are still intact and a
lot of the interior is at least navigable - most notably the underground
bits. Now it houses several groups who compete with each other for territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book doesn’t give you maps, leaving those as an exercise to the GM. There’s
enough going on here that it could be a full megadungeon and the focus of the
campaign… or it could be “downsized” to the site of a single targeted delve
for groups who want to keep their focus elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;surface-areas&quot;&gt;Surface Areas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface portion of the castle is partly ruined but still contains a large
number of navigable areas. There are some places of interest that should feature
in whatever map you draw for it, like the &lt;strong&gt;locked armory&lt;/strong&gt; or the odd places
detailed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drow-encampment&quot;&gt;“Drow” Encampment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This used to be a campsite in a hidden spot in the city, near Castle Never. It
was originally set up by Drizzt and Jarlaxe around the time of the cataclysm,
when they were here investigating the Thayans and trying to stop their
plan. They come back every once in a while to attempt to tie off those Thayan
loose ends, usually without much success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location of the encampment was recently discovered, however… by their
&lt;em&gt;fans&lt;/em&gt;. These eager youths and would-be adventurers have made the spot into a
permanent “DrowCon” of sorts. They train together, challenge themselves by
delving the castle, and hope to become good enough to join their idols’
entourages once they return. Neither of the two celebrities have been back for a
while, but Jarlaxe has heard of these events and has sent some of his Bregan
D’Aerthe agents to mind the place and keep a watch for promising recruits from
among the fans. They are Xalbyn the quick-witted rogue, Kimmuriel Oblodra the
quiet and focused mage, and Aerlyse the half-drow psion who spies on the other
two for Jarlaxe. Xalbyn hides his drow heritage with a Hat of Disguise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book makes an effort to take this place seriously… but I just can’t see it
as anything but comic relief. It would be a funny place to use whether there are
Bregan Spies on the party or not. If there are, then I’m guessing the three
stooges here don’t know about them. Jarlaxe seems very fond of keeping his
underlings in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hall-of-ashen-mirrors&quot;&gt;Hall of Ashen Mirrors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hallway inside Castle Never. It has huge windows and used to be lined
with mirrors, being a popular spot for young Alagondar heirs to practice their
regal posture. When the cataclysm hit, air pressure shattered all the mirrors,
filling the place with flying glass and killing everyone inside right before a
pyroclasm came in through the windows and turned the corpses to ash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the hallway is very, very haunted. When living people enter, it will
reconstruct itself, and the reflections in the mirrors will re-enact the events
that happened just before the explosion. The replay ends with the
explosion-and-pyroclasm combo, just as deadly as it originally was. Anyone
lingering here for too long is gonna have a bad time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;surface-factions&quot;&gt;Surface Factions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These groups make up the inhabitants of the castle’s above-ground
portion. They’re all hostile to each other, though some are more amenable to
befriending the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghosts&quot;&gt;Ghosts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the castle’s destruction was so sudden, pretty much everyone who perished
in it ended up becoming a ghost. They can be found all over the interior, and
are a varied lot. They’re not automatically hostile, and PCs who approach them
correctly might strike up some extremely useful conversations with them. However
they tend to talk in riddles both because they like it and because their sanity
might have been a little damaged in the last 30 years. And if the ghosts come to
believe the characters are just there to loot the ruins, they &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; become
hostile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thayan-forces&quot;&gt;Thayan Forces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castle Never is Valindra’s second major focus in the city of Neverwinter (the
first is Neverdeath Cemetery, as we saw earlier). On the surface, her forces are
engaged in a small war against those of Talgath, which consists of a tense
standoff with occasional battles. There’s at least one residential area that
became isolated due to cave-ins after a battle. The ghoul troop that got trapped
inside passes its time wearing the former inhabitants’ clothes and pretending to
be nobility, waiting for a rescue that will never come. The PCs will probably
stumble upon them first. Other undead patrols can probably act as random
encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;talgath-watcher-of-castle-never&quot;&gt;Talgath, Watcher of Castle Never&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talgath the Beholder has recently moved in. He wants to be king of the castle,
starting with the ettercaps on the upper spires and working his way down. He
pays little attention to humanoid intruders like the PCs, unless they get in his
way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valindra sees Talgath as the greatest threat to her goals in the castle. She’s
sent people to kill him several times, but Talgath has defeated them all. Not
only is he a powerful monster in his own right, he also makes extensive use of
his charm ray to keep a small army of minions. He brought in a coven of harpies
and a pack of displacer beasts from outside, and has charmed many of the
assassins sent to kill him as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;independent-communities&quot;&gt;Independent Communities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle’s atrium was boarded up long ago, and the heat and darkness have
turned the garden within into a fungal paradise complete with a village of very
territorial myconids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its upper spires have been taken over by a group of ettercaps who used to live
in the dungeons but were pushed out and up by Valindra. She ignores them these
days, but Talgath is currently trying to enslave them. Their leader says he had
a prophetic dream where a group of outsiders would deliver them from the
beholder, which makes them more likely than usual to befriend the PCs (and give
them that quest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;underground-areas&quot;&gt;Underground Areas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle’s underground areas are structurally intact. The things that make
them dangerous are of another nature entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neverneath&quot;&gt;Neverneath&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle had a sizable dungeon area underneath it, protected by strong wards
that let it survive the cataclysm intact. Radiation from the Spellplague pocket
at the bottom of the Chasm has altered the wards, however, making it so they
actively trap any who enter the dungeon, causing its corridors to shift and
close around these intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space here is all wonky. A straight corridor can lead you through a circuitous
route full of loops and circles. A door might lead you to a different place than
it did the fellow PC who was just in front of you. The place is filled with
self-resetting traps, and inhabited by a large pack of gargoyles who love to
attack anything fleshy they find. It also houses a small force of desperate
gnolls that stumbled upon it several months ago and haven’t managed to escape
yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vault-of-the-nine&quot;&gt;Vault of the Nine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below Neverneath lies the Vault of the Nine, where those legendary bodyguards
have been entombed to honor their meritorious service in life. If you’re using
the subplot where Valindra plans to reanimate them, her forces are already here
and have turned the vault’s many outer chambers into their base of operations,
filling it with guardian undead. If she manages to animate the Nine, she will
order them to kill and replace all of New Neverwinter’s leadership, including
Neverember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;player-tie-ins&quot;&gt;Player Tie-Ins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would the PCs want to mess with this place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Neverwinter Noble&lt;/strong&gt; has the most reasons for wanting to do so. The ghosts
are likely to be their direct ancestors, for starters! The fabled Crown of
Neverwinter is also lost somewhere inside the castle, and it’s likely the most
definitive proof of legitimacy for anyone wanting to claim the throne. Legend
says the crown’s magic properties only work for someone of the line of
Alagondar, and that anyone else who tries to wear it gets simultaneously burned
and frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching the Vault of the Nine would also be a desirable goal for the Noble even
if Valindra’s forces are not down there. It could be possible to call the Nine
back into service through their oaths to the line of Alagondar, and if the noble
can do so that would be another excellent proof of their legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oghma’s Faithful&lt;/strong&gt; would also love to explore this place and find its many
lost historical secrets. They might be mostly interested in interviewing the
ghosts and finding any sealed off libraries, but finding a safe path to the
Vault would also be a worthy goal even if they wouldn’t actually want to loot
the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the &lt;strong&gt;Devil’s Pawn&lt;/strong&gt; might benefit from talking with the ghosts, as it’s
quite possible one or more of them have had to deal with a similar problem
in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For everyone else, Neverember is always hiring adventurers &lt;del&gt;stupid&lt;/del&gt; brave
enough to delve the Castle in search for the Crown or any other relics and
documents that might help increase his legitimacy. He also wants it to be clear
of monsters so he can move in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-crown-of-neverwinter&quot;&gt;The Crown of Neverwinter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for the Crown, and it’s indeed a nifty item (level 15, head slot,
strong protections against mental conditions and a nice bonus to social
skills). The stats &lt;em&gt;do not&lt;/em&gt; include the genetic lock from the legend, so it’s up
to the GM whether those stories are true or not. The people certainly believe
them, in any case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the GM likes the idea of the Crown but doesn’t want to bother with the
Castle, the crown might be placed in another place that’s more relevant to the
campaign. As a lost artifact, it could turn up anywhere for any number of
reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the dynamic with the different factions here. There’s a lot going on in
this castle and as in any megadungeon the situation here feels a lot less stable
than even the one in the city outside. PCs who come in here are definitely going
to have a drastic effect whether they have themed ties to the place or not.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/29/neverwinter-castle-never.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/29/neverwinter-castle-never.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Blacklake District</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Blacklake district, named after the lake located here, was where most nobles
of Neverwinter used to live. Pretty much all of them died in the fires of the
cataclysm, but their very sturdy and well-built residences remained
standing. They sheltered many of the city’s survivors during the following
decades, even though the lake became a fetid, ash-choked pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Blacklake is a rough-and-tumble place still largely outside of
Neverember’s control. His forces have begun moving in and attempting to extend
the Enclave to the district, but so far they have not met much success. This is,
after all, where everyone who can’t stand his harsh rule lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castle Never is located in Blacklake, and we will cover it in its own post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-driftwood-tavern&quot;&gt;The Driftwood Tavern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The place where everybody knows your name. The Driftwood tavern has been open
since before the Cataclysm. Its owner, Madame Rosene, opened the tavern’s doors
to shelter refugees in the event’s immediate aftermath, and it became a kind of
makeshift city hall for the survivor community in the following years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the Madame is in her fifties and the tavern is filled with mementos and
relics of Neverwinter That Was, making it a sort of museum. Both the place’s
somber atmosphere and its high prices keep the Mintarn mercs at bay - the only
customers are long-time regulars and old friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suits Madame Rosene just fine, because the Driftwood Tavern is also the
main headquarters of the Greycloaks faction of the Sons of Alagondar, which she
leads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A text box says that Madame Rosene would react positively to PCs who can
recognize the historical and sentimental value of the Neverwinter relics that
decorate her tavern, and that she might test their patience and resolve by
sending them on seemingly pointless quests to recover more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-beached-leviathan&quot;&gt;The Beached Leviathan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tavern is actually built out of an old pirate ship that ran aground decades
ago. Its owner Harrag was also the boat’s former captain. He presents himself as
an adventuresome scallywag but the truth is Neverember owns him. Anything people
say within earshot of him eventually makes its way to the lord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tavern also acts as the current residence of Len-Jes, a watersoul genasi who
works as Neverember’s harbormaster. Her job includes keeping track of (and
taxing) every ship at port, and also dredging the bay to open more berths for
trade ships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Len-Jes only took this job because if facilitates her second, much shadier
source of income. The exact nature of that is up to the GM. Is she a spy for an
Abeir trade house or pirate crew? Does she have buried treasure somewhere? Does
she actually work for some other faction like the Harpers or the Ashmadai?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vellgard-manor&quot;&gt;Vellgard Manor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mordai Vell’s family home. They used to be a prominent Neverwinter noble family
but they all died in the Cataclysm. Mordai Vell was the only survivor because,
as a tiefling, he was a source of shame and was sent away from town. As the sole
heir, he came back to reclaim his home shortly before Neverember arrived… and
he brought his Ashmadai buddies with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vell’s charisma and wealth soon secured him an informal community leadership
role in the district, and there are those who think he’d make a fine lord of the
city. I don’t think he ever made overt claims to the throne, but perhaps he will
when his cult is in a strong enough position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vellgard Manor is very well fortified, and guarded by a small army of cultists
and summoned devils. A direct assault would be difficult… but Vell likes to
party, so the PCs might get in by arranging invitations to his latest social
function. The devils are kept hidden during these. Of course, Vell is no fool,
so he might allow the PCs to get in and spring a trap on them if they’re not
subtle in their maneuvering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;house-of-a-thousand-faces&quot;&gt;House of a Thousand Faces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tavern used to be a fancy boutique, and it’s still decorated with
mannequins in old-fashioned clothing. It closed after the cataclysm and reopened
as a tavern when the city’s population began to recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its owner, the elf Theryis, is a member of the Harpers. Her brother Toram took
over as the leader of the group once Cymril died. As mentioned elsewhere, these
two are the sole remaining full Harpers in the city, and they aren’t predisposed
to trust the PCs just because they’re PCs. Their default stance is to watch and
test them until they prove themselves properly heroic, or until they bring
evidence of the larger factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toram, however, will attack the Harper Agent on sight because he’s convinced
they were responsible for Cymril’s death. He was in love with her, you
see… or, as the book puts it, &lt;em&gt;she was seducing him before her supposed
death&lt;/em&gt;. Make of that what you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All those secret society HQs gathered up in one convenient neighborhood! In most
campaigns the PCs are guaranteed to end up visiting one or more of them, either
to talk to its owners or to raid them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blacklake is not quite the “bad” part of town, but it definitely has a different
atmosphere from the Enclave. I’d portray it with a more “frontier” feeling -
it’s a bit more dangerous and run-down, but also more free, and the residents’
opinion of Neverember is significantly worse even when they aren’t involved in
organized resistance against him.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/25/neverwinter-blacklake.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/25/neverwinter-blacklake.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Overview and Protector's Enclave</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Neverwinter is a coastal city-state built at the mouth of a river. There are
several stories about how it got that name, but the most popular one is that it
was from the warm waters of that river, which prevent the delta from freezing
during winter and so keep its port viable year-round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing the book and the computer games, I see present-day inhabitants of
Neverwinter have a somewhat romanticized view of Nasher Alagondar, the former
adventurer who ruled the city about 150 years before this campaign starts. He
was an effective ruler, though, and his descendants formed a dynasty that
remained unbroken until the cataclysm 27 years ago, when the last of them died
or vanished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cataclysm wrecked the city, opening a huge chasm that destroyed its
southeastern quadrant and began to vomit forth mutated monstrosities. Most of
the citizens who didn’t die left as refugees, and only a minority of holdouts
decided to stay and protect their ancestral homes. They built a makeshift wall
to isolate the Chasm and its monsters from the rest of the city, and soon began
to see its defense as a sacred duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Neverember arrived nearly ten years ago at the head of an army of
carpenters and builders, protected by a mercenary force from Mintarn. Around
five years ago he established the Protector’s Enclave, a sort of “green zone”
taking up the southwestern quadrant of the city, which he declared safe for
occupation. There were already people living all over the city, but the
establishment of the Enclave opened the way for refugees to return and for new
immigrants to come seeking opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people of Neverwinter, then, can be split into two demographic groups: the
“holdouts” who never left the city, and the “newcomers” who arrived or returned
after Neverember declared it once again open for business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-enclave&quot;&gt;The Enclave&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Enclave’s infrastructure has been restored to pre-cataclysm levels, more or
less. This includes the port, which has once again begun to see trade from
Waterdeep and elsewhere. The variety of goods in its markets does a lot to make
life in Neverwinter easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all is roses in the Enclave, though. Neverember’s government imposes a steep
tax on all commercial transactions, and the place is heavily policed by those
Mintarn mercenaries. The taxes are something one can get used to, but those
mercs have spies and goons stationed everywhere and love to employ all sorts of
excessive force against any perceived sign of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverember doesn’t personally care about this police brutality, but he does make
an effort to keep it at a level that’s beneath his notice, occasionally blaming
and punishing one of his underlings to get things to simmer back down for a
while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s discontent aimed at Neverember from a lot of sides. The holdout
population dislikes him because he’s taking credit for much of their work, and
sidelining them in his new government. The newcomers see him in a better light
but still dislike the heavy taxes and oppressive mercs. Those who like him
usually also like the whole New Neverwinter rhetoric and say the harsh measures
and heavy taxes are needed to keep the city’s restoration going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sons of Alagondar in particular see him as a foreign occupier and call him
Lord Pretender. If your PCs want to brawl with a guard patrol, saying those
words within earshot of them is the best way to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverember’s current headquarters is at the Hall of Justice, the former temple
of Tyr. If you played the first Neverwinter Nights game you might recognize this
as your quest hub during Act 1. Tyr died in the Spellplague, but the citizens
refused to convert the temple to worship of another god. Neverember had it
restored and sponsors a group Torm priests that perform rituals following the
old Tyrran tradition in here. While many people see this move in a positive
light, the Sons of Alagondar claim Neverember’s presence defiles the temple and
call it the “Hall of Never-Justice”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-moonstone-and-other-earthmotes&quot;&gt;The Moonstone and Other Earthmotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three earthmotes in Neverwinter. These were created by the
Spellplague, and became fixtures in the city’s skyline long before the
eruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first as the Moonstone, so called because it’s the current site of the
Moonstone Mask. Another familiar location from the computer games, this fancy
inn fell on hard times and shut its doors after the cataclysm. About five years
ago it reopened under new management, with some financial help from
Neveremeber. Liset Cheldar, the current owner, repays him by housing a large
number of Mintarn mercenaries in her establishment. They take up most rooms and
a bunch of them can be found there at all hours, dragging the atmosphere down
and picking fights with non-merc patrons. The Moonstone is lashed to the docks
with heavy chains, and connected by a bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book suggests making Liset the puppet of one of the other factions, but I
think that’s a bit too cliche to make the pretty and flirty woman a secret
monster. The inn is already dangerous enough with all the mercs in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The southernmost earthmote is called Fisher’s Float, and it’s home and workplace
to a small community of fishers that have lived there since before the
cataclysm. Their catch provides a great deal of food to the city, though their
isolated location often gives rise to rumors of sinister goings-on. They’re just
rumors unless the GM decides otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mote that flies the highest and furthest from town is the Pirate’s
Skyhold. A gang of sky pirates used it as a base because it’s impossible to
reach without flight. One night, though, the pirates apparently all killed each
other in a frenzy of betrayal, leaving the island deserted. Their skyship, and
all of their treasure, are rumored to have stayed there intact - though other
rumors say that a dragon made the island its lair after a while. You can still
see the ruins of wooden buildings poking out of this island’s forested slopes,
but it remains inaccessible to most. The GM is explicitly encouraged to make
this place into a cool aerial dungeon of their own design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-wall&quot;&gt;The Wall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wall was built by Neverwinter’s holdouts after the cataclysm. It separates
the southwestern quadrant of the city from the Chasm in the SE quadrant. It was
initially built from rubble and barricaded buildings, and manned by
martially-inclined survivors. Neverember reinforced it with proper defensive
architecture and assigned a significant chunk of his mercenaries to supplement
the survivor garrison. Those survivors still guard the Wall alongside the mercs,
because they see it as their sacred duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with Neverwinter River, the Wall has been effective at preventing any
plaguechanged horrors from leaving the area of the Chasm, but recently some of
them have been spotted north of the river and near sewer entrances. Mayor Galt
fields several daily petitions for expanding the Wall further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guarding the Wall and repelling plaguechanged assaults is one of the quickest
ways to win the hearts and minds of the city’s inhabitants. The increasing
friction between the mercs who make up most of the guard forces and the hardened
native veterans who refuse to abandon their posts can also be a source of many
plot hooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-house-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;The House of Knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This used to be a great temple to Oghma, occupying what is now the northeast end
of the Wall. After the cataclysm, the elderly Brother Anthus became its head
priest for a while, and they dedicated themselves to studying the plaguechanged
creatures that emerged from it. When Anthus died under mysterious circumstances,
the priestess Rohini took over and moved their whole operation to Helm’s Hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To know the truth about those mysterious circumstances, check Rohini’s bio).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single volunteer priest remained behind to look after the temple’s extensive
library and archive, Brother Atlavast. Long years of solitude and isolation have
made the priest a paranoid eccentric. He keeps to the lower levels underground
and I don’t think a lot of people even remember he’s there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, Atlavast is ornery but not evil. He’ll be very happy to see Oghma’s
Faithful, for example, though he will insist on testing them and any other PCs
to see if they’re worthy of the archives. If they do manage to befriend him, he
can be a great help when exploring the library. Optionally, he might be in
thrall to the aboleths (like the rest of the priests over at Helm’s Hold), and
must be freed before he can become an ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surface levels of the temple, long abandoned, have been taken over by a
group of squatters which decided to make themselves useful by serving as
lookouts on the Wall and ringing the temple’s bells when they see monsters. The
mercs often leave them gifts of food and clothing, and are becoming fast friends
with them… unaware that the squatters are all undercover Ashmadai
cultists. They already managed to get one of the Mintarn captains possessed by a
devil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neverdeath&quot;&gt;Neverdeath&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This huge graveyard was in use for centuries until the cataclysm, when the vast
expanse of graves and mausoleums was wracked by tremors. Some sections of it
sunk, others rose up, and these convulsions exposed graves and underground
crypts, causing coffins and bones to tumble about the whole area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current inhabitants of the city fear this place. The Mintarn mercs burn dead
bodies outside the city walls instead of burying them here. It’s not uncommon
for unburied bodies on or near the cemetery to rise as undead of their own
accord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t help that the Thayans have a major secret base in here, and are using
it as their main source of bodies for reanimation. The place also contains a
shadow crossing into Evernight, and Valindra has built a teleportation circle
here to make use of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Netherese are aware of the shadow crossing and one of their goals is to
destroy it or otherwise deny it to Valindra. They want to be discreet about it,
though, and don’t want to jeopardize their project to raise Xinlenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;waterclock-crypts&quot;&gt;Waterclock Crypts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverwinter was once known for the amazing quality of its water clocks. The
guild responsible for making them built this crypt to inter its dead. Located
somewhere inside Neverdeath, it’s filled with clever traps and engines built
using hydraulics and elemental magic. Hidden here is the laboratory of its
founder, who first arrived in the city coming from Luskan with a cartload of
stolen magic knowledge. Its library contains all of that knowledge and more,
including notes on the original ritual that bound Maegera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An underground vein of elemental magic that links Luskan and Gauntlgrym passes
through the crypt - it’s why the founder’s lab was built here. Following the
vein could be one way in which the PCs find the lost city. Of course, they need
to get through all the undead and Thayans up above, as well as whatever defenses
this place has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-docks&quot;&gt;The Docks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rebuilding the docks was one of Neverember’s greatest priorities. While there’s
still plenty of work to be done here, the docks are already functional and able
to receive ships. Trade with the rest of the world has resumed, and the lord
makes a pretty penny charging tariffs on its cargo. There’s lots of crime and
corruption here as well, but I get the feeling Neverember only cares about it to
the extend that it impedes trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also here is the Tarmalune Trade House, belonging to a merchant guild from
Returned Abeir (the new continent a ways off to the west of Neverwinter). In
what might be an unexpected development, they’re just a normal trading house who
can offer supplies and filler quests to our protagonists. Their goal is entirely
mundane: to form commercial ties with the very lucrative markets at
Waterdeep. They’ll be extra-friendly towards any PCs that have ties to the
nobility of that city, like the Neverwinter Noble or the Devil’s Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is the “safe” part of town there are still quite a few sources
of danger in it. A lot of that danger comes from the mercs, who will mercilessly
harass anyone who looks like they might start trouble, a description that fits
most PCs. Neverdeath will be a major location in any campaign focused on either
the Thayans or on Gauntlgrym.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/22/neverwinter-enclave.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/22/neverwinter-enclave.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Other Factions, Part 3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post, we’ll cover the minor factions that are located underground, in
and near the ruins of Gauntlgrym.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dwarven city was a major metropolis in its heyday, and the capital of the
dwarven empire of Delzoun. Its underground location allowed it to survive the
fall of Netheril mostly unscathed, but it would fall to an orcish invasion a
couple of centuries later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original inhabitants of Gauntlgrym either perished in this attack or fled to
the surface, and the location of the city was lost to them after a few
generations. The history of the city did not end there, however, as passed
through the hands of several Underdark factions over time. It’s also still
inhabited by the ghosts of the dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means our encounter table here is mostly undead. While some dwarven ghosts
might be helpful to their descendants, most of the undead here are of the usual
mindlessly murderous variety. The table contains several skeletons, zombies,
ghouls, wraiths, ghosts, and even mummies. It also has dire corbies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dire-corbies&quot;&gt;Dire Corbies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These critters look like buff skeksis, and are given the same header style as
actual Gauntlgrym factions, but they’re not really organized enough to be called
that. This is mostly a “new monster” entry. Looks like they made their debut in
a Gauntlgrym-focused post in Dungeon 183.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry says they’re descended from predatory birds who were lost and trapped
in the Underdark a long time ago. The evolutionary pressure and uncanny
radiation of the Underdark changed them into these monstrous humanoids. Their
wings have been changed into powerful clawed arms, and their coal-black feathers
blend into the darkness. They’re predatory and ravenous, pulling themselves
through narrow underground tunnels and viciously attacking anything that looks
even remotely edible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire Corbies are Medium Natural Humanoids and Level 7 Brutes with 96 HP. They
attack with &lt;strong&gt;Gashing Beaks&lt;/strong&gt; that do immediate and ongoing damage, and when
first bloodied emit a &lt;strong&gt;Rending Screech&lt;/strong&gt; that covers a Close Burst 2, deals
psychic damage, and inflicts Vulnerable 5 to Everything for a turn. A miss does
half damage with no riders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since they’re classified as Humanoids and have an Int of 11, it might be
possible that they could form more complex communities and interact with PCs in
non-violent ways… but as written the typical dire corby is Chaotic Evil and an
enthusiastic cannibal. Even if they weren’t, the stronger factions are fond of
enslaving them, so the PCs would still end up fighting dire corbies when facing
those groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mind-flayers&quot;&gt;Mind Flayers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The orcs that invaded Gauntlgrym were eventually conquered by mind
flayers. Those mind flayers ruled for a while, conducting an extended experiment
on illithid-derro hybridization, but that got out of control and the resulting
creatures kicked them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the primordial Maegera woke up for a brief time thirty years ago, the
resulting shakeup in Gauntlgrym allowed a new mind flayer colony to move in. I
guess they initially wanted to reclaim their old haunts, but shortly after
arriving their Elder Brain was targeted by the Abolethic Sovereignity’s Symphony
of Madness and infected with the Spellplague. Now the brain and its colony are
completely under AbSov control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mind flayers are researching the bound primordial on behalf of their
masters, and also act to protect it from meddlers and would-be conquerors. As
the aboleths funnel more and more Spellplague radiation to them, both the Elder
Brain and its subordinate illithids are becoming more mutated. The brain knows
what’s going on, but it’s become addicted to these energies and will keep
obeying the aboleths in exchange for its regular fix. The individual mind
flayers’ perceptions are clouded, however. They believe all is business as
usual and are incapable of perceiving their own mutations or discovering their
elder brain is working for someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats here for a &lt;strong&gt;Plaguechanged Mind Flayer&lt;/strong&gt; (Level 8 Controller) and
the &lt;strong&gt;Plaguechanged Elder Brain&lt;/strong&gt; (Level 9 Elite Controller). They work a lot
like their baseline versions, adjusted to Heroic Tier. The illithid is of the
type that can perform thrall surgery on PCs instead of eating their brains. The
brain is mostly immobile (unlike its nimble base version) but has the usual
assortment of psychic attacks and an aura (3) that can strip resistance to
psychic damage. It can also use an interrupt to redirect forced movement effects
back to the enemy who tried to impose them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duergar&quot;&gt;Duergar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These duergar are relatively recent arrivals to Gauntlgrym. Led by an unholy
warrior of Asmodeus named Kholzourl the Fire-Speaker, they have come here under
orders from their diabolical master. They’ve occupied a section of the ruined
city and resumed some of its ancient and abandoned mining operations. They’ve
enslaved dire corbies and other nearby sapients to work for them, but fear the
ghosts and undead that plague other areas of the ruins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only Kholzourl knows the expedition’s real goal, which is actually left for the
GM to determine (the book gives several options later). Regardless of that true
goal, they have been profiting from the ores extracted from the Delzoun mines,
which include iron, mithral, and a metal known as Hellthorn which takes
remarkably well to enchantments based on infernal magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duergar and Ashmadai do not know about each other, and despite serving the
same masters the two factions have no inherent inclination to cooperate unless
directly ordered to do so by a devil emissary of Asmodeus. The default reaction
of the duergar to outsiders is “kill or enslave on sight”: they’re not here to
do diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one notable exception here: a duergar named Nimor Ironvoice found a
tunnel leading from Gauntlgrym to the surface. He disguised himself, explored a
bit, and found out about the Ashmadai. Now he has a profitable side gig
smuggling small quantities of hellthorn up the well and selling it to the
cult. He knows Kholzourl would punish him if he found out, and soon he will have
to decide between severing his ties to the surface or turning against his fellow
duergar. He’s hoping an infernal sign will tell him the way before either his
boss or Mordai Vell discover the truth by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duergar get their own encounter table, which as expected is mostly made up
of duergar from the MM2 and Monster Vault. Kholzourl gets a stat block, which is
fairly typical aside from being level 9. We also get stats for Steeders, the
disgusting devil-spider-things these duergar use as mounts; and for Hellthorn
weapons, which start at Level 10/+2, do immediate and ongoing fire damage on a
critical, increase your fire resistance if you have any, and can let an allied
devil make a free attack once per encounter when you miss one of your own
attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;house-xorlarrin&quot;&gt;House Xorlarrin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Forgotten Realms drow house is said to be “atypical” because its matriarch
is less authoritarian than the others and even occasionally asks for input from
male advisors. But it also has a full-on eugenics program where males are “bred
for magical ability” and sacrificed if they turn out to lack it. So we’re back
on icky old-school drow territory here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newest arrival to Gauntlgrym is a Xorlarrin expedition. They’re after the
sleeping primordial, wanting to control it and use it to turn Gauntlgrym into a
drow capital to rival Menzonberranzan. Their encounter table is all drow and
unlike most others it goes up to level 14. We also get stats for a Drow
Spellspinner, a Level 8 Artillery mage that uses lightning-based spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These drow feel like an optional addition, and work best if you have a Bregan
D’Aerthe spy in your party. If that’s the case, they work well to tie that PC
more strongly to the campaign’s “endgame”, since the Bregan would want to
prevent a Drow house from gaining control of a primordial. For added drama, the
Xorlarrin could have been the ones responsible for destroying the PC’s own
house, or that of one of their friends. They’ve sent their own spies to the
surface, so that can provide the party with an initial lead to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fires-below&quot;&gt;The Fires Below&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is less of a faction and more of a grab-bag of thematically related
monsters. These are the elemental creatures that live beneath Mount Hotenow and
usually feed on slumbering Maegera’s ambient magic. They got very happy with her
awakening and the volcano’s eruption and some of them want to find a way to
awaken her for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most other groups with a similar goal, they don’t intend to control the
primordial once she’s awake, but to serve her instead. I don’t think they are
likely to succeed on their own, since they’ve been at it for 30 years with
nothing to show for it. They’re more intended as a group of secondary
antagonists that you find on your way to Maegera’s resting place… or as an
additional complication if someone else &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; manage to wake her up. Whoever
ends up controlling Maegera will also get to order these creatures around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The encounter table here is all about fire and/or earth elementals, and it goes
up to level 14. We also get a couple of new stat blocks for salamanders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/15/neverwinter-other-factions-3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/08/15/neverwinter-other-factions-3.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
