<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 19:47:54 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 19:47:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read Hell&apos;s Rebels 04, Part 01</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell&apos;s_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/hells-rebels&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first three volumes of this adventure path were dedicated to building up the
Silver Ravens and their rebellion. Strikes against Thrune were indirect and
targeted peripheral facilities, which prevented the enemy from mounting a big
response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this changes at the very end of Adventure 03, where Barzilai lays a
deadly trap for the PCs and potentially kills a lot of innocents. At the start
of this one, Barzilai Thrune makes his final three proclamations: he outlaws the
Silver Ravens, he forbids worship of any god that’s not Asmodeus, and he
blockades the bridge that separates the two halves of the city. As soon as this
happens, his forces begin a brutal series of reprisals against the Ravens and
the population in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silver Ravens immediately begin to fight back, since at this point their
rebellion has reached its maximum power and anyone who was even a little
sympathetic to them throws their full support behind the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zzNs4-kRLaE&quot;&gt;shit’s going down&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs start this adventure at level 10 and are expected to finish halfway into
level 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gming-the-rebellion&quot;&gt;GMing the Rebellion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of this adventure is dedicated to commanding the full might of the
rebellion to topple Barzilai Thrune. While you might have been able to ignore
the custom rebellion rules up until now, they’re unavoidable here. If you didn’t
bother with them before the book suggests assigning a default set of stats for
the organization (Notoriety 75%, focused stat +15, secondary stats +10). Those
numbers are higher than what’s on the Player Guide, probably to account for
bonuses the PCs would have gotten if they kept track of things in detail. Even
if you were using detailed rules before I recommend upgrading the org’s stats to
at least that level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that Thrune’s government can be “killed”, it gets stats of its own. The
important one is Authority, which must be brought down to 0 for the Ravens to
win. When that happens, Thrune and his remaining lackeys lock themselves up in
the Temple of Asmodeus for a last-ditch desperation move, and the PCs can get at
them with a final assault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCs and the Silver Ravens fight the Thrune government by completing
missions. These usually involve raids against important facilities controlled by
named villains. Success at these usually removes whatever capabilities that
villain brought into play, and gives the Silver Ravens control of the city
district they’re in. Districts under Raven control become safe from patrols and
such, and lower both current and maximum Authority by a certain amount (10 or 20
points, depending on the district). This is why I linked the Assassin’s Creed:
Brotherhood trailer above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrune’s government tries to resist the rebellion through brutal reprisals
against the Ravens and the population in general. They can launch one such
reprisal per day for every 25 Authority or fraction thereof they have. Specific
reprisals are rolled out of a d100 table. The best possible result here is “No
Reprisal”, an organizational snafu that actually decreases Thrune’s
Authority. The other events result from mere defamation or increased patrols all
the way to a dragon air strike, each one increasing Authority by an amount
proportional to its badness. As Authority drops and named villains are killed,
some of these entries will be removed and replaced with No Reprisal. Can’t have
a dragon attack if the dragon is dead! Authority also increased by 1d6 at the
start of every day, to represent the population’s and the Ravens’ war weariness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with those reprisal events is that they also kill some of the city’s
population. While the chance that the PCs will lose the game at this stage is
small, they must act quickly and forcefully to prevent Thrune from doing too
much damage to the city they’re trying to protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authority starts at 100 by default, but past Silver Raven victories in previous
adventures can reduce this starting amount. A “perfect run” means allying with
both the sea elves and Vyre; destroying Menador keep &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; stealing the
documents kept there; and finishing the Ruby Masquerade with 20 or more Masque
Points. This would mean Thrune starts this adventure with Authority at 65/100,
giving the PCs a major starting advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-missions&quot;&gt;The Missions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default expectation here is that the PCs managed to win the battle at the
opera house and fully explore it at the end of the last adventure. If this is
the case, the adventure starts with an emergency meeting of the Silver Council
taking place as soon as the PCs are recovered, to update them on the state of
the rebellion and explain the available district control missions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If on the other hand the PCs &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; the opera house battle, they wake up in a
cell in Kintargo Keep, and must escape. They basically tackle the hardest
mission first, from the inside out, and then add the Opera House to their to-do
list later - it’s still full of stuff vital to their success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the missions consist of relatively short dungeon raids that are
essentially big set-piece battles against the villain of the hour and their
minions. These encounters tend to all be CR 13. This is where the game
introduces a new monster type, the Troop, which works a lot like a 4e Swarm but
occupies an area that’s more “malleable” than the standard square. There are
Dottari and Inquisitor troops here, representing the fact that Thrune’s security
forces are out in well, force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, PCs can order the Ravens to perform support actions before
every dungeon raid instead of just at the end of every week. If the named
villains in each one manage to survive and escape, they’ll likely join Thrune at
the Temple of Asmodeus. Even if this happens, they still count as defeated for
district-taking purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the mission list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rescue-hetamon-jarvis-end-district&quot;&gt;Rescue Hetamon (Jarvis End District)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hetamon Haace is the Rose of Kintargo. He became an ally and a member of the
Silver Council back in adventure 02, but is missing from this adventure’s
emergency meeting. Finding him is a priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out he’s been kidnapped by his evil half-succubus sorceress of a mother,
who is holed up in the basement of Shensen’s former home and plans to sell him
to Thrune in exchange for some sort of cushy job or at least a license to hunt
people in Kintargo. She has a bevy of minions both voluntary and enslaved. The
former consist of a covey of hags; some of the latter can be freed instead of
fought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shensen can give the PCs the full layout of her own basement, of course. And if
she comes along the PCs might also recruit her best friend who is hiding in
there, a sapient dinosaur rogue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completing this one and reconsecrating the basement as a shrine to Sarenrae
gives PCs control of Jarvis End.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;take-the-records-hall-the-greens-district&quot;&gt;Take the Records Hall (The Greens District)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Records Hall is full of important information about the city and its
inhabitants, and denying this to Thrune will be a major blow to his forces. It’s
also the current lair of Tiarise Izoni, the witch responsible for most
atrocities of an arcane nature committed so far in the campaign. Opposition here
consists of the witch, two inquisitor troops, and two invisible stalkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiarise’s notes can give the PCs clues about Thrune’s ultimate plan for
immortality, and also alert them to the fact she has performed a ritual on
herself that will turn her into a powerful undead creature when she dies. Unless
she is killed under specific circumstances, Tiarise returns in the last
adventure in undead form as one of its named villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bleakbridge-yolubilis-harbor-district&quot;&gt;Bleakbridge (Yolubilis Harbor District)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bridge is blockaded by a huge force of dottari (three troops, two captains,
a named commander). They’re being helped by a gang of tengu named the River
Talons, who are acting as lookouts. Fortunately, their alliance is shaky and the
Talons’ leader is the brother of Silver Council Member Chok (a weapon shop owner
who joins at the start of this adventure). If the PCs can arrange a meeting
between Chok and his brother, the latter can be convinced to betray the
dottari. In that case, the Talons will not raise the alarm when the PCs sneak
into the bridge, and will take care of one of the dottari troops “offscreen”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sneaking into the bridge is possible at all because it’s huge - there are
actually buildings on both sides, with plenty of space to cross in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;skinsaw-assassins-villegre-or-redroof-districts&quot;&gt;Skinsaw Assassins (Villegre or Redroof Districts)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cultists are led by Hei-fen, the spiteful and vengeful wererat who has it
in for the PCs. The PCs are warned about them by Molly Mayapple, the helpful and
grateful wererat from Vyre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultists will attack the PCs in three separate occasions, possibly while
they’re busy with something else. The first strike is six cultists, the second
one a jorogumo, and the final one another twelve cultists, another jorogumo, and
Hei-fen herself. They’re also doing murders for Thrune on the side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eliminating all of them changes the corresponding reprisal table entry to “No
Reprisal”, and gives the city enough breathing room for the PCs to take control
of either Villegre or Redroof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kintargo-keep-castle-district&quot;&gt;Kintargo Keep (Castle District)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where Thrune’s most important political prisoners are being kept. If the
PCs have been captured at the end of the last adventure, they start here and
must escape. Otherwise, this will probably be the last place they hit. The keep
and castle are much less guarded than usual because Barzilai ordered most of the
troops stationed here to go out and hunt for the PCs, which ironically lets them
approach the Keep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the tower has five levels, only the ground floor and basement are truly
relevant. When the PCs attack the tower is being guarded by six Hellknights of
the Rack and their leader, Paralictor Kyrre Ekodyre. The knights should spot the
PCs as soon as they make it past the door, so they will eventually need to deal
with all of them and the paralictor in the same fight. There are some undead
knights possessing suits of armor guarding a shrine, but they will not join the
main fight unless disturbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keep’s archives contain the contracts Barzilai made with the order of the
Rack, to transfer all of the assets of the Order of the Torrent to them (back in
adventure 02). Turns out there are a lot of irregularities in these contracts
that make them illegal. The Hellknights, who are Lawful-Eviler-than-thou, will
abandon Thrune once these documents are made public. This will remove them from
all random and pre-arranged encounters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The archives also contain prisoner records showing that Jackdaw, the original
leader of the Silver Ravens, is still here! House Thrune’s redaction efforts
were so effective that not even Barzilai or the knights remember why she was
important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jackdaw is being held in a special cell in the basement, behind a secret
door. She’s guarded by a being known as the First Warden, a former warpriest of
Asmodeus who was turned into a lich and bound to this prison as a punishment for
some forgotten transgression. The Warden will at first attempt to talk to the
PCs because it’s been a long time since she had a proper conversation, but will
attack when she realizes they’re here to free Jackdaw. She has a lot of priestly
abilities and the help of four more of those possessed armors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jackdaw is in a pretty sorry state - the lich has kept her from dying, but
hasn’t done anything to make her comfortable. Once the PCs restore her health
and sanity, she becomes a very valuable ally. She can also supply them with the
lyrics for the Song of Silver, which combined with the score from the opera
house allows the PCs to use the ritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dragon-villegre-or-redroof-district&quot;&gt;The Dragon (Villegre or Redroof District)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did mention a dragon, didn’t I? She’s an adult blue dragon named Rivozair. She
first attacked the city during the Chelish civil war, and was nearly killed by
the original Silver Ravens. Rivozair returned shortly before the campaign
started and agreed to join up with Barzilai for a chance to take revenge on the
city. He invested her with additional infernal power, binding her to a horned
devil in the same way Nox from Adventure 01 was bound to a bearded one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rivozair is a powerhouse of a solo boss, and one of Barzilai’s most powerful
minions. In addition to her usual “I’m a dragon!” suite of abilities, her
lightning breath has been replaced with hellfire, she can summon barbed devils,
and she has Regeneration 5 that can only be overcome by Good-aligned spells and
weapons (though that last bit shouldn’t be a problem at this point). After the
PCs finish the other five missions, or after they reduce Barzilai’s Authority to
0 (whatever happens first), the dragon will be unleashed to hunt down and kill
the PCs directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the GM wants to make this battle a bit easier, they can have some of the PC’s
allies help in the fight. If on the other hand they want to make it harder, they
can have the dragon begin its hunt earlier than scheduled. Rivozair will try to
become invisible and run away when she’s badly wounded, but instead of rallying
at the Temple she will flee the region. She might come back to disrupt the
victory celebration, if the GM wishes. Otherwise she will remove herself from
the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defeating Rovizair removes her entry from the reprisal table… but more
importantly it &lt;em&gt;instantly reduces Authority to 0&lt;/em&gt;. I guess any remaining minions
will see that the PCs can handle the dragon and will immediately leave their
posts as if they had been defeated, rallying at the Temple of Asmodeus. We now
enter the final stage of the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that brings this post to a close. There’s actually little I would cut from
this part of the adventure, since all of the fights here seem pretty cool. When
playing in Pathfinder, they are also quite amenable to alpha-strike tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next post, we’ll take a look at the effects of the Song of Silver and at
the Temple of Asmodeus, which unlike these short raids is a huge grinding slog.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/10/03/hells-rebels-04-part-01.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/10/03/hells-rebels-04-part-01.html</guid>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GURPS is Brutalist, or Tweaking The Flow of Combat in GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/long-lines-building.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Long Lines Building in New York
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common complaint I hear about people who tried GURPS for the first time coming
in from other systems is that the “flow” of combat feels odd. Mainly that those
1-second turns are too short and don’t let you do enough. Sometimes also that
these short turns lead to fights that end too quickly to be dramatic&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this comes from a mismatch between the player’s learned expectations and
the way GURPS actually does things. In this post I’ll try to describe this
difference, and give a few suggestions on how to reduce the friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;describing-the-difference&quot;&gt;Describing the Difference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with an example. You’re in a typical dungeon fantasy combat against
a bunch of zombies, playing an archer character. You make an attack, and
describe it like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I draw and nock an arrow, then I take aim at the closest zombie and shoot! As
soon as the arrow flies, I’m already drawing another one from my quiver!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do other systems&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; usually handle this, and what does GURPS do that’s so
different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract-action-economies&quot;&gt;Abstract Action Economies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most tabletop RPG systems are fairly abstract when it comes to combat. To the
rules, it doesn’t matter what motions your PC is actually going through when
they perform an action, nor does it matter how long a turn lasts. It is enough
to know what the action is, and that a turn is long enough for you to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In systems that work this way, our archer’s narration is just a cool
embellishment that adds some fun detail to a standard ranged attack roll. All
the rules need to know is that it’s a ranged attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the choice of which actions perform in your turn matters a lot. You get
a certain number of them, all of which have an immediate effect in the current
turn but don’t influence future ones. Therefore the system’s incentives gently
push you to be maximally efficient on a turn-by-turn basis&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Attacks are good
because they bring the fight closer to an end. If you use your main action for
something else, it better bring as much benefit to you as attacking would, or
you have just “wasted” your turn. This set of mechanics and incentives is
usually called an “action economy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-gurps-way&quot;&gt;The GURPS Way&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where other systems are abstract, GURPS is so concrete it’s practically
brutalist. Turns last one second and its combat maneuvers are a lot more
fine-grained than combat actions in other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Union of Generic Universal Republics our example description is not just
a bit of flavor: it’s a five-turn plan. Ready (draw arrow), Ready (nock arrow),
Aim, Attack, Ready (draw arrow)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only the actual blow from your weapon, press of the trigger, or release of the
bowstring counts as an Attack. The other stuff in the plan above are maneuvers
that make your Attack possible and set it up for success. In GURPS, you want to
increase the &lt;em&gt;quality&lt;/em&gt; of your attacks, not necessarily their &lt;em&gt;quantity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the same reason GURPS is a bit less amenable to “needless embellishment”
than more abstract games. Combat goes much more smoothly when you keep your
action declarations to short sentences that map to a single maneuver. The
structure you build out of these simple blocks can end up looking every bit as
beautiful as the freeform narrative, though. This too, is brutalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/barbican-conservatory.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Barbican Conservatory in London
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;proposed-solutions&quot;&gt;Proposed Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The GURPS way” is neither better nor worse than the action economies of other
systems. It’s just different. But it’s different enough that it can trip up
people coming in from other games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the description above helped you smooth the friction between the rules and
your expectations, then great! But it’s likely that it didn’t, and you still
having trouble with it. In that case, here are a couple of suggestions on how to
make your experience smoother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solution-1-its-a-character-skill-issue&quot;&gt;Solution 1: It’s a (Character) Skill Issue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big reasons to use “setup” maneuvers like Evaluate, Feint, and Aim is
that your character’s skill level might not be high enough to give you a decent
chance of success. Without those maneuvers, you’ll end up missing more often, or
will have trouble getting past your enemy’s defenses. This is common at the core
books’ default 150 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to make attacking every turn more feasible and fun is to raise the power
level of your characters. This is the approach taken by Dungeon Fantasy and
Action: not only do they use 250 point templates, they optimize them a fair bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the physical combatant templates in DF start with 16 in their main combat
skill &lt;em&gt;at the very least&lt;/em&gt;. Many have a 18, and a couple either start with a 20
or can get there with a bit of point shuffling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might sound excessive at first glance. Your base chance of success doesn’t
increase past 16, and it’s unlikely anyone had more than a 18 in all of human
history. Why allow PCs to &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; there, and possibly go even higher with earned
points? Because this is what you need to be able to reliably attack every second
without taking the time to perform setup maneuvers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these “overpowered” skill levels you can absorb more penalties without
having to Evaluate or Aim to offset them, and you can use Deceptive Attacks
instead of Feints without affecting your chances of success. If you still have
enough spare skill levels left, you can even thrown in a Rapid Strike to make
two attacks in that second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution-2-mandatory-dramatic-pauses&quot;&gt;Solution 2: Mandatory Dramatic Pauses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fighters in real-world combat sports and action movies don’t spend every second
of their fights furiously attacking each other. They’ll circle while looking for
openings, stop to catch their breaths, and only go in for an exchange of actual
blows every once in a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of setup maneuvers helps stretch fights out to be more similar to these
examples, but if you’re reading this it’s because you don’t think they’re a good
solution. And even if you do, you might want to go further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to do this is to crib from the rules for tournament fights in GURPS
Martial Arts. Under those rules, fights are composed of &lt;em&gt;lulls&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;flurries&lt;/em&gt;. Combatants can only use the Attack maneuver&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; during a
flurry. During a lull, they cannot attack but can still use maneuvers like
Change Posture, Evaluate, Move, Ready, Aim, or even just Do Nothing while
waiting for an opening. In fantasy settings it would be a good time to cast
those healing spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS Martial Arts has flurries last for 2d seconds and lulls for 4d seconds,
rolled at the start of the corresponding period. You can tweak these durations
to best suit your campaign. If the combatants’ actions look like they’re going
to force an early change, you can end the current “period” early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of introducing lulls is to extend a fight’s in-character
duration to something like that of a real-world boxing or MMA round. They can
also help change the mental “efficiency” calculation of someone who’s used to
action economies. If there’s a part of the fight where you can’t attack,
performing setup actions for when you can becomes the most efficient thing to
do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lulls work both in melee and ranged combat (when everyone might hunker down
behind cover for a while), but they might get a bit hard to manage or look a bit
silly when you have a large number of combatants in a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;10 minutes to beat the bad guy and disarm the bomb is not a problem at all
if you beat the bad guy in 5 seconds. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Other Systems” here means the last three editions of D&amp;amp;D, Pathfinder 2E,
most editions of Shadowrun, and any others that might be similar in outlook
but which I’m not too familiar with. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And if there are any obsessive optimizers in your group, they’ll push you
much less gently. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I admit I tacked that extra Ready at the end to make the “five-second
plan” joke work. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And its cousin All-Out-Attack. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/09/17/turn-length.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/09/17/turn-length.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Abandoning Weapon Master</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A while back I made a post about &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html&quot;&gt;combining Weapon Master and Trained by a
Master&lt;/a&gt; into a single advantage. After thinking about it for a while, I think
I might have changed my mind about it. I not sure the two traits are really
meant to coexist in the same campaign, despite what Dungeon Fantasy tries to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy character creation rules are all about replicating a lot of
D&amp;amp;D’s conventions in GURPS. And one of the D&amp;amp;D-isms it tries to replicate is
that a combat centric character can be either strong or fast, but not both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dd-combat-conventions&quot;&gt;D&amp;amp;D Combat Conventions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent editions of D&amp;amp;D, that happens because characters have a very limited
number of points to distribute at creation, and every class is meant to have
only 1 or 2 attributes that are important to its abilities. Physical combatants
end up having either STR or DEX as their main attribute, and the rules are
usually set up so that the other member of the pair can be safely dumped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STR-based combatants use the heaviest armor and weapons they can get. The vast
majority are melee specialists. Some buy a single thrown weapon at creation and
then promptly forget about it. All of these options are designed to make
Dexterity not matter to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DEX-based combatants are the opposite: they wear light or no armor, and are
evenly split between archers and melee skirmishers who rely on “finesse weapons”
that use DEX instead of STR. Therefore Strength doesn’t matter to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every physical combatant&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the last three editions of D&amp;amp;D is going to lean
heavily towards one of these archetypes. A few classes incentivise players to
try and be a bit of both, but for most of them that’s going to lead to a weaker
character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-gurps&quot;&gt;What about GURPS?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dungeon Fantasy gives you templates to emulate the classes from recent D&amp;amp;D, so
it ends up bringing this particular trope wholesale into GURPS. You have your
Strong Delvers, and your Fast Delvers&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But we run into some issues because
GURPS is much less abstract than D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both in real life and in GURPS, combatants want to be &lt;em&gt;both strong and
fast&lt;/em&gt;. You need speed and precision to hit, and you need to put some force
behind your blows for them to be effective. Sure, an individual character might
have ST or DX that’s a bit higher than the other, but they’ll never be 10+
points apart like they are in their D&amp;amp;D equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, DF tries, and Weapon Master is a significant component of this
attempt. It’s a mandatory trait for Swashbucklers, and an optional one for the
other fast delvers. It more or less takes the place of D&amp;amp;D’s Weapon Finesse,
since it allows these characters to do improved melee damage without investing
many points into ST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also an optional Knight trait. And it’s quite easy to take a starting
Knight and give them ST 18, Weapon Master (Dueling Halberd), and a starting
weapon skill of 20. Such a character literally combines the best of both
worlds. They can do all the same fancy tricks as the ST 11 Swashbuckler, and
their strikes to a massive amount of damage when they land, due to the higher
base number of damage dice and the per-die damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a player, this damage bonus seems so good to me that I’d feel bad about
“leaving it on the table” and not taking Weapon Master. As a GM, I worry that
any enemy that can withstand a hit from the Knight will be impervious to attacks
from the other PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-do-about-it&quot;&gt;What to do about it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first option is of course to do nothing. This is admitedly a very niche
concern and you might be okay with it in your game. But if you are having Weapon
Master Problems at your table you might try one of these other possible
solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solution-1-flat-damage-bonus&quot;&gt;Solution 1: Flat Damage Bonus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “minimally invasive” solution is to change the damage bonus from +1 or +2 &lt;em&gt;per
die&lt;/em&gt; to a flat +1 or +2. All advantage costs remain the same, as do all
templates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that the skinny swashbuckler who rolls a single die for damage still
gets the same bonus. Meanwhile Mister Halberd with his three dice of swing
damage gets a much smaller relative benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solution-2-no-more-weapon-master&quot;&gt;Solution 2: No More Weapon Master!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weapon Master no longer exists and Trained By a Master comes in categories
similar to the removed advantage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;20 points makes you trained in One Weapon. This gives you improved parries,
improved Rapid Strikes, and access to the same limited set of Chi Skills as
Weapon Master did. No damage bonus, though!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;25 points gives you the same benefits for Two Related Weapons or all weapons
covered by One Skill.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;30 points works as printed, giving you the full set of Trained By a Master
benefits for all muscle-powered weapons and unarmed attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All knives” counts as a single weapon for these purposes, like in the books. So
do “all unarmed attacks”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who had Weapon Master as an optional advantage gets the corresponding
version of Trained by a Master instead, and has the option to upgrade to the
full version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a more drastic and slightly more complicated solution. No one gets a
damage bonus any more, but no one overpays for the full Weapon Master package
either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And then you have spellcasters, who choose to be slow and weak so they can
be good at magic. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And Smart Delvers, for which see Footnote 1. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/09/03/no-weapon-master.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/09/03/no-weapon-master.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels: Player Character Origins</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell&apos;s_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell’s Rebels includes some traits in its Player’s Guide that can be assigned to
PCs to tie them to the campaign either by providing a motivation or by giving
them additional ways to contribute. A PC could be a minor worker in the opera,
or a fed-up citizen, or interested in the city’s history, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think those quite fit what I have in mind for my solo campaign. They are
suitable as backgrounds for level 1 starting characters and their mechanics can
be useful at the start, but pretty much cease to be a factor in the story once
the “main plot” kicks in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being released six years earlier than Hell’s Rebels, the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/neverwinter/&quot;&gt;Neverwinter
Campaign Setting&lt;/a&gt; for D&amp;amp;D 4e does a much better job at allowing players to
create characters who are &lt;em&gt;deeply&lt;/em&gt; involved with the campaign at hand. More than
starting motivations, its character themes provide entire story arcs that will
remain relevant throughout the entire campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the same thing for my game, so I’m going to replace the relatively
generic reasons given in the Hell’s Rebels player guide with something that’s
narratively on par with Neverwinter’s themes. I want them to not only be more
exciting, but also to reflect the increased starting power of Dungeon Fantasy
characters. They’re going to be key players in the rebellion from minute one of
the campaign. Why just be a random history buff when you can be The Last
Archivist instead? This status might be reflected in some of their traits, but
the story consequences are the main thing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the “character themes” I intend to use. There are five, one for each of
my intended PCs, but presenting them separately will help provide some
inspiration to other GMs who want to do the same thing whether in GURPS or
another system. I’m using Dungeon Fantasy archetype and ancestry names instead
of those from Pathfinder, but the correlations should be pretty easy to
deduce. Each of them also has plot ties to some of the game’s possible allied
factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each theme bellow includes a short background description, and paragraphs
listing prerequisites, benefits, and drawbacks. These are mostly story-related,
but they might also add optional mechanical traits to your character’s
template. You can buy these right away with your starting points, or buy them
later with earned points like any other template trait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-sixth-raven&quot;&gt;The Sixth Raven&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most surviving historical documents about the Silver Ravens say they were five
in number: Jackdaw the elf swashbuckler, Amyreid the half-elf cleric, Ba the
halfling wizard, Kyda the human bard, and Brakisi the human scout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These documents were wrong. There was one other: you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were a small orphan child then, adopted by the group as a kind of mascot
somewhere along their career. You shared their love for Kintargo and its
freedom, but you were too young to go on any actual adventures, so you mostly
helped by running small errands, and heard from their big battles when they
returned to tell the tale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lasted until the last battle, the one against the massed armies of House
Thrune. Jackdaw sent you away with many of her other non-combatant friends the
day before that one, promising she’d call you back when the danger was past. She
never did, because the Ravens lost. Jackdaw surrendered so that the demonic army
would spare the city, and the others were either killed by Thrune agents over in
subsequent years or disappeared forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the following decades you would finally reach adulthood and set out on your
own, becoming an adventurer of some skill and renown elsewhere in the Inner Sea
region. Now, you’re ready to return home and finish the work of your
old friends. Your name has been struck from the history books, but your passion
burns as brightly as it ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;: You must belong to a species long-lived enough that you could
have been a child 70 years ago and still be of adventuring age in the
present. Being a dwarf or some kind of elf is enough, but the Half-Spirit
ancestries from DF 3 might also fit. Another alternative is to play a
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/02/07/warforged-variants.html&quot;&gt;Warforged&lt;/a&gt; who was an &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; member of the Ravens and spent some of the
intervening decades disabled and unconscious, but was recently repaired. You can
belong to any profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: You remember things. The GM might occasionally give you hints and
clues about old Silver Raven safehouses and stashes. You also knew the Ravens
personally and they knew you - should any of them still be around, you will be
able to recognize each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add the Serendipity {15} trait to your template if it’s not already
present. This represents your memories of old Kintargo and Raven hangouts, and
might let you find useful shortcuts, items, and passages that are not
pre-written into the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;: Things remember you. Demons, vampires, and other similarly
long-lived monsters who faced the original Ravens back in the day will recognize
you just as readily, and will be extra-mean to you as a result. Once word
spreads that you’re back, some of them might even travel to Kintargo for the
sole purpose of killing you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be represented by the Enemy (Monster of the Week, 9 or less) {-15}
trait, which gets added as an optional disadvantage to your template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only have the DFRPG, the disadvantage works like this: the GM rolls 3d6
in secret at the beginning of each adventure or each session of an extended
adventure. If the result is a 9 or less, a significantly powerful monster will
appear somewhere along the coming adventure or session, inserting itself into
one of the upcoming situations and making things more complicated and dangerous
for you and your group. It’s usually something complicated to fight, and not
necessarily the same monster every time. This is &lt;em&gt;in addition&lt;/em&gt; to any
pre-existing monsters in the adventure who recognize you and want you dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-last-archivist&quot;&gt;The Last Archivist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You were a member of the Sacred Order of Archivists, a secret society made up of
worshipers of various deities of knowledge and wisdom. The Order was dedicated
to preserving the true history of Kintargo and other such “forbidden” knowledge
from Thrune redactors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Order is no more: its hideout was raided and ransacked by Thrune forces
during the Night of Ashes. You were away when it happened, on a mission to
retrieve an important document in another city. That’s why you survived. When
you returned, you reached out to a few contacts and learned that some of your
colleagues have surviving family. They were nobles and their family estate was
razed during the Night of Ashes, but one of their sons is still at large. You
are now trying to find this son, help him stay safe, and then get revenge on
House Thrune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;: None! While the Order is an excellent origin for Clerics,
Wizards, and other big brains, it could easily have employed fightier or
sneakier types as security or retrieval specialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: It’s impossible to be a member of the Archivists and not learn
&lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. In addition to being familiar with the Order’s hideout and its
procedures, you also know a bit of the region’s unredacted history and a few
other tidbits of unrelated but potentially useful knowledge. You can recognize
the Sixth Raven if run into them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add the History and Research skills as an option to your template, and
also all specialties of Hidden Lore if they aren’t there already. You also add
Wild Talent {20} as an optional advantage, representing a large trove of random
knowledge. If you’re using the Basic Set, add Intelligence Analysis to your
template as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;: You’re riven by grief and driven by revenge against Barzilai
Thrune and his minions. This might manifest as Intolerance (Diabolists) {-5}, an
Obsession (depose Thrune)(12) {-10}, or both! The Obsession might seem redundant
since it’s also the overall campaign goal, but it also compels you to take
potentially risky and unwise courses of action if they seem like they will yield
quicker results. It could also prevent you from retreating from a fight against
Thrune’s minions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;knight-of-the-deep&quot;&gt;Knight of the Deep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You come from one of the subaquatic communities off the coast of Ravounel, where
you enjoy an heroic reputation. You recently went to visit your friend Aava in
the coastal village of Acisazi, only to find her missing and the village
suffering under a strange malaise. The village’s elder told you Aava had led a
small party of scouts into Kintargo to ask seek help breaking the curse, but she
never reported back. She begged you to find Aava, and you accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You arrive at this land-lubber town to find it embroiled in a lot more trouble
than you thought possible. Aava is nowhere to be found and neither is her
contact, the singer Shensen. You suspect both of them vanished into the prisons
of the despotic Barzilai Thrune, and your queries have led you to the Aria Park
protest. You suspect you might need to bloody this human despot’s nose to
fulfill your mission, and that’s just fine with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;: You must belong to a species capable of breathing underwater!
Dungeon Fantasy 3: The Next Level contains two possible choices here: the Sea
Elf and the Water-Infused. From this blog, you might also pick the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/10/10/elder-scrolls-others.html&quot;&gt;Argonian&lt;/a&gt;
or perhaps a &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/02/07/warforged-variants.html&quot;&gt;Warforged&lt;/a&gt; who has been modified to be hydrodynamic and
Amphibious. And of course we also have a whole article about the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/04/28/atlantis.html&quot;&gt;Denizens of
the Sea&lt;/a&gt; that also contains a few usable ancestries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theme is open to any profession, but martial types should probably keep in
mind the rules for &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html&quot;&gt;underwater combat for fish-people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: The people of Acisazi know and trust you, and Aava is your good
friend (or even a relative if you’re also a sea elf).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can add Swimming, Aquabatics and Survival (Undersea) to your template as
optional skills, and should probably put some points in them during character
creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;: Add Obsession (find Aava and her scouts) (12) {-5} to your
template as an optional disadvantage. It’s what you already want to do anyway,
but like the Last Archivist’s Obsession it might drive you to unwise actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;phantom-thief&quot;&gt;Phantom Thief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are one of Lady Docur’s School for Girls’ most distinguished graduates. You
had parted ways with your alma mater and set up shop in nearby Vyre, but a
recent letter from Lady Docur herself brought you back to Kintargo. The city’s
political climate is getting rather inhospitable to the school, and she hopes
you will be able to help them survive these turbulent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words: the school is currently the closest thing Kintargo has to a
thieves’ guild. They specialize in training secret couriers and the nicer sort
of thief. Thrune prefers the &lt;em&gt;nasty&lt;/em&gt; sort of thief, so things might get
difficult for the school and its students. That’s where you come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you’re not here just to help your old school. You’re also, er, taking
a breather from some rather complex entanglements you left behind in the good
city of Vyre. Hopefully it will be a long while before you have to set foot
there again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;: It’s a school for girls, which means you either are a woman
or only discovered you &lt;em&gt;weren’t&lt;/em&gt; after graduation. You must also be some manner
of Thief, either the base template or one of the variants from the corresponding
Dungeon Fantasy Denizens book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: You know Lady Docur and other characters associated with your alma
mater, and have their trust. You also know Vyre’s customs, which might come in
handy if you ever need to go back there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add Area Knowledge and Current Affairs for both Kintargo and Vyre to your
template, as well as Connoisseur, Savoir-Faire and the Fashion Sense
advantage. The School does give one a proper high society education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;: Those Vyre entanglements will come back to haunt you if you ever
return there during the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No extra disadvantages here: everything which could make a thief’s life harder
is already part of the relevant templates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mysterious-satirist&quot;&gt;Mysterious Satirist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before Barzilai Thrune rolled in like he owned the place, you were already
well-known among Kintargo’s rebels, malcontents, and antifascists. Whether you
make poems, plays, essays, or songs, your work criticizing House Thrune was on
everybody’s minds and the pseudonym you chose for yourself was spoken in the
same tones as that of The Poison Pen and other such figures. Thrune’s opponents
speak it with admiration; his supporters, with disgust. That’s how you like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While no one has figured who you are yet, Barzilai’s arrival and the Night of
Ashes have made your life very difficult already. Most of your contacts among
Kintargo’s several resistance organizations have vanished, left town, or gone to
ground. While you still value your art, you also feel it’s time to engage in
more direct action against this dictator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/strong&gt;: None! While Bards obviously have a head start in terms of the
artistic skills implied by this theme, the Mysterious Satirist could be anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: Choose one of the Bellflower Network, the Cult of Sarenrae, the
Rose of Kintargo, or the Poison Pen. You’re indirectly acquainted with that
group or individual. Though you have never met, you have corresponded and set up
pre-arranged signs that will let you recognize each other when the meeting does
happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add the artistic or performance skills of your choice to your template, as well
as an appropriate Talent covering them to your optional advantages. Writing,
Poetry, and Musical Composition are appropriate if you share your work through
in written form. Public Speaking, Singing, Acting and Musical Instrument are
also good if you actually perform it. If you have the GURPS Basic Set, you can
also add Artist to the list of possible artistic skills, and you also add
Propaganda no matter what your medium is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;: Add a 10-point Secret (Mysterious Satirist), Selfless, and
Trickster to your optional disadvantage list if they are not already there. The
first represents the risk of bad things happening when the authorities discover
who you are, above and beyond what being a Silver Raven would bring. The other
two represent possible reasons for you to have chosen this path in the first
place.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>character</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels: Adjusting Setting Assumptions</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell&apos;s_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time for me to put on my GM hat and begin preparing my solo Hell’s Rebels
campaign. As mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/07/08/lets-play-hells-rebels.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I want to play this using the
GURPS Dungeon Fantasy rule set instead of the campaign’s native Pathfinder
1e. Let’s take a look at what this means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait a minute! Wasn’t that previous most published more than a year ago?
Well, turns out I started writing this one shortly after publishing it, but one
thing and another got in the way and I’m only getting around to publishing it
now. I’m actually a fair bit along in campaign preparation and even started
playing, I’m just behind on documenting the process. Anyway, let’s keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-setting&quot;&gt;The Setting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we all know by now, Hell’s Rebels takes place in Golarion, Pathfinder’s
setting. Golarion was built from the ground up to support dungeon fantasy
campaigns so we don’t have any fundamental friction between it and the Dungeon
Fantasy rules. Despite the many D&amp;amp;D-isms of Pathfinder’s first edition we
already know the setting can easily be used with other systems, since it has an
official Savage Worlds port and Paizo itself is in the process of removing those
D&amp;amp;D-isms from the latest iteration of their house system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, I do want to make a few changes to the version I’m going to
use. The most obvious one is I’m going to drop the many different fiend
classifications from D&amp;amp;D and Pathfinder in favor of Dungeon Fantasy’s
simplified “it’s all demons from Hell”. Any of the demons from DF will be fair
game as opposition here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since I’m talking about setting changes, any mention I find of Cheliax’s
fascists and diabolists being in any way “disciplined” or “organized” despite
their evil will be altered because incompetence, corruption, and a disregard for
any rules lies at the heart of fascism. These fucks do not make the trains run
on time and never have. You do not, at any point, gotta hand it to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to lean on the similarities between this campaign and Assassin’s
Creed Brotherhood, so we’ll be at a Renaissance tech level with early guns
widely available to guards and rebels. Make ready your blessed bullets, o devil
hunters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mechanics&quot;&gt;The Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this will mostly be pretty simple, because this won’t be the first time
I’m converting between Pathfinder and DF. I did already run the first two
volumes of Hell’s Rebels and the first three volumes of Iron Gods to different
player groups. During those times two issues jumped at me as being the most
difficult to handle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one was treasure conversions, but I think I’ve arrived at a satisfying
process for that &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/06/25/dungeon-fantasy-wealth.html&quot;&gt;in this post&lt;/a&gt;. Our delvers will eventually end up very
wealthy, but I imagine the rebellion will prove to be a great money sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other difficulty concerns the only somewhat common part of the dungeon
delving experience that’s harder to do in Dungeon Fantasy than in D&amp;amp;D:
underwater adventures. There’s a couple of extended underwater segments in the
middle of the adventure path, and Pathfinder’s default items and spells for it
are a lot more accessible than Dungeon Fantasy’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But hey, it turns out I already solved that too! &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html&quot;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; collects the
underwater rules I’ll be using, and &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/11/13/underwater-items.html&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; has a nice set of more
accessible items to let our PCs go for a swim and live to tell the tale. The
truth is that I started writing this post before I wrote the underwater ones, so
they were actually part of my effort to figure this campaign out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monster conversions used to be a big problem back when I started the Let’s Read,
but now I have enough DF monster books that I can swipe appropriate stat blocks
for nearly every one of them. If I need to create new ones for specific foes,
you can be sure I’ll post them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coming-up-next&quot;&gt;Coming up Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Character themes! Everybody loves character themes!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 14:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/08/26/lphr-setting-assumptions.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/08/26/lphr-setting-assumptions.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>gm-hat</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Denizens of the Sea</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve published an article about &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html&quot;&gt;underwater adventuring&lt;/a&gt; in the past, in
which I mentioned that “fish-people” had several advantages over “land-lubbers”
when it came to mobility and fighting in an underwater environment. A later post
included &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/11/13/underwater-items.html&quot;&gt;a few items&lt;/a&gt; that could help those land-lubbers close the
gap… so how about we take a look at those fish-people now? As a bonus, you get
a nice little bundle of setting info you can drop on your campaign if you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fate-of-atlantis&quot;&gt;The Fate of Atlantis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name “Atlantis” figures in the myths and legends of many more places than it
should. Cultures that have never heard of each other have stories about an
empire that ruled the waves in ancient times but no longer exists. The stories
might differ but the name is always the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s because ancient Atlantis was the largest and most powerful underwater
civilization to ever exist. They discovered a means of traveling to other worlds
and exploited it with gusto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its power Atlantis eventually fell, as all empires do. The exact
sequence of events is more or less impossible to piece together, and mostly
irrelevant in the present day. The important bit is that their inter-world
travel network was the first thing to go, instantly fragmenting the
empire. That’s why each of them has a different story about how Atlantis fell -
those stories talk only about the bits of it they knew about. In some, it
happened overnight due to a cataclysm. In others, they eventually morphed into
successor cultures that might still be extant in the present day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from giving rise to a whole bunch of legends and to fueling the occasional
would-be despot’s ambitions, the most enduring legacy of Atlantis was its
underwater engineering. They pioneered a lot of the techniques that used to make
sturdy weapons and tools out of implausible aquatic materials like bone, shell,
coral, and mother-of-pearl. They were also the first civilization to
successfully make and work orichalcum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we’re not here to talk about &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;, we’re here to talk about &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-lets-talk-about-people&quot;&gt;So Let’s Talk About People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opinions differ on whether Atlantis was a Golden Age utopia or a despotic empire
whose downfall was a blessing to the world, but everyone agrees it was pretty
diverse. Unlike most typical dungeon fantasy kingdoms, its citizens belonged to
many different species with none of them making up an overwhelming majority of
the population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of Atlantis’ citizens can be described using already-published stats. Sea
Elves and Water-Infused from GURPS DF 3: The Next Level fit very well, as do the
Argonians from &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/10/10/elder-scrolls-others.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. The octopus- and shark-folk from GURPS Banestorm
are also good fits, though they’re a bit more complex and costly than the
standard for DF racial templates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are a few new templates, with the overall goal of allowing a diverse
all-underwater party if the group wants to play that type of campaign. A couple
of the new ancestries I present here might have equivalent official templates
already, but since I don’t have those I’m writing new ones for my own use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These templates assume that being Amphibious also makes you able to see and hear
unimpeded while submerged, and the ability to breathe underwater also makes you
able to speak there. I feel this is in line with the simpler feel of Dungeon
Fantasy. If you want to follow Banestorm’s assumptions instead, give all
templates here one level of Nictitating Membrane {1} and Speak Underwater {5},
increasing their costs by 6 points each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;atlantean-20-points&quot;&gt;Atlantean (20 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This template describes people who are a product of successive generations of
intermarriage between the other species that made up the population of Atlantis,
and possibly some surfacers too. They are known as “Atlanteans” because their
general look became associated with that empire. Surprisingly, they look a lot
like humans even when they have no humans among their ancestors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlanteans are warm-blooded, have legs, and can breathe both water and
air. Their human-looking bits exhibit the same ethnic variety as
humans. Individuals can also have a variable number of “fishy” traits like visible
gills, fins, blue or gray skin, and so on. These might be visually striking but
are never significant enough to count as more than 0-point features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlanteans can appear in worlds that had an Atlantis, or those whose underwater
peoples are generally friendly with each other. The base stats could also be
used as they are or modified a bit to represent any species of underwater
humanoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages&lt;/strong&gt;: Amphibious {10}, Gills {10}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Traits&lt;/strong&gt;: Those fishy bits might count as varying levels of Unnatural
Features in a setting where almost everyone is human and the character is the
only known Atlantean, but in all other situations they’re 0-point traits. If the
character has something like rigid fins or a prominent tail growing out of their
lower back, they might need adapted body armor. This doesn’t cost extra, but
might restrict their usage of looted armor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;crab-folk-40-points&quot;&gt;Crab-Folk (40 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crab-folk are sapient humanoid crustaceans easily distinguished by their heavy
segmented carapaces. Like crabs, they lack distinct heads and their eyes are
located at the end of a pair of flexible, retractable stalks. Unlike crabs, they
only have the usual complement of humanoid limbs, though these are still
armored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crab-folk can operate normally on the surface, but their gills begin to dry out
if they go more than a day without being immersed in sea water. This means they
tend to stick close to the coast. Their voices sound strange and “bubbly”
outside the water, which most surfacers find off-putting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages&lt;/strong&gt;: 360-degree Vision {25}; Amphibious {10}; Gills {10}; Damage
Resistance 5 (Cannot Wear Armor) {15}; No Neck {5};&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/strong&gt;: Cold-Blooded {-5}; Disturbing Voice (In Air, -50%) {-5},
Dependency (Sea water, Daily) {-15}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optional Traits&lt;/strong&gt;: If your campaign takes place far from a coastal area, the
Dependency disadvantage is worth -30 points, and the template therefore costs
only 25. Your local alchemist can prepare a solution close enough to seawater to
satisfy the requirement, but it’s still not free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-ones-50-points&quot;&gt;Deep Ones (50 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These humanoids are much more obviously “fishy” than Atlanteans, with an anatomy
closer to that of an abyssal fish than a human’s. They’re adapted to the
lightless depths of the ocean and that’s where they prefer to make their
homes. Deep Ones can swim up to the shallows without suffering ill effects, but
can’t breathe air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Atlantis fell, it was not uncommon for its Deep One settlements to become
more isolated and break contact with shallower or surface communities. This some
times gave rise to sinister legends and rumors about what they got up to down
there. These are mostly bunk: they are no more prone to worshiping Elder Things
than any other species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages&lt;/strong&gt;: Amphibious {10}, Dark Vision {25}, Fangs {2}, Gills {0},
Pressure Support 3 {15}, Tough Skin 1 {3}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/strong&gt;: Cold-Blooded {-5}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optional Traits&lt;/strong&gt;: A variant that can operate on the surface would be closer
to several classic D&amp;amp;D fish-people. They have the 10-point version of Gills and
so cost that much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;merfolk-20-points&quot;&gt;Merfolk (20 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merfolk are humanoid from the waist up and have fish bodies from the waist
down. They can breathe both air and water and have naturally melodious voices in
both mediums, but they require magic or assistive devices like wheelchairs to
operate on land. Their human halves display the same variance as Atlanteans, and
their fish halves can resemble a variety of species of fish, shark, or cetacean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages&lt;/strong&gt;: Gills {10}, Voice {10}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/strong&gt;: No Legs (Aquatic) {0}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Features&lt;/strong&gt;: The “Leg” and “Foot” hit locations on merfolk refer to their tail
and lower fins instead. Armor for those locations must be specially
constructed. As usual this doesn’t cost extra but limits which looted armor they
can use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optional Traits&lt;/strong&gt;: If your character’s fish half mimics a particularly speedy
species, they might have Enhanced Move 1 (Water) for an extra 20 points. At the
GM’s option, this might be a matter of training instead of biology, which means
any merfolk character can buy this with earned points as a power-up.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/04/28/atlantis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/04/28/atlantis.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackaton: Hard Wired Island</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/hard-wired-island-cover.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Hard Wired Island&apos;s cover.
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard Wired Island is a cyberpunk game published by Weird Age Games in 2020. It’s
a beefy 400 page tome comparable in size to the Shadowrun or CP RED cores, but
only about 25% of that is rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-overview&quot;&gt;Setting Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard Wired Island takes place in Grand Cross, an O’Neil Cylinder habitat
orbiting Earth’s Lagrange 5 point, in the “distant future” of 2020. It was built
according to an idealistic plan in the wake of terrible environmental and
economic disasters on Earth, but is currently in the process of being co-opted
and corrupted by the interests of ultra-rich corporations and elites. The way in
which this is happening is described in very realistic detail throughout the
book, which also talks a bit about what people do to fight back. PCs are usually
expected to help in that fight, if not for moral reasons then because those
billionaires cause constant economic shocks that threaten their survival. This
is the main conflict in the setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grand Cross has cybernetic implants, gene editing, fully sapient AI and
androids. However its “global net” is still pretty much the internet
of 2020. It’s even &lt;em&gt;named&lt;/em&gt; “the internet”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every building in the station is wired for high-speed internet. The airwaves are
serviced by cell carriers like the ones you know from the real world, and some
of its wards even have free public wi-fi, though that tends to be poor quality
because capitalism is the worst virus. The station is linked to Earth’s internet
by satellites, with a 1.2-second lag there due to the physical distances
involved. Most big services have station-local data centers to try and get
around this, and there are some GC-native ones as well like HeoCities (website
hosting) and Pulser (a Crosser social network).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hackers are simply called hackers. Their equipment is collectively known as a
Hacking Suite, and it can be anything from computers that wouldn’t look out of
place here in the real world to some fancy cybernetic implant. Target systems
tend to be private corporate intranets or other networks located on the station,
and whether hacking is done remotely or on-site depends on the specific mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics-overview&quot;&gt;Mechanics Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most tests in Hard Wired Island use 2d6, with bonuses coming from one of the
PC’s main stats/approaches (Cool, Clever, Tough, and Quick), from a skill
specialty, from Augments (implants), and from Assets, which are special
equipment. There are rules for rolling with advantage/disadvantage (add a d6 and
drop the lowest/highest) or for Boosting rolls (add a d6, don’t drop
anything). Criticals happen when two or more dice roll the same value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system for hacking is a mixture of the systems for stealth and social
interaction. It has a set of specific actions associated with it, but also uses
some actions from those other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hackers begin each hacking attempt in a state called “Ghost”, meaning they
haven’t been detected by the target system’s security. They also begin with
three chances to avoid getting caught. Every time a hacker needs to do something
that requires a die roll, they might get caught if that test fails, and must
spend a chance in order to avoid that. If they fail a roll after running out of
chances, they’re discovered and their physical location is traced. Security is
on its way, but the hacker can still disconnect and try to run. A hacker can try
a Cover Your Tracks action to restore lost chances, but that’s also a roll so it
might backfire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Target networks have two stats: a Network Level that determines the basic
difficulty of all tests made against it, and a Mood that describes the
strictness of its security procedures and how willing it is to let you do
things. Hacking is mostly about improving the network’s Mood towards
you. &lt;em&gt;Friendly&lt;/em&gt; networks are helpful, giving Advantage for data searches within
then. &lt;em&gt;Indifferent&lt;/em&gt; networks neither help nor hinder. &lt;em&gt;Hostile networks&lt;/em&gt; assume
everyone is an intruder until they can prove otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most networks start out Indifferent, and their mood can be improved to Friendly
through hacking actions, or degrade to Hostile by failures. Hostile networks
can’t have their mood improved except by gaining admin access. This can be done
by succeeding at a number of rolls equal to its Network Level, but it’s not
strictly necessary to accomplish your goals. Admin access on a network makes it
Friendly, and prevents its mood from lowering. Doing anything in there becomes
almost trivial and you only need to maintain Ghost if someone intelligent is
monitoring the network (like another admin or an AI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no deadly ice here, and no cybercombat at all. Getting discovered and
traced is usually enough of a threat here, since those armed goons will kill you
just as dead, and the heightened state of alertness from the target will also
complicate your teammates’ lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard Wired Island tries to abstract the extensive planning sessions players of
other games engage in with a resource named “Prep”. Before the mission itself
you use actions to gather both Individual and Group Prep, and you spend those
points during missions to use your Assets or acquire new ones on the spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-parameters&quot;&gt;Run Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do have a sample hacker here, the ever adorable Maru. Her Hacking Suite is
built into her cybereyes but she still operates it with a keyboard. She will be
going with the team on this one, which might mean leaving that keyboard behind
but won’t affect her effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will once again go with three separate target networks here. The office
network is level 5 and Friendly to access from the inside; the security network
used by the guards is Indifferent and level 6; and the isolated server is
Hostile and level 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the first two detect intrusion they grow Hostile, trace Maru’s location, and
notify both the guards and the police. If the secret server detects intrusion it
will destroy itself in a very messy and noisy fashion, drawing guard
attention. This counts as a mission failure for our purposes, since the team
will spend the rest of the run trying to leave the office without the evidence
they came here to collect. As these are separate networks they have separate
Ghost counters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-summary&quot;&gt;Run Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in our series we’ll have to concern ourselves with stuff that
happens before the mission itself. Let’s make an Individual Prep roll for
Maru. She’s getting her software in order before the run, at her hacker den. We
roll 2d6 + Clever + Hacking + Hacker’s Den against a difficulty of 7, and get
a 11. Since this is the first Prep roll we’re making, Maru gains 1 automatic
Prep, and an extra 1 Prep for beating the difficulty by 4. She takes part in
Group Prep later, and let’s say they agree to leave 1 of those points for her
use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for the actual run. As always, the rest of the team manages to bullshit the
receptionist and make into the office posing as a repair crew. Maru locks
herself into a stall in the ladies’ room and begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security network isn’t advertising itself, so I rule Maru needs a Search
roll to find it. Her bonus here is +3 from Clever and +2 from Hacking; the
difficulty is 11 (the network’s level + 5). She succeeds with 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there’s a lot she must do in this net, we spend 1 of her 3 Prep to
activate the Data Bomb program Asset, which gives her Advantage on her next
three rolls here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rule that opening the door and turning off the camera each require an Operate
roll. From what I see in the rules this seems to use the Drone specialty instead
of Hacking. Maru doesn’t have that, so she’s rolling only 2d6+3 from her
Clever. Thankfully, the Data Bomb still gives her Advantage on these rolls. She
succeeds at both rolls with a 12 and a 11, precisely because of that Advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maru and her team move to the records room, and find the secret server. She
jacks into it and begins searching for the data. The difficulties here are all
12 from the Network Level. Maru spends another Prep to activate the Ghost
Protocol program, giving her Advantage on her next Hacking roll and an extra
Ghost chance. These rolls &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; use her Hacking specialty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advantage once again lets her succeed with a 14. I think succeeding at this lets
her take the data? Let’s be cruel instead and ask for a Spoof roll to download
the data without authorization. This is a Hostile server after all. No more
advantage here, but she still gets a 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team leaves the records room and Maru connects to the security wifi to open
the exit door. She still has one roll with Advantage remaining from her use of
Data Bomb, and succeeds on the Spoof roll with a 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the way out secured, she searches the office network for the money. No roll
needed to locate it, it’s Friendly and advertising itself to people inside the
office premises. A Search with Advantage lets her find the money with a roll of
11 versus the network’s lower difficulty of 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has no advantage for the Spoof roll to transfer the money elsewhere, but she
still succeeds with a 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mission accomplished! Time elapsed: around 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-analysis&quot;&gt;Run Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hard Wired Island feels more complex than Neon City Overdrive in its
presentation, but the hacking sequence here was about as fast. This was in part
due to good rolls all through the run, but a failure here would have had less
impact than in my Neon City run. There, a failed roll would have meant
cybercombat, a system I didn’t get to try at all. Here it would have meant an
extra roll or two as I lost one of my Ghost points and retried the test. Perhaps
I’d have spent another action or two recovering those points as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping it to about one roll per Thing You Do seems to be key to keeping hacking
brief.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/01/28/hackaton-hwi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2024/01/28/hackaton-hwi.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        <category>neon-city-overdrive</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon: Neon City Overdrive</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/nco-cover.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Neon City Overdrive&apos;s cover.
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neon City Overdrive is a game written by Nathan Russel and published by Peril
Planet Game Studio in 2020. This is the smallest core book of all the ones we’ve
seen so far at 72 pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll also be looking at a supplement named The Grid, which focuses on hacking
and has another 60 pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-overview&quot;&gt;Setting Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of those 132 pages are dedicated to the setting and to a set of adventure
seeds, both of which are largely based on &lt;em&gt;vibes&lt;/em&gt; instead of relying on
laboriously crafted timelines or detailed maps. This is the game of stylish
cyberpunks running dangerous jobs in a neon-lit sprawl. The reader is expected
to take it from there to add details as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setting as provided is just a basic sketch. The game takes place in The
City, which is divided into dense residential and commercial zones called
Metroplexes, equally dense hellish industrial blocks named Grinders, and the
Streets that flow in between. The City and the world it’s in are covered by the
Grid, a global computer network where nearly every device that can be described
as “electronic” or “computerized” has a presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grid gets a somewhat more detailed description because I’m using material
from the supplement here. Like the physical world it has several components. The
Signal lets all those devices connect to the Grid. It’s maintained by an army of
antennas, and repeater drones. The devices attuned to the Signal generate The
Overlay, which is projected into the physical world as a combination of
holograms and augmented reality. Most devices have an augmented reality
interface instead of physical controls, and most signage exists in the Overlay
only. Hubs are big static computers. Some of them help route and maintain the
Signal and the Overlay, or host public virtual environments, but others are
private servers used by the sort of organization your cyberpunks need to hack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use the grid through an interface that resembles a real-world smartphone
or desktop browser, but it’s also possible to go into full immersion VR. This
works as you’d expect if you’re familiar with the genre (and if you’ve read the
other entries in this series, you are). We have our Gibsonian matrix here, with
wireframe or low-poly graphics by default, but with specific hubs represented as
more realistic environments. The more powerful the owner, the more realistic
their hubs’ presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of social events happen entirely in the Grid’s virtual reality, from
important business conferences to sport tournaments and nightclub
gatherings. Virtual reality ensures they feel mostly like physical events. That
sure would have been handy during our real world pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside is that “common” grid users are constantly monitored and
tracked. Player characters and other dirty criminals have their ways of evading
this, and despite the efforts of law enforcement agencies and corporate
security, grid crime is very common and not going away any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you go into VR, you emerge at the Local Area Zone corresponding to your
physical location but can move to any other LAZ you can access with a
thought. Movement within a LAZ is restricted to the sort of thing a real person
would be able to do in the physical world, and the landscape reflects this. Want
to go to a site in your LAZ? You need to walk. The book recognizes this is
inconvenient. Some area zones are private, either disconnected from the public
Grid entirely or separated from it by virtual gates that admit only those with
the proper credentials. A skilled enough hacker might be able to break through a
gate. Totally isolated networks can only be accessed by physically jacking into
their hubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can access the grid using wearable computers, which are cheap and widely
available. Serious hackers (called &lt;em&gt;codeslingers&lt;/em&gt; here) have an implanted
interface chip that has all the same functions and allows diving into VR as
well. Those who can’t or won’t use implants can make do with a “Grid-box”, a VR
helmet that also covers the mouth and nose. And both can further benefit from a
sensory deprivation chamber if they’re &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; serious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This default presentation is subject to change, as GMs are encouraged to tweak
the arrangement to get the right vibe they want. By tweaking the list of
available technologies and how common they are you could get anything from
mainframes-and-telephones with a chrome veneer to a Ghost in the Shell-like
ubiquitous net where everyone has implanted computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics-overview&quot;&gt;Mechanics Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I understand the rules of Neon City Overdrive belong to the lineage of
Forged in the Dark games. There are &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; specific mechanics for the Grid here,
not even if you use the supplement. Hacking uses the exact same mechanics as
everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tests use six-sided dice. You start with one Action Die, and gain more for each
factor in your character sheet or the story that helps you succeed, and a Danger
Die for each factor that gets in the way. Then you roll the resulting pool. Each
Danger Die cancels an Action Die that rolled the same value. You take the
highest value rolled in the remaining Action Dice, and use it to determine the
result. A 3 or less is a failure, a 4 or 5 is a partial success with a cost
attached, and a 6 is a complete success. The book goes into a bit more detail
than this, but we don’t need it for this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narration and the fiction it creates are &lt;em&gt;supremely&lt;/em&gt; important because they’ll
set the stakes for the roll and inform you of which positive and negative
factors are in play to build your die pool. Players are the only ones who roll
dice. Enemies and obstacles are a source of Danger Dice but the GM never needs
to roll for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacking also uses those rules. The additional rules material in the Grid
supplement is just a clarification that purely physical traits and tags don’t
apply to tests made in the Grid, and Grid-specific ones don’t apply to the meat
world. Can´t use your muscle grafts to hack the Gibson, can’t use your fancy
programs to lift a car. Mental traits might apply to either “reality”, though.
The book encourages focusing on the imagery of the simulation and making it as
close to the physical world as possible, to make it easier for the group to
describe actions without needing to know a lot about computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-parameters&quot;&gt;Run Parameters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re supposed to set the exact shape of our Grid when we play, so let’s say
it’s more or less the same as Shadowrun 4th Edition’s. It’s not a pure mesh
network, there’s cell tower hubs and such, but it’s close enough for our
purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hacker will be going along with the physical team. The target office’s Grid
layout is the same as in the SR4 version. The physical location surely has its
own set of tags but the one that affects us is that our good disguises give us
the &lt;em&gt;element of surprise&lt;/em&gt;. Losing this might be one of the consequences for a
hacking complication here. In a real game that’d affect the rest of the team
too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;target-systems&quot;&gt;Target Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an office intranet that’s connected to the general Grid through a
firewall, which we bypass by being inside the office. Its security from the
inside is &lt;em&gt;nothing special&lt;/em&gt; except that access to the bank accounts is
&lt;em&gt;well-guarded&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internal security wireless network covers the office but not connected to
the outside. It’s &lt;em&gt;hardened against intrusion&lt;/em&gt; and has a piece of Blue ICE
that will trigger at the first complication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our secret server in the records room with no wireless network at all. Our
hacker must physically jack into it. It’s also &lt;em&gt;hardened&lt;/em&gt;, and has Black ICE
constantly watching over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-hacker&quot;&gt;Our Hacker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pixie-non-binary-human&quot;&gt;Pixie (non-binary human)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trademarks and Edges&lt;/strong&gt;: Metroplexer, Codeslinger (Hacking, Cyber Combat),
Infiltrator (Alarms, Locks)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flaws&lt;/strong&gt;: Greedy, Socially Awkward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gear&lt;/strong&gt;: Interface Chip (Fast, Advanced), Icebreaker (Silent, Deadly), Stealth
Program Suite (Mimetic, Subtle), something else non-hacking related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pixie is kinda min-maxed to fit our scenario, to be honest, with lots of traits
that would apply to hacking. They’re a passable sneak in the physical world but
not very good at physical combat and bad at social interaction. That’s what the
rest of the team is for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-summary&quot;&gt;Run Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team gets into the office as usual - we always assume this part works
out. Pixie hides in the bathroom to find the security network and hack into it
via VR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decide to roll the security server hack as an extended task, since those
require three successes and we have three goals in here. Pixie decides to use
Infiltrator instead of Codeslinger for this, since it is an infiltration of
sorts and that’s where they put put their Alarms and Locks edges. I’m being
lenient towards my player (who is also me) here. Those traits plus all other
relevant tags give Pixie a total of seven action dice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pixie is opposed by a single danger die, from the server being Hardened, but
that die rolls a six and eats the one I rolled on the action dice. They’re left
with a 5 and a 4, which count as successes towards our goal but apply
consequences as well. So I rule we lost our Element of Surprise and that the
Blue ICE on the server activated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rule that the ICE hasn’t found Pixie yet, but it does get to add its relevant
tags as danger dice on the next roll as it looks for them. Fortunately none of
those roll a six and the action dice do, allowing Pixie to unlock the final door
ahead of time. Tests from this point on are made using Codeslinger as expected,
since they deal purely with stuff that lives in the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get to the secret server and I rule that the Black Ice in there is already
active but will only spot Pixie as a consequence - they start out stealthy. The
ICE however does get to add its Counter-Intrusion and Scary tags as danger dice
even so. Fortunately its rolls are crap and Pixie gets a 6, finding and
downloading the evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let’s go for the money! This means the office network’s Well-Guarded
tag becomes a danger die, but as before the ice only comes online as a
consequence. We roll a 5 here, so it does come online, but not before we
transfer the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physical team proceeds to try to leave the office, but as usual we stop our
simulation here since the main hacking bits are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total elapsed time: 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-analysis&quot;&gt;Run Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love engaging with crunchy mechanics but narrative systems do have their
advantages! 15 minutes is the fastest time we have so far, beating the “silent
run” from SR 4th Edition by 2 minutes. And this only took so long because I have
absolutely no experience with Neon City Overdrive and had to keep looking at the
books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible this run was too easy, but it’s okay because it’s inserted into
the larger context of the physical break-in. Pixie would have plenty to do in
that part of the run. I might have made a mistake here in simply having
“unaware” ICE add some of its tags to the hacking roll. The system is abstract
enough that I could have ruled slipping past the ICE undetected would require
“fighting” it and filling its Harm boxes while describing it as a sneaking
attempt. Whatever form it took in the narrative, combat would have made things
take longer, but not by much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanical bits of the run would probably be much faster than the 50/90
minutes I’ve been assuming here, but this would be offset in all cases by the
extended narration and roleplaying the game demands to frame those mechanics and
establish all the influencing factors for each roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our experiment however does allow us to conclude the obvious: when you use the
exact same simple resolution mechanic for everything, everyone has more or less
the same spotlight time and the classic “Decker problem” won’t manifest.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/11/16/hackaton-nco.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/11/16/hackaton-nco.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        <category>neon-city-overdrive</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Underwater Dungeon Fantasy 2: Items and Artifacts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A while ago I posted a compilation of methods and tools for &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/07/11/underwater-dungeon-fantasy.html&quot;&gt;underwater
adventuring&lt;/a&gt;. In this post, I’ll add a few items and artifacts that further
help with that or that make sense as possessions for underwater people. This is
a grab-bag article without much direction, but I hope it will be useful
nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alchemical-pills&quot;&gt;Alchemical Pills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any drinkable concoction (including magic potions) might be made as a solid pill
instead. Pills tend to be round, thumbnail sized, hard, and meant to be
swallowed whole. Pills are popular with alchemists and herbalists who don’t have
a line to a crystal vial supplier, and with underwater civilizations since
liquid potions don’t really work there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pill costs the same as the equivalent liquid potion. It’s waterproof and not
at risk of breaking from falls and the like, but it also can’t be put into
bandoliers for easy access during combat. Dry-swallowing a pill during a fight
requires either two Ready maneuvers or a single maneuver and a HT roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; put each of your pills into a separately-purchased crystal vial (DF1
p. 111) in order to have them in your potion belt, but that does add an extra
Ready maneuver to the process of ingesting it since you have to open the vial
first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elixir-of-water-breathing&quot;&gt;Elixir of Water Breathing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This alchemical elixir can be found on GURPS Magic, and is “reprinted” here with
additional options. It’s a drinkable potion that lets you breathe underwater as
if you had Gills for 1d hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GM rolls the die in secret when you drink it, and you remain unaware of how
long you have… until 5 minutes before that time expires, when you get an
instinctive mental warning that you only have 5 minutes left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GMs who dislike the randomness can set a fixed duration based on how much they
want their PCs to spend on these potions. I suggest from 1 to 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purely aquatic people can instead get Elixirs of &lt;em&gt;Air&lt;/em&gt; Breathing for the same
price and with the equivalent effect for air. Both variants are very likely to
be found in pill form (see above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all cases, the potion is $600, 0.25kg (0.5 lbs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coral-items-4-cf&quot;&gt;Coral Items (+4 CF)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coral is a new implausible material: items made from it have a somewhat porous
texture but are covered in intricate natural patterns of bright colors. Coral
comes in rough or polished varieties, though both cost the same. Surfacers value
it because it’s pretty, underwater civilizations value it for its incidental
properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coral items can be made without fire, though they do require special magic and
techniques known to underwater armorers. They also have neutral buoyancy: their
weight does not count towards Encumbrance when determining the user’s penalty to
Swimming. Anything that’s usually made of metal or wood can be made of coral
instead. Being made of coral adds +4 CF to the item’s total cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;artifact-atlantean-armbands&quot;&gt;Artifact: Atlantean Armbands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Origin: Divine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pair of gilded orichalcum armbands decorated with reliefs of sharks
and other marine creatures. The Atlantean Armbands were said to be a gift of the
gods to a human hero destined to become the queen of a great underwater
nation. That did indeed happen, and since all of the queen’s descendants were
born with the ability to live underwater the armbands became honored museum
pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That ancient empire has long since fallen to the tides of history, so who knows
where these artifacts might surface next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sell Price&lt;/strong&gt;: $50.000.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weight&lt;/strong&gt;: 0.5kg (1 lb) for the pair.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power Item Capacity&lt;/strong&gt;: 20 FP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;properties&quot;&gt;Properties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When worn (one in each arm), they allow the wielder to freely breathe and move
underwater as if they had the Gills and Amphibious traits.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If used as power items, any FP from the armbands that’s spent on the Swim and
Breathe Water spells is worth double the energy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;variations&quot;&gt;Variations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some legends tell of another pair of armbands, of silver-plated orichalcum and
decorated with land-animal motifs, that would allow an aquatic wearer to breathe
air and walk on land, assuming a humanoid form if necessary. These were created
by an evil but powerful witch for a mermaid that wanted to walk among humans,
and are Druidic in origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of armbands, you could have rings, piercings, or amulets with the same
enchantments.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/11/13/underwater-items.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/11/13/underwater-items.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>items</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Tabletop Hackathon: Shadowrun 5th Edition, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/sr5-cover.png&quot;/&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Shadowrun 5th Edition&apos;s cover.
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set our parameters in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2023/11/09/hackaton-sr5-1.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, so let’s do the actual run in this
one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;run-summary&quot;&gt;Run Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our decker enters with her team, and they get past the reception as usual. This
time I decide to do things a little bit differently and go for spoofing
peripheral devices over trying to control them from inside the host. This seems
to be the correct way to do it in SR5, judging from the examples in the Matrix
chapter. The Control Device action is only used for things that would require a
conventional skill test if done in the physical world, like shooting a turret’s
gun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the camera. It’s visible both in the real and in the Matrix, since
running silent would harm its functionality. Ms. Decker always prefers to use
the “quiet” Hack on the Fly action, since that’s her specialty. The camera and
other devices are tied to the office’s host, so they use the host’s ratings
instead of their own to resist. But when Ms. Decker places a mark on a device,
she automatically places a mark on the host as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She manages to place a mark on the camera, and therefore on the host. This means
she can dispense with silent running from this point on, since the Patrol IC
can’t tell the mark she has right now was illegally obtained and will no longer
try to raise an alarm. She uses a Spoof action on the camera, disabling it. Our
tally sits at 6. We do not want it to reach 40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Decker knows there is an alarm, but it’s not immediately visible as an icon
on the Matrix. Unlike the camera, the alarm &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; running silent. A Matrix
Perception action reveals that there is indeed a hidden icon nearby. A couple
more attempts at it reveal the alarm’s icon. None of these perception tests
accrues Overwatch, since they’re not tied to the “illegal” attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She tries to mark the alarm, but fails! I spend 1 Edge to roll an additional 2
dice (her Edge score) on this, and get 2 extra hits. From what I understand, a
tie here isn’t a victory for either side, so ms. Decker still fails to mark the
alarm but the system does not detect her. Whew! The next attempt succeeds, but
both sides roll really well. The spoof attempt succeeds handily. Our tally sits
at 17 after all of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Decker disconnects from the host at this point since she needs to move with
the physical team. But since she does not reboot her deck, all of the marks she
placed remain on the host. Her Overwatch Tally also stays at 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team enters the records room and begins the physical search. Ms. Decker
spots a physical jackpoint here and uses that. She’s inside the host again, and
now she is able to see all of its remaining files and devices automatically
since none of them are silent. This includes the evidence she’s after, which is
only accessible from this jackpoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Downloading a file is automatic, but it requires a mark on it first. She manages
to mark and download the evidence, and then decides to go for the money. I rule
that this will require marking the account file and then editing it to transfer
the money. The marking goes smoothly, the editing runs into a tied test first,
succeeding on the second attempt. Fortunately only the marking accrued
Overwatch, which at this point sits at 23.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, still jacked into that physical access point, Ms. Decker attempts to
mark and spoof the exit door to unlock it. The marking succeeds, and the
spoofing gives me a bit of stress as again the first attempt ties and the second
one succeeds. Good rolls all around here, so our final Overwatch tally is a
dangerous 37.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hacker has time to safely jack out, and the team gets to walk away through
the now-unlocked door. All mission goals have been accomplished. She waits until
they’re out to reboot her deck, since that would erase all of her marks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total time: 31 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analysis&quot;&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;31 minutes is something I consider fast, comparable to CP 2020 and CP RED. It’s
also about as easy to slice up into manageable chunks as CP RED’s and SR 4’s
runs were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However this was a near-perfect run, with our decker remaining undetected
throughout the whole thing despite a couple of close calls. If we had been
detected at any point there would have been cybercombat and things would have
taken longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most of the other games we’ve looked at so far, it’s impossible to simply
kill all the ice, since each one a hacker destroys is just going to be
relaunched at the start of the next turn. The occasional assurances by the book
that you can rely on brute force alone to smash through a host ring a bit
hollow, since that seems like it leads to combat sooner even with good rolls
from the hacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had she activated the host’s ice, Ms. Decker would need to spend actions to hide
instead of just attacking. That Patrol IC would be trying to find her every turn
and she’d take a universal -2 dice penalty for silent running. I could see this
maybe doubling our run time, but I’m not going to count that as an official
timing. It’s just a guesstimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with this near-perfect run, we ended up with a tally of 37. With even
slightly better rolls from the host in a couple of places we’d have hit 40. This
wouldn’t have meant instant death since we’re inside a host, but it still would
have placed 3 marks on Ms. Decker at once, and let the host see her and start
activating IC. She sure hopes the team doesn’t get into a firefight on the way
out, because if she has to do anything else Matrix-related to help then she is
definitely going to draw the ire of Overwatch.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/11/12/hackaton-sr5-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/11/12/hackaton-sr5-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk</category>
        
        <category>hard-wired-island</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
