<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 18:26:24 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 18:26:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Wood Woad</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-wood-woad.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I remember seeing mention of Wood Woads in AD&amp;amp;D somewhere, but I
couldn’t find them in my books. This is their 4e debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood Woads are fey creatures distantly related to dryads. Like dryads, they
devoutly protect the natural environment of their home region. Unlike dryads,
they all look male and have absolutely zero chill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do wood woads attack would-be despoilers of nature with murderous
intent, they tend to blame each new intruder for the crimes of all the previous
ones. So even if you’re careful with the environment and try to approach them
peacefully, they’ll still try to kill you because some fool cut a tree down
years ago and managed to run away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood woads tend to ally with other sworn protectors of nature, like dryads,
centaurs and some elves or other fey. So I guess you could still deal with them
peacefully if you manage to approach those allies first and get them to vouch
for you, or have them act as intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a single Wood Woad stat block. It’s a Medium Fey Humanoid with the Plant
keyword, and a Level 8 Soldier with 92 HP. It has trained Perception, and a
ground speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood Woads wield wooden shields and clubs. Their basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt;,
which does average damage and has no special effects. They can channel magic
through it to inflict &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Judgment&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+, Reliable) on a
target. This is an attack that does more damage than the basic club,
immobilizes, and inflicts ongoing physical damage on the target. When the target
takes this ongoing damage, the closest fey or plant ally of the wood woad heals
the same amount of HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reliable keyword means this power isn’t used up if the attack misses. The
wood woad can keep trying to use it until it hits someone, and only them will it
need to make recharge rolls. This attack becomes more useful if all of the wood
woad’s allies are either plants or fey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can also curse someone with &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Mystery&lt;/strong&gt; as a
minor action. This inflicts a -2 penalty on all of the target’s attacks,
defenses, and saves. The save to end this effect has an &lt;em&gt;additional&lt;/em&gt; -5 penalty
unless the target can succeed at a DC 20 Nature check before rolling it. Guess
this spell has a loophole somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is different from the sphinx ability we saw earlier in this Let’s Read,
because no one else can make the Nature test in the target’s place. This makes
Nature’s Mystery an excellent ability to use on most defenders, since they tend
to have low-to-middling Wisdom and no training in Nature. Wardens are the big
exception to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Targets affected by this Nature’s Mystery are also prime targets for Nature’s
Judgment. Make sure to surround them with plant and fey monsters after they get
hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: Two dryads, two vine horror spellfiends, 2 wood woads. Did the vine
horror manage to convince the fey it’s part of the local natural environment?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 1 Gnome Entropist, 1 Satyr Piper, 1 Shambling Mound, 3 Wood Woads. I
guess the gnome is a actually a druid using the entropist stat block.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the feel of the mechanics on this one, but the lore is once again a bit
uninspiring. It’s another humanoid fey plant that’s fanatical about protecting
nature, just like dryads and treants. I guess they can round out the cast when
you want to focus a game on a faction of such beings, but we already have a lot
of other possible creatures that belong there as well (satyrs, centaurs, elven
druids, and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use the wood woad stat block but don’t want to say they’re a
completely separate species, just say they’re small treants instead.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wood-woad.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Winter Wolf</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-wolf-winter.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual already gave us &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/13/wolves.html&quot;&gt;wolves normal and dire&lt;/a&gt;, and it also gave
us &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/19/worg.html&quot;&gt;worgs&lt;/a&gt;. Now the Monster Manual 2 continues to climb the wolf power
ladder. I first remember seeing Winter Wolves in the 3e monster books, but I’m
pretty sure they’ve been around longer than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I tried to explain how all of these monsters fit together I suppose I’d say
it all starts with the Sons of the Spirit Wolf. The Great Spirit Wolf is a
godlike primal spirit, and his progeny wander the world forever trying to
satisfy their endless hunger. I guess they’re more or less equivalent to the
various wolf spirits worshipped by the Uratha from Werewolf: The Forsaken, only
not nearly as nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These primal spirits probably had descendants themselves, which would be your
“standard” winter wolves. These fit above worgs in the Wolf Power
Ladder. They’re a bit smaller than worgs, but are much deadlier, much smarter,
and just as evil. They also have ice powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point a primordial entity of ice and cold might have taken a look at
the Sons of the Spirit Wolf and thought hey, I want me some of that. So it
developed a process where it takes the living heart of an elemental blizzard and
fashions a Rime Hound out of it. Unlike the creatures they are modeled after,
Rime Hounds are entirely made of ice. Their creators give them as gifts to loyal
servants and worshippers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the creatures in this entry are Magical Beasts. Winter wolves are Natural,
and the others are Elemental. They all have low-light vision and a ground speed
of 8 with Ice Walk, which means they ignore cold-themed difficult terrain. Sons
of the Spirit Wolf have Resist Cold 30, all the others have Resist Cold 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their powers are a combination of the usual wolfy bites and takedowns with a
suite of frost breath weapons and the like, but the specifics vary with each
stat block. Their Int scores are in the average human range. We’ll look at them
by order of level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winter-wolf&quot;&gt;Winter Wolf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winter Wolves are Medium, and are Level 14 Skirmishers with 141 HP. They attack
with &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; that deal bonus cold damage, and deal about double damage to
prone targets. They can get people prone with a &lt;strong&gt;Takedown&lt;/strong&gt;, a charge attack
that’s stronger than the basic bite and knocks the target prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a winter wolf is adjacent to a prone target it can use &lt;strong&gt;Drag&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will
minor action that allows the wolf to shift 1 square and pull the prone victim
along with it. It’s more than smart enough to use this to put the victim in a
position to be surrounded by its wolf buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, winter wolves can use a &lt;strong&gt;Freezing Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a Close
Blast 5 that targets Reflex and deals cold damage (half on a miss). This
attack’s damage is smaller than the wolf’s cold resistance, so a pack of winter
wolves is going to try to get the party all bunched up and then hit them with
multiple blasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winter-wolf-snowfang&quot;&gt;Winter Wolf Snowfang&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snowfangs are Level 16 Lurkers with 124 HP, representing the sort of wily wolf
that keeps out of sight and nips at your heels until you’re too weak to fight
back. Rather than relying on takedowns, it tries to freeze its victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do bonus cold damage, and are stronger against victims who are
taking ongoing cold damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;Frigid Breath&lt;/strong&gt; works like that of the
standard winter wolf with an added ongoing cold damage rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snowfang’s lurker-y ability is &lt;strong&gt;Snow Zephyr&lt;/strong&gt;, a reaction that triggers
when it gets damaged and turns it into a whirlwind of snow. This causes the
snowfang to become insubstantial, and to gain the ability to shift its speed as
a move action. In this form it can only attack with Frigid Breath, which also
causes it to revert to wolf form. It can also revert voluntarily as a minor
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These powers allow snowfangs to act as very effective harriers: they charge in,
use Freezing Breath, and fight until damaged. Then they shift away in Snow
Zephyr form, and vanish for a while. Then they come back, perhaps even still in
zephyr form, use Freezing Breath again, and repeat the process. You could use
them like this as persistent foes who refuse to have a stand-up fight to the
last, and who pop up to make opportunistic attacks in the middle of other
encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rime-hounds&quot;&gt;Rime Hounds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These knockoff winter wolves are quite well-made! They’re Huge in size, and are
Level 17 Elite Skirmishers with 332 HP. They have the Earth, Cold, and Mount
keywords, so they’re appropriate mounts for ice giants!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have Reach 2 Bite and Takedown attacks identical to those of a winter wolf,
with bigger numbers. They have the same Drag ability as well. Instead of a
Freezing Breath, they have &lt;strong&gt;Frost Storm&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Burst 3 that targets
Fortitude and deals cold damage (half on a miss). This creates a zone of frozen
difficult terrain that lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, their “elite multi-attack” power is actually a reaction: &lt;strong&gt;Ice
Spikes&lt;/strong&gt; which extend whenever the hound or its rider are missed by an enemy
melee attack. This acts as a free attack on the triggering enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;son-of-the-spirit-wolf&quot;&gt;Son of the Spirit Wolf&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Large wolfy demigods are Level 26 Elite Skirmishers with 486 HP. Their
surrounded by an aura (1) named &lt;strong&gt;Everfrost Coat&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals 10 cold damage
to enemies who enter it. Enemies damaged by the aura can’t make opportunity
attacks for a turn, which allows this wolf to freely disengage from most PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do the usual physical/cold damage mix and grab the
target on a hit. They can then use &lt;strong&gt;Drag Away&lt;/strong&gt; to either shift 1 square or
move their speed while pulling the victim along. They can also use &lt;strong&gt;Rending
Jaws&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) against the grabbed victim, a much stronger attack than the
basic bite that also pushes the target 5 squares and knocks them prone as the
wolf ends the grab and flings the victim away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing in the text forbidding the wolf from using normal bites on other
enemies while it has a victim grabbed. You are of course free to forbid it since
it only has one mouth… but what if it doesn’t? What if this is a vaguely
wolf-shaped ball of dark spirit stuff instead of being just a big wolf? What if
it can grow extra mouths to bite people with? Maybe it’s not canon, but it’s
metal as fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the thing’s last attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Black Ice Breath&lt;/strong&gt; which is kind of a
hybrid between the breaths of the other two varieties: big cold damage in a
Close Blast 5, and it leaves a zone of frozen difficult terrain that lasts for
the whole encounter. This is an encounter power that recharges when the wolf is
first bloodied, just like dragon breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the links between the different monsters here are purely my
invention. Judging from the descriptions of the book alone, they don’t have
anything in common other than being generally wintery and wolfy. The individual
stat blocks have good mechanics, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 14: a Chillfire Destroyer elemental and a pair of
winter wolves being bossed around by a Beholder Eye of Frost.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wolf-winter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/wolf-winter.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Witherling</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-witherling.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witherlings feel like a new monster to me. They’re certainly new to 4e, making
their debut in this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, those deranged cannibals who worship Yeenoghu don’t
actually eat everyone they kill. Sometimes they raise their victims as undead
abominations. This is a relatively new development, as the technique was only
recently handed down from the demon lord to its cultists. They are both a new
weapon in the war brewing between Yeenoghu and Orcus, and a way for the former
to muscle in on the latter’s territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process to create a witherling involves replacing the corpse’s head with
that of a hyena, and summoning the essence of a demon into the resulting piece
of “art”. Gnolls and other Yeenoghu cultists prefer to do this to the corpses of
their slain foes, not those of their own side. The result tends to be a lot
faster, smarter and more versatile than that of your typical zombie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All witherlings are Natural Animates with the Undead keyword. They have no
particular resistances or vulnerabilities. Their signature trait is a lesser
form of the gnoll &lt;strong&gt;Pack Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, giving them a +2 damage bonus when two or
more of their allies are adjacent to the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling&quot;&gt;Witherling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is usually made from the corpse of a Small humanoid like a
goblin, kobold, or halfling. It’s a Level 4 Skirmisher with 56 HP and a Speed of
8 (Climb 6).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witherling &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are a bit weak, but they slow on a hit (save ends) and the
creature can make a &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; with them. It also deals extra damage when
it has combat advantage. While bloodied, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Blood Dance&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 2
squares instead of 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its final ability is a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Leap&lt;/strong&gt; that allows it to jump 4 squares and gain
a +5 to AC against opportunity attacks during the jump. If an enemy misses the
witherling with an opportunity attack while it’s jumping, the witherling gains
combat advantage against that enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So these things will come at you en masse from the walls and the bottoms of
pits, and use Sudden Leap to jump juuust a bit past the PCs and attack them from
behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-death-shrieker&quot;&gt;Witherling Death Shrieker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made from the corpse of a Medium creature, the Death Shrieker is a Level 5
Controller with 65 HP and the Leader keyword. Its a bit slower with a ground
speed of 6 and no climbing ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are just a typical basic attack, but it shrieks do damage over a
wide area (close blast 5). The most common one is the &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Shriek&lt;/strong&gt;, which
targets only enemies, does thunder damage, and pushes 2 squares. There’s also
the &lt;strong&gt;Death Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which also targets only enemies and does
untyped damage. Any undead ally adjacent to an enemy hit by this recovers 5
HP. There’s a note saying allies can only benefit from this once per round, so
if you have multiple shriekers they should coordinate and stagger their screams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-horned-terror&quot;&gt;Witherling Horned Terror&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is Large, and made from a minotaur. Since Yeenoghu is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; locked in
eternal battle against Baphomet, they’re more common than you think. Minotaurs
of all alignments hate these things, which is perfectly understandable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horned Terrors are Level 8 Brutes with 107 HP and a ground speed of 7. They have
a decent &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack, and can use their &lt;strong&gt;Horns&lt;/strong&gt; to the same amount of
damage and push the target 2 squares. They can also perform a &lt;strong&gt;Rampaging
Charge&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which uses the horns to attack and allows them to make
up to three additional attacks against different targets who happen to be in
reach at the end point of the charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;witherling-rabble&quot;&gt;Witherling Rabble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a witherling whose creation process glitched out, producing an inferior
specimen. I guess they’re stockpiled and sent out as a huge mob against
enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This defective undead has the exact same attacks as a standard witherling, but
is a Level 9 Minion Skirmisher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eh… I guess witherlings are okay mechanically, and they’re a nice addition to
a campaign focused on battling Yeenoghu and evil gnolls, but they don’t do much
for me personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are different groups of gnolls with witherling
support. One of them also has a cambion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/witherling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/witherling.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Will-O'-Wisp</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-will-o-wisp.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will-O’-Wisps in D&amp;amp;D are inspired by folklore, and their legend is in turn
inspired by the natural phenomena that make swamp gas glow at night. I think
they’ve been in the game since AD&amp;amp;D, though their exact lore might have changed
a bit over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will-o’-wisps are cruel fey spirits who feed on the fear and despair of other
sapients. They like to hang out in swamps and marshes, whose natural mists and
swamp lights provide them with hiding places. Their bodies are orbs of gauzy
material, and they glow with an otherwordly light that has the power to lure
unwary victims. It can also burn their flesh and drain their spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their tactics are pretty much iconic - lure victims to an isolated place full of
hindering terrain and kill them in a way that produces maximum horror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures can communicate in Elven, and when they speak they have that
cool effect where they brighten and dim in compass with their speech. They can
also douse their light for better stealth, but this also prevents them from
using it as a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will-o’-Wisps are Small Fey Magical Beasts, and Level 10 Lurkers with 57
HP. They count as Insubstantial, taking only half damage from non-force
attacks. They have low-light vision and a flight speed of 6 with Hover, and an
altitude limit of 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, wisps can turn their light on or off using the &lt;strong&gt;Fey Light&lt;/strong&gt;
ability (minor action 1/round). A darkened wisp has concealment and can make
Stealth checks to become hidden, but it cannot attack. If a wisp is missed by an
attack, it can &lt;strong&gt;Blink Out&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. When this happens, the wisp darkens
and teleports 5 squares. I guess it can make that Stealth check as part of this
action too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wisp’s attacks are all light-based. The most classic one is of course
&lt;strong&gt;Luring Glow&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a Close Burst 20 that targets one non-blinded creature,
which is another way to say it’s a ranged attack that doesn’t draw opportunity
attacks. It targets Will, does no damage, pulls the victim 3 squares, and dazes
it (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the victim is in range and vulnerable, the wisp is going to hit it with its
basic &lt;strong&gt;Glimmer Wisp&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which is Reach 2, targets Reflex, and does
radiant damage. Once per encounter it can also use &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Drain&lt;/strong&gt; on a
bloodied target. This is a Reach 3 attack that targets Fortitude, deals psychic
damage, weakens (save ends) and heals the wisp for 14 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wisps are lurkers and have a couple of good stealth powers, but they don’t
seem to have a lot of ability to take advantage of this stealth. Their best
power is the very controller-y Luring Glow. When building wisp fights, you
should pair them with other opportunistic monsters that can bring the hurt to
those dazed characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our sample encounter is level 9: two wisps and a quartet of spriggans (two
powries, 2 thorns). Evil fairies all around.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/will-o-wisp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/will-o-wisp.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Warforged</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-warforged.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged were originally introduced with the Eberron setting in 3e, as a
playable option. They made their 4e debut in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/07/warforged.html&quot;&gt;first Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;,
which a couple of “monster” stat blocks for warforged and some abbreviated rules
for using them as PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full support for playable warforged in 4e would arrive with the Eberron Player’s
Guide, published in June 2009. However, just before that happened we’d get a few
more NPC stat blocks here in the MM2, which was published in May 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic lore for warforged remains the same as in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/02/07/warforged.html&quot;&gt;the Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;. The
Eberron-specific info would only appear on the Eberron Player’s Guide, but I
guess the two books were developed in parallel because the extra stat blocks we
get here seem like a particularly good fit for that setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature traits remain the same: the Living Construct keyword, a +2 to
saves against ongoing damage and the &lt;strong&gt;Warforged Resolve&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power (see
the link above to read about what this does).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-resounder&quot;&gt;Warforged Resounder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are warforged spellcasters whose power derives from a retained echo of the
ringing sound of their creation forges. Their spells tend to have themes of
sound and impact, dealing a mix of thunder and force damage. They wear robes and
wield staffs, so I guess they’re meant to come across as “arcane”, but you could
easily use their lore for a more priestly type since it’s so close to that of
the Anvilpriest (below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resounders are Level 6 Artillery with 57 HP and the common traits described
above. Their &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaves&lt;/strong&gt; are weak melee attacks, so they prefer to stay
away and cast &lt;strong&gt;thunder orbs&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that do good thunder
damage and push 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a couple of encounter spells: &lt;strong&gt;Resounding Sphere&lt;/strong&gt; is an area
version of Thunder Orb that knocks prone instead of pushing, making it a good
fight opener; and &lt;strong&gt;Rumble Staff&lt;/strong&gt; is a “keep-away” melee power that does
thunder damage, pushes 1 square, and knocks prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their final encounter spell is the amusing &lt;strong&gt;Collision Bolt&lt;/strong&gt;, a ranged attack
that targets two enemies and slams them together. It works by dealing force
damage to both targets, and sliding the second one 3 squares towards the
first. If the slide ends with both targets adjacent to each other, they’re both
knocked prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-savage&quot;&gt;Warforged Savage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an unfortunate name and a somewhat unfortunate illustration, this is a
warforged who feels emotions more intensely than most of its kin, and channels
all of that extra intensity into anger. It was likely produced in a forge
belonging to the Lord of Blades, since the Cannith smiths tend to go for
cool-headed discipline instead. It’s a Level 7 Brute with 98 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This warforged has the &lt;strong&gt;Battlefield Tactics&lt;/strong&gt; trait that was common in the MM1
entries, gaining a +1 to melee attacks when an ally is adjacent to their
target. It also gains 4 temporary HP whenever it hits with an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warforged savage uses a &lt;strong&gt;scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; to fight. This is a High-Crit weapon,
and when it hits it deals a bit of automatic damage to another enemy adjacent to
its target. It can use the weapon to attack in a Close Burst 1 (recharge 5+),
and to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Wild Charge&lt;/strong&gt; that deals heavy damage, and gives it a +3 AC
bonus during the movement part of the charge. This recharges whenever the
warforged hits two or more enemies with the burst attack. All of these maneuvers
benefit from the scimitar’s High-Crit property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-anvilpriest&quot;&gt;Warforged Anvilpriest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the resounder, this spellcaster retains a bit of the power of its creation
forge and uses that as a source of magic. The main difference is that the
anvilpriest focuses on the searing heat of forge-fire. Despite the name, many
anvilpriests aren’t all that religious. Some are real clerics, though, and a
small number of them actually worship the creation forges themselves. I guess
the latter are mostly found amid the Lord of Blades’ forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anvilpriests are Level 8 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 89 HP. They
wield a &lt;strong&gt;fiery warhammer&lt;/strong&gt; that does bonus fire damage and inflicts a -2 AC
penalty for a turn. They can use that to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Heat of Battle&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver
(recharge 4+), which is like a basic attack but replaces the AC penalty with
ongoing fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this they have two encounter spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is &lt;strong&gt;Blunted Mind&lt;/strong&gt;, an area burst that targets Will and inflicts
psychic damage. It also inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks and a -4 penalty to
damage on a hit - the first save improves this to a -2 damage penalty, and only
the second removes it entirely. This only targets enemies, so it’s safe to cast
into a messy melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is &lt;strong&gt;Mending Flash Fire&lt;/strong&gt;, a close burst that deals fire damage to all
enemies inside (vs. Reflex) and gives both the caster and any allies in the
burst 5 temporary HP. If those allies are Warforged, they can also use their
Warforged Resolve power as an immediate reaction to this power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warforged-titan&quot;&gt;Warforged Titan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-warforged-titan.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titans were some of the earliest models of warforged developed by Cannith
engineers. They’re as big and as powerful as their name implies, but they’re
also only barely sapient. In a battle, they fulfill the same role as tanks or
siege engines, but they need to be accompanied by smarter infantry or at least
by a minder who can direct them. They’re loyal to whoever holds or displays a
symbol of the titan’s creator, regardless of whom it may be or how long it’s
been since their creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged Titans are Huge Natural Humanoids with the Living Construct
Keyword. They’re also Level 19 Elite Soldiers with 362 HP, which makes them
plausible counters to Slaughterstone Constructs and other near-epic giant
monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These towering creatures fight with their built-in weapons. Their basic attack
is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Axe&lt;/strong&gt; with the same “splash damage” effect as the Savage’
scimitar above, and that also marks on a hit. As a minor action they can also
use a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Hammer&lt;/strong&gt; that does more or less the same damage, slides the
target 2 squares, and knocks it prone. It does a bit of damage even on a miss,
likely from the shockwave. Both of these weapons enjoy the benefits of
&lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the titan’s &lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable Charger&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes it so a charge attack
&lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; end its turn. It can perform any actions it still has after charging,
such as using a Move to shift or reposition, or a Minor action to perform a
hammer follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged are people. You can find them fighting for any cause people tend to
fight for. Good, evil, or just plain selfish. They’re relatively recent
creations in Eberron, but other settings might have then as ancient
survivors/relics of a fallen empire. Titans work well as McGuffins in that role,
since they’ll obey anyone who displays the mark of their creator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: A resounder, an anvilpriest, and 3 savages. Lord of Blades patrol?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: A cambion hellfire magus, a steel predator, and a warforged
titan. Someone found themselves a few control amulets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/warforged.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/warforged.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Moster Manual 2: Vine, Predatory</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-vine-predatory.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the actual title of the entry, so we have another case of Old School
Titling here. Dangerous plants have been a part of the game since its
beginnings, and I bet a lot of the individual monsters collected in this entry
appeared before in some form or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, there isn’t much on these other than “they exist”. They don’t have
strange magical origins like some of the other plant creatures we saw before,
they’re just ambulatory carnivorous plants with enough strength and mobility to
hunt people. D&amp;amp;D worlds are already filled with impossibly lethal predators, so
it’s not such a stretch to say some of those are plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the monsters in this entry are Beasts, which in rules terms means they
behave like “animals” rather than like people. They also have the Plant keyword
(obviously). Their Int score is 2, so their behaviors are all
instinctive. Everything else varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ambush-vine&quot;&gt;Ambush Vine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apex predator of the plant kingdom, ambush vines can hunt anywhere: on the
surface, underground, and even in water. Wherever they are, they’re always
hunting, and using the tasty nutrients of their victims to fuel their explosive
growth rate. Ambush vines can form blights so vast they threaten civilization,
and its rumored that this contributed to the fall of the old eladrin empire of
Cendriane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As their name implies, ambush vines are a lot more cunning than your average
plant. They can burrow just under the surface or blend into the surrounding
normal vegetation to wait for victims, and then launch surprise attacks against
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambush Vines are Large Fey plants, and Level 16 Elite Controllers with 308
HP. They have tremorsense 20, and nothing in their stat block says they’re blind
so I guess they can see as well even without eyes. Their speed is 6 in almost
any mode of movement other than flight. They can move over the ground with
Forest Walk, climb, burrow and swim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vine’s most basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Poison Lash&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex,
deals physical damage, and inflicts ongoing poison damage. It can also attack
with &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Vines&lt;/strong&gt; in a Close Burst 4 pattern, which does more damage than
the basic attack. It’s also super-effective against immobilized targets, dealing
extra damage and healing the vine for 5 HP. As a minor action, the vine can use
a Reach 4 &lt;strong&gt;Foot Snare&lt;/strong&gt; to deal the same damage as the basic attack and knock a
target prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though ambush vines deal extra damage to immobilized foes, they can’t do the
immobilizing themselves, so they must be paired with other monsters capable of
it. Fortunately, they can make their own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the vine is first bloodied, it undergoes &lt;strong&gt;Rapid Growth&lt;/strong&gt; as an emergency
response, producing two Ambush Vine Shoot minions (see below). It can also make
a minion voluntarily using &lt;strong&gt;Sprout Vine&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action which costs 10 of its
own HP and produces a single minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ambush-vine-shoot&quot;&gt;Ambush Vine Shoot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the juvenile form of the ambush vine. It’s a Medium Fey plant, and a
Level 15 Minion Controller. Their senses are the same as those of an adult
specimen, though their only special movement mode is burrowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These minions have a single attack, &lt;strong&gt;Wrapping Vines&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals minion-tier
damage and restrains (save ends). “Restrained” is one step worse than
“immobilized”: it roots the victim in place and inflicts a -2 penalty to
attacks. A restrained target also counts as immobilized, so the shoot’s “parent”
vine can deal extra damage against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shoot also has a passive trait named &lt;strong&gt;Enwrap&lt;/strong&gt;, which affects adjacent
enemies and inflicts a -2 penalty to their saves against being immobilized or
restrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloodthorn-vine&quot;&gt;Bloodthorn Vine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a vine with pale leaves and one single large thorn. It feeds by impaling
victims on that thorn, which is hollow and capable of draining blood. As it does
so, the vine’s leaves take on a reddish coloration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bloodthorn vines are Medium Natural plants, and Level 2 Soldiers with 41 HP. By
the logic I’ve been using, them being low-level means they might occur near the
archetypical Starting Village. This means they’re one more threat common
civilians must be wary of in their daily lives, along with stirges, anhkegs, and
giant ants. Bloodthorns are much less lively than Ambush Vines, having only a
ground speed of 5 with Forest Walk and no special movement modes. They have
Blindsight 10 but again are not blind themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Striking Vine&lt;/strong&gt; with no riders on its physical
damage. The real danger here is the &lt;strong&gt;Impaling Thorn&lt;/strong&gt;, which does the same
damage and grabs the target. The vine can sustain the grab with a standard
action to deal heavy automatic damage to the victim and heal 5 HP. It can use
&lt;strong&gt;Pulling Vines&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to shift 1 square and pull a grabbed victim
along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the bloodthorn vine can only impale a single victim at a
time… but you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; have multiple bloodtorn vines on the same encounter group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;greenvise-vine&quot;&gt;Greenvise Vine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-vine-greenvise.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So named because “Piranha Plant” is already taken. This is a Large Natural
plant, and a Level 7 Soldier with 83 HP. Its speed is only 4, so it relies on
grabbing targets to prevent them from running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greenvise’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Striking Vine&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can also use an
&lt;strong&gt;Ensnaring Vine&lt;/strong&gt; vs. Reflex to do the same damage and grab the target. That’s
when the big chomper comes into play: &lt;strong&gt;Vise Bite&lt;/strong&gt; targets a grabbed victim’s
Fortitude, deals a bit of initial damage, restrains, and inflicts ongoing
physical damage. A save ends both the restrained condition and the ongoing
damage &lt;em&gt;but does not end the grab&lt;/em&gt;. You have to escape from that using the
default rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greenvise also has the same Pulling Vines trait as the Bloodthorn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually have an easier time distinguishing between killer plants when I see
them all together than when I see them in separate entries over multiple books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have three encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 2: 3 bloodthorn vines and 3 stirges. Probably competing to see who can
drain the party dry first.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 2 greenvise vines, 1 spectral panther, 3 quickling runners. The
quicklings and the panther can be used to herd the party towards the
slow-moving plants.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 17: 1 ambush vine, 1 lingerer fell incanter, 1 lingerer fell
knight. Sinister vestiges of lost Cendriane.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/vine-predatory.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/08/vine-predatory.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Trolls</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-troll.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a situation that has been common in this reading, we’re in a halfway place
when it comes to trolls. The Monster Manual marks their debut in this edition,
and the Monster Vault gives us a final selection of updated stat blocks. Here in
the Monster Manual 2, published between those two books, we have a selection of
trolls that expands the options from the MM, but is not yet updated for the MV’s
math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ice-troll&quot;&gt;Ice Troll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear from the text whether ice trolls are a variant troll species or
just a variant culture. They inhabit the Frostfell, one of the world’s coldest
regions, but occasionally make their way to slightly warmer climates. Ice trolls
have a more complex and technically advanced culture than that of “typical”
trolls. They know how to make weapons, and prefer to use them in combat instead
of their claws. They also emanate a cold aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to portray your trolls less universally hostile, ice troll
communities could make good trading partners in cold regions, trading their
weapons and crafts for other products they need. Ice troll mercenaries might
also be found among the forces of anyone who sets up shop in the frozen regions
of your campaign world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ice trolls are Large Natural Humanoids and Level 10 Soldiers with 109 HP. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Emanating Cold&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) slows any enemies caught inside for a turn. They
have a ground speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ice troll regeneration works exactly like that of standard trolls: Regeneration
10 plus Troll Healing that allows them to keep regaining HP after
hitting 0. Both are shut down for a turn if the troll takes acid or fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This troll wears scale armor and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;maul&lt;/strong&gt;. If their maul attack
bloodies an enemy, &lt;strong&gt;Frenzied Strike&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make another free
attack. This &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; lead to a big chain combo if the ice troll manages to hit
several near-bloodied PCs, but most likely you’ll be looking at one extra attack
when this triggers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weapon use would make ice trolls a lot more dangerous than standard ones in a
“realistic” system like GURPS, but here it’s mostly for color since damage is
entirely level-based. It does allow you to place magic weapons and armor as
treasure by saying the troll was using them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bladerager-troll&quot;&gt;Bladerager Troll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This troll was updated for the Monster Vault, so we already saw its numbers on
the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/09/troll.html&quot;&gt;MM/MV reading&lt;/a&gt;. A new bit of lore in this entry says that some of the
weapons and armor implanted on a bladerager are magic, which gives GMs an excuse
to place magic items as treasure in bladerager encounters. This makes them the
only monster in the game to have literal loot drops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troll-vinespeaker&quot;&gt;Troll Vinespeaker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s something you don’t see every day: a troll spellcaster with genius-level
intellect! You go, vinespeaker! Break those stereotypes! Unfortunately the
vinespeaker doesn’t break &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; troll stereotype, so it’s still Chaotic
Evil. You’ll have to break that one yourself if your campaign calls for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vinespeakers use a style of primal nature magic that involves wrapping
themselves in thorny vines and letting their blood soak the plants to gain
control over them. This would be lethal for any other practitioner, but for a
troll it’s no trouble at all. With their magic power and high intelligence,
vinespeakers tend to become leaders or revered advisors of larger troll
communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vinespeakers are Level 14 Controllers with 142 HP. They have Regeneration 10,
Troll Healing, and the usual vulnerabilities, as well as the usual Speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can use their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; to fight like a typical troll, but their vines give
them many more options. They have a ranged attack named &lt;strong&gt;Ray of Thorns&lt;/strong&gt; that
deals physical damage, and an area burst attack named &lt;strong&gt;Thorny Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that
deals light physical damage and immobilizes (save ends). This also creates a
zone of thorny difficult terrain that deals damage to those caught inside, and
lasts until the end of the encounter. If any of these attacks bloodies a target,
the vinespeaker gets to make a free claw attack. No target is specified, so any
PC within reach will do fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: Thorny Burst is at-will. Vinespeakers can turn the entire battlefield into
a spiky mess in no time at all. A good tactic for the is to spam this attack
until there’s no more ground to cover or until the PCs are all immobilized, then
target the most vulnerable foes with the single-target Ray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they have an encounter ability named &lt;strong&gt;Chant of Power&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives
allies in within 5 squares 10 temporary HP and a +4 damage bonus while the
temporary HP lasts. This works wonderfully as either a fight opener or a
mid-fight boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these MM2 trolls, they do a good job of subverting the troll stereotype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: 2 ice trolls, 2 worgs, and 1 manticore. Lots of raw melee power in
this one, with a maneuverable skirmisher thrown in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 12: 3 bladeragers, 1 duergar blasphemer, 1 duergar hellcaller. Duergar
diabolists are exactly the sort of person who’d make bladerager trolls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 15: 4 war trolls, 1 destrachan far voice, 1 vinespeaker. The war trolls
can more or less ignore the thorns. They’ll be slowed by the difficult
terrain, but so will everyone else. The destrachan offers some artillery
support and can stay far away from the thorn zones.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troll.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Troglodyte</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-troglodyte.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already saw troglodytes in our reading of the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html&quot;&gt;Monster Manual and Vault&lt;/a&gt;,
and their basic lore remains the same. We get a few additional entries with
their own lore here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like before, these troglodytes are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Reptile
keyword, and their signature ability is the &lt;strong&gt;Troglodyte Stench&lt;/strong&gt;, an aura that
inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks. They have Darkvision and a speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troglodyte-thrasher&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Thrasher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already discussed their lore in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html&quot;&gt;MM/MV post&lt;/a&gt;, so I’m not going to
repeat that discussion here. However we do get a bit of additional lore. It
seems thrashers are actually &lt;em&gt;nonsapient&lt;/em&gt;, and their fellow troglodytes keep
them in cages when not using them as attack beasts. I wouldn’t use this
“charming” bit of lore in my own campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troglodyte-deepscourge&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Deepscourge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deepscourges are spellcasters. Like some poisonscale lizardmen, they follow a
tradition based on internal alchemy. The specific variant practiced by
deepscourges centers around manipulating and empowering their natural malodorous
secretions to turn them into damaging and debilitating spells. Like Curse
Chanters from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/01/08/troglodyte.html&quot;&gt;MM/MV post&lt;/a&gt;, deepscourges act as priests and leaders of
troglodyte tribes, or as advisors to those leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deepscourges are Level 9 Artillery with the Leader keyword and 78 HP. Their
slime is turbocharged: it projects the same Troglodyte Stench aura as the
others, but it also projects an aura of &lt;strong&gt;Dizzying Stench&lt;/strong&gt; out to 10 squares!
Despite the name this is actually a “buffing” effect, increasing the radius of
the stench of any troglodytes inside by 1 square. I wonder if the auras of
multiple deepscourges stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main ranged attacks are an at-will &lt;strong&gt;Debilitating Ray&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
physical damage and weakens the target for a turn if it’s inside a stench
aura. The stat block doesn’t list an attack roll, but I guess this is an
editorial error and it should target AC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also attack with an area-effect &lt;strong&gt;Rancid Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which
only affects “non-reptiles”, targets Fortitude, does more damage than the ray
attack, and weakens for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hit by an attack the deepscourge can project a &lt;strong&gt;Blinding Stench&lt;/strong&gt; in a
burst around itself, targeting Fortitude and blinding (save ends) with no
damage. If that doesn’t give it space to move away, it will be forced to use its
weak &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troglodyte-temple-champion&quot;&gt;Troglodyte Temple Champion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, these are troglodyte holy warriors, usually tasked with
guarding their temples. These temples usually honor Torog, but some are
dedicated to even worse entities like Demogorgon or other demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blessings they receive tend to be subtle, of the type that makes them
smarter and more disciplined. They use a highly technical fighting style and
carry much better equipment than the rank and file. Though champions can be most
often found guarding a temple, they’re also sometimes sent on divine missions at
the head of troglodyte expeditionary forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Troglodyte Temple Champion is a Level 9 Soldier with 101 HP. It wears scale,
wields a flail, and also carries 2 javelins into battle. The &lt;strong&gt;flail&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;javelins&lt;/strong&gt; make up their basic attacks, and they also have a couple of special
techniques. &lt;strong&gt;Sweeping Trip&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will maneuver that does a bit less damage
than an attack and knocks prone. &lt;strong&gt;Whirlwind Attack&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that
does basic attack damage in a Close Burst 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No marking mechanic here - the champion’s stickiness comes from their liberal
use of Sweeping Trips to keep opponents prone at their feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find the Deepscourge notable for being the first troglodytew stat block that
can’t be easily re-skinned into another humanoid opponent. Its abilities are all
about the stench, both its own and that of its allies. It’s a uniquely
troglodytic monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, my opinion on troglodytes hasn’t changed much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s four sample encounters between levels 7 and 12, and they’re all assorted
bands of troglodytes. Sometimes they’re accompanied by drakes, and one of them
has a balhannoth that likely appears as an opportunistic predator during the
fight.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troglodyte.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/troglodyte.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Tiger</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-tiger.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tigers are real animals and have been part of the game since its
beginnings. They’re some of the only animals whose “mundane” version was
considered worthy of a monster stat block at this point in the edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book describes tigers as powerful and cunning predators that can be found in
“rugged natural environments”. Let’s elaborate on that a bit, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Wikipedia “rugged natural environments” means mostly flat or hilly
forests, but those can range from cold Siberian taigas to temperate forests to
tropical jungles. A tiger requires a large amount of territory, which allows it
to range far and hunt its prey (usually large herbivores). Tigers are “solitary
but social”: they hunt alone but might nest together, with their range areas
overlapping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 does add a bit of interesting fantastic lore by saying
tigers are sometimes domesticated by &lt;em&gt;ogres&lt;/em&gt; of all people to serve as guard and
hunting animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wild D&amp;amp;D tiger is not shy about including adventurers in its menu. If they run
across a battle while hunting, they might stalk its edges and pounce on any
combatant that gets separated from the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire tigers are as usual larger, stronger and spikier. They’re bolder and less
opportunistic, directly stalking prey that seems to be alone and weaker than
them. Their behavior is a lot closer to that of the tiger in &lt;em&gt;The Jungle Book&lt;/em&gt;
than that of a real-world animal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both mundane and dire tigers are Large Natural Beasts with low-light vision, a
ground speed of 8, and a climb speed of 4. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Feral
Surge&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that allows them to take a move action as a minor
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tiger&quot;&gt;Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mundane” tigers are Level 6 Skirmishers with 73 HP. Their basic attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does immediate and ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a fight, the tiger always wants to be moving and charging, as being on
the move makes it much more dangerous. If forced to choose between a static
fight and running away, it will likely take the second option every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traits that make it want to move are &lt;strong&gt;Blur of Fur&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives it +4 AC
against opportunity attacks in any turn where it moves 2 or more squares; and
&lt;strong&gt;Charging Pounce&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives it bonus damage on charge attacks and makes it
so charging &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; end its turn. So it could use its standard action to
charge, and then either a move action or Feral Surge to move away immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dire-tiger&quot;&gt;Dire Tiger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire Tigers are Level 8 Soldiers with 89 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; are stronger, and
they’re much more likely to accept the challenge of a stand-up fight. Even then
they’ll try to single out the weakest available target and kill it first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hunter’s Instinct&lt;/strong&gt; is an ability that helps then with that. It works exactly
like the Hunter’s Quarry ability of a PC ranger. The tiger spends a minor action
to make the nearest enemy its quarry, which lasts until the end of the encounter
or until it uses this ability again. The quarry takes extra damage from all of
the tiger’s attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dire tiger can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction whenever its
quarry is within 5 squares. It allows the creature to shift to a space adjacent
to the quarry and bite it. Since this is a leap, the tiger can cross enemy
spaces during the shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marking the right quarry requires some clever positioning, but once that happens
it will be hard for the other players to protect the victim from the tiger’s
leaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tigers have some cool mechanics to them, which is better than the generic
bags of HP I remember them being in previous editions. They also feel pretty
different from each other! I still would hesitate a bit before placing wild
tigers as opposition to my PCs, what with them being endangered in reality and
all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two sample encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: A couple of ogre savages taking their two pet tigers and their pet
macetail behemoth out for a stroll. Shrek and Fiona?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A weretiger running with a pack/harem of three dire tigers. The fact that you
have tigers running in packs should be a hint that there’s something unnatural
going on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/tiger.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/18/tiger.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Steel Predator</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-steel-predator.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I first saw this monster in one of the “late” Monster Manuals for 3.x,
which makes it fairly recent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed by Bane himself (“Original Design: Do Not Steal”), these living
constructs are designed as long-ranging assassination engines. They seem to be
his take on the “Retriever” concept pioneered by the primordials, with the main
difference being that the god of war is not interested in taking prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steel Predators are a little weaker individually, but unlike the retrievers
they’re still in production. They can travel the planes in search of their
target, though their means of travel is not quick enough to be a combat
ability. These things just love eating magic items: the more loaded the victim,
the more vigorous the pursuit. Once a steel predator kills its target it will
usually devour them, items and all. They also have a bit of golem-like magical
resistance that means they get stronger when they take thunder or lightning
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side effect of this refined palate, steel predator bodies are rich in
residuum, which can ironically make them a target for powerful, brave or
foolhardy hunters looking for a big score. When not on a mission, most steel
predators hang out in Bane’s native plane of Chernoggar, patrolling it alongside
platoons of bladelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steel Predators are Large Immortal Animates with the Living Construct
keyword. They’re Level 20 Elite Soldiers with 388 HP, darkvision, and a ground
speed of 8. As mentioned above, they can cross planar boundaries but this
ability doesn’t make it into their combat stat block. They have a +2 bonus to
saves against ongoing damage (for a total of +4 when combined with their elite
save bonus).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures have the body structure of a big cat, and they fight
accordingly, pouncing and biting with their metal jaws. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;
attack marks for a turn on a hit. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Vicious Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; that
works as a charge against Fortitude, does the same damage as a bite, and knocks
prone. Their multiattack ability is a bit weaker than a standard double attack,
but it’s still flavorful: &lt;strong&gt;Snap Jaw&lt;/strong&gt; allows the steel predator to make a bite
attack. If that hits it also knocks the target prone, and the creature can make
another bite attack against a different target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their most overtly supernatural attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Resonating Roar&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Burst 3
attack that deals heavy thunder damage, dazes, and deafens (save ends
both). This is a “recharge 5+” attack, but it also recharges automatically when
the predator takes thunder or lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when an adjacent creature shifts, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Shifting Steel&lt;/strong&gt; as a
reaction to shift into the vacated square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactics are fairly simple: pounce, roar, then keep biting with Snap Jaw until
the roar recharges. This should keep the PCs quite busy while the other monsters
attack them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things look enough like xenomorphs from &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; that I’m surprised they
don’t have acid blood. Maybe that would be too on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, Bane often sends steel predators on remote missions. They
end up working alongisde other servants of the god, or with other creatures that
share the same immediate goals. In that latter case, they’re known for turning
on their allies of convenience if those allies behave in a way that displeases
Bane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example encounter is Level 21, and has 2 steel predators accompanying 2
marut castigators. The maruts are likely mercenaries hired by an agent of Bane.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/09/steel-predator.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/02/09/steel-predator.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
