<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 15:04:38 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 15:04:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Hellwasp</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-hellwasp.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember seeing hell wasps before, but they sound like the sort of
monster that might have debuted in 3e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In past editions the Blood War was this eternal alignment-based conflict, but
here it’s part of Asmodeus’ safety net. You see, the other gods don’t
like Asmodeus very much, both because he’s an evil asshole and because he got
his position by murdering a popular non-evil deity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the measures he took to prevent them from ganging up on him was to commit
the considerable armies of Hell to the task of containing the demons of the
Abyss. As we mentioned before, demons are too busy with infighting to launch
regular invasions on the rest of the universe, but when they do manage to
briefly get their shit together and spill out, they find a few legions of devils
waiting to fight them. Hell also launches occasional raids into the Abyss to
prevent demons from organizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a war that rages on eternally, but a series of sporadic conflicts
that flare up whenever one of the two sides feels a bit stronger. The gods lets
Asmodeus be because he provides a valuable service, and because providing that
service also serves as a check on his power. Asmodeus and his underlings in the
meantime keep enacting diabolic schemes to acquire more power in an attempt to
dominate the other gods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most enthusiastic participants in the Blood Wars seems to be Glasya,
Asmodeus’ daughter. Because of this she tends to be involved in stories where
demons and devils switch sides, corresponding to her failures and successes. We
already heard about Graz’zt the devil who became a demon lord. And now we get to
hear about a whole species of demon who became devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellwasps were once a species of demon related to the insectile mezzodemons,
servants of a wasp-like demon lord whose name was lost to time. Glasya fought
and killed this demon in one of her raids, and its spawn immediately swore
allegiance to her. She took the lot of them to Hell and converted them into
devils. Now they inhabit the Garden of Delights, a region of Malbolge. As loyal
servants of Glasya, they can be found alongside any of her other servants or
allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellwasps are Medium Immortal Magical Beasts (devils). They have Darkvision and
a Flight Speed of 8 (hover), but their ground speed of 0 means they can’t
actually &lt;em&gt;walk&lt;/em&gt;. They fight with their natural weapons: a pair of sword-like
talons, and a huge venomous sting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hellwasp-colony-guard&quot;&gt;Hellwasp Colony Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 19 Minion Skirmisher of the kind you can find by the score in
hellwasp hives. Their &lt;strong&gt;Sword Talon&lt;/strong&gt; attack allows them to shift 1 square
before or after the attack, and their &lt;strong&gt;Sting&lt;/strong&gt; deals poison damage, slows, and
prevents the target from shifting for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re good for slowing the PCs down and setting them up to be surrounded by
sturdier allies. The ability to shift away after a talon attack makes them
slightly less vulnerable to melee-centric PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hellwasp-devil&quot;&gt;Hellwasp Devil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regular version is a Level 23 Skirmisher with 212 HP. Since it’s higher
level it probably represents an exceptional individual within a hive, of the
kind that gets loaned out to allies and sent on away missions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from a somewhat weak &lt;strong&gt;Sword Talon&lt;/strong&gt; attack, the hellwasp can also perform
a &lt;strong&gt;Talon Skewer&lt;/strong&gt;. This also counts as a basic attack. It allows the wasp to
fly its speed and make two talon attacks at any point along the movement. The
wasp doesn’t draw opportunity attacks when moving away from the target of these
attacks. If both attacks hit the same target, the wasp grabs them, and the
&lt;strong&gt;Drag Off&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows it to pull the grabbed victim when it moves without
drawing opportunity attacks from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is another one of those fliers that allows you to have fun with
cliffs. And at epic level we’re probably taking the cliffs of Hell itself, which
have lava pools or other layer-appropriate hazards at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hellwasp regulars also have a stronger &lt;strong&gt;Sting&lt;/strong&gt;. It deals more poison damage,
slows, prohibits shifts and deals ongoing 15 fire damage (save ends all). This
is a “recharge 5+” attack, and a good one to use on a PC that was dragged off to
an isolated position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs with sword-arms that slot neatly into the same slot as Swordwings. Perfect
for those players who dislike monsters that lack ties to AD&amp;amp;D lore. You can
reskin these into swordwings, or take inspiration in swordwing abilities when
building more hellwasp varieties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they’re interesting without overstaying their welcome. It’s always
fun to see a monster who can carry PCs off and drop them into lava pits.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/28/devil-hell-wasp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/28/devil-hell-wasp.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Hell Knight</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-hell-knight.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/09/20/death-knight.html&quot;&gt;Death Knights&lt;/a&gt; have a long and storied existence in D&amp;amp;D, but this is the
first time I hear of Hell Knights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell Knights are absolutely not Nazgul, no way, no how. They’re &lt;em&gt;narzugons&lt;/em&gt;,
which is a completely different thing. Jokes aside, their origins are quite
tragic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first hell knights used to be servants of He Who Was, the god Asmodeus
rebelled against. Asmodeus tricked them into betraying their former master, and
their betrayal damned them to serve Asmodeus forever. From that point forward,
whenever someone got tricked into betraying their deity, they would become new
hell knights upon death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is the first time I see an explicit mention of people going to Hell
and becoming devils in 4e. This used to be a 3e thing, so I guess Hell Knights
come from that edition. It could also be that angels and other immortals become
hell knights when they get tricked into betraying their deities, if you want to
play it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though hell knights are powerful, becoming one is definitely a form of
punishment. A Hell Knight’s existence is an eternity of hatred. They hate
themselves for their betrayal, they hate their new masters, they hate their
immortality, and they hate free mortals. Though many of them serve Asmodeus
directly, every potentate of Hell has at least a few knights at their
disposal. The most famous group of them is the Order of the Nightmare, so named
for their preferred mounts. Other groups have other mounts, like the
mammoth-riding knights of Cania, or the ash riders of Avernus with their
wyverns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell Knights usually only associate with members of their own order, but will
work together with other devils when commanded to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell Knights are Medium Immortal Humanoids (devils), and Level 15 Soldiers with
146 HP. They have Darkvision, are immune to fear, and have Resist 20 Fire. Their
ground speed is 6, but they will almost always be mounted on something
faster. Their gear is the full “Classic Knight” setup of plate armor, heavy
shield, a lance, and a mace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Hell’s Rider&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows their mount to use the knight’s Athletics,
Acrobatics and Stealth scores if they would be better than the mount’s own. The
&lt;strong&gt;mace&lt;/strong&gt; does bonus fire damage and knocks prone on a hit, and the &lt;strong&gt;lance&lt;/strong&gt; has
better base tamage and crits on a 19-20 when used on a charge. Both count as
basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action they can use &lt;strong&gt;Eyes of the Narzugon&lt;/strong&gt;, which causes a creature
within 10 squares to be marked and slowed for a turn. This is an effect, so it
auto-hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell Knights pair really well with Nightmares! As I mentioned in the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/08/09/nightmare.html&quot;&gt;Nightmare&lt;/a&gt; article, enemy riders can still take actions independently of
their mounts, so the knights can charge with their lances and maces at the same
time their nightmare mounts set the map on fire. Since they have native fire
resistance, they can ignore the burning terrain even when unhorsed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple but effective hell knight encounter would consist of three knights and
three nightmares, using classic medieval cavalry tactics (charge early, charge
often). This group’s lack of ranged attacks would be compensated by the
nightmare’s high teleport speed.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/23/devil-hell-knight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/23/devil-hell-knight.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Devil, Corruption</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember when I told you the MM3 had the very good idea of giving each devil and
demon its own entry rather than lumping them all together? Here’s where they
kinda toss that out the window and make a big entry full of diverse stat blocks
for a single type of devil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corruption Devils, or Paeliryons, first appeared in one of the later Monster
Manuals for 3rd Edition. I remember they were not very well-received because
their lore and appearance had some quite unfortunate implications. This book is
still making an effort to make them a big part of the game, so let’s see if the
lore improved in any way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book describes these devils as “bloated infernal masterminds of graft,
sleaze, and vice”. They’re better at politics and intrigue than almost anyone
else in Hell, and they put that skill to use in subverting mortal societies to
their benefit, turning them into decadent kleptocracies via a network of agents
and dupes. Most paeliryons work for Dispater, lord of the second layer of Hell,
acting as the civil administration of that wretched city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A corruption devil’s agent network is somewhat inverted from what you’d
expect. Its most powerful members are kept at a safe remove from the devil,
while those that work directly with it are ignorant sycophants and expendable
muscle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see that they kept the Paeliryion illustration from the previous edition, but
if I’m remembering it correctly the lore was changed to something a little less
problematic. With an extra decade of hindsight, I’d probably replace the Ursula
cosplay with a big suit and an orange wig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;corruption-devil&quot;&gt;Corruption Devil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-corruption.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model, depicted in the illustration. These are most likely to be found
running the city of Dis, but can also go out into the other planes to perform
specific missions. Though physically imposing, the creatures prefer to avoid
direct conflicts, and will try to negotiate their way out of trouble. If forced
into combat they fight like PC bards, staying away from the melee and hurling
magically-charged insults and mind control spells at their enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They pal around with other manipulative devils such as succubi, vizier devils,
and cambions, though these are almost always pawns rather than full allies. If
things see to be going bad for it, the paeliryion will definitely fly away and
abandon its “friends”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corruption Devils are Large Immortal Humanoids (Devils), and Level 22
Controllers (Leaders) with 208 HP. They have Darkvision and a +5 to save against
fear and charm effects. Their ground speed is only 4, but they’re excellent
fliers with speed 6 (hover).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These devils project a &lt;strong&gt;Corruptive Presence&lt;/strong&gt; that works as an aura (5) and
inflicts a -2 penalty to saves on all enemies inside its radius. It fights in
melee with &lt;strong&gt;Corrupting Claws&lt;/strong&gt; and at range with &lt;strong&gt;Words of Corruption&lt;/strong&gt;, both
of which deal no immediate damage and instead inflict ongoing psychic damage
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their mind control magic takes the form of two minor-action spells. &lt;strong&gt;Sway the
Corrupt&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will) targets an enemy that’s taking ongoing psychic damage. It
hits automatically, and dominates them for a turn. &lt;strong&gt;Doom the Corrupt&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) targets an ally or a dominated creature, forcing them to make a
melee basic attack against an enemy of the devil’s choice. If that attack hits,
its target is also immobilized (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Desperate Measures&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to allow an ally to
make a basic attack that crits on 19-20, in exchange for the ally granting
combat advantage for a turn. This recharges when the devil is first bloodied,
and if used while it’s bloodied it applies to every ally within 5 squares
instead of just one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sire-of-corruption&quot;&gt;Sire of Corruption&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the most powerful corruption devils, and among some of the most
powerful devils in Hell. They’re the ones who run long term projects of the
“turn a whole kingdom to evil” variety, and have a particular strong hatred of
“incorruptible” people or institutions, working extra-hard to prove that
assertion wrong or destroy these offenders if they can’t. Sires of Corruption
can make a particular kind of infernal contract that can make the signing mortal
gain power from utterly embracing their vices, thought they still remain pawns
of the devil in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are Medium Immortal Humanoids (devils), and Level 29 Elite
Controllers (leaders) with 530 HP. They have 15 fire resistance and a ground
speed of 6, but no special senses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Lasting Corruption&lt;/strong&gt; aura is actually a bit worse than that of a basic
corruption devil, since the save penalty only applies to charm effects. All of
their non-basic attacks are charm effects, so it doesn’t make a difference to
the sire itself, but it’s less helpful to its allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Corrupting Touch&lt;/strong&gt; that does a sizable amount of
psychic damage and inflicts a -2 penalty to defenses against charm effects for a
turn, so you want to alternate it with the other attack: &lt;strong&gt;Touch of Vice&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 4+), which deals the same amount of psychic damage and inflicts one of
&lt;em&gt;six&lt;/em&gt; possible effects named after different vices or sins. They’re all (save
ends), and have the following effects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lust&lt;/strong&gt; causes the target to be marked by another enemy within 5 squares.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Excess&lt;/strong&gt; dazes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greed&lt;/strong&gt; slides the target 5 squares to a space adjacent to one of its
allies, and forces it to make opportunity attacks against allies whose actions
would provoke them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear&lt;/strong&gt; pushes the target 5 squares and forbids it from moving closer to the
sire of corruption.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sloth&lt;/strong&gt; immobilizes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vengeance&lt;/strong&gt; auto-damages the target whenever they use an attack power.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sire chooses which effect happens whenever it hits with Touch of Vice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s not all! At the start of the fight it can issue a &lt;strong&gt;Call to
Corruption&lt;/strong&gt; to summon six Corrupted Followers into the fight, and it can do
that again after it’s bloodied! As a minor action it can use &lt;strong&gt;Spread
Depravity&lt;/strong&gt; to give one of these servants a free attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, when the sire is reduced to 0 HP, it uses a final attack named
&lt;strong&gt;Lasting Vice&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets everyone in a Close Burst 5 with a Touch of
Vice (same damage, same choice of effects).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things are nasty, and unlike basic corruption devils they want to get
right into the fray while surrounded by their corrupted servants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;corrupted-followers&quot;&gt;Corrupted Followers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-corruption-glutton.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-corruption-lunatic.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-devil-corruption-monger.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are mortals who were prey to some vice in life, and who were offered a
very specific kind of infernal contract in their moment of greatest despair or
misery. The contract gives them what they desire, and immediately afterwards
turns them into monsters made of the same vice that controlled their mortal
lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Followers retain no memory of those lives. Left to their own devices, they
contrive to spread their ruling vice among the surrounding population. Most
often, though, they’re found in the service of their devil master. Usually this
is a Sire of Corruption, but it can also be some other powerful devil, or some
mortal villain to whom the fiend has loaned them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corrupted Followers are epic-tier minions, and there’s a different variety for
every vice a Sire of Corruption can generate. It’s entirely appropriate for the
Sire’s Call to Corruption power to summon a full sentai team with the six
varieties, but you can vary its composition to have simpler combats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each Follower type has a touch attack that targets Will and does a bit of damage
with a rider, an effect that happens when it dies, and sometimes an aura or
passive trait. All of those will be related to each Follower’s Thematic
Vice. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lust&lt;/strong&gt;: Corrupted Lechers are Level 24 Minion Lurkers. They can’t be
targeted unless they’re the closest enemy to the attacker; their attacks can
be melee or ranged, and make the target be marked by another enemy for a turn;
when they die, they make their killer move its speed towards another enemy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Excess&lt;/strong&gt;: Corrupted Gluttons are Level 25 Minion Soldiers that attack with
bites that also grab the target. Once they have a target grabbed they can chew
on them for automatic damage. When they die, they curse their killer to take
damage next turn unless the PC recovers HP in the intervening time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greed&lt;/strong&gt;: Corrupted Mongers are Level 26 Minion Artillery. Their melee
attacks slide the target adjacent to one of their allies; their ranged attack
drain daily or encounter powers from magic items until the end of the
encounter! When they die, they cause any daily or encounter powers from the
item that killed them to become spent.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sloth&lt;/strong&gt;: Corrupted Idlers are Level 27 Minion Soldiers. They have a small
slowing aura, and their attacks prevent the target from taking move actions
for a turn. When they die, they make an attack against the killer’s Will that
will knock the PC unconscious for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vengeance&lt;/strong&gt;: Corrupted Lunatics are Level 28 Minion Brutes. Their attacks
are weak even for a minion, but force the target to make a basic attack
against its nearest ally. If someone misses then with an attack, they can make
a free attack against that PC, with the same rider as above. When they die,
their killer must again make an attack against an ally. They’re walking Three
Stooges skits.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear&lt;/strong&gt;: Corrupted Cravens are Level 29 Minion Controllers. When they hit
with an attack, they force the target to move its speed away from them. The
same happens to their killer when they die.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess I’m still not entirely sold on the whole “Corruption Devil” lore. It
feels kinda redundant because this sort of thing was already supposed to be one
of the central themes for Hell as a whole. And the stat blocks use the word
“Corruption” so much it kinda starts to lose its meaning. The Sire of Corruption
seems like it was an entirely different monster that got retrofitted into this
entry. It’s obviously inspired by the Seven Deadly Sins, which I feel is kinda
played out. But at least it’s all seven in one monster, and it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in-theme for
Hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanics-wise, the Corruption Devil stat block might work quite well for any
bard-type enemies, with a few minor adjustments. The Sire of Corruption is a
scary combatant, but its mechanics are extremely tied to the concept of sin so
it might be harder to reskin. It would make an excellent basis for an Aspect of
Asmodeus, though!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The minions are flavorful, but fiddly. I wouldn’t recommend using the full
spread in the same encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/22/devil-corruption.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/22/devil-corruption.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Derro</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-derro.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derro have been in the game since AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, where they appeared in the
Monster Manual II. They’re based on the writings of an American author named
Richard Sharpe Shaver, who wrote a lot about a civilization of psychic and
torture-obsessed underground humanoids he named the dero (from “Detrimental
Robots”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D Derro have a different origin from Shaver’s dero, though the flavor is quite
similar in 4e. When the world was still young, it gave rise to an advanced and
power-hungry civilization. Its people, the derro, craved power like that of the
primordials, but they wanted to bow to no master. So derro scholars came up with
an alternate solution: open a portal to this unoccupied magic-rich dimension
they found. There would be no one to contest their claim! Free unlimited power!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They succeeded in opening their portals, but found out this new dimension was
far from unoccupied. It was the place known today as the Far Realm. After the
derro beheld what came through to greet them, they suddenly realized they had
finally found a master worth worshiping. In other words, their sanity was
blasted to dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derro civilization became so horrifying in its depravity that the World Serpent,
one of the most powerful primal spirits, coiled around it and dragged the entire
thing underground. This stopped their grand machinations but did not destroy
them. Many centuries later, a drow expedition found the ruins of the derro
empire, and what the derro became in the dark. Only one of their number made it
home… mostly. Her report convinced the drow these maniacs must be
eradicated, but this is harder than it looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our narrative present, derro live in small groups that crawl around the ruins
of their old cities, and worship the energies and beings of the Far
Realm. They’re enthusiastic slavers, going on frequent raids to the surface or
to other Underdark communities to find new captives. They treat these slaves
badly, torturing them for fun and killing them for the smallest of offenses. The
slaves, in turn, will turn on their captors as soon as the smallest chance to
escape presents itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derro are only capable of making true alliances with beings from the Far Realm,
suck as grells, mind flayers, and aboleths (whom they sometimes
worship). They despise everyone else, and everyone else hates them right
back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derro are statted up as mid-Paragon threats, suitable for inclusion in encounter
groups that feature their preferred allies listed above. The entry also gives
enough Derro stat blocks to make decent all-Derro encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derro are Small Aberrant Humanoids. They have Darkvision, and their signature
ability is named &lt;strong&gt;Strength of Madness&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s an encounter power that lets them
roll a d6 and add the result to all of their attack rolls until the end of their
next turn, but also makes them grant combat advantage during this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derro-warrior&quot;&gt;Derro Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combatants like these typically make up the patrols that keep derro territory
“secure” by engaging in preemptive attacks against its neighbors. Gotta keep
them guessing, y’know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warriors are Level 13 Artillery with 101 HP and all standard Derro traits. Their
speed is 5, and they have a +2 to saves against fear effects. They carry daggers
and a repeating hand crossbows with several magazines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; is their default melee attack, and they can fire the &lt;strong&gt;Repeating
Hand Crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action, or use a standard action to let loose a
&lt;strong&gt;Bolt Spray&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that hits a Close Blast 5 for heavy damage and
pushes 1 square on a hit. Any of these will deal extra damage against targets
granting combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bolt Spray is not selective, and most derro warriors don’t particularly care if
their allies are caught in its area of effect. They’ll use it whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derro-thug&quot;&gt;Derro Thug&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be a less capable warrior, or just your average civilian
psychopath. Derro thugs are Level 14 Minion Brutes and they fight with
clubs. Their only special ability is &lt;strong&gt;Mad Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt;: when the thug misses an
attack, it can sacrifice itself to turn the miss into a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using them in combat is simple: get a whole bunch of them to charge the PCs and
hit whoever’s closest, using Mad Sacrifice liberally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derro-fanatic&quot;&gt;Derro Fanatic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warriors that display notable skill and potential are invited by Derro savants
to peer directly into the Far Realm. Those who remain functional after the
experience use this stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fanatics are Level 14 Skirmishers with 140 HP. They carry battleaxes into
combat. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;axe&lt;/strong&gt; attack has an attached effect that allows them to
end any mark on themselves and shift 2 squares before making the attack roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they bloody an enemy, their &lt;strong&gt;Insane Bloodlust&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to immediately
make another attack against that same enemy. And while a fanatic is themselves
bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Unleashed Madness&lt;/strong&gt; gives them a -2 attack penalty and 2d6 bonus
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That effect on their basic attack allows them to slip right past the party’s
front line and go for the squishies, and by the time they get there they might
even have turned into mini-brutes. Fanatics always fight to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derro-harvester&quot;&gt;Derro Harvester&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This derro is specialized in capturing slaves, a very important function in
derro society. They always need more people to do the labor derro consider
beneath themselves, and to act as experimental subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harvesters are Level 15 Lurkers with 116 HP. They wield war picks and carry a
set of shackles. Their attacks do bonus damage if the target is granting them
combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a strike with the &lt;strong&gt;pick&lt;/strong&gt; and has no special effects, but
they have a frightening power named &lt;strong&gt;Harvest&lt;/strong&gt;. To use it, the derro must have
started its turn hidden from the target. It’s an attack against Fortitude, which
does no damage but &lt;em&gt;knocks the target unconscious&lt;/em&gt; (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The harvester can them use its &lt;strong&gt;shackles&lt;/strong&gt; to bind the helpless victim, which
from that point on is restrained and falls prone whenever it’s hit with a melee
attack. The victim can try to escape by succeeding in an escape action against
the harvester (Athletics vs. Fort 27, or Acrobatics vs. Ref 28).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Harvest fails or a victim gets loose, the derro can use &lt;strong&gt;Flee to the
Shadows&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it to move its full speed and make a Stealth test to
hide if it has concealment at the end of the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shackles can only be used once per encounter, but Harvest is at-will. So a
harvester could knock someone out, shackle them, and have its buddies drag the
victim to their base, keeping them unconscious with multiple applications of
Harvest. I guess that once they’re no longer using combat turns, the victim just
stays down until they wake up in a cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derro-ironguard&quot;&gt;Derro Ironguard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironguards are more disciplined than your typical derro warrior, which
admittedly is not a high bar to clear. They are proficient in the use of hooked
spears, and are often employed to catch runaway slaves or guard them so they
don’t run away in the first place. Paranoid derro bigwigs (i.e, all of them)
also hire ironguards to watch their stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironguards are Level 15 Soldiers with 150 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;hooked spears&lt;/strong&gt; deal extra
damage against prone targets, so they love stabbing people when they’re
down. The weapons are also used in &lt;strong&gt;hooking jabs&lt;/strong&gt; attacks, which deal damage
and grab on a hit, and on non-damaging &lt;strong&gt;unbalancing thrusts&lt;/strong&gt; (minor actions)
which target a grabbed creature and knock them prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their tactics are obvious from the ability descriptions: Hooking Jab;
Unbalancing Thrust; stabstabstabstab. Send your beefy defenders to fight them,
because Unbalancing Thrust targets Fortitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derro-savant&quot;&gt;Derro Savant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our spellcasters, or more precisely psions. They preserve the old lore that gave
the original derro access to the Far Realm, and spend their time deep inside the
ruins of their empire trying to find ways to reopen the old portals. They wield
scourges in combat, and use orbs as their implements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savants are Level 16 Controllers with 154 HP. They have a ground speed of 5 and
a teleport speed of 3. Their &lt;strong&gt;scourges&lt;/strong&gt; damage and inflict a -2 attack penalty
for a turn. Their basic ranged attack is &lt;strong&gt;Mind Scourge&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals psychic
damage and forces the target to choose between taking 10 ongoing psychic damage
or being dazed. The chosen condition is (save ends) either way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The savant can also open a mini-portal to the Far Realm with the &lt;strong&gt;Window to
Madness&lt;/strong&gt; power. This creates a small zone (area burst 1) centered on an ally
within 10 squares. The zone lasts until the end of the encounter, and any
non-derro that enter the zone or ends their turn there take 10 psychic
damage. The savant can end the zone early with a minor action, in which case the
power recharges. It can also slide every creature inside the zone 2 squares as a
minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;warped-slave&quot;&gt;Warped Slave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a derro, but a slave that was subject to their experiments and
warped into a tentacled abomination. The stats could also be used for a generic
Thing From Beyond summoned from a derro portal or other Far Realm opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These unfortunates are Large Aberrant Humanoids and Level 16 Brutes with 193
HP. They have Speed 6 but can’t shift, and they have Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warped slave’s &lt;strong&gt;Disintegrating Mind&lt;/strong&gt; works as an aura (1), which deals
psychic damage to enemies caught inside. If a derro inside the aura uses its
Strength of Madness ability, the slave gets to make a free tentacle attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thing can &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; or use &lt;strong&gt;Tentacles&lt;/strong&gt; to fight. The tentacles grab and
pull the target 1 square in addition to dealing damage. When bloodied, it gets
desperate and gains a &lt;strong&gt;Flailing Tentacles&lt;/strong&gt; attack that affects all enemies in
a Close Burst 2, damaging and pulling them 1 square on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warped Slaves follow the orders of their derro masters, or rampage about the
battlefield trying to attack the nearest enemies. It often amounts to the same
thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole “Shaver Mysteries” horrific underground humanoid vibe is quite
evocative, and judged on that merit alone I’d rate the derro very highly as RPG
monsters. However, in the context of D&amp;amp;D they end up being just one more species
of evil Underdark dwellers who like slavery and torture, this time in size
Small. If I include derro in a game, I’m probably removing at least one of the
others, and maybe more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically they’re okay, and you have enough here to make a whole derro-themed
dungeon. For spice, you could add aboleth leaders and mind flayer allies.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/19/derro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/19/derro.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Demon, Ultrodemon</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-demon-ultrodemon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creature first appeared as an “Ultrodaemon” in AD&amp;amp;D, as part of the effort
to give every alignment its own brand of outsider. In 4e, daemons lost an “a”
and became demons. We already saw some of them in the readings of earlier books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultrodemons are somewhat atypical among demons because they’re more about greed
than about cruelty for cruelty’s sake. They enjoy carnage and torture as much as
the next demon, but their real passion is material wealth. They command armies
of mezzodemons and nycademons, sell their mercenary services for ruinous prices,
and loot as much as they can during these operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultrodemons and their underlings can be found in a wide variety of places,
either under contract to some other villain, or working independently. They’re
very rarely loyal to their employers, though, and will turn on them as soon it
looks more profitable than fulfilling the contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry only has a single stat block, for an &lt;strong&gt;Ultrodemon Schemer&lt;/strong&gt;. This is
a manipulative villain who will likely only fight the PCs in a battlefield of
its own choosing and backed up by a large number of demon allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a Medium Elemental Humanoid with the Demon tag, and a Level 22 Controller
(Leader) with 205 HP. It has a ground speed of 7 with Phasing, which allows it
to walk through walls. It also has Blindsight with range 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The schemer wields a &lt;strong&gt;longsword&lt;/strong&gt; whose attacks deal physical damage and daze
for a turn on a hit. It can also use magic to shoot &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Rays&lt;/strong&gt; that deal
fire damage. Its command ability is represented by the &lt;strong&gt;Demonic Authority&lt;/strong&gt;
power, which allows each ally adjacent to the schemer to make a melee basic
attack with combat advantage as a free action. This recharges when the demon is
first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To complement its sword, combat magic, and command ability, the schemer also has
a few nasty mind tricks it can use as minor actions. The first is &lt;strong&gt;Hypnotic
Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) immobilizes on a hit, and has an effect that prohibits the
target from attacking the schemer for a turn. “Effects” in 4e parlance are
things that happen even on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other trick is &lt;strong&gt;Treacherous Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), which dominates for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As its triggered actions, the schemer has a middling version of Variable
Resistance, which gives Resistance 20 but only works once per encounter. It also
has &lt;strong&gt;Self-Preservation&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when an enemy bloodies it. It causes
the schemer to teleport and swap places with an ally within 10 squares, and
gives the ally a chance to make a free basic attack against the triggering
enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this points to a demon who wants to be close to Team Monster’s
skirmishers and assassins, and who will accompany them to try to get around the
party’s front line. It things become too hot, it will bring in a soldier or
brute from its own front line to spice things up while it flees to safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remain a big fan of folding daemons into demons! Mechanically, ultros work
well as “sneaky leaders”, which isn’t a combination you see very often.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/15/ultrodemon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/15/ultrodemon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Star Wars RPGs and The Force: A Thought</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/Princess-Leia-Shirt.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heruniverse.com/product/star-wars-princess-leia-self-rescuing-princess-t-shirt/10920417.html&quot;&gt;
     Image source.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t part of a series or anything, but it’s a random though I’ve been
having and I feel it’s worth turning into a post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-thought&quot;&gt;The Thought&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I ever to a Star Wars adaptation, it’s going to be one where everybody is
Force-sensitive. Let’s do away with the absolutist “magic/no-magic” divide
inspired by D&amp;amp;D that all the official RPGs so far have used. If the Force is
described in the source material as being in everyone, then it should &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; in in
everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players would not be forced to play Jedi - rather, the badassitude of their PCs
would be explained by their connection to the Force. No more of that nonsense
about how “you can still be cool even though you’re blind to the Force”. No,
you’re cool because you opened yourself to it. It’s everywhere, and getting past
a certain threshold of skill at any endeavor means becoming attuned to the
Force. By definition, any character who is PC material in the sort of heroic
story Star Wars favors is past that threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, yeah, you can still be a Jedi who throws stuff around telekinetically and
parries blaster bolts with a lightsaber, but you can also be an amazing
gunfighter from the slums of Coruscant who can &lt;em&gt;dodge&lt;/em&gt; blasters, react to stuff
before it happens, and make shots that ricochet from five different surfaces
before hitting some impossibly small target. And maybe both of you can jump
really high because that’s always useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a set of Force-based mechanics that all PCs gets access to, even if they
have the least mystical background possible. They can use it to perform
impossible feats of skill and luck. They can have intuitions and
premonitions. Maybe they can study a mystical tradition to do more overtly
supernatural stuff, but that’s not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe one of the reasons the Dark Side and the Empire are evil is that
they’re the ones who believe that only a select few elites should be given
access to the Force.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/14/star-wars.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/14/star-wars.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>star-wars</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Demon, Quasit</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-demon-quasit.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe quasits have been around since AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, and they’ve
re-appeared in every edition since. This is where they enter 4e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back when they first appeared, quasits were simply the demon equivalent of
Imps: tiny, winged, and tricksy. The only reason they were a different creature
at all is was because of the game’s insistence that demons and devils are
completely different creature types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons Fourth Edition, quasits are… the demon equivalent of
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/30/imp.html&quot;&gt;Imps&lt;/a&gt;. Still tiny, still tricksy, they’re extremely easy to summon as
familiars and live to tempt their masters into committing ever more horrible
acts of destruction. When one of these masters die, the quasit captures their
soul and takes it to its &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; master, usually a demon lord. Demons don’t need
souls, but I guess they’re tasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quasits are usually encountered with whatever dupes they’ve managed to tempt
this time or with other, bigger, demons. Minions might include people of any
sapient species, with or without a spellcaster. They also like
arcanians. Quasits tend to remain invisible for as long as possible and let the
others do most of the work for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quasits are Tiny Elemental Humanoids with the Demon tag. They’re a bit stronger
than imps by default, being Level 7 Controllers with 75 HP. They have darkvision
and a fantastic ground speed of 8, though they’re not winged and can’t fly in
this edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re unusual among demons in that most of their attacks have a trickery and
temptation theme, to an even greater extend than an imp. This starts with their
&lt;strong&gt;Tempter’s Influence&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2), which inflicts a -2 penalty to saves on
enemies caught inside. They can also become &lt;strong&gt;Invisible&lt;/strong&gt; at will with a minor
action (1/round), and stay in this state until they make an attack roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 0 venomous &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which does physical damage
and forces the target to grant combat advantage (save ends). Reach 0 means they
need to enter the target’s square, which they can do because they’re Tiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their other attack is &lt;strong&gt;Evil Temptation&lt;/strong&gt;, a mind-affecting spell that targets
Will and affects enemies in a Close Blast 3. This is another at-will minor
action (1/round), and though it does no damage it dazes (save ends). The
“temptation” here is that victims can choose to end the effect early by making
an attack against one of their allies!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I guess quasits aren’t just demonic imps in 4e. They’re also doing some of
the succubus’ job now that she left to become a devil. PCs affected by Evil
Temptation are likely to try to shrug it off with saves at first, but if they
have a streak of unlucky rolls that friendly fire incident is going to start
feeling mighty attractive. Daze is such a serious condition after all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a genuine temptation mechanic! I think I only saw one other instance of
this, for the MM2’s &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/07/11/devils-02.html&quot;&gt;Misfortune Devils&lt;/a&gt;. Not even succubi themselves have
temptation mechanics, since their powers and “lore baggage” end up making them
better for &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/12/15/succubus.html&quot;&gt;making PCs run away&lt;/a&gt;. This is an at-will Blast attack, so you’ll
likely have &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; PCs affected by the power at any one time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quasits should fight by alternating Evil Temptation and Invisibility, and should
hang around close to “tempted” PCs while invisible to make their saves
harder. While this is happening, the quasit’s larger allies are going to have a
field day with all those dazed heroes. Brutes and artillery work well here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PC tactics when fighting a group containing a quasit are very clear: crush it
&lt;em&gt;as soon as possible&lt;/em&gt;. Have your party’s scouts use their high Perception to
find the invisible little bugger and smite him with close or area attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/13/demon-quasit.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/13/demon-quasit.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Demon, Nafelshnee</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-demon-nafelshnee.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember seeing these things in 3e, and they probably date from earlier. My
memory of them is not very detailed because I had no patience for reading
page-long lists of spell-like abilities, which were the style of the time for
epic demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nafelshnees are something of a rarity in the Abyss: demons with a
&lt;em&gt;civilization&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These demons hail from the 400th layer of the Abyss, known as the Woeful
Escarand. In the distant past, this layer was ruled by a demon lord named
Tantagaras, a corpulent beast who sired many lesser demons made in his
image. These were known as his Waddling Legions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tantagaras took part in Tharizdun’s uprising against the gods, during which he
entered a duel with Kord. Kord killed him, and the Waddling Legions brought his
corpse back to the Woeful Escarand. They paid their respects by devouring the
corpse, which causes fragments of Tantagaras’ essence to transfer to them and
make them a lot smarter and more ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This of course resulted in a long and bloody demon civil war, which in turn
ended when six of the most powerful nafelshnees got together and named
themselves the rulers of the 400th layer. Known as the Lords of Woe, they carved
the layer into a sprawling feudal realm, each of them sitting at the top of a
large hierarchy of vassals that rule their own fiefs as they see fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, these lords and ladies exhausted all the resources of their abyssal
layer, because demons might be able to build a society but they can’t make it
sustainable. So now they make deals with “foreign” demon lords, offering their
services in exchange for slaves, materials, food, and treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your typical nafelshnee divides people into three groups: “food”, “tools” and
“masters”. The first group includes almost everyone weaker than themselves, from
animals to humanoids to lesser demons. They never negotiate with food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second group includes those who aren’t tasty enough to eat, like insects,
spiders, immortals, powerful elementals and, amusingly enough, gnomes. They’ll
try to bully the weaker “tools” into servitude, and might try to manipulate the
stronger ones, but I guess they might just try to kill them without eating if
talks break down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last group is very small and consists of the mightiest demons, demon lords,
and efreets. With these, their usually arrogant behavior melts into a wheedling
servitude worthy of Starscream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nafelshnees are Huge Elemental Humanoids with the Demon tag, Darkvision, and a
ground speed of 6. They can also fly with a speed of 4 (clumsy). They have very
good Variable Resistance (20). We get two stat blocks for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nafelshnee-swine-guard&quot;&gt;Nafelshnee Swine Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most nafelshnees fit this profile, and have a role roughly equivalent to that of
a landless knight in their society. They serve more powerful lords and hire
themselves out as mercenaries, and have actually managed to get a good
reputation for being both resilient and obedient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swine Guards are Level 20 Brutes with 237 HP. They wield giant Reach 3
&lt;strong&gt;halberds&lt;/strong&gt; that do solid physical damage and push the target 2 squares on a
hit. If someone manages to get closer they can try to take a &lt;strong&gt;Noisome Bite&lt;/strong&gt;
out of the enemy, which does slightly less damage but inflicts ongoing 10 poison
damage (swine guards never brush their teeth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their variable resistance can change twice per encounter, and when they’re first
bloodied they immediately use a power called &lt;strong&gt;Shattered Minds&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a
Close Burst 3 that targets enemies’ Will. On a hit it does psychic damage and
dazes (save ends). If the first save fails, the demon can slide the victim 3
squares, and the daze worsens to a stun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes swine guards the kind of brute who wants the PCs to surround them and
beat them up a bit. The halberd’s push rider means they can also herd the PCs
towards other monsters as this happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nafelshnee-tyrant&quot;&gt;Nafelshnee Tyrant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the lords and ladies of the Woeful Escarand. They’re powerful
magicians with great knowledge of rituals and access to libraries of forbidden
lore. They are willing to part with ritual scrolls and bits of relevant
information in exchange for suitable tribute, which usually consists of food
(the book mentions “a brace of plump halflings” as an example). In a fight, they
like to fling destructive magic while sitting on their thrones, though they can
move at standard nafelshnee speeds if forced to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyrants are Level 23 Controllers with 215 HP. Their reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; slide the
target 3 squares on a hit, and their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Black
Lightning&lt;/strong&gt; spell that does necrotic damage and makes the victim vulnerable 15
to psychic damage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their psychic attack is &lt;strong&gt;Unholy Whispers&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a fireball sized area
burst that does psychic damage and dazes (save ends). A miss still does half
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, they can curse enemies with a &lt;strong&gt;Vile Glare&lt;/strong&gt;, a non-damaging
attack that targets Will and makes it so the target is only able to use basic
attacks (save ends). It recharges every time a target fails a save against the
effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I say this all the time, but I really love these more focused fiend stat
blocks. Earlier editions just had long lists of spell-like abilities and
memorized spells for each demon, so I tended to just skip over their
descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyrants obviously pair really well with other monsters that can deal psychic
damage. A simple but flavorful and effective encounter might be a pair of
happily married nafelshnee tyrants and their swine guard retinue. Two tyrants
means you can assemble the Black Lightning + Unholy Whispers combo much quicker.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/12/nafelshnee.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/12/nafelshnee.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Demon, Molydeus</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-demon-molydeus.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Tharizdun first planted the cosmic Seed of Evil in the Elemental Chaos, he
ordered his seven most powerful angels to stand guard over it. The angels’ oaths
and sense of duty compelled them to obey. However, they all had some serious
personal misgivings about this whole “corrupt and destroy the universe”
business, so they were reluctant guardians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the seed inevitably corrupted them, it seized on this reluctance and turned
the seven into two-headed Molydeus demons. They have a wolf’s head symbolizing
their fierceness, and a snake’s head symbolizing their uncertain loyalty. They
also carry the same axes they wielded as angels, which in a surprising twist
contain a bit of the unspoiled light of creation. The demons are bound to their
weapons - when one dies, the axe dissolves into sludge. If it’s stolen or lost,
the molydeus will not rest until it has been recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seed of evil hasn’t needed guarding for a long time now, and the molydeus
have scattered. They wander the Abyss alone, or followed by small retinues of
other epic-level demons. They usually prefer Mariliths, but will also work with
Balors or Klurichirs. Very rarely you’ll find one of them doing a demon lord’s
dirty work, but these relationships rarely last long. I mean, if anyone is
really at an “almost demon lord” level of power it’s the molydeus, so I guess
they don’t like being the junior partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s only one stat block in this entry, which is okay because there are only
seven molydeus demons in all the universe. They’re Large Elemental Humanoids
with the Demon tag, and Level 29 Elite Soldiers with 544 HP. Stronger than
balors and pit fiends, and on par with primordial colossi. They have Blindsight
5, a ground speed of 8, and are immune to fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, molydeus share some similarities with Ettins, due to their two
heads. They have &lt;strong&gt;All-Around Vision&lt;/strong&gt; and therefore can’t be flanked; &lt;strong&gt;Double
Actions&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to roll Initiative twice and take two full turns per
round; and &lt;strong&gt;Dual Brain&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to automatically save against dazing,
stunning or charm effects at the beginning of each of their turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all demons, the molydeus has &lt;strong&gt;Variable Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;, and since it’s epic
the trait is at its most powerful: 30 resistance to an element, switchable 3
times per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a fight, it’ll probably open up with its &lt;strong&gt;Dread Word&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power, a
fear attack that targets Will in a Close Burst 5, affecting only enemies. A hit
dazes them (save ends); a miss slows them and inflicts a -2 attack penalty (save
ends both). If it needs to mark someone, it will attack with its Reach 2
&lt;strong&gt;axe&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a pretty beefy attack already. Otherwise it will alternate
between &lt;strong&gt;Wolf Bites&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Snake Bites&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolf bites are Reach 2 do about as much damage as the axe and slide the target 6
squares to a square adjacent to the demon. Snake Bites are weaker, but have
Reach 3, make the target grant combat advantage, and inflict 20 ongoing poison
damage (save ends both). Both the axe and the bites count as basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wolf bite is an excellent positioning tool, so I guess the demon might use
if a few times to set the party up for the Dread Word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now &lt;em&gt;here’s&lt;/em&gt; some proper epic demon lore! Mechanically, it has a suite of
attacks that’s both thematic and varied, and indeed pairs well with mariliths
and klurichirs. The klurichir stat block works better as a demon created to
serve the molydeus than as a demon lord contender itself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/10/demon-molydeus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/10/demon-molydeus.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Demon, Maw</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-demon-maw.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t much to a maw demon. It’s a huge fanged mouth with some extra bits
attached so it can move to wherever the food is. While most other demons are
motivated by rage, hatred, or ruinous ambition, these things just want to
eat. They’re a bit like sharks, drawn to the smell of blood, and will prioritize
an easy meal over a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maw demons are still demons, so they prefer their meals bloody and still
twitching. If there are none already in that state, they’ll advance on the
nearest living creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical maw demon is rather weak as far as demons go, though it still
presents a big threat to non-combatants. Those who manage to live longer become
much stronger and hungrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maw demons are sapient, but just barely. They don’t really form alliances, but
stronger demons can bully them into servitude, and even amateur demonologists
might be able to summon and bind one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;maw-demon&quot;&gt;Maw Demon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Medium Elemental Humanoid with the Demon tag. It’s a Level 2 Brute
with 42 HP, darkvision, and a speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demon’s &lt;strong&gt;snapping jaws&lt;/strong&gt; act like an aura (1) that make all enemies inside
grant combat advantage. Its basic attack is obviously a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;. It can use a
move action to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Ravenous Advance&lt;/strong&gt; and shift 5 squares to end
adjacent to a bloodied enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a demon, it has &lt;strong&gt;Variable Resistance&lt;/strong&gt; and can switch it once per
encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;greater-maw-demon&quot;&gt;Greater Maw Demon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is mostly just a leveled-up maw demon. It’s a Level 16 Brute with 187 HP
and correspondingly bigger numbers. Its variable resistance works twice per
encounter, and  it has a new hability: &lt;strong&gt;Howling Hunger&lt;/strong&gt; targets Will, hits a
Close Burst 3, does thunder damage, and knocks targets prone. It can only be
used when the demon is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just another demonic brute. Its low level makes it an interesting variation on
the MM2 dretches, with better math. Their most interesting power is actually the
Snapping Jaws aura, which makes them pair really well with ranged monsters that
benefit from combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the MM2 reading on the RPG.net forum, someone mentioned that these things
could be abyssal xorns, and it fits really well with their mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/07/demon-maw.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/07/demon-maw.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
