<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 13:35:08 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 13:35:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Norker</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-norker.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norkers have been around since the days of AD&amp;amp;D, where their major mechanical
distinction was that they were stronger goblins with AC 3. They play a
significant role in The Forgotten Temple or Tharizdun as the rank and file of
the occupying force the PCs need to clear out before they can delve the temple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norkers in 4e are descendants of goblins who emigrated to the Elemental Chaos
and sought shelter in deep caves in order to survive the harsh conditions of
that plane. The earth-aspected ambient energy of their chosen habitat mutated
them over generations, granting them stony skin and minor earth-based powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norker populations have since crossed back into the middle world, where they
live in mountainous regions, in the Underdark, and near fonts of earth-aspected
elemental power. Some sages speculate that the original norkers lived near sites
of power related to Ogrémoch, the Evil Elemental Prince of Earth, because modern
norkers are often found working for his cultists or those of the Elder Elemental
Eye, guarding his forgotten temples in another very obvious historical
reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norkers retain their conceptual role as rank-and-file opposition for
paragon-tier (AKA “name level”) characters, which in 4e means they’re much
stronger than they ever were. Their levels range from around 12 to 15 here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re Small Elemental Humanoids with Low-Light Vision and Speed 6, with
abilities combining martial training and minor earth magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;norker-stone-shield&quot;&gt;Norker Stone Shield&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Shields look like an unruly mob at first glance, but they’re professional
soldiers trained by those elemental cults and other earth-themed villains. Their
training and equipment allows them to fight a bit like a roman legion, keeping
tight formations, throwing javelins and them closing in to batter enemies with
their short clubs and shields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Shields are Level 12 Soldiers with 124 HP, which means a sizable group of
them can eat most typical human military units for breakfast. Their basic
attacks are a &lt;em&gt;club&lt;/em&gt; and a &lt;em&gt;javelin&lt;/em&gt;, both of which mark for a turn on a hit. If
a marked enemy adjacent to the norker shifts, it can attack them with a &lt;strong&gt;Shield
Slam&lt;/strong&gt; vs. Fortitude that damages and knocks prone on a hit. And if someone hits
them in melee they can respond with an &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Rebuke&lt;/strong&gt;, a reaction that
attacks AC and does some minor damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;norker-grunt&quot;&gt;Norker Grunt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, it seems stone shields are rarified elites. The actual rank and
file of a norker force will be made of of these guys, who are far less organized
and prefer to use “charging horde” tactics with their clubs. Their natural
strength and toughness still makes them a very hard problem for human
militaries, and even PCs don’t want to get surrounded by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grunts are Level 15 Minion Brutes, and their only active ability is their
&lt;strong&gt;Club&lt;/strong&gt; attack. Their &lt;strong&gt;Harrassing Brute&lt;/strong&gt; trait is what makes them truly
dangerous. All of the grunt’s allies get a damage bonus against enemies equal to
twice the number of grunts adjacent to that enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s unpack that for a moment. Let’s say 4 grunts are adjacent to the party’s
fighter. Each of those grunts will get a +8 damage bonus when they attack the
fighter. So will the grunt’s artillery and controller bosses who are 5 squares
away from this scrum. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, grunts want to slip past the front line and harrass the enemy
squishies, but as we can see from the example above they can still do pretty
well against defenders if Team Monster decides to focus fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;norker-stone-walker&quot;&gt;Norker Stone Walker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Walkers norkers who received proper training in earth magic, and who
combine that with a mobile fighting style. They’re Level 15 Skirmishers with 150
HP. They can attack with &lt;strong&gt;handaxes&lt;/strong&gt; in melee or at range, doing extra damage
if they have combat advantage. They also have a +4 AC bonus against opportunity
attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magic-wise, they have the same &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Rebuke&lt;/strong&gt; reaction as the Stone
Shield, and they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Earth Glide&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action to move their
speed and phase through earth and rock during this movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That last one makes them excellent additions to an underground encounter. Place
a couple of them behind a thin rock wall and have them flank the PCs after the
stone shields and grunts begin their frontal assault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tough norkers still fill more or less the same narrative role as before, they do
so in a very different way. I think my favorites are the grunts; the damage
bonus they grant is both very distinctive and terrifying to players. When
scaling their level, I’d probably make it +1/tier instead of a flat +2.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/26/norker.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/26/norker.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Nerra</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-nerra.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first I’ve heard of Nerras, though it’s possible they originated in
a previous edition. If they did, their lore was completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many ages ago, a sect of mortal invokers called the Sect of Seventy came to
believe that the gods had grown too detached from the middle world in the
aftermath of the Dawn War. They had become incapable of defending it from the
many threats and hazards that lingered from those terrible battles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sect of Seventy decided to claim for themselves the role of protectors of
the middle world, and set about building a grand work that would allow them to
keep watch over all reality. They used their divine magic to build an astral
dominion they named The Constellation of Eyes. Located far from all the other
known dominions, it consisted of a central reflective crystal sphere around
which orbited uncountable mirrors that reflected different parts of the universe
and could be used as portals to reach those places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the Constellation is the ultimate panopticon, capable of
maintaining surveillance over the entire universe and allowing its owners to
instantly deploy to places of interest. The Sect intended it to be the perfect
“superhero base” from which they would keep watch over reality, but other
interested parties had far more nefarious uses in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sect was unknowingly infiltrated by a small group of priests of Asmodeus,
who intended to seize it for themselves and use it to open a permanent portal to
the Nine Hells that would give devils free access to the rest of the
multiverse. The invokers only managed to discover this after the final ritual
had already began. The ensuing battle was every bit as epic as you imagine, and
the resulting flare of divine energy from both sides was strong enough for the
other gods to notice and send their angels to investigate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The angels would have been a great help, but they arrived too late. As far as
they were able to determine, the invokers realized they were losing the battle,
and enacted a desperate ritual of their own that would bring terrible ruin upon
all that were in the Constellation of Eyes. The ritual worked. It turned both
the invokers and the Asmodean priests into the creatures now known as Nerras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mirrored crystaline humanoids still dwell in the Constellation of
Eyes. With no apparent memory of their previous lives, they spent the following
eons acting as dispassionate observers of the multiverse. Their observations are
recorded in specially constructed glass tablets that can only be read from a
slanted angle, and their collected store of information is one of the greatest
in existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relatively recently, though, the nerras have changed their behavior and become
more proactive. They’ve taken to crossing their mirror portals and kidnapping
certain powerful and influential individuals. Back at the Constellation, the
nerras use their magic to create a perfect duplicate of the subject, with a
diametrically opposite moral outlook. Then they send both back home. This
predictably causes a lot of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerras target both terrible villains and virtuous heroes in equal measure. Those
scholars aware of their history theorize that ancient memories of the nerras’
former lives are resurfacing and causing divisions among them, and that their
new activities are an experiment to see which between good and evil is stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerras also travel to places they consider interesting to monitor things from up
close, and sometime they interfere in local events for inscrutable
reasons. Sometimes their interference ends up causing wars and disasters, some
times they prevent them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerras despise demons, devils, and creatures of the Far Realm, but they ally
with other creatures when their goals happen to align. Even their occasional
allies have little insight on their true motives, which they keep to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nerra are Medium Immortal Humanoids, with Speed 6 and human-standard
senses. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Mirror Step&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will move action that
allows them to teleport 5 squares to a space adjacent to a mirror or to another
nerra. This means a group of nerras finds it very easy to maintain a cohesive
formation, and that their preferred battlegrounds have lots of mirrors that they
can use for extra mobility. All of the ones we see here are Unaligned, and they
speak Supernal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their other abilities vary per stat block, though they all tend to share
a strong “mirror” theme. Their levels cover the mid-to-late Paragon tier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;varoot-nerra&quot;&gt;Varoot Nerra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varoots are elite scouts and spies. They’re the first to venture forth from the
Constellation of Eyes to lay the groundwork for a nerra expedition. Their
ability to copy the appearances of others makes them great infiltrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varoot Nerras are Level 16 Lurkers with the Shapechanger keyword and 116
HP. Their main weapon is a &lt;strong&gt;shard blade&lt;/strong&gt; similar to a longsword. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Reflection Theft&lt;/strong&gt; ability allows them to perfectly duplicate an enemy within
10 squares of it. The effect lasts until the end of the encounter, or until the
varoot attacks. If the varoot is adjacent to the copying enemy, it gets to roll
a save against any melee or ranged attack that targets it, with a success
forcing the attack to target the copied enemy instead. It also gains a +2 bonus
to attack and a +5 bonus to damage against the copied enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its last ability aside from Mirror Step is &lt;strong&gt;Mirrored Grasp&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor-action
power that lets the nerra teleport an unattended object of up to 20 pounds /
10kg that’s within 10 squares and line of sight to its hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat, the Varoot does it’s Lurker routine by “hiding” next to a PC it’s
copying, attacking the copied PC with a damage bonus, and teleporting away using
Mirror Step so it can transform and try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no way to pierce the varoot’s disguise with a skill check, at least in
the ability’s combat form. It would make sense to rule that outside of combat
this works like a doppelganger’s transformation: it lasts a long time and can be
contested with Insight vs. the nerra’s Bluff of +20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meerak-nerra&quot;&gt;Meerak Nerra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeraks are the rank and file of a Nerra strike force. They charge into the
enemy to cut it up with their spiked, jagged bodies, softening them up for the
more powerful individuals that always follow close behind them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeraks are Level 18 Minion Soldiers. Their &lt;strong&gt;Mirror Slash&lt;/strong&gt; basic attacks mark
on a hit, and their &lt;strong&gt;Mirror Defense&lt;/strong&gt; ability is an interrupt that triggers
when they’re hit by a melee attack and deals 10 damage to a different enemy
within 10 squares. The meerak is still going to die from the hit, but not before
reflecting some damage to a PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kalareem-nerra&quot;&gt;Kalareem Nerra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kalareems are elite knights among the nerra. Unlike a lot of their crystalline
relatives, they look like they’re made out of mirror-smooth liquid metal. This
makes them hard to hurt, and they can also briefly solidify parts of their
bodies to launch a spray of deadly metal shards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kalareem Nerras are Level 19 Soldiers with 175 HP. Their liquid metal
construction doesn’t translate to specific abilities but it’s a nice
in-character explanation for the high defenses and HP a level 19 Soldier
has. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Shard Blade&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and marks on a hit, as
do the &lt;strong&gt;Shard Blasts&lt;/strong&gt; they can fire at-will in a Close Burst 3 pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the standard nerra Mirror Step, they also have two other
mirror-themed abilities that make them good bodyguards. &lt;strong&gt;Mirror Image&lt;/strong&gt; is an
interrupt that triggers when a marked enemy makes a melee or ranged attack that
doesn’t include the nerra as a target. It makes the enemy target the nerra
instead. &lt;strong&gt;Mirror Defense&lt;/strong&gt; is another interrupt that triggers when the kalareem
is hit by a melee attack. The creature can then make an attack against the Will
of the triggering enemy, which on a hit deals the same damage inflicted by the
triggering attack. This is an interrupt, so the attacker gets damaged &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt;
the nerra, and if they get reduced to 0 HP the kalareem wouldn’t suffer the
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sillit-nerra&quot;&gt;Sillit Nerra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sillits are nerra spellcasters, who often act as field agents and
mystically-oriented scouts. Like other spellcasting monsters, out of combat they
should have access to whatever rituals are required by the story. In combat,
they use mirror-themed spells and specialize in forcibly teleporting enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sillits are Level 19 Controllers with 181 HP. Even their basic attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;Mirror Portal&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Will, and on a hit damages and teleports the
target adjacent to one of the sillit’s allies within 10 squares. Their basic
ranged attack is &lt;strong&gt;Warped Image&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Fortitude and on a hit damages
and teleports the target 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Captured Image&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a ranged power that
targets Will. On a hit it removes the target from play (save ends), trapping it
within the mirrors that make up the sillit’s body. While the target is captured,
it takes 20 damage whenever the sillit is damaged. The effect ends when the
target successfully saves, or when the sillit is reduced to 0 HP. When this
happens the target appears on a square of the sillit’s choice within 5 squares
of the sillit itself. Yes, it’s entirely possible that a sillit who gets lucky
with its recharge rolls will manage to capture multiple targets at the same
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sillits have the standard Mirror Step power, and the same Mirrored Grasp power
of the Varoots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging from their powers, Sillits love to fight in maps containing plenty of
hazardous terrain, and accompanied by bruiser allies. They’ll use Captured Image
as soon and as often as they can, and then move to the front lines to dare PCs
to attack them. Inconveniently strong melee PCs can be teleported next to the
bruisers with Mirror Portal, and Warped Image is good for disrupting the
remaining PCs if no other opportunities arise. Hazardous terrain on the
battlefield makes those forced teleports more dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;delphar-nerra&quot;&gt;Delphar Nerra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delphars are the officers and commanders of nerra forces. They’re similar to
kalareems in their training, but they’re much larger and their mere presence has
bolstering effects on the abilities of their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike other nerra, delphars are Large and have Speed 8. They’re Level 20
Soldiers with 187 HP and the Leader tag. They project a &lt;strong&gt;Mirrored Rampart&lt;/strong&gt;
aura (5) that extends the range of other nerras’ Mirror Step to 10. They fight
with a &lt;strong&gt;Shard Blade&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Shard Blasts&lt;/strong&gt; that have the same effects as those
of kalareems, with slightly higher numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have a different way of punishing marked enemies, though: &lt;strong&gt;Mirrored
Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; triggers when a marked enemy within 10 squares ignores the mark, and
teleports the enemy adjacent to the delphar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teltarym-nerra&quot;&gt;Teltarym Nerra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would expect the strongest monster in the entry to be some sort of dread
overlord, but we’re talking about topsy-turvy mirror people here. Teltarym are
the nerra’s manual laborers, joining the fight either because they must defend
themselves or because they were ordered to. Despite not being formal combatants
they’re very strong and aggressive, charging in to smash enemies with their huge
fists, and reflecting their own wounds back at their attackers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teltarym are Level 21 Brutes with 237 HP. Like delphars, they’re Large and have
Speed 8. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Hammer Fist&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and pushes 1
square, and they can use it twice in the same action. &lt;strong&gt;Reflected Pain&lt;/strong&gt; is a
reaction that triggers when they’re hit by a melee attack, and which inflicts
half the damage they suffered to the attacker. This recharges when they’re first
bloodied. Their last ability is Mirror Step, so like most brutes they’re fairly
simple to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the perfect bruiser allies for Sillits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the lore of the nerra quite a lot. It’s nice and epic and introduces a
new and interesting location on the Astral Sea. I also like how they’re depicted
as enigmatic instead of evil. A campaign against nerra is one where violence
might be necessary to drive them off, but where true victory can only be
achieved through unraveling their mysteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanics wise it seems varoots are a bit too low level to hang out with their
nerra buddies, so you’re going to meet them alone at the start of a
nerra-focused story arc. They might be accompanied by local agents or
mecernaries. The others are all of a level range where you can use them to build
all-nerra encounter groups.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/25/nerra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/25/nerra.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Nagpa</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-nagpa.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 1982, there was a movie named &lt;em&gt;The Dark Crystal&lt;/em&gt;. It introduced these
cool villainous vulture people called the Skeksis, which became kind of
iconic. D&amp;amp;D wanted in on some of that action, so it added a species called the
Nagpa to Mystara. Nagpas are to Skeksis what Halflings are to Hobbits, which
means that they started out just barely different enough to avoid a lawsuit and
got significantly changed in each subsequent edition. This is their 4e debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, during the Dawn War, the Primordials realized they needed
servitors that could act as special forces. They already commanded uncountable
hordes of elementals, but they were mostly dumb as rocks and only good as shock
troops. Giants and djinns were smart and individually powerful, but too few in
number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So they decided to take a page from the playbook of the gods and create a
servitor species they named the nagpas. Created to be as beautiful as nymphs and
as clever as devils, the nagpas readily took to their new role and proceeded to
wreak havoc on the armies of the gods for a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when the Dawn War was nearing its end, the nagpas were clever enough to
realize that their side would lose. And so it was that they made a deal with the
gods to betray their masters. However, they were caught, and the primordials
cursed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curse took away the beauty of the nagpas, turning them into horrid
vulture-like beings. It also doomed them to never touch that which they desired
the most. A nagpa who loved fine food and wine would always taste foulness when
he tried to eat or drink. One who loved art would see it crumble at a touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagpas were either already immortal, or were made so by the curse. Even when
slain, they reincarnate within a few decades with all memories of their previous
lives and deaths. Every nagpa alive today remembers their life before the curse,
and is obsessed with those things it cannot have. They tend to destroy mirrors
or any other surface that can show them their own faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primordial curse angle is interesting. Without it, you could argue that
their vulture-like appearance is a subjective thing. Some people think they’re
ugly, they themselves like it just fine. But a curse might make them
“axiomatically” ugly: not only are others unable to see beauty in them, they are
incapable of seeing it in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagpas are Medium Elemental Humanoids with Low-Light Vision and a speed
of 6. Everything else comes from training and varies per stat block. The two
stat blocks here have a wizardly bent, and use magic with a corruption and decay
theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nagpa-corruptor&quot;&gt;Nagpa Corruptor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nagpa Corruptor is given as an example of an art-loving nagpa. Its lair
looks like a museum, with cordoned-off works of art on display (but no
reflective surfaces!). It employs a large number with a similarly evil
disposition to protect its collection and acquire more pieces for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corruptors are Level 9 Controllers with 97 HP. Their basic attacks are a
&lt;strong&gt;withering staff&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic damage and pushes 2 squares, and a
ranged &lt;strong&gt;Withering Blast&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic damage and immobilizes (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a ranged &lt;strong&gt;Devouring Fire&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) spell that deals
fire damage and ongoing fire damage (save ends). Each failed save also deals a
bit of fire damage to up to 3 enemies adjacent to the target. The text says
“each ally” but I’m interpreting that to mean “each ally of the target”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their strongest attack is an encounter power named &lt;strong&gt;Corrupting Curse&lt;/strong&gt;, a close
blast 5 that deals necrotic damage and creates a zone that prevents enemies
inside from regaining HP. It lasts until the end of the encounter. Their other
encounter power is an &lt;strong&gt;Enervating Blast&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s another close blast 5 that can
be cast as a minor action, deals no damage and weakens those it hits for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corruptors let their hired muscle do most of the fighting, hitting their enemies
with opportunistic spells from afar. They’re one of the rare monsters that
include more specific “director’s notes” in their text, though: if the fight
happens inside the corruptor’s lair/gallery, PCs should be able to its beloved
art objects. The first time one is destroyed, the corruptor becomes dazed for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nagpa-carrion-lord&quot;&gt;Nagpa Carrion Lord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is a gourmand who loved good food and drink, but who is cursed to only
taste ashes and filth when it eats. It still likes holding feasts, but its
inability to enjoy them fill it with rage and frustration, which it takes out on
any nearby PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Carrion Lord is a Level 14 Artillery monster with 111 HP. All of its
abilities have a “rot” theme, starting with the &lt;strong&gt;Rotting Staff&lt;/strong&gt; basic melee
attack that targets Fortitude and does necrotic damage. Its basic ranged attack
is the &lt;strong&gt;Bolt of Putrescence&lt;/strong&gt;, targetting Reflex and doing, you guessed it,
necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hand of Ruin&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a ranged attack that changes things up a
little and does acid damage. &lt;strong&gt;Consuming Shadows&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a ranged area
attack that deals immediate and ongoing necrotic damage, and creates a zone that
blocks line of sight to the carrion lord’s enemies. Its allies can see through
it just fine, though. It lasts for a turn and can be sustained with a minor
action. The lord’s last encounter power is &lt;strong&gt;Ghostly Escape&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action
that gives it insubstantial and phasing for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Carrion Lord likely opens the fight with Consuming Shadows, and then keeps
using its two ranged attacks from beyond the sight of the PCs while its
melee-oriented bodyguards keep them pinned in place. Ghostly escape is reserved
for doing what its name says, and letting the nagpa get away after it sees the
fight is lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to say the same thing everyone who has reviewed a Nagpa entry always
says: they’re skeksis. The way in which they’re skeksis tends to vary with the
edition, though. I think the ones from the source material were pursuing
immortality. These ones achieved it, but found that it brings them no joy.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/22/nagpa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/22/nagpa.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Minotaur</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-minotaur.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minotaurs made their 4e debut right in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/07/23/minotaur.html&quot;&gt;first Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;. They’d
also appear in the Monster Vault. As it happens with a lot of other monsters in
the same situation, the MM3 gives us a set of minotaur stat blocks that
complements the ones from the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minotaurs are a playable option as of the PHB 3, so their &lt;a href=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/07/23/minotaur.html&quot;&gt;basic lore&lt;/a&gt; is
quite a bit more lenient with them than that of other “monstrous humanoids”. The
MM3 innovates here by presenting us with a &lt;em&gt;specific organization&lt;/em&gt; of evil
minotaurs rather than trying to describe the whole species again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This organization is called the Blood League. Its members have invented rituals
that allow them to steal the power of another creature by eating its
still-beating heart. They like to capture potential targets and release them
into a special labyrinth they control, hunting the victim to the limits of its
endurance and only then making the kill. They often work with worshippers of
Torog and Baphomet, who share aspects of their worldview and tastes. They also
work with mind flayers, who get to eat the victims’ brains after the Blood
League is done with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry presents several Blood League minotaurs that take their powers from a
variety of creatures. They’re all early Paragon threats. All of them are Medium
Natural Humanoids and have a &lt;strong&gt;Goring Charge&lt;/strong&gt; attack that does heavy physical
damage and knocks prone on a hit. They also have a &lt;strong&gt;Ferocity&lt;/strong&gt; trait that gives
them one final basic attack when they’re dropped to 0 HP, with an additional
rider that varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novel thing here is the &lt;strong&gt;Heart&lt;/strong&gt; ability each minotaur gets. This is
something thematic to the creature they killed to gain their powers. It’s
usually an encounter or recharge power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pale-bloodfiend&quot;&gt;Pale Bloodfiend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one has eaten the heart of a vampire, proving that “still-beating” is a
poetic flourish and not a requirement. It’s a Level 12 Brute with 140 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bloodfiend gained most of a vampire’s cool powers without any of the
disadvantages, much like Marvel’s Blade. It has a Speed of 8, Darkvision, claws,
and a blood-draining bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; are a basic attack, and can be used twice in a &lt;strong&gt;Double Claw&lt;/strong&gt;
maneuver. If both attacks hit, the bloodfiend grabs the target. It can then use
&lt;strong&gt;Heart of the Vampire&lt;/strong&gt; against the grabbed victim, an attack vs. Fortitude
that deals a light physical damage, dazes and weakens (save ends both). A hit
also heals the bloodfiend for 20 HP. This is an encounter power that recharges
on a miss, and likely represents some sort of blood-draining bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Bloodfiend’s Ferocity&lt;/strong&gt; makes its final attack daze for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cinderhoof-trampler&quot;&gt;Cinderhoof Trampler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one has eaten the heart of a nightmare. It’s a Level 13 Skirmisher with 132
HP. It smells of brimstone and burnt hair. It runs very fast, and gains a few
fire- and trample- based powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its speed is 8, and it has Resist 10 Fire. When it hits a target granting combat
advantage to it, it inflicts ongoing 10 fire damage (save ends). It’s basic
attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Gore&lt;/strong&gt;, and its special ability is &lt;strong&gt;Heart of the Nightmare&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 6+). This allows it to move its speed and enter enemy spaces during
this move. Anyone that hits the trampler with an opportunity attack during the
move takes 10 fire damage, and any creatures whose space it moves through are
targeted by an attack vs. Reflex that deals heavy physical damage and knocks
them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Trampler’s Ferocity&lt;/strong&gt; pushes the target 2 squares and knocks it prone on a
hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ironskin-warrior&quot;&gt;Ironskin Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This elite Blood Leaguer has eaten the heart of a gorgon, one of the
metal-skinned gas-breathing bulls of D&amp;amp;D. It’s a Level 14 Soldier with 140 HP,
and has Resist 10 Poison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, the ironskin warrior has metal skin, but that’s rolled into
its Soldierly high AC. It fights with a &lt;strong&gt;greataxe&lt;/strong&gt; that damages, slows and
prevents shifting (save ends both). The &lt;strong&gt;Heart of the Gorgon&lt;/strong&gt; encounter bility
is a poison breath attack (close burst 5 vs. Fortitude). A hit deals poison
damage and slows (save ends). This worsens to immobilization on the first failed
save, and to full petrification after the second failure. Petrification is
permanent and requires magic to reverse. It’s a good fight opener, because it
has the chance to take an unlucky PC out of the fight completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Ironskin’s Ferocity&lt;/strong&gt; immobilizes the target for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shardhorn-hunter&quot;&gt;Shardhorn Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fearsome assassin has eaten the heart of a unicorn and made a dagger out of
its horn. Just in case you doubted the Blood League was evil. It’s a Level 15
Lurker with 116 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;horn dagger&lt;/strong&gt; can be used for basic attacks, and it can also &lt;strong&gt;backstab&lt;/strong&gt;
an enemy granting combat advantage to the hunter. This deals the same damage as
the basic attack, plus ongoing 10 damage (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Heart of the Unicorn&lt;/strong&gt;
helps with this: it allows the hunter to teleport 6 squares and turn invisible
for a turn or until it attacks. It recharges when the hunter uses Backstab (hit
or miss).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Shardhorn’s Ferocity&lt;/strong&gt; dazes for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a specific evil organization with specific methods and goals, and a nice
set of thematic powers. It’s not something that would have flown in the first
Monster Manual (which needs to be more generic), but it’s very welcome in a
subsequent supplement like this one. I want more of this!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/20/minotaur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/20/minotaur.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Mind Flayer</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-mimic.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind flayers made their 4e debut back in the first Monster Manual. This entry
adds more lore to them, and more stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind flayers maintain one of the most evil civilizations in the Underdark, and
that’s saying something. Illithids are aggressive supremacists who prefer to
engage with even drow and duergar through slave-taking raids rather than
anything resembling diplomacy. Their settlements consist of a large population
of permanently mind-controlled thralls from every other sapient species in the
Underdark, supporting a small collective of illithid masters, who in turn might
be led by an Elder Brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elder Brains live in special life support vats, and are psionic
powerhouses. Third Edition had Elder Brains as deceivers who absorbed the
knowledge and power of deceased illithids. Fifth Edition would make mind flayers
into a full-on hive mind centered on the brains. Here in Fourth they’re neither
of those things. Instead, they are revered leaders and masterminds. They form
the center of a telepathic network linking all the illithids in the collective,
who can communicate and share information instantly through it while retaining
their individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an illithid collective passes a certain threshold of size and combined
power, it performs a specific procedure on its wisest and most respected
member. The volunteer’s head is severed and placed in the support tank, where it
is kept alive. The other mind flayers then focus their psionic energy on the
head over an extended period of time, causing it to grow in size and power until
it becomes an Elder Brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, mind flayers don’t really “do” diplomacy. Their
non-illithid allies are almost all slaves and mind-controlled thralls. They
usually come from some of the other sapient people of the Underdark, though a
mind flayer with access to the surface will happily enthrall surfacers as
well. Occasionally you’ll find other aberrant monsters working alongside them,
either as thralls or as allies of convenience in a symbiotic relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lone illithids might end up making actual alliances with other villains, though
they only cooperate on their own terms even then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, mind flayers are Medium Aberrant Humanoids with Darkvision and
Speed 7. All of them have psychic powers and something that lets them mess with
other people’s brains, but the specifics vary per stat block. The entries in the
MM1 and Monster Vault focus on the mid Paragon tier. These show stronger
individuals in the early Epic tier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mind-flayer-inquisitor&quot;&gt;Mind Flayer Inquisitor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, inquisitors are strong telepaths. The flavor text describes
one of them hiding in abandoned tunnels and kidnapping nobles and sages to feast
on their brains and memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inquisitors are Level 20 Controllers with 190 HP. Their basic melee attack are
the classic grabby &lt;strong&gt;tentacles&lt;/strong&gt;, which target Reflex. A hit damages and grabs
the victim (Athletics DC 31 or Acrobatics DC 33 to escape). Once the inquisitor
has grabbed a victim, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Implant Delusions&lt;/strong&gt; on them. This targets
Will, does psychic damage, and inflicts the custom “delusions” condition (save
ends). Victims suffering from delusions inflict a -2 penalty to all attacks and
defenses of adjacent allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their ranged powers start with the classic &lt;strong&gt;mind blast&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) that
inflicts psychic damage and dazes (save ends). A miss does half damage. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Own Worst Enemy&lt;/strong&gt; ability is an Area Burst 2 with a range of 10 squares. It
hits &lt;em&gt;automatically&lt;/em&gt; and forces every enemy in the area to use an at-will power
of the inquisitor’s choice against themselves! Thankfully it’s an encounter
power that recharges when the inquisitor is first bloodied, but it’s still rough
on those Essentials martials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the inquisitor can force an &lt;strong&gt;Unwilling Confession&lt;/strong&gt; from an
enemy within 10 squares. This is an attack against Will, and though it does no
damage it prevents the victim from being affected by healing and by powers that
grant saves (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, when the inquisitor sees an enemy succeed at a saving throw, they
can use &lt;strong&gt;Forceful Submission&lt;/strong&gt; to force them to re-roll that save with a -2
penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inquisitors work well with a solid frontline of brutes or soldiers who can keep
them safe and isolate possible victims for melee attacks. They also pair well
with other monsters loaded with save-ends powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mind-flayer-scourge&quot;&gt;Mind Flayer Scourge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flavor text here tells the story of how early surface psionics honed their
abilities by raiding mind flayer lairs and trying to steal their secrets. The
discipline of the mind flayer scourge was developed in response to these
raids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scourges are Level 21 Skirmishers with 199 HP. They have Resist 10 Psychic,
which does help a lot against most psionic PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have the usual grabby &lt;strong&gt;tentacles&lt;/strong&gt; and dazing &lt;strong&gt;mind blast&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
5+). Their tentacles also daze the grabbed victim while the grab lasts, and
the &lt;strong&gt;Mind Leech&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait allows them to make an extra saving throw or
recharge roll while grabbing a victim. They can even recharge their &lt;strong&gt;Psychic
Assault&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power with a roll of 6+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychic Assault targets the grabbed victim’s Will. On a hit it deals a bit of
psychic damage and dominates the victim (save ends, but with a -4 penalty). On a
miss, it deals half damage and &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; dominates the victim (save ends). As
mentioned above this is an encounter power but the scourge can recharge it with
Mind Leech. It’s extremely bad news for the PCs. Scourges prefer to use it on
spellcasters or psionics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If surrounded, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Alter Reality&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to teleport an
adjacent enemy 2 squares, allowing them to potentially disengage from a defender
without triggering any reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thoon-hulk&quot;&gt;Thoon Hulk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind flayers aren’t a very religious lot, but there is at least one entity they
speak of with the reverence others would reserve for a god. Its name is Thoon,
and that’s pretty much all non-illithids know about the subject. Whatever
relationship Thoon might have with these brutish monstrosities remains a
mystery, but they do show us that mind flayers have no problem performing
horrific experiments on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoon Hulks are much stronger and less intelligent than a typical mind flayer,
but they still retain their psionic powers. They’re found as servants to
“baseline” mind flayers and to other powerful aberrants like aboleths. They’re
Level 22 Brutes with 255 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hulk’s basic attack is named &lt;strong&gt;Eviscerate&lt;/strong&gt;, and uses its giant axe
hands. This deals extra damage against creatures grabbed by the hulk. It can
still grab using &lt;strong&gt;tentacles&lt;/strong&gt;, which do no damage but are a minor action. This
means it can grab and eviscerate on the same turn. Its &lt;strong&gt;mind blast&lt;/strong&gt; is the
usual psychic damage + daze combo, but it happens a little less often (recharge
6+). Once per encounter it can focus its powers and issue the &lt;strong&gt;Call of Thoon&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 10 vs. Will), which does heavy psychic damage and pulls the target up to
10 squares so it ends up adjacent to the hulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the hulk dies, it triggers a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Explosion&lt;/strong&gt;, which covers a Close
Burst 2 and inflicts ongoing 15 psychic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hulks are excellent front-liners, and the Call of Thoon also allows them to pull
a PC squishy into Eviscerate range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-brain&quot;&gt;Elder Brain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, Elder Brains are the big bosses of a medium-to-large
illithid enclave. They rule with absolute authority and live in ooze vats that
amplify their powers and allow them to communicate with their subjects over vast
distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting to an elder brain’s vat is an adventure in itself, since it will
inevitably be in the most secure and heavily guarded part of a sizable illithid
enclave. Once there, the PCs will have to contend with the brain itself and with
whatever bodyguards are in the chamber with it. Elder Brains are usually too
arrogant to run away from a fight, though they may change their tunes after
their bodyguards are taken down and they’re reduced to low HP. However, getting
there is harder than it looks, because not only can the brain fight, it can also
&lt;em&gt;move&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elder Brains are Large Aberrant Magical Beasts with the Blind keyword. They have
Blindsight 10 and are immune to the blinded condition and to gaze attacks. They
have a ground speed of 2 and a teleport speed of 6, which I think is a first in
the game - earlier edition brains were pretty much confined to their vats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brains are Level 23 Elite Controllers with 436 HP. They start off with a host of
passive traits. The first, &lt;strong&gt;Warp Reality&lt;/strong&gt; is an aura (5) that deals 10 damage
to any enemy that teleports while inside. The second, &lt;strong&gt;Absorb Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;,
grants the brain a saving throw or recharge roll whenever a non-minion ally
drops to 0 HP within 10 squares. And the third, &lt;strong&gt;Unseeing Telepathy&lt;/strong&gt;, allows
it to communicate telepathically even when it doesn’t have line of effect to the
other creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warp Reality’s effect doesn’t care whether it was the enemy who initiated the
teleport, or if someone else teleported the enemy. Damage happens either
way. This is important because most of the elder brain’s attacks teleport the
target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic melee attack is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Warp&lt;/strong&gt;, which does light physical
damage, teleports the target 3 squares, and immobilizes them for a
turn. &lt;strong&gt;Flailing Warp&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make three such attacks in a single
action, each against a different target. Instead of a mind blast, they have a
&lt;strong&gt;mind burst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which targets all enemies in a Close Burst 5 with
the usual effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use &lt;strong&gt;Sensory Overload&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action, which works almost
identically to the mind burst. It does a little less damage, and instead of
dazing it blinds and deafens for a turn &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; teleports the target 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, every time the elder brain successfully saves against an effect,
&lt;strong&gt;Baleful Transfer&lt;/strong&gt; automatically afflicts an enemy within 5 squares with the
effect the brain just saved against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stats seem to reward aggressive tactics. All of the brain’s attacks have a
range that’s equal or less than that of its aura, so it wants to fight from
close range. It will probably try to teleport to be near the PC’s squishier back
line, using Tentacle Warps to keep them close and to keep defenders away. It
also has enough melee reach to fight from behind a wall of soldiers or brutes,
and pairs well with other enemies that inflict forced teleports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the mind flayers here have interesting mechanics, and I particularly like
this edition’s take on the elder brain as a highly mobile close-range
combatant. It’s probably the last thing your players will expect if they’re used
to the more static depiction from other editions.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/16/mind-flayer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/16/mind-flayer.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Mimic</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-mimic.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mimics have been in the game since its beginning, and are are one of D&amp;amp;D’s most
iconic monsters. They’re also notable for originating within D&amp;amp;D and “breaking
out” to become a popular monster in other games and media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image of a trasure chest growing teeth and eating the hapless adventurer
trying to open it is a popular classic even within D&amp;amp;D’s own implied
setting. Everyone knows it, and most think it’s a pretty funny joke. Everyone
but those who have actually gone through this and survived the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mimics are highly intelligent creatures originating from the Far Realm. Despite
their intelligence they don’t seem to be interested in friendly relations with
other sapients, and are mostly interested in using their smarts to fool and eat
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth edition mimics also take over the “murderous alien shapeshifter” role
from doppelgangers, which as we saw before are now mostly just people. You see,
the classic chest mimic is actually a juvenile individual. As it matures, it
gains the ability to absorb the memories of the people they devour and to take
their shapes. These impersonator mimics infiltrate mortal society, moving around
and taking different shapes as they feed. They reproduce by budding. Their spawn
spend a time joined to the mass of their parent before setting out on their own
as object mimics. In an emergency, the parent can reabsorb them for a quick
burst of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mimics rarely seek out alliances, but they often enter a symbiotic relationship
with inedible monsters like constructs or incorporeal undead. The mimic will
lure victims to the other monster’s lair, and help with the fight so it can eat
the bodies later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mimics are Medium Aberrant Magical Beasts. They have Resist Acid 5/tier,
Darkvision, and Tremorsense 5. Their signature ability, of course, is
&lt;strong&gt;Shapeshift&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability allows a mimic to switch between Ooze and Object forms. In Ooze
form, it gains the standard Ooze ability to ignore all penalties for squeezing
through small spaces. In object form, it can’t attack but gains Resist 10 to all
damage and others must succeed at a Perception check to notice it’s a mimic. The
DC varies with the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;object-mimic&quot;&gt;Object Mimic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, this is a junevile of the species and the one PCs are most
likely to meet first. It’s a Level 8 Lurker with 71 HP, Speed 5, and all
standard traits listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mimics have an &lt;strong&gt;Ambush&lt;/strong&gt; trait that gives them 2d6 bonus damage on all
attacks against surprised victims. The creature has two attacks beyond its basic
&lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;strong&gt;Crushing Tendrils&lt;/strong&gt; do light physical damage, grab the target (with
a -5 penalty to escape) and inflict ongoing 15 acid damage while the grab
lasts. &lt;strong&gt;Ravening Maw&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) does heavy physical damage and slows (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either of these special attacks would make a good opener against a surprised
victim, benefitting from combat advantage and from bonus Ambush damage. The
Perception DC to pierce the mimic’s disguise is 24. They usually take forms that
are enticing to their potential prey - a treasure chest is a classic for luring
adventurers, but any other Medium object will do. Berry bushes, fancy statues,
comfy chairs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impersonator-mimic&quot;&gt;Impersonator Mimic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an older specimen that specializes in impersonating its victims and
infiltrating mortal society. Unlike the monstrous doppelganger of editions past,
impersonator mimics are more interested in &lt;em&gt;food&lt;/em&gt; than in political power. Their
main goal at any given time alternates between staying hidden and luring their
next victim to an isolated spot. They can use psychic powers to help with those
goals, in addition to their shapeshifting and mundane deception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impersonator Mimics are Level 16 Controllers with 160 HP. The impersonator’s
&lt;strong&gt;Shapeshift&lt;/strong&gt; ability allows them to take humanoid form in addition to the two
standard ones. This form gives them a +4 bonus to Bluff and allows them to use
all languages known by the last person they killed. The DC to pierce any of the
impersonator’s disguises is 31.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its attacks are the usual &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt;, and a pair of psychic powers. &lt;strong&gt;Forcible
Conversion&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a non-damaging melee power that attacks Will
dominates its target (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Call to Harvest&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action) is a
non-damaging ranged power that also attacks Will. On a hit, it slides the target
4 squares and makes it grant combat advantage for a turn. Finally, as a free
action, they can &lt;strong&gt;Absorb&lt;/strong&gt; a mimic spawn that’s adjacent to them or occupying
their space. This kills the spawn and gives them 1 Action Point. This does make
it one of the few regular monsters with access to action points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that only the object form forbids the mimic from attacking - they can use
all of these abilities in humanoid form without having to shapeshift, and they
can Absorb in any form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mimic-spawn&quot;&gt;Mimic Spawn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very young mimic that hasn’t left the “care” of its parent yet. It can already
shapeshift into objects, and it can also meld into its parent’s form for
protection and increased stealth. This does make it susceptible to being
re-absorbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spawn are Level 16 Minion Lurkers, which make them suitable for hanging out with
impersonator mimics. Not every impersonator will have spawn, but those who do
will be a bit more dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;One With Master&lt;/strong&gt; trait represents the spawn’s ability to merge with its
parent. A merged spawn occupies the same space as the parent, cannot attack, and
cannot be targeted or take damage. Up to four spawn can meld to a single
impersonator. Their only attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that does average damage for a
minion of this level. The DC to pierce their object disguise is 31.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You just gotta have mimics available in a D&amp;amp;D game. I don’t think I’ve ever used
one, but I feel good just knowing that they exist. I guess it took the authors
a long time to come up with cool mechanics for their shapeshifting, which is why
it took a while for them to asppear appear in 4e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level mechanics make it seem that mimics start their lives pretty good at
shapeshifting and get worse at it for a while before reaching their former level
of skill, but that’s just a mechanical artifact. Levels can be adjusted freely -
you could easily have lower-level spawn and higher level object mimics.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/13/mimic.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/13/mimic.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Meenlock</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-meenlock.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another one from the 1e Fiend Folio, though its lore is new for this edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monster is considered “aberrant” in 4e when their origins or workings are
heavily tied to the Far Realm. Usually this means they come from the Far Realm,
but that’s not the case with meenlocks. Meenlocks are the victims of an alien
disease, and it’s this disease that comes from that horrible place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as Meenlock Corruption, it eventually changes its victims into naked mole
rat/crab hybrids like those in the illustration. Meenlocks gather together in
subterranean lairs built in caves, ruins, or in the shallow Underdark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These lairs usually have relatively easy access to the surface, with at most an
easily-rolled boulder blocking their main entrance. The creatures themselves
scatter and hide when their lairs are invaded, fighting only when cornered. All
of this is because their main defense is Meenlock Corruption itself. Anyone who
enters their lairs is exposed to the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the corruption progresses, it dominates the victim’s mind and compels them to
return to the lair where they were infected. If such a victim spends more than
two days in there, they turn into a new meenlock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meenlocks are driven to seek new victims as well - that’s how they increase
their numbers. To that end they can ally with other creatures who are themselves
resistant to their infection, in exchange for victims who are not. Potential
allies include foulspawn, or powerful evil wizards and psions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text of the book is a bit confusing but it looks like it’s possible to
restore someone who was turned into a meenlock. You need to kill the creature,
burn its body, and then apply the Remove Affliction and Raise Dead rituals to
the remains. How’s that for an extreme treatment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by detailing the &lt;strong&gt;Meenlock Corruption&lt;/strong&gt; disease. It’s a Level 9
Disease, with an improve DC of 20, and a Maintain DC of 15. Unlike most other
diseases, its resistance rolls use Insight instead of Endurance. Stage One
inflicts a -4 Will penalty. Stage Two makes the victim grant combat
advantage. Stage Three makes the victim become dominated by the meenlocks who
infected it, and driven to return to their lair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual for 4e diseases, when you reach Stage Three you stop making resistance
rolls to improve. A Remove Affiction ritual might be able to save the victim if
performed before the transformation is complete. Otherwise you need the more
drastic procedure described above (kill them, burn the body, Remove Affliction,
Raise Dead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meenlocks themselves are Small Aberrant Humanoids with Speed 5 and
Darkvision. Their signature ability is Dimension Step (recharge 4+), a move
action that allows them to teleport 8 squares. All of them fight with their
claws and with a suite of mental powers blending fey magic and aberrant
psionics. The specifics vary per individual stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meenlock-stalker&quot;&gt;Meenlock Stalker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalkers possess powers that make them particularly suitable for the gathering
of new victims. They’re Level 9 Controllers with 97 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat, a Stalker will first and foremost try to forge a &lt;strong&gt;Horrid Link&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor action, recharge 4+) with a victim. It has a range of 10 squares and
happens automatically. Whenever the stalker takes damage, the linked victim
takes 1d10+5 damage. The link lasts for a turn or until the stalker uses the
power again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stalker can then use two powers against the linked victim. Both are ranged
attacks targetting Will and inflicting light psychic damage, with different
rider effects. &lt;strong&gt;Maddening Whispers&lt;/strong&gt; dazes (save ends). And &lt;strong&gt;Twisting
Whispers&lt;/strong&gt; force the victim to make a basic attack against a creature of the
stalker’s choice. It also exposes the victim to Meenlock Corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; are simple basic attacks with average damage, so stalkers have
an incentive to stay away from the PCs and work solely through the Horrid
Link. Their default goal in a fight is to infect as many PCs as possible with
Meenlock Corruption, though they might have others depending on who they’re
allied with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meenlock-corruptor&quot;&gt;Meenlock Corruptor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one trades damage potential for increased control. It’s devastating to
party cohesion in both defensive and offensive ambushes. It’s a Level 11 Lurker
with 89 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, its &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are simple basic attacks. The star of the show here is
&lt;strong&gt;Corrupting Mind&lt;/strong&gt;, a very complex at-will ranged attack. It deals no damage
itself, but does a lot of other things. First, it exposes the target to meenlock
corruption. Then, it inflicts a custom condition named Mental Disarray (save
ends). A target affected by this is considered dominated, gains 2d6 bonus damage
to all attacks, and is unable to see the corruptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failing the first save against mental disarray makes the condition last until
the end of the encounter! Whenever a victim in this state takes more than 10
damage, the meenlock corruptor takes the same amount, and the victim can make a
saving throw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter the corruptor can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; to hit a
close blast 5, dealing psychic damage and knocking targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, another dominator that’s worse than a succubus. Since Corrupting Mind
is at-will, it’s possible that the whole party would get dominated at once when
fighting a corruptor. The more of them you add to a single encounter, the bigger
the chance of this happening. Once a target is dominated for the encounter, Team
Monster should avoid attacking them. It’s up to the PCs to do those 10+ damage
to their mind-controlled friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another disease-themed monster that tackles its theme in a creative
manner. Not many diseases use Insight instead of Endurance. Your beefy
Endurance-trained defenders will get a nasty shock if the party doesn’t figure
this out before exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, both of them are quite dangerous. PCs fighting an all-meenlock
encounter group will spend as much time attacking each other as they will
fighting the monsters. The corruptor is particularly terrifying in this
regard. If possible, avoid using more than one of those in an encounter group
unless you want your PCs to really suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/11/meenlock.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/11/meenlock.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Meazels</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-meazel.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first time I’m seeing this monster, but it’s been around since the
1e Fiend Folio. Most iterations kept the same haircut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, a certain city was ravaged by a plague. Many died from both the
disease itself and from the violence that erupted as starvation, terror and rage
gripped the citizens. When everything seemed to be lost, those that were still
alive heard a soothing voice in their ears. It said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Your gods have fled this place. The spirits of the world no longer walk with
you. Your mages’ spells have failed you. In your hour of need, I alone hear your
pleas.” This entity proposed a simple bargain. The people of this city would
swear fealty to it, and in exchange the plague would cause no more deaths and
they would enjoy limitless food forever more. Out of carelessness or
desperation, the people accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out the soothing voice belonged to Baalzebul, the archdevil ruler of the
seventh hell. And as in any devil’s bargain, he fulfilled his promises to the
letter. His new servants no longer died from the plague, but they still caught
it and suffered from the weeping sores and endless hunger that were its hallmark
symptoms. The only thing that could nourish them and quell this hunger was the
flesh of other sapient beings, which technically counts as a “limitless” source
of food if you tally the world’s population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These wretched creatures soon left their original city and spread through the
world, to fulfill the will of their new master and to look for new food
sources. They became known as Meazels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meazels rarely work with other sapients, because they can’t resist their hunger
for long. They prefer to work with trained or magically controlled beasts, and
their spellcasters can also summon and bind elementals. Some groups of Meazels
leave Baalzebul’s service and pledge allegiance to others who promise to rid
them of their curse. Most of these end up being Baalzebul’s rival devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meazels are Medium Natural Humanoids, usually former humans. They have a ground
speed of 6 and Darkvision. They’re immune to disease, but suffer from an
infernal curse that mimics the symptoms of that original plague. This manifests
as the &lt;strong&gt;Wretched Curse of Baalzebul&lt;/strong&gt;, their signature ability. It’s an aura
(1) that inflicts the same symptoms on any enemy inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afflicted enemies take a -2 penalty to all defenses and become vulnerable 5 to
all damage while inside the aura. They also inflict the same effects on any of
their allies who are adjacent to them but outside the aura. Auras from multiple
meazels don’t stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their other abilities all come from training, and vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meazel-bravo&quot;&gt;Meazel Bravo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are rank-and-file frontline fighters. Their tactics are straightforward -
charge in and hit the enemy until it stops moving. Their curse aura makes them
extra-effective in close quarters, and they love narrow terrain that leaves
their enemies little room to maneuver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bravos are Level 11 Brutes with 136 HP. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Morningstar&lt;/strong&gt;.
They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Gut Shot&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge 5+), which does slightly
less damage but weakens the enemy for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that neither attack takes the aura into account in their damage formulas,
which means they hit even harder than standard Brute of their level. Anyone in
reach of either attack is also inside the aura!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meazel-hunter&quot;&gt;Meazel Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunters are archers that like to coat their arrows in their own cursed
blood. Their preferred tactic is to snipe at their targets from behind a wall of
bravos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hunters are Level 12 Artillery with 88 HP. They fight in melee with &lt;strong&gt;Spears&lt;/strong&gt;
that benefit from their aura, but prefer to stay back and use their
&lt;strong&gt;Longbows&lt;/strong&gt;. Their basic ranged attack damages and slows for a turn on a
hit. They can use a &lt;strong&gt;Distracting Shot&lt;/strong&gt; instead, doing the same amount of
damage and forcing the target to grant combat advantage for a turn. Once per
encounter they can do the blood-dipping thing and fire a &lt;strong&gt;Plague-Tainted Shot&lt;/strong&gt;
that does the same damage and inflicts 10 ongoing necrotic damage (save
ends). While this effect remains, any of the target’s allies that starts their
turn adjacent to them takes 10 necrotic damage as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plague shot is an interesting way to disrupt PC formations, since anyone
adjacent to a stricken victim will have an incentive to move away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meazel-strangler&quot;&gt;Meazel Strangler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While bravos and hunters do the obvious battling, stranglers sneak around the
edges of the fight looking for isolated enemies they can drag away. They’re
Level 13 Controllers with 125 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their attacks are Reach 1, so they all benefit from the aura. The basic
attack is a &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt;, but the real star of the show is the
&lt;strong&gt;Garrote&lt;/strong&gt;. Its intiial attack is weaker, but it grabs the target on a
hit. (Athletics DC 24 or Acrobatics DC 26 to escape). In subsequent rounds the
Strangler can spend a standard action to sustain the grab and deal a heavy chunk
of physical damage to the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Plage Touch&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude, does
immediate and ongoing necrotic damage, and blinds (save ends both). It’s a good
opener to make that wizard easier to strangle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action, the strangler can use &lt;strong&gt;Drag to the Feast&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it
to move its speed and pull the grabbed victim along without provoking
opportunity attacks from them. Other PCs can still make OAs against the meazel,
but any that miss damage the grabbed victim instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of the meazels is the story of a bunch of people who, when faced
with the spread of a dangerous disease, chose to abandon science and put their
faith in an instant cure sold by a charlatan. They suffered the consequences and
still decided to double down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will note that this entry was written way back in 2010. Any similarity between
meazels and anti-maskers, anti-vaxxers, and chloroquine/ivermectin enthusiasts
is mere coincidence. Mechanically, they’re okay. The aura makes for some nice
synergies with their other abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/10/meazel.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/10/meazel.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Lolth</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-lolth.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lolth is likely to be among the very first Big Bads of D&amp;amp;D. I think her first
officially published mention was in The Village of Hommlet, an adventure
published in 1979 featuring one of her priests as the final antagonist. Since
that adventure and the Temple of Elemental Evil that follows it were all based
on Gary Gygax’s original campaign, there’s a chance Lolth was was a thing for a
few years before that even though she doesn’t appear in the first Monster
Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She would make a personal appearance in 1980’s Queen of the Demonweb Pits, where
she officially became the patron goddess of the drow and started getting a lot
more publicity. The drow and their goddess would get plenty of spotlight time in
that edition and all subsequent ones, for good and ill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we get to this entry in the MM3, we’ve already seen most
Lolth-associated monster make their appearances, populating the entire range
from heroic to epic tier. We also heard a lot about Lolth herself as a goddess
in other supplements. This is where we finally get her stats. She is the second
“epic end boss” to make an appearance in this book, but not the last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lolth is described by the DMG as the goddess of shadows, lies, and spiders. As
we saw in the various Drow entries, back in mythic times she led a major
uprising against the other elven gods. Her defeat in that civil war saw her and
her proto-elf fey followers banished from the Feywild. Her followers moved to
the Underdark, where over time they evolved into the drow. Lolth herself took up
residence in the Abyss, crafting a whole layer of it into her personal domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I remember correctly, some of the divine-oriented supplements hint that
Corellon wasn’t entirely innocent in all of this, and that the reason Lolth rose
up against him is that he committed a great injustice against her. It wouldn’t
be too far off the mark to say that she wasn’t evil back then, and that it was
either the trauma of this first betrayal or a few aeons of living in the Abyss
that made her so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of her past history, the Lolth of &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; is certainly Chaotic
Evil. Her followers organize themselves into strict hierarchies whose goal is to
enable an endless cycle of bloody betrayal: the powerful are free to abuse the
weak, and the weak are encouraged to rise in power by murdering their rivals and
superiors. Lolth herself doesn’t much trust her followers as we’ve seen in past
entries: she created at least two monsters whose main purpose is to infiltrate
those hierarchies and keep an eye on their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in a way, you could say Lolth is the goddess of the cycle of abuse. She
inflicts on her followers the same suffering she went through long ago, and
encourages them to do the same to their subordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her dominion is the sixty-sixth layer of the Abyss, a place known as the
Demonweb. As the name implies it’s a gigantic web strung across a series of
titanic pillars. On its strands rest many relics stolen from other worlds,
ranging from standard magic items all the way up to entire ruined
cities. Beneath the Web is a black void, and at the bottom of this void are the
Demonweb Pits, Lolth’s true headquarters. Here is where she holds court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pits contain a multitude of portals to other layers of the Abyss and to
other planes entirely, and they’re one of the reasons why Lolth’s machinations
have such a large reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry contains stats not only for Lolth, but also for her Aspect and her
Exarch. We’ll describe them in order of level, like we’ve been doing for the
other big shots in this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no entries for Lolth’s cultists. Most of them are the drow described
in the other monster books, as well as the Abyssal Drow and the Chitine from
this one. Like the other big bads, Lolth can certainly have cultists from other
species as well, using “generic” stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aspect-of-lolth&quot;&gt;Aspect of Lolth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aspects are fragments of a deity’s power and mind. They share the original
deity’s personality and goals, but their existence is independent. Though
they’re never as powerful as the original deity, they’re still epic-tier. These
used to be called “avatars” in previous editions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most gods send their aspects to aid their most favored mortal servants, usually
in response to a ritual requesting this aid. Lolth is an exception. Anyone who
would have the power to call an aspect of Lolth is sufficiently initiated into
her mysteries to know that this is a &lt;em&gt;very bad idea&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, they spend their
effort making sure she never has cause to send one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is what Lolth sends her aspects as infiltrators whose goal
is to influence drow society in ways that align with her goals. The aspect’s
natural form is that of a giant demonic spider, but it can assume the form of a
drow. It’s usual MO is to kill and replace an authority figure, and use the
victim’s power and influence to fulfill its mission. When forced to fight, it
reverts to its true form and “generously” spends the lives of its underlings to
buy victory, or at least survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aspects of Lolth are Level 25 Elite Lurkers with 368 HP. They’re Large Immortal
Magical Beasts in their natural forms, but shrink to Medium size when disguised
as drow. They have ground and Spider Climb speeds of 6, Darkvision, and
Blindsight 5. They have Resist 30 Poison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an aspect hits a creature granting &lt;strong&gt;Combat Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; to it, that
creature is weakened and takes 20 ongoing poison damage (save ends both) in
addition to suffering all the standard effects of the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;. It can also shoot &lt;strong&gt;Acid Webs&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) in
a Clost Blast 5. This deals acid damage and slows (save ends). On the first
failed save, the target also begins taking 20 ongoing acid damage until they
pass a save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a nasty power named &lt;strong&gt;Worthy Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt;, an area burst attack
centered on a non-minion drow, spider, or demon ally. This causes the ally to
explode into gory webs, reducing it to 0 HP, and attacks the Reflex of every
enemy in the blast area. This attack doesn’t damage enemies, but immobilizes all
those it hits (save ends). It also creates a zone of webbed gore that lasts
until the end of the encounter and immobilizes any non-spider who ends their
move inside (save ends). This recharges when the Aspect is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As minor actions, the aspect can create a &lt;strong&gt;Cloud of Darkness&lt;/strong&gt; that blinds and
blocks line of sight for anyone but itself; and &lt;strong&gt;Change Shape&lt;/strong&gt; to appear as a
Medium drow. The Insight DC to pierce the disguise is 43, hard even for someone
who min-maxed their Insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone moves adjacent to the aspect, it can use its &lt;strong&gt;Impaling Legs&lt;/strong&gt; as an
interrupt. This is an attack that deals physical damage and grabs the
target. Grabbed targets take 10 ongoing poison damage until they escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being immobilized doesn’t actually make you grant combat advantage, but being
blinded does. The Aspect should fight alongside allies who can flank the
immobilized PCs. Worthy Sacrifice should be reserved to use on an ally who’s
about to die anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eclavdra-exarch-of-lolth&quot;&gt;Eclavdra, Exarch of Lolth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-lolth-eclavdra.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclavdra has an interesting publication history. Turns out &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt; is the actual
final boss of the GDQ series, the one who used to be behind the giant attacks
and everything. And she’s not even a Lolth worshipper there! Facing Lolth in
those modules is more of a weird detour than the actual thing that solves the
problem. A reference to this makes it into her description here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclavdra is described by the book as the “quintessential drow”. Another way of
putting it might be that no one in the universe has a deeper understanding of
Lolth’s mysteries aside from the goddess herself. This means Eclavdra is both
Lolth’s greatest ally and her most dangerous enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclavdra has tried to betray Lolth not once, but &lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt;. The first time she
worked with the Elder Elemental Eye (that’s the GDQ adventures), and the second
she worked with Graz’zt. She still carries a relic of the Eye, the Tentacle Rod,
and uses it as her main weapon and implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these previous betrayals, Eclavdra has not only remained in Lolth’s good
graces, but her standing seems to have &lt;em&gt;improved&lt;/em&gt;. Maybe the Lady of Spiders
admires her audacity. When roleplaying Eclavdra, it would not be out of place to
take your cues from Vriska and Starscream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclavdra is a drow, and thus a Medium Fey Humanoid. She’s also a Level 28 Elite
Soldier with the Leader keyword. She has the drow’s Speed 7 and Darkvision. She
has no special resistances, even to poison, because Lolth is not stupid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As she is the &lt;strong&gt;Spider Queen’s Emissary&lt;/strong&gt;, any demon, drow, and spider allies
within 5 squares of Eclavdra have a +2 bonus to attack and can shift 1 square as
a minor action. Her &lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Rod&lt;/strong&gt; is stretchy and has Reach 3. It can be used
in a few special maneuvers in addition to giving her a basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tentacle Lash&lt;/strong&gt; has the same reach and damage as a basic attack, but on a hit
it also strips all poison resistance or immunity from the target &lt;em&gt;for the rest
of the encounter&lt;/em&gt;. The target is also slowed (save ends). This is an at-will
power!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insidious Offer&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged spell that deals very weak psychic damage for
its level… but on a hit it forces one of those interesting choices I like so
much. The target must choose between taking an extra 30 psychic damage from the
attack, or becoming dominated (save ends). That’s very in theme - it’s not
“real” betrayal if it’s not a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclavdra’s minor-action attacks are an unfortunate throwback to the “sexy
dominatrix drow” days. &lt;strong&gt;Entrancing Beauty&lt;/strong&gt; is a Close Burst 5 that targets all
enemies, deals light psychic damage, and pulls then 2 squares on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;On
Your Knees&lt;/strong&gt; is a non-damaging attack with the tentacle rod that makes the
target fall prone and prevents them from standing up (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Blinking Escape&lt;/strong&gt; allows Eclavdra to teleport 6 squares and gain
concealment as a reaction when she’s hit by a close or area attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclavdra is loathe to risk her own life. She will make use of guile and
manipulation to prevent hostilities from initiating, and when they do she will
use her underlings as shields. When the tide of battle turns against her, she
will attempt to run away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lolth-the-demon-queen-of-spiders&quot;&gt;Lolth, The Demon Queen of Spiders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no need to repeat the lore of Lolth here - it’s all up at the start of
the article. Mechanically, she is notable for being the first official two-stage
boss I’ve seen. I believe she’s also the first actual god to get stats in this
edition, and the most powerful endgame boss so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means she has two stat blocks! The first is her drow form, in which she is
a Level 35 Solo Lurker with 634 HP. When she hits 0 HP in this form, she becomes
a Huge demonic spider who is a Level 35 Solo Brute with another 634 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both forms Lolth has ground, climb, and teleport speeds of 8. She also has
Darkvision, Blindsight 20, and is immune to poison. Her remaining abilities are
entirely different in both forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her &lt;strong&gt;drow form&lt;/strong&gt;, Lolth fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Scourge&lt;/strong&gt;, a multi-tailed whip. Its
attacks are Reach 3, do some light physical damage, and slide the target 3
squares. They also inflict ongoing 20 poison damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She can use the &lt;strong&gt;Insidious Poison&lt;/strong&gt; ability (recharge 4+) to automatically
force an enemy that’s taking ongoing poison damage to attack an ally. That
attack deals a lot of extra poison damage as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has three minor-action attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Lolth’s Kiss&lt;/strong&gt; is a Reach 1 melee attack
that deals a bit less damage than the scourge, but inflicts the same amount of
ongoing poison damage. &lt;strong&gt;Poison Strands&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack that deals no
immediate damage but immobilizes (save ends). After the first saved throw, this
worsens to Restrained. After the second the target begins taking &lt;em&gt;50 ongoing
poison damage&lt;/em&gt; until they pass a save to end all of this at once. That’s the
deadliest poison in existence! And yeah, both of these are at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third is an encounter power: &lt;strong&gt;Impenetrable Darkfire&lt;/strong&gt; is a Close Burst 5
that targets enemies. It blinds, inflicts 20 ongoing fire damage, and makes
it impossible for them to benefit from cover or concealment (save ends all). It
also creates a zone that lasts for a turn, blocks line of sight for everyone
but Lolth, and blinds anyone inside who is not Lolth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy hits Lolth, she can use a &lt;strong&gt;Dominating Rebuke&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to
&lt;em&gt;automatically&lt;/em&gt; dominate them for a turn. And as a deity, her &lt;strong&gt;Immortal
Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; allows her to immediately roll a save when she is inflicted by any
effect a save can end. This is a “No Action” effect, meaning it &lt;em&gt;always
happens&lt;/em&gt;, giving her a 75% chance of ignoring all save ends effects outright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transformation that happens when Drow Lolth hits 0 HP is also an attack. It
targets all enemies in a Close Burst 10. On a hit they become vulnerable 20 to
all damage, and are stunned (save ends both). As an aftereffect after passing
the save, they’re pushed their speed away from her and are dazed for a
turn. After this resolves, Lolth assumes her spider shape, and uses that stat
block going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lolth the Spider Queen&lt;/strong&gt; is, as mentioned, a Huge spider and a Level 35
Brute. Her basic attack is now a &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; that deals much stronger base damage
and still inflicts 20 ongoing poison damage. &lt;strong&gt;Insidious Poison&lt;/strong&gt; is still here
and work the same, but the damage bonus is bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action she can spray &lt;strong&gt;Burning Webs&lt;/strong&gt; in a Close Burst 5 that deal acid
damage and immobilize (save ends). After failing the first saving throw, victims
are restrained instead and take 30 ongoing acid damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immortal Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; is still here and works the same. She also has
&lt;strong&gt;Impaling Legs&lt;/strong&gt; like those of her Aspect, but they’re Reach 3 and trigger when
an enemy moves into reach. A target hit by the attack is restrained and begins
taking ongoing 20 poison damage (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when Spider Lolth is first bloodied, she uses &lt;strong&gt;Divine Discorporation&lt;/strong&gt;
to escape. This works automatically, and causes her mind to leave her body and
be unable to assume physical shape for a while. This period can last several
years, and while Lolth’s power will be greatly diminished during this time she’s
still alive and can direct her forces. A bit like Sauron in Lord of the Rings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To truly kill Lolth, the PCs must fulfill a condition or complete a quest that’s
specific to her. If this happens, then she’s prevented from discorporating and
can be fought until truly killed. The book presents three example quests, and
the GM is encouraged to come up with something that fits their specific world
and campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example quests are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Loom of Fate&lt;/strong&gt;, an artifact hidden deep within Corellon’s palace in
Arvandor. It was once used by Lolth, and it can be used by the PCs to
rearrange the threads of her fate and make her defeatable. Corellon knows this
but fears to use it. What doesn’t he want you to know?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Egg of Lolth&lt;/strong&gt;, a mysterious artifact that can be destroyed to seal the
gates going out of the Demonweb Pits and thus prevent Lolth’s escape. But
then how do you get out?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lolth’s Prison&lt;/strong&gt;, a demiplane beyond even the Demonweb Pits, where a dread
Bone Colossus guards the Pendant of Truth. Brandishing the Pendant before the
goddess of lies prevents her from discorporating. How will you get there, and
what truths will you find within?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these enemies are quite interesting mechanically. I particularly like
Lolth’s two-stage-boss design. Her drow form is all about the insidious
poisoning of mind and body. Her attacks deal little immediate damage, and the
riders are what kills you. The spider form is a lot more direct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Level 35 monster, a max-level party is going to have some trouble hitting
Lolth and avoiding her strikes. This fortunately doesn’t affect saves, but even
so the PC’s leaders should have plenty of save-granting abilities and items on
hand, because failing those saves has dreadful consequences. Conversely, offense
should focus on abilities that deal direct non-poison damage and whose riders
are either immediate or last a turn, because she’s almost immune to anything
that requires a save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love Eclavdra’s description as a Starscream figure. That even works as a
proper elven surname if you want it to be really on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/07/lolth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/07/lolth.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Kuo-Toa</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-kuo-toa.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kuo-toa made their 4e debut in the Monster Manual, and would get a MV style
upgrade in Dungeon 193. This entry gives us extra stat blocks that don’t overlap
with either, even though it came out months before the Dungeon update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kuo-Toa basic lore remains the same. They’re the spear-wielding fish people that
live in the Underdark and worship aboleths and other aberrant entities. Their
priests, known as whips, are their absolute rulers, and discipline is enforced
by individuals known as monitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry adds that whips and monitors are able to force their underlings to
follow a coherent combat strategy even though those underlings tend to be very
mentally unstable. If these leaders fall before their underlings, the group’s
tactics will become a lot more erratic. Some will run, some will go berserk, and
so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All kuo-toa in this entry have ground and swim speeds of 6. They are Aquatic and
have Darkvision. Their signature ability is Slick Maneuver, a move action that
can be used when they’re adjacent to an enemy and allows them to shift 3
squares, though they must end the move still adjacent to the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kuo-toa-mad-one&quot;&gt;Kuo-Toa Mad One&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can guess from the name, Mad Ones are unstable even by the standards of
other kuo-toa. They’re afflicted by a form of supernatural insanity that
originates in the Far Realm and is contagious. They hang around old ruins and
temples, worshipping and guarding ancient artifacts far away from the rest of
their society. If one of these is stolen, they’ll give chase to punish the
thieves and recover the relic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mad Ones are Level 12 Minion Skirmishers, and notably lack Slick
Maneuver. Instead, they have an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Spreading Madness&lt;/strong&gt; that gives all
enemies inside 5 Vulnerability to psychic damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks damage
and allow them to shift 1 square on a hit. They can also release a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic
Scream&lt;/strong&gt; in a Close Blast 3. It deals a small amount of psychic damage, though
that gets a boost from Spreading Madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kuo-toa-drowner&quot;&gt;Kuo-Toa Drowner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drowners specialize on raiding ships and dragging their crews to a watery
doom. They wield hooks and barbed nets in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drowners are Level 14 Soldiers with 137 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;hooks&lt;/strong&gt; can be used for
basic attacks and for a &lt;strong&gt;Dredging Hook&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that does the same damage as
a basic attack and slides the target 3 squares to another square adjacent to the
kuo-toa. Combined with Slick Maneuver, this makes the process of dragging a
victim overboard into a sort of spiral dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Barbed Net&lt;/strong&gt; can be thrown as a ranged attack vs. Reflex. It deals a bit
less damage than the hook, and if the target willingly moves in their next turn
they take extra damage. Drowners carry 4 of these nets each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kuo-toa-lash&quot;&gt;Kuo-Toa Lash&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lashes are a caste of lesser priests, subservient to the whips and responsible
for overseeing sacrifices. This includes leading raids to acquire victims. They
fight with tridents and a combination of lightning and water-based magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lashes are Level 15 Artillery with 115 HP. They can use their &lt;strong&gt;tridents&lt;/strong&gt; in
melee or throw them in a &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Trident&lt;/strong&gt; attack that’s stronger, deals
lightning damage, and causes the weapon to return to the lash. Its main
disadvantage is that the range on this attack is only 3/6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Fill Lungs&lt;/strong&gt; spell reaches a lot farther. It targets Fortitude, does
physical damage, and inflicts ongoing 5 damage. It’s also very scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Forked Lightning&lt;/strong&gt; spell that works as a lightning-based
fireball that also blinds on a hit. This recharges whey they’re first bloodied,
or when they reduce an enemy to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kuo-toa-cutter&quot;&gt;Kuo-Toa Cutter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutters are classic skirmishers, trained to slip through enemy frontlines and
stab their squishies with serrated daggers. They’re Level 16 Skirmishers with
151 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;barbed dagger&lt;/strong&gt; does standard damage for their level, and they can also
use it in a &lt;strong&gt;Crippling Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that does less damage but inflicts slowness and
ongoing 10 damage (save ends). If someone misses them with a melee attack, the
cutter can shift 4 squares and use Barbed Dagger as a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These go well with the Dungeon 193 updated kuo-toa, and if you’re already using
those then you’ll like these ones. No big lore changes here, but the stat blocks
are cool enough.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/05/kuo-toa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/09/05/kuo-toa.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
