<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 20:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 20:24:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Hydra</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-human-hydra.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydras made their 4e debut in the first Monster Manual, and here we get a few
more of them. Their basic lore remains the same and you can check it out on the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/06/06/hydra.html&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt; I made on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hydras on this entry have several passive traits in common: &lt;strong&gt;Threatening
Reach&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make opportunity attacks out to their full melee reach,
instead of only against adjacent enemies. &lt;strong&gt;Many-Headed&lt;/strong&gt; makes it resistant to
being dazed on stunning. These conditions only disable one of its heads for a
turn. And &lt;strong&gt;Regenerating Heads&lt;/strong&gt; causes the hydra to lose a head at 75%, 50%,
and 25%, regrowing two others at the start of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of heads an hyda has is important because of &lt;strong&gt;Hydra Fury&lt;/strong&gt;, an
at-will power that allows them to make a bite attack for each active head they
have. The effect of an individual bite, and the starting number of heads, vary
per hydra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, MM2 hydras are kind halfway between the ones we saw on the first
Monster Manual, and the ones from the Monster Vault. Most of their mechanics
still work like in the MM1, but Regenerating Heads debuts here and reappears in
a slightly weaker form in the Monster Vault. With the MV version you can prevent
head regrowth by dealing fire or acid damage to the hydra before the start of
its next turn, but nothing can stop it in this version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hydras are also lacking the Darkvision and Swim Speed of their relatives
from the other two books, though they still have trained Perception and
&lt;strong&gt;All-Around Vision&lt;/strong&gt; that prevents them from being flanked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;razor-hydra&quot;&gt;Razor Hydra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This species of hydra is covered in gleaming metal scales and has extra-sharp
serrated teeth. It’s drawn to the scent of blood in much the same way a shark
is, and one head bites a victim the others get into a frenzy. Because of this,
it’s also known as the Blood Hydra. They are Large Natural Beasts, and Level 16
Solo Brutes with 640 HP and a ground speed of 7. They start with four heads,
gaining extras at 480, 320, and 160.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A razor hydra’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; has Reach 2 and inflicts &lt;em&gt;stackable&lt;/em&gt; ongoing physical
damage. A healthy target would take ongoing 5 damage (save ends), but if the
target was already taking ongoing physical&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; damage, then that damage would
increase by 5 instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A poor sod on the receiving end of a razor hydra’s Fury attack would have
ongoing &lt;em&gt;20&lt;/em&gt; damage (save ends) to deal with, assuming all four bites hit. A
single save will clear it all, but if that save fails and the hydra bites again,
the total will increase even further. There’s no cap!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Blood Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes it so the hydra gains a +2 bonus to attack
targets who are bloodied, or who are taking ongoing physical damage. That’s
one more incentive for it to focus fire on a single PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the hydra drops to 0 HP, its &lt;strong&gt;Ferocity&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make one last Hydra
Fury attack. At this point it will have seven heads, for a potential 7d8+28
damage plus 35 ongoing damage against a single PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;heroslayer-hydra&quot;&gt;Heroslayer Hydra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This interestingly-named hydra occupies the same narrative niche as the one
Hercules faced in his labors. As a Huge Natural Beast and a Level 20 Solo Brute,
it’s likely the most powerful hydra in the natural world, and is stronger than
any PC who isn’t an actual demi-god or equivalent. There are stronger specimens,
but you have to travel to the Elemental Chaos to find them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroslayer hydras have 776 HP and five heads at the start of the fight, gaining
new ones at 582, 388, and 194. Its &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; are Reach 3 and have no riders,
though its &lt;strong&gt;Hydra Fury&lt;/strong&gt; deals 10 extra damage to any target hit by two or more
bites. &lt;strong&gt;Rampage&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to bite every target in reach and inflict 10
ongoing damage to every target it hits. It recharges whenever the hydra suffers
a critical hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The titular &lt;strong&gt;Heroslayer&lt;/strong&gt; trait is a big “Fuck You” to defenders everywhere:
while the hydra is marked, it gains a +2 bonus to attack and a +5 bonus to
damage against the creature that marked it. Yes, this applies to every
individual bite in a Fury combo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we have a hydra with a decent incentive to spread its bites around until
a defender marks it, when it will instead focus exclusively on the defender
until they’re good and dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chaos-hydra&quot;&gt;Chaos Hydra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those stronger species native to the Elemental Chaos. Chaos
Hydras start out with only two heads, but their bites are very strong and
infused with deadly elemental energies. The new heads it grows when wounded also
gain new random elemental abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chaos Hydra is a Huge Elemental Beast and a Level 22 Solo Brute with 848
HP. It has two Reach 3 basic bite attacks, one for each head: &lt;strong&gt;Frostfire Bite&lt;/strong&gt;
deals fire and cold damage, and &lt;strong&gt;Storm Bite&lt;/strong&gt; deals lightning and thunder
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever the hydra grows a new head (at 636, 424, and 212 HP), it gains a new
bite attack chosen by a d4 roll. It can gain multiple copies of the same
attack. Its &lt;strong&gt;Hydra Fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to bite with the two original attacks and
any new ones it might have gained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four additional bites deal less base damage but have “save ends”
riders. They are: &lt;strong&gt;Crushing Maw&lt;/strong&gt;, which slows and deals ongoing 10 damage;
&lt;strong&gt;Mind bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which dazes; &lt;strong&gt;Paralyzing Fang&lt;/strong&gt;, which immobilizes and inflicts
a -2 penalty to all defenses; and &lt;strong&gt;Venom Tooth&lt;/strong&gt;, which inflicts ongoing 10
poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thematically this hydra is all over the place, but that’s the point. It’s hard
for PCs to protect themselves from everything it can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydras are solitary, so you will usually only find one of them at a
time. However, they’re also frequently followed by opportunistic scavengers who
feed on the remains of their meals and who might be impatient enough to give
them a bit of help with killing those meals. Examples given are carrion crawlers
and shardstorm vortex elementals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, a powerful character might be able to capture a hydra for use as a
guardian. The example encounter given is for this scenario, with a razor hydra
and its minotaur cabalist master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydras are cool, particularly those with the regenerating heads
mechanic. However, I think they should be used sparingly to prevent the novelty
from wearing off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I say “physical”, but the strictly correct term would be
“untyped”. Untyped damage is almost always dealt by physical attacks, but
you could have magic powers that also did it. It’s written like “1d8+5
damage” or “ongoing 5 damage” instead of “1d8+5 fire damage” or “ongoing 5
fire damage”. Very few monsters resist it, but none are particularly
vulnerable to it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/17/hydra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/17/hydra.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Human</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As we saw in the Monster Manual Let’s Read, Fourth Edition makes the usual D&amp;amp;D
human description a little more specific. They’re the mortal people without a
patron deity, which makes their outlooks on life very varied and leaves extra
room in their hearts that can be filled with extreme dedication to any number of
causes. Therefore, humans can produce some of the world’s greatest heroes as
well as its most depraved villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This MM2 entry brings us a huge grab bag of human stat blocks. Most of them are
the usual Unaligned people that can be repurposed as either allies or enemies,
but a few are Evil or Chaotic Evil and meant to always be used as threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numbers-wise, they have absolutely no common traits beyond being Medium Natural
Humanoids with a ground speed of 6. You can easily take a human stat block and
make it into a member of another species by adding the relevant signature
ability to them (Goblin Tactics, Elven Accuracy, Savage Demise, Fey Step…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-cavalier&quot;&gt;Human Cavalier&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An armored knight that fights with lance and sword. It’s highly recommended that
you give them a mount when building your encounters, though they can give a good
account of themselves on foot as well. Horses and griffons are the most common
cavalier mounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cavalier is a Level 7 Soldier (Leader) with 78 HP. Their basic attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; strike that damages and marks on a hit, and they can exploit the mark
with two different interrupt abilities. &lt;strong&gt;Champion’s Retort&lt;/strong&gt; is at-will and
allows the knight to make a slightly weaker attack against a marked enemy who
decides to ignore the mark. &lt;strong&gt;Hasty Parry&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that forces
the enemy to target the knight instead, and gives the knight a +3 AC bonus
against that attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When mounted, the knight can also attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Lance&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and
knocks prone on a hit. The text doesn’t say it can be used as part of a charge,
but it really should have this ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-diabolist&quot;&gt;Human Diabolist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-human-diabolist.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A warlock-type who’s in tight with the forces of Hell, and wields
fire-and-brimstone themed magic to achieve their Evil ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diabolist is Level 20 Artillery with 147 HP, powerful enough to be
encountered alongside groups of high-end devils. Their main weapon and implement
is a &lt;strong&gt;kukri&lt;/strong&gt; that does a mix of physical and fire damage. Like all attacks in
this book it needs a damage boost, but make sure its roll is still a fistful of
d6s because this attack has the Brutal property. This means you re-roll any dice
that show a 1 until they show something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their attack magic is all about &lt;strong&gt;Darkfire&lt;/strong&gt;, in an “at-will single-target” and
“area encounter power” versions. It does fire and necrotic damage, and the area
version also does ongoing fire and necrotic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For enemies who get a bit closer, the diabolist can use a &lt;strong&gt;Sulfurous Flash&lt;/strong&gt;
attack that deals fire damage and gives the caster concealment against the
target until the end of the caster’s next turn. If attacked, the diabolist can
use &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Deflection&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) as an interrupt to take half damage
from the attack and deal an automatic 15 fire damage to the attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these attacks can be enhanced by &lt;strong&gt;Hell Blight&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action that
automatically makes an enemy in sight “blighted”. If a blighted enemy takes fire
damage from the diabolist, they can’t recover HP until the end of the
diabolist’s next turn. The blight ends when the fight does, or when the
diabolist blights someone else. This makes focusing their fire on a sincle PC at
a time a very effective tactic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the &lt;strong&gt;Life From Fire&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait gives the diabolist 10 temporary
HP whenever they take fire damage from any source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-dire-beast-hunter&quot;&gt;Human Dire Beast Hunter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone has to protect all those scattered villages if no PCs are around to
help! This hunter is Level 9 Artillery with 76 HP, wielding a spear, a crossbow
with poisoned bolts, and a net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;net&lt;/strong&gt; is a Ranged 3 attack that does no damage and restrains (save
ends). The &lt;strong&gt;crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; has good range and its bolts have an ongoing poison
damage (save ends) rider. The &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; is there for emergencies, because its
best to hunt dire beasts from a distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hunter is not meant to be alone. It should be encountered either as part of
a sizable NPC hunting party, or attached to the PCs as an ally for a
particularly tough hunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-dread-assassin&quot;&gt;Human Dread Assassin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An epic-level assassin armed with a dreadful sword and with spells of poison and
darkness. The perfect person for the job when that job is to kill a king or
emperor. Though they’re unaligned, their clientele is unlikely to be very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assassin is a Level 22 Lurker with 161 HP and a speed of 7. Their &lt;strong&gt;Zealot’s
Scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; is a High-Crit weapon that also deals ongoing poison and necrotic
damage (save ends). They can use a power named &lt;strong&gt;Cloak of Zeal&lt;/strong&gt; as a move
action to shift 3 squares and gain concealment until the end of their next
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the assassin has cover or concealment, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Deadly Blade&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) as a minor action to make is so their next attack has combat
advantage and deals 5d6 extra damage on a hit. And finally, &lt;strong&gt;Assassin’s
Determination&lt;/strong&gt; triggers when they’re bloodied and either immediately recharges
Deadly Blade or (if it’s charged already) heals them for 20 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess the idea is that this is a deadly foe that will never stop trying to
kill you until they succeed, but you should really boost their damage for that
to be true. Also, since they’re regulars you should expect these epic ninjas to
team up with either other assassins, or with some distracting heavies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-gladiator&quot;&gt;Human Gladiator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-human-gladiator.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gladiator is described by the book as a “consumate athlete”, which isn’t
really the term I’d use to refer to someone forced to fight in deathmatches for
the amusement of a bloodthirsty crowd. Still, some of them might end up
becomming bloodsport celebrities, and this one is powerful enough to fit that
role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular individual is a Level 14 Elite Soldier with 276 HP, so we’re
either looking at a Spartacus in the making or at the reigning champion of the
arena that must be taken down before the revolt can start. He wears armor
equivalent to scale and carries a light shield and a gladius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gladiator has a &lt;strong&gt;Fighting Focus&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) that marks enemies who start
their turns inside, lasting until the start of their next turns. It’s a lot like
the Essential Knight’s Defender Aura, with a bit more stickiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That &lt;strong&gt;gladius&lt;/strong&gt; can be used to make melee basic attacks, and in a &lt;strong&gt;Gladius
Display&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks a Close Burst 1 and does the same damage. This is
supplemented by a variety of dirty tricks. They’re all minor actions, and though
none of them do damage they inflict a variety of conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knock to the Dirt&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that targets Fortitude and knocks
prone; &lt;strong&gt;Sand in the Eyes&lt;/strong&gt; is another encounter power that targets fortitude,
and causes blindness (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Well-Placed Kick&lt;/strong&gt; is recharge 5+, targets
Reflex, and both slows and dazes the target (save ends). I bet it targets
the… knee. Yeah, that’d do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the sort of fighting style that’d mark you as a heel in wrestling, but
since the gladiator fights in actual life or death matches I’d say it’s just
good sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-hexer&quot;&gt;Human Hexer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-human-hexer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfect for playing the part of a sinister witch or a seer whose dire prophecies
go unheard. The hexer is a Level 7 Controller with 77 HP, wearing robes and
wielding a staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hexer is extremely weak in terms of damage, and is meant to be used
alongside monsters who are better in that area. They have some interesting
control options, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their only melee attack is a weak bonk with the &lt;strong&gt;staff&lt;/strong&gt;, but insted of
bothering with it they’re going to stay away and open up with &lt;strong&gt;Hex&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor
action that targets all enemies in a Close Burst 10. That’s guaranteed to cover
all PCs unless one of them is a sniper ranger or something. It’s an attack
against Will, and a hit means the target is &lt;em&gt;hexed&lt;/em&gt;. Hexed targets have a -2
penalty to damage the hexer, and become valid targets for the hexer’s other
spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of them is &lt;strong&gt;Capricious Earth&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter), a big area burst that targets
Will, does a bit of damage, slides targets 3 squares, and knocks them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other one is &lt;strong&gt;Beast Curse&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), a ranged spell that targets
Fortitude and turns the target into a Tiny creature until the end of the hexer’s
next turn. While in this state the target cannot use powers. Yes, this &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt;
include basic attacks, so your Slayer won’t turn into a surprisingly deadly
frog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-insane-noble&quot;&gt;Human Insane Noble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-human-insane-noble.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to be confused with the standard Human Noble, shown later. The picture is
pretty much a caricature of Carlota Joaquina, a historical figure who was rather
unpleasant but not epic-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Insane Noble wears finery and wields a scepter, but as a Level 23 Elite
Skirmisher it doesn’t need much more than that to ruin your day. &lt;strong&gt;Sheer
Madness&lt;/strong&gt; makes them immune to opportunity attacks. The &lt;strong&gt;scepter&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic
attack, and &lt;strong&gt;Flurry of Madness&lt;/strong&gt; allows the noble to shift 6 squares and make a
scepter attack against every enemy they pass by during the shift. These traits
and abilities combine to make them a combatant that never stands still,
scuttling about the battlefield with alarming alacrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the noble is first bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Ignoble Fury&lt;/strong&gt; triggers and lets them bonk
everyone in a Close Burst 1 with a scepter attack that also knocks targets prone
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-javelin-dancer&quot;&gt;Human Javelin Dancer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specialized martial artist, lightly armored and wielding a spear for close
combat and a brace of javelins for range. Their &lt;strong&gt;Skirmisher&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows them
to do increased damage if they move at least 4 squares before attacking, and
&lt;strong&gt;Adept Retreat&lt;/strong&gt; makes them not grant combat advantage when running. “Running”
is something everyone can do, greatly increasing their Move at the cost of
granting combat advantage. That’s what the dancer ignores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to basic attacks with the &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; or a &lt;strong&gt;thrown javelin&lt;/strong&gt;, the
dancer can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Mobile Attack&lt;/strong&gt; at will, shifting 3 squares and
attacking with the spear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-knife-fighter&quot;&gt;Human Knife Fighter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knife fighters are rogue-types that are much more focused on acrobatic stabbing
than on other types of crime, which makes them quite similar to PC rogues when
you think about it. They also do well in the role of a knife-focused martial
artist, or the classic super-dangerous lieutenant for a criminal gang whose
actual boss isn’t a fighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This knife fighter is a Level 7 Elite Skirmisher with 162 HP. They go unarmored
(which doesn’t affect their defenses, since they’re all based on level), and are
equipped with a dagger and a net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The net is probably a typo, since none of the fighter’s abilities use it, but
the knife is a &lt;strong&gt;Wounding Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; with an ongoing damage rider and the
High-Crit property. It can also be used in an attack named &lt;strong&gt;Dance of the
Knife&lt;/strong&gt;, where the knife fighter makes two dagger attacks and shifts 2 squares
between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these attacks deal extra damage when they have combat advantage, and they
can also use &lt;strong&gt;Peerless Tumbler&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) to shift 4 squares while
ignoring difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very skirmishery, and goes very well with a pack of soldier monsters with
marking and punishing abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-mystagogue&quot;&gt;Human Mystagogue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A divine spellcaster who delves into divine mysteries few mortals can
understand. Their magic focuses a lot on mind- and perception-affecting
effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mystagogues are Level 20 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 188 HP. They
wear robes and carry a holy symbol - all of their attacks are magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic melee attack is &lt;strong&gt;Mystery’s Touch&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex), which deals psychic
damage and inflicts a -2 penalty to attack the mystagogue until the end if their
next turn. At range they use &lt;strong&gt;Bend Perception&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20 vs. Will), which
deals psychic damage, slows, and inflicts a -2 penalty to all attacks and saves
until the end of the mystagogue’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Awestrike&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5 vs will), which does the
same damage as Bend Perception to all it hits, and also slides the targets 6
squares and dazes them (save ends). The mystagogue also chooses one ally in the
area to slide 6 squares and heal for 10 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the mystagogue can use a &lt;strong&gt;Veil of Inscrutability&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to
being hit by a melee or ranged attack. This allows them to shift 2 squares and
gain a +2 bonus to AC and Reflex for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As opposition, mystagogues pair well with enemies who can exploit combat
advantage or (save ends) effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-noble&quot;&gt;Human Noble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to be confused with the Insane Noble from a few entries ago. This type of
noble can still be pretty horrible, but not the “epic-level scuttling nightmare”
kind of horrible. They’re Level 5 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 60 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Noble wears mail and wields a longsword and a light shield. Their &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt;
strikes are nothing special, and their actual superpower is ordering people
around. It’s very much meant to be encountered alongside its bodyguard detail,
which will be made up of more competent fighters. In other words, this is the
NPC version of the Lazy Warlord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noble is &lt;strong&gt;Protected&lt;/strong&gt; by their allies, and gains a +2 to all defenses when
adjacent to at least one of them. &lt;strong&gt;Appoint Champion&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will order that
allows an ally to make a basic attack and shift 1 square before or after
it. &lt;strong&gt;Inspirational Authority&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that allows one of those
allies to use any of their attacks as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noble can also order &lt;em&gt;enemies&lt;/em&gt; around. &lt;strong&gt;Urge Hesitation&lt;/strong&gt; is an attack
against Will that, on a hit, prevents the target from using a standard action in
its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-pirate&quot;&gt;Human Pirate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yarrr! Pirates are Level 9 Skirmishers with 95 HP, armed with cutlasses. They’re
pretty fast, with a Speed of 7 and a &lt;strong&gt;Rigging Monkey&lt;/strong&gt; ability that gives them
a climb speed of 7 for a turn once per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Cutlass&lt;/strong&gt; strike with no additional riders, but
they’re extra-good at flanking: &lt;strong&gt;Scurvy Dog’s Flank&lt;/strong&gt; gives them an extra +1 to
hit and +2d6 bonus damage to all attacks against a flanked target. This stacks
with combat advantage for a total of +3 to hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their tactics section says they like to stay near the water or near the edge of
the boat if this is a boarding action, but I see no reason for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-pirate-captain&quot;&gt;Human Pirate Captain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-human-pirate-captain.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Double Yarrr! The captain is a Level 10 Soldier with the Leader keyword and 104
HP. It’s clearly meant to be used alongside a bunch of Pirates and perhaps a
small horde of minions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Cutlass&lt;/strong&gt; attacks have a slow (save ends) rider, and they have the same
Rigging Monkey and Scurvy Dog’s Flank abilities as the rest of the
crew. Captains complement their swordplay with occasional bouts of &lt;strong&gt;Vicious
Mockery&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action; recharge 6+). This doesn’t require an attack roll and
causes a nearby enemy to provoke an opportunity attack from one of the captain’s
allies. When first bloodied, they shout out a &lt;strong&gt;Call to Arms&lt;/strong&gt; that allows all
allies within 10 squares to make a basic melee attack or shift 3 squares as a
free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;human-slaver&quot;&gt;Human Slaver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the few explicitly Evil stat blocks in this entry, the slaver is an
unpleasant villain that fights with a mace and a scourge. Their focus is on
immobilizing enemies for capture, and on inflicting pain. They’re level 8 Brutes
with 102 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is &lt;strong&gt;Thump and Lash&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals damage and inflicts a -2
attack penalty for a turn. They can also use the scourge to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Slaver’s
Tangle&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge 4+) that does all of the above and also immobilizes
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slavers are meant to be use as part of larger capture teams featuring one or
more of them plus an assortment of other goons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the first Monster Manual, the Vault, and the MM2, you have enough human
stat blocks that you can include one or more of them in any encounter that
demands sapient humanoid opposition. The PCs themselves are proof that humans
work well with members of any other sapient species that share their individual
goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “generic” stat blocks also work as seasoning for more specialized groups,
like cultists. It might surprise the PCs a bit if the guy holding the
sacrificial dagger is an elite knife-fighter instead of a squishy caster, for
example.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/15/human.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/15/human.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Homunculus</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-homunculus.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual included an Homunculus entry. The MM2 has a few more,
which we’ll look at now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/05/22/homunculus.html&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;, homunculi are relatively simple
constructs distantly related to golems, the model rocket to the golem’s Saturn
V. They’re much weaker but also much simpler to make, and their construction
includes some programming shortcuts that make them good at being guards. There
are specific shortcuts to guard an object, a creature, or an area. Homunculi are
quite intelligent and clever when fulfilling the tasks they were designed for,
but are not good for anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this entry we meet two new homunculus models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stonefist-defender&quot;&gt;Stonefist Defender&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Small, spiky animated statue is built to act as a bodyguard and combat
buddy to a living creature. Its programming makes it very good a coordinating
with its “client” during a fight. I imagine a society with plenty of access to
magic would build mass quantities of them for use as “combat drones”,
supplementing infantry or scouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defender is a Level 2 Skirmisher with 38 HP. It has darkvision, runs at a
nice speed of 8, and is immune to disease and poison. It’s surprisingly
acrobatic: it can &lt;strong&gt;Tumble&lt;/strong&gt; as an at-will move action to shift 3 squares
instead of the usual 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defender’s only attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Spiked Fist&lt;/strong&gt; that’s pretty average on its
own, but gains all sorts of situational bonuses when the creature fights
according to its programming: by using its high mobility to flank enemies
engaged with its “client”. It has a +2 bonus to hit enemies adjacent to the
client, and gains +1d6 bonus damage when flanking those enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arbalester&quot;&gt;Arbalester&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arbalesters are animated ballistas! They can move around using wheels or legs,
and reload themselves. They’re used as mobile turrets, and can be ordered to
watch over a specific area. That same magic-rich society that makes defenders
could have arbalesters helping defend fortresses or following patrols around as
mobile artillery pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arbalesters are Level 4 Artillery with 43 HP. They move around at Speed 6, and
have the standard traits of darkvision and immunity to disease and
poison. They’ll attack with improvised &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; if pressed into melee, but
their &lt;strong&gt;Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; are of course a much better option. They can temporarily
increase their rate of fire to make a &lt;strong&gt;Double Shot&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), firing
bolts at two targets within 5 squares of each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can be set to &lt;strong&gt;Guard an Area&lt;/strong&gt; 5 squares on a side. If any enemy is within
this area when the arbalester starts its turn, Double Shot recharges
automatically. Their use as defensive turrets is obvious, but they can also be
used offensively if transported within range of enemy positions and ordered to
“guard” those positions. This will cause them to rain bolts upon those areas
until no enemies remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our sample encounter is Level 3: 3 stonefist defenders, 1 arbalester, and a
dwarf hammerer. This is obviously a military squad from that magic-rich civ - an
organic officer, and his drone complement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of these two homunculus models as military drones makes them seem quite
interesting as opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/12/homunculus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/12/homunculus.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Hawk</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-hawk.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawks are real world animals, and though they are birds of prey they’re fairly
small and don’t usually attack people. For these reasons, 4e doesn’t consider
them “monster material”, and this entry focuses on supernatural hawks that can
pose a bigger threat to adventurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blood-hawks&quot;&gt;Blood Hawks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Small Natural Beasts, Blood Hawks are bloody enormous for hawks. They’re also
a lot more aggressive than usual, and their claws deal wounds that bleed
profusely. This, and their reddish coloration, gives them their name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blood hawk is a Level 1 Skirmisher with 27 HP. It has a flight speed of 6, and
a ground speed of only 2 (and it’s Clumsy while walking). Its basic attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;Claw Rake&lt;/strong&gt; that deals standard physical damage and inflicts 2 ongoing damage
(save ends). This ongoing damage raises to 5 if the hawk is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blood hawk can also make &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attacks&lt;/strong&gt; at will. This follows the
standard rules seen in other monsters: it flies its speed, makes a basic attack
at any point, and doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks when moving away from the
target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;frost-hawk&quot;&gt;Frost Hawk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Small Elemental Beast native to certain ice-aspected regions of the Elemental
Chaos, the Frost Hawk can also be found in mountaintops and other cold places of
the world. It’s a Level 7 Skirmisher with 80 HP, making it a lot more formidable
than any mundane hawk. Its flight speed is 8, and its ground speed a
clumsy 2. It has Resist Cold 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hawk’s &lt;strong&gt;Ice Talons&lt;/strong&gt; serve as its basic attack, dealing a mix of physical
and cold damage. It has the same Flyby Attack as the blood hawk, and it adds a
couple elemental powers to its arsenal. &lt;strong&gt;Freezing Screech&lt;/strong&gt; is a Close Blast 3
vs. Fortitude that deals cold damage and slows (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Shattering
Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is a passive trait that make all its attacks deal extra damage against
slowed targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a frost hawk is going to start a fight with the Screech, and will then focus
its flyby attacks on one of the targets it managed to slow. It pairs really well
with controllers and other monsters with the ability to slow enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being found in the wild, hawks might also be found in the service
of many sapients. Falconry is a real-world sport with roots in the Middle Ages,
so of course it’s extensively practiced in the medieval-ish setting of 4e. The
sample encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 2: 3 blood hawks, 2 bloodseeker drakes, 2 elf archers. A hunting party
going after dangerous game?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: 2 frost hawks, 1 orc bloodrager, 1 orc eye of gruumsh. Orcs also know
falconry.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think these supernatural hawks would make for an exciting encounter by
themselves, but the falconry angle has promise. Lots of enemies become 20%
cooler if you give them a badass hawk friend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/08/hawk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/08/hawk.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Half-Orc</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-half-orc.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-Orcs have been in the game since the days of AD&amp;amp;D, where they appeared as a
playable option in the Player’s Handbook. Historically, they were one of the
first “edgy” options for players, but they’ve always been a bit controversial
and surrounded by Unfortunate Implications. The main one being that most
versions of them implied that there was only one very unpleasant way in which an
orc and a human could have a child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In more recent years, several different solutions to this have been
proposed. Some remove half-orcs from the game, others say they’re full orcs and
that’s what a full orc looks like. Fourth Edition went with a third common
option, which is to diversify the origins of half-orcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They appear as a playable option in the PHB 2, and have their NPC/enemy-style
entries here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-Orcs as a people tend to combine the daring and ambition of humans with the
strength and ferocity of orcs. Their build and features are orcish, but their
hair and skin tones resemble those of humans rather than the greens and blues
this edition uses for orcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-orcs are as numerous as any other people without “half-“ in their
name. They have their own communities and cultures, and also live in more
cosmopolitan settlements along with other sapients. You could play a half-orc
who has neither humans nor orcs anywhere in their family tree, or at least none
in living memory. In fact, they’ve been around in this state for so long that no
one knows their true origins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several competing theories. A more mythical version says that they
arose when Gruumsh lost his eye and his spilled blood hit the world. Another
myth says Kord created them by copying the best elements from his two favorite
species. Others say they started out as a super-soldier experiment by an evil
wizard, or when human and orc barbarian tribes joined in alliance in ancient
times. Another still says they were engineered by the ancient goblin empire to
act as orc wranglers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, you can still have a half-orc who’s the product of a happy
marriage between a human and an orc. If you really want to you could also make a
half-orc PC with the classic “Unfortunate” origin, but now it’s no longer
exclusive to them. If you really want to play an edgy character, there are
better options around these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that has been removed this edition is the “caught between two
worlds, hated by both” cliche that used to plague both half-elves and
half-orcs. And to that I say good riddance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NPC Half-Orcs have the same signature traits as their playable version:
low-light vision, a +2 bonus to speed when charging, and the &lt;strong&gt;Furious Assault&lt;/strong&gt;
encounter power. This can be used as a free action right after the half-orc hits
an enemy, and increases the damage of the attack by 1d10. It’s a bit better than
the PC version, which only increases it by 1d8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;half-orc-hunter&quot;&gt;Half-Orc Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ranger-type who really likes to jump into melee combat, fighting in a reckless
manner. Wearing light armor, they carry a battleaxe and a longbow into combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;axe&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;bow&lt;/strong&gt; are basic attacks, and &lt;strong&gt;Evasive Chop&lt;/strong&gt; allows the
hunter to shift 1 square before making an axe attack. &lt;strong&gt;Draw First Blood&lt;/strong&gt; is a
passive trait that increases their damage against any enemy who hasn’t yet taken
damage in this fight. Combining it with Furious Assault makes for a good “alpha
strike”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;half-orc-death-mage&quot;&gt;Half-Orc Death Mage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The death mage is more of a priest-type, serving an exarch of Gruumsh named
Yurtrus. Yurtrus presides over disease, misery, and death, so their magic
follows the same themes. Death Mages are always Evil, unlike the others here who
are presented as Unaligned. They wear robes and carry quarterstaffs that work
more as implements than as weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though they can attack with that &lt;strong&gt;staff&lt;/strong&gt;, their main melee attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;rotting touch&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude and does both immediate and ongoing
necrotic damage (save ends). The touch also strips any necrotic resistance or
immunity the target might have! This opens it up to necrotic attacks from
others, and allows that ongoing damage to have an effect. Saving against the
damage also ends this condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range, they can shoot &lt;strong&gt;Bolts of Putrescence&lt;/strong&gt; vs. Reflex that deal physical
damage and inflict a -5 penalty to all the target’s defenses for a turn. Their
area attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Flies&lt;/strong&gt; that deals physical damage and creates a
zone over the affected area. Anyone caught inside takes damage from fly bites,
and has their visibility restricted to 3 squares. The death mage can move the
zone 2 squares as a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The death mage has the racial Furious Assault power, and it’s worth remembering
that it can enhance &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; attack, not just physical ones. Its final power is
&lt;strong&gt;Death Mark&lt;/strong&gt;, which automatically deals heavy physical damage to whoever
reduces the mage to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;half-orc-scarthane&quot;&gt;Half-Orc Scarthane&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scarthanes are veteran warriors that eschew armor and proudly display the
tapestry of scars covering their skin. The more wounded they are, the more
dangerous they become, and either ferocity or blood magic allows them to keep
fighting even through all those wounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Scarthane is a Level 7 Brute with 96 HP, wielding a greataxe and fighting
unarmored. The &lt;strong&gt;axe&lt;/strong&gt; is a High-Crit weapon, and they’re limited to basic
attacks and Furious Assault at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the scarthane hits a bloodied target, &lt;strong&gt;Blood for Blood&lt;/strong&gt; makes the attack
deal +1d6 damage and heals them for 5 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the scarthane becomes bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Wounded Retaliation&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make
a basic attack against whoever bloodied them. They also gain &lt;strong&gt;Bloodfury
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, an axe attack that lacks the High-Crit property but deals more base
damage and heals the scarthane for 10 HP when it hits. This does stack with
Blood for Blood!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-orcs can be found among humans, orcs, or other creatures that associate
with them. They can easily be reskinned by replacing their signature traits with
those of the target species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: 2 half-orc hunters, 1 human hexer, 4 human berserkers. A barbarian
hunting party.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 4 scarthanes, 1 orc chieftain, 1 orc eye of Gruumsh. The scarthanes
make an excellent honor guard.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/04/half-orc.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/04/half-orc.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Half-Elf</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-half-elf.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-elves have been a part of D&amp;amp;D since races were first separated from classes
back in AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition. I guess they might have been inspired by Elrond from
Lord of the Rings, who was said to be a half-elf. They appeared as a playable
option right in the first PHB, but they’re only getting their monster/NPC
entries here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to report that Fourth Edition half-elves no longer follow the tired
and somewhat problematic “outsiders to both parent cultures” narrative from
previous editions! In fact, everyone likes them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, half-elves aren’t just an “average” of their two parents. Yes, they’re
sturdier than elves and pointier than humans, but they also have a lot of traits
that are uniquely their own. Chief among those is a noticeable facility with
social interaction and cultural adaptability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-elves whose parents are a human and an elf can spend their early years in
either of the two cultures, depending on their specific family
circumstances. Their names and mannerisms tend to be taken from that
culture. You can also have all-half-elf cultures and communities whose
human and elven ancestors are several generations behind them. In all cases it’s
very common for individuals to journey abroad for a while out of a sense of
curiosity and wanderlust, and they tend to fit in well in any place where they
linger for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, “Nice” doesn’t necessarily mean “Good”, and you can also find
villainous half-elves who become bandit leaders or fall in with dark
forces. They’re technically better-suited to be infernal warlocks than
&lt;em&gt;tieflings&lt;/em&gt;, given their stat adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three stat blocks here, more suitable for use as opposition than as
allies, though they could also fill that role in a more morally ambiguous
adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half-elves are Medium Natural humanoids, with a native speed of 6 and low-light
vision. Everything else about their stat blocks comes from training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;half-elf-bandit-captain&quot;&gt;Half-Elf Bandit Captain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be a murderous marauder or a Robin Hood figure. They’re a level 6
Skirmisher with the Leader keyword and 69 HP. They wear light armor, wield a
sword, and carry a bunch of throwing daggers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic melee attack that allows the captain to shift 1 square
on a hit. Their basic ranged attack is a thrown &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt;. A maneuver named
&lt;strong&gt;Slash and Dash&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) allows them to make a sword attack, shift 2
squares and throw a dagger. Their leaderly move is named &lt;strong&gt;Triggering Slash&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+), a sword attack that on a hit allows an ally to shift 1 square and
make a melee basic attack of their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;half-elf-con-artist&quot;&gt;Half-Elf Con Artist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 7 Controller with 77 HP. Whether they’re a lovable rogue or a
dastardly deceiver depends on which side of the con you’re on. The con artist
goes unarmored and clad in fine clothes, with a dagger hidden somewhere for
protection. They’re trained in all the skills you’d expect them to have:
Stealth, Bluff, Thievery, and Insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; isn’t anything special, but it deals extra sneak attack damage
if the con artist has combat advantage against the target. Their real weapon is
&lt;em&gt;manipulation&lt;/em&gt;, though. This is implemented as a trio of charm powers that
target Will. It’s up to you whether they’re actual magic or just the con artist
being very sly and convincing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deceptive Maneuver&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will melee power that causes the target to make
a melee basic attack against an ally of the half-elf’s choice. The classic
“getting between two enemies to make them hit each other”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silver Deception&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10; recharge 5+) does no damage, but dominates the
target until the end of the con artist’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;Pathetic Appeal&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that targets every enemy in a
close burst 5 and, on a hit, prevents them from attacking the con artist until
they pass a save. If the con artist makes an attack roll against an affected
target, they get an immediate extra save against this effect. “I’ve seen the
error of my ways, honest!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close things out, &lt;strong&gt;Grifter’s Flight&lt;/strong&gt; is another encounter power that allows
the con artist to shift 6 squares and make an unpenalized Stealth check at the
end&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;half-elf-baleful-thaumaturge&quot;&gt;Half-Elf Baleful Thaumaturge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An epic-level evil wizard for all of your epic-level evil wizard needs. The stat
block itself is Unaligned, so you could also use it to represent a wizard that’s
merely edgy. No reason it has to be a half-elf either, the stats could apply to
any Medium sapient. Their magic has a “blood and teeth” theme, which gives you a
hint as to what kind of entity they learned it from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thaumaturge is Level 24 Artillery with 169 HP. They go unarmored, and wield
a wand as an implement. Their basic melee attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Infernal Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that
targets Will. A hit damages the target, pushes it 3 squares, and allows the
thaumaturge to teleport 3 squares. Their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Soul Bite&lt;/strong&gt;
spell (ranged 10 vs. Reflex) that does physical damage and gives the thaumaturge
10 temporary HP on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “bitey” theme continues with their two special attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Wall of Shadow
Teeth&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) creates wall 2 squares high and 8 squares long within 10
squares of the caster. This wall bites, attacking anyone adjacent to it. A hit
deals necrotic damage and immobilizes the target (save ends). It lasts for a
turn but can be sustained with minor actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mouths of Hell&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Will; encounter) deals heavy psychic
damage and also gives the thaumaturge 10 temporary HP. This creates a zone of
ghostly maws that lasts until the end of the encounter, deals 15 psychic damage
to anyone caught inside, and gives the caster 5 temporary HP when it damages
someone in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thaumaturge can also spend 5 temporary HP if it has them to teleport 8
squares as a minor action, with a spell called &lt;strong&gt;Bloody Step&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t much of a theme to the half-elves in this entry, but I guess that’s
the point. They’re as varied as humanity. Each individual entry has their own
thing going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two sample encounters we get are a Level 7 one with a bandit captain leading
a gang of humans and halflings, and a Level 25 one with an epic lich and its
entourage of 2 thaumaturges and 2 slaughterstone hammerers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/02/half-elf.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/02/half-elf.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Gray Render</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-gray-render.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see something of a rarity in this series: a monster whose 4e incarnation
I find &lt;em&gt;strictly worse&lt;/em&gt; than its previous ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray Renders first appeared in 3e, where they were these big, clawed,
carnivorous brutes with an oddly endearing trait: they would sometimes imprint
on another creature and basically dedicate their lives to protect it and take
care of it. This creature could be a sapient, or even a PC if the GM was feeling
cute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth Edition gray renders lose the imprinting, and replace it with a constant
urge to destroy and feed. Some sages theorize they’re somehow tied to the
metaphysical concept of entropy despite being natural beasts, since they seem
particularly fond of targetting sapient settlements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t like this change because, as you might have surmised by now, I’m not
fond of always-hostile, attacks-on-sight-and-fights-to-the-death monsters. I
literally never saw anyone mention grey renders online without also mentioning
and praising the imprinting. Remove that and you’re left with something that’s
virtually indistinguishable from, say, a goristro demon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray Renders are Large Natural Humanoids with a Chaotic Evil alignment and
Int 2. They’re Level 19 Elite Brutes with 452 HP and blindsight, who fight using
claws, bites, and sheer brutality. In other words, almost like slightly smaller,
slightly dumber goristros with blindsight. They have Speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that also grabs on a hit. They can make
two claw attacks per action, and if both hit the same target they also inflict
ongoing damage on account of the rending. They can use a grabbed victim as a
club, inflicting more damage than the claw, pushing the target of the attack 4
squares from the impact, and dealing half the rolled damage to the “weapon”. Or
they can bite the grabbed victim for massive damage, with a Daze rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While bloodied, their claw attack also knocks a target prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray renders are said to be too destructive to cooperate with anyone, but some
predators and scavengers have taken to following them from safe distance to
exploit their rampages. So we get these encounter groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 18: 1 gray render, 1 bodak skulk, 2 guulvorgs. Opportunistic followers
can be sapient too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 20: 1 dire bullette, 1 gray render, 3 nabassu gargoyles. The gargoyles
are watching the kaiju battle and waiting to feast on the loser’s remains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat block is cool, but the lore is “meh” at best. Reskin this into a demon
and/or add the imprinting back to make it more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/01/gray-render.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/01/gray-render.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Goliath</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think Goliaths first appeared in the Races of Stone supplement for 3.5. In
Fourth Edition, their first appearance was as a playable option in the
PHB 2. They get their corresponding “monster” entry here, with a couple of stat
blocks suitable for use as opposition or NPC allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re one of the many playable peoples designed to give players a “taste” of
being a cool fantasy monster without being unbalanced. Eladrin arguably do it
for Sidhe; dragonborn do it for dragons; tieflings for fiends; deva for
angels. Goliaths do it for giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-goliath.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical goliath is stated to be between 7 and 8 feet tall, so whether
they’re on the large side of Medium or the small side of Large is a matter of
opinion. The book’s opinion is that they’re Medium, since that allows them to be
playable. Their skin is gray or brown, and speckled with coin-sized bony growths
that look like rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goliaths have existed since shortly after the Primordials created the world,
which might mean they’re a kind of byproduct of the creation of the Giants in
the same way the origin of the Dragonborn is tied to that of dragons. Goliaths
don’t care enough about that to make myths about it, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All throughout their history they’ve preferred to keep to a nomadic existence in
the more mountainous areas of the world, so there isn’t much about them in other
people’s records either. While it’s fairly common for individual goliaths to
travel the “lowlands” as adventurers or explorers, they haven’t engaged in any
grand diplomacy or empire-building as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culturally, goliaths place a lot of value in individual skill and prowess, and
this makes them very competitive. Their communities probably have all sorts of
tournaments and contests in their calendars. Individual goliaths tend to turn
everything into a contest, even if only in the privacy of their own minds - they
keep score and constantly compare themselves both to their companions and to
their own past performance. That battle where Legolas and Gimli compare their
kill counts? That’s every fight where a goliath is involved. This does have the
downside of making them get a bit depressive when they fail to measure up to
their own standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect Kord is a very popular deity among goliaths, and they also often
worship the primal spirits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as the rules are concerned, Goliaths are Medium Natural Humanoids. They
have a natural speed of 6, and human-equivalent senses. Their signature ability
is &lt;strong&gt;Stone’s Endurance&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor-action encounter power which gives them
some resistance to all damage for a turn. The value of this resistance is 5/tier
(5 at heroic, 10 at paragon, 15 at epic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-sunspeaker&quot;&gt;Goliath Sunspeaker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is more of a primal priest of the sun spirits than a cleric of Pelor,
focused on burning people with sun-powered lasers. Sunspeakers are Level 7
Artillery with 64 HP, wearing light armor and using an orb as an implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their melee basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Sunspeaker’s Hand&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex and
deals light radiant damage. &lt;strong&gt;Solar Sphere&lt;/strong&gt; does the same at Range 20 with
better damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often, the sunspeaker can use &lt;strong&gt;Solar Rays&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) against up to 2
targets within Range 10. This deals light radiant &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; fire damage, as well as
ongoing damage of the type chosen (save ends). This allows them to potentially
stack two sources of ongoing damage on someone with the same power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If cornered, the sunspeaker can use &lt;strong&gt;Flaring Leap&lt;/strong&gt; (move action; encounter) to
jump 3 squares and then move its remaining speed. This jet-powered jump causes a
fire in the sunspeaker’s starting space, which deals damage to adjacent enemies
or to those foolish enough to enter the flaming square. The fire lasts for a
turn and can be sustained with minor actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it can use a big area attack named &lt;strong&gt;Call Down The Sun&lt;/strong&gt; once per
encounter, which is a bit weaker than Solar Sphere but targets a lot of people
and does half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-guardian&quot;&gt;Goliath Guardian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more straightforward but no less powerful martial type. The guardian is a
Level 9 Soldier with 96 HP. It’s heavily armored by still has speed 6, wielding
a bastard sword and a light shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; attack marks for a turn, and if the target is prone it’s
also prevented from getting up for the same amount of time. The guardian knocks
people prone with &lt;strong&gt;Ram’s Charge&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a maneuver that deals light
physical damage and has a long list of riders: it pushes the target 2 squares,
knocks it prone, and allows the goliath to make a free sword attack against the
target. As the name says, it can be used as part of a charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Warrior’s Leap&lt;/strong&gt; is a passive that allows the guardian to jump
without provoking opportunity attacks. It still uses the standard jump rules
(and it’s high Athletics score) for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guardians are awesome in moutainous terrain that’s full of cliffs. Even if their
targets aren’t thrown overboard, they’ll still stay on the ground for quite a
while, granting advantage to the guardian and any sneak-attacking skirmisher
buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goliaths often team up with similarly-inclined mountain-dwellers, which can
include dwarves, galeb duhrs, or goblins. I suppose that might include stone
giants as well, if you level your goliaths up a bit. The sample encounter is
level 9, and includes a galeb duhr rock-caller, 3 goliath guardians, and 1
sunspeaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like goliaths, they fill a very specific “huge person” niche. These two stat
blocks are interesting from a mechanics standpoint as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/28/goliath.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/28/goliath.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Golem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Golems showed up in the first MM and were iconic enough to later make it to the
Monster Vault. I covered those &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/30/golem.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and you can check that same post to
see their basic lore. The Monster Manual 2 brings us yet more golems, which
share the same basic lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, golems are Natural Animates with the Construct keyword. They’re
immune to disease, poison, and sleep. They have darkvision, and though their
ground speed tends to be high they cannot shift. Most are Large, but one of the
examples here is Huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bone-golem&quot;&gt;Bone Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-golem-bone.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bone golems are made from the skeletons of several creatures, whose bones are
sharpened and fitted together to form the construct’s body. Despite being made
of bones and beloved of necromancers, it’s a construct animated through
elemental magic and not an undead monster. Throw this one into an encounter that
does have undead skeletons in it, and it should be good to surprise your PCs a
bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bone Golems are Level 12 Elite Brutes with 302 HP. It’s so spiky the pointy bits
count as a &lt;strong&gt;Bone Spikes&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) that deals 5 damage to any enemy that enters
it. The pointy bits also justify the &lt;strong&gt;Osseous Retaliation&lt;/strong&gt; trait, which deals
a bit of automatic damage to anyone who hits the golem with an opportunity
attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This construct fights with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Bone Spurs&lt;/strong&gt;, and can attack twice per
action with them. It can also fire a &lt;strong&gt;Bone Volley&lt;/strong&gt; (burst 3 vs. Reflex,
recharge 6+) that deals heavy physical damage and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the golem is destroyed &lt;strong&gt;Bone Death&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make one last
attack. If Bone Spurs is charged then it uses that, otherwise it makes a basic
bone spur attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chain-golem&quot;&gt;Chain Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-golem-chain.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Huge golems are modeled after chain devils, and are often tasked to guard
prisons and Actual Dungeons instead of the usual tombs or treasure vaults. As
you might have guessed, their fighting style is very grapple-intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chain Golems are Level 22 Elite Soldiers with 418 HP, a speed of 8, and all
standard golem traits. Their &lt;strong&gt;Entangling Chains&lt;/strong&gt; act as an aura (3) that slows
everyone caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Chain&lt;/strong&gt; that does physical damage and pulls
the target 2 squares. &lt;strong&gt;Chain Smash&lt;/strong&gt; is their double attack power, allowing it
to attack two different targets in one action. While they’re bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Berserk
Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make a chain strike against anyone who damages them as a
reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that and we didn’t even use the grappling rules yet! We have to do that for
&lt;strong&gt;Chain Grab&lt;/strong&gt;, though. This at-will attack is a Close Burst 2 that does the
same damage as the basic strike, pulls targets 1 square, and grabs them. The
escape DC is 32 or 35 depending on the skill you use. The golem can move away
from the grabbed victims without ending the grab because chains. Once it
finishes moving it can either slide the victims next to itself or let them go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your typical chain golem will try to keep the whole party grabbed while it
smacks them around with its chains. PCs who aren’t grabbed will still be slowed,
and the golem’s strikes will pull them back if they try to run away. Staying far
away and using ranged attacks is a good tactic against them, but that speed of 8
will make keeping away a real chore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clay-golem&quot;&gt;Clay Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-golem-clay.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clay Golems were one of the original golem types described in the first entries
back in AD&amp;amp;D or in the nebulous times before it. They were originally inspired
by the legend of the golem of Prague, and so were the only golem that required
divine magic to make (all the others were arcane).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fourth Edition, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/12/eidolon.html&quot;&gt;eidolons&lt;/a&gt; are used to represent divine constructs, so
clay golems have the same arcane/elemental origin as the other types. They have
a somewhat “runny” appearance, but are surprisingly fast and retain a slightly
less harsh version of the ability to inflict unhealing wounds that they had in
previous incarnations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stat-wise, they’re Level 15 Elite Brutes with 368 HP, Large size, a speed of 6,
and all common golem traits. Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that does
heavy physical damage and curses the target, making it unable to regain HP. This
is a (save ends) condition, but it’s still quite dangerous, since it makes
wounds inflicted by &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; enemies unhealing, not just the golem’s. &lt;strong&gt;Clay
Smash&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to slam two different targets in one action, and they have the
same Berserk Attack reaction as the chain golem above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Hasty Reaction&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait allows them to roll initiative twice and
take the highest result, and &lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable&lt;/strong&gt; is a move-action encounter power
that allows them to move 8 squares and pass through enemy spaces. They draw
opportunity attacks when doing this, but reduce their damage by 10. This isn’t
worded like a resistance, so I guess powers that bypass or reduce resistances
don’t work against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iron-golem&quot;&gt;Iron Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These made it into the MV, so we already covered them. The MM2 has two versions,
the Level 20 one that we saw, and a Level 26 “Iron Golem Juggernaut” that’s
basically the same aside from being size Huge and having bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each kind of golem presented here gets a sample encounter. I guess there was
something of an editing snafu here, because most golems have their encounter
listed right after their stats, but the one for chain golems is all by its
lonesome in an “Encounter Groups” section at the end of the overall entry. I
guess it must be there because it has two golem types in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: 1 bone golem, 4 horde ghouls (minions), 1 human wizard lich. So
that’s the kind of caster who makes bone golems.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 15: 1 clay golem, 1 shadar-kai gloom lord, 2 shadow snakes. A Zehiri
operation, if you still want to associate clay golems with clerics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 21: 1 chain golem, 1 dark naga, 1 iron golem. Someone &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; wanted
this place guarded.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 24: 1 iron golem juggernaut, 1 storm gorgon, 1 djinn skylord. A noble,
his pet, and his mechanical manservant.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a point past which adding more golem types feels a bit redundant. There
are also so many non-golem constructs out there that I almost think “golem”
should be a singular monster type with very specific characteristics, rather
than a whole family of them. Otherwise it would be best to do away with the term
entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/golem.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/golem.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Goblin</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-goblin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D Fourth Edition uses “Goblins” to describe a set of closely related species
of humanoids: actual goblins, hobgoblins, and bugbears. They’re a very
traditional component of the game and we looked at lots of them in the
MM1/Monster Vault Let’s Read. The post covering their basic lore is &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/22/goblinoids.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the first Manual covered them so well, the second brings us a small number
of more specialized stat blocks for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bugbear-wardancer&quot;&gt;Bugbear Wardancer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wardancers are specialized martial artists. Their weapon of choice is a
two-handed heavy flail, which they swing in wide arcs while moving through enemy
forces in the battlefield. The end result looks something like a dance, thus the
name. There’s a religious element to the art: there are different schools
organized around the worship of different exarchs of Bane, who compete among
each other to see whose war dance is the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wardancer presented here is a Level 6 Skirmisher with 70 HP, low-light
vision, and Speed 7. Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Flail Dance&lt;/strong&gt; that does physical
damage and has a lot of stacked riders: it pushes the target 2 square and knocks
it prone, and also allows the bugbear to shift 1 square. Yes, this is an at-will
basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wardancer also has a couple of special attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Flail Barrier&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
5+) does a bit of automatic damage in a burst 2 around the bugbear, and makes it
take half damage from weapon attacks until the end of its next turn. &lt;strong&gt;Flail
Assault&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs Reflex; encounter) does a bit more damage and knocks
those it hits prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the wardancer’s attacks deal extra damage if it has combat advantage against
the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goblin-acolyte-of-maglubyet&quot;&gt;Goblin Acolyte of Maglubyet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another martial artist, this one a goblin from a sect devoted to Maglubyet. In
previous editions (and again on 5th), Maglubyet is the main goblinoid deity, but
here he’s one of Bane’s Exarchs. His acolytes seek to make themselves in his
image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Acolyte is a Level 1 Controller with 29 HP, Speed 6, and low-light
vision. They wield a battleaxe in combat, and back it up with a bit of divine
magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acolytes are surrounded by a &lt;strong&gt;Life Scourge&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that prevents enemies
inside from recovering hit points. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Slashing Shroud&lt;/strong&gt;
that consists of an axe strike that also makes the acolyte invisible to the
target until the end if the acolyte’s next turn. A good option against PC
defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can attack at range with the &lt;strong&gt;Hand of Maglubyet&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Fortitude), a telekinetic attack that deals force damage and either slides
the target 3 squares or immobilizes it for a turn. &lt;strong&gt;Maglubyet’s Fists&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) allows them to use this attack twice in a single action. So as far
as martial artists go, this is one of those annoying hadouken spammers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acolyte also has the standard &lt;strong&gt;Goblin Tactics&lt;/strong&gt; power that allows it to
shift 1 square as a reaction when missed by a melee attack. This is what you
would change if you were making acolytes of other species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lolthbound-goblin&quot;&gt;Lolthbound Goblin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goblins are generally big on Bane worship, but that’s not universal among
them. This is a goblin whose people have been slaves to the drow for
generations. Their training, and even their physiology, have some important
differences from your usual goblins. They’re clearly meant to be encountered
alongside drow, though for that to work out you’ll need to make those drow lower
level or the goblin higher level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As written, the Lolthbound Goblin is a Level 3 Soldier with 45 HP. They have
speed 6, and replace the usual low-light vision with full darkvision. They wear
light armor and fight with a war pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Lolthbound Goblins are within 5 squares of a drow, they gain a +2 bonus to
all their attacks and defenses. That &lt;strong&gt;pick&lt;/strong&gt; is a high-crit weapon and marks
targets for a turn on a hit. Once per encounter they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Stinging Blow&lt;/strong&gt;
that deals poison damage and instead of marking increases any ongoing poison
damage the target is taking by 5. This synergizes with the poisoned weapons drow
so often carry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also once per encounter they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Lolthbound Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5
vs. Fortitude), which deals light thunder damage to anyone in the area who is
not a drow or spider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the usual Goblin Tactics reaction, they also have &lt;strong&gt;Drow Protector&lt;/strong&gt;,
an interrupt where the goblin throws himself in front of a drow that’s just been
targetted by an attack, becoming the target instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lolthbound-goblin-slave&quot;&gt;Lolthbound Goblin Slave&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 12 Minion Skirmisher version of the lolthbound goblin above,
which makes it appropriate for use with drow without the need for level
adjustments. They’re also armed with war picks, and add a hand crossbow to their
loadout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Stinging Pick&lt;/strong&gt;, which works just like the
Stinging Blow from the regular version. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; attack deals a
bit more damage if they’ve moved 3 or more squares before making it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also gain the attack and defense bonus from being near drow, and have
Goblin Tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hobgoblin-fleshcarver&quot;&gt;Hobgoblin Fleshcarver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the hobgoblin specialized martial artist. Unlike the bugbear and goblin
examples, fleshcarvers don’t seem to have a religious component to their
training. It’s all about hard work and crafting your own custom-fitted
weapons. Their weapons of choice are a polearm and a set of poisoned throwing
darts, whose poison is harvested from serpents they hunt as part of their
training. Fleshcarvers never refuse a challenge to combat, though they’re smart
enough to not let such a challenge distract them in the middle of an ongoing
battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleshcarvers are Level 6 Elite Controllers with 146 HP. They have Speed 6 and
low-light vision, wear heavy armor, and are armed with the afore-mentioned
specialized weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their stance and movements act as an aura (2) named &lt;strong&gt;Fleshcarver’s Trap&lt;/strong&gt;,
dealing 5 damage to any enemy inside the first time they move during their
turn. Their &lt;strong&gt;glaive&lt;/strong&gt; is reach 2 and is used both for basic attacks and for an
at-will &lt;strong&gt;Glaive Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; that targets all enemies in a close burst 2, does more
damage than the basic attack, and slides targets 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range they can throw those &lt;strong&gt;Toxic Darts&lt;/strong&gt; to do a bit of poison damage and
slow the target (save ends). If the target was already slowed, it’s immobilized
instead. When they’re hit by a melee attack, they can use their reaction to
shift 2 squares and make a dart attack. And finally, fleshcarvers have the same
Hobgoblin Resilience and Phalanx Soldier powers from MM1 hobgoblins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hobgoblins are more effective when lots of enemies are in reach, but the
selective targetting on their area attack means they engage all those enemies
while fighting in formation for that sweet defense bonus from Phanlanx Soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new goblinoid specialists can be inserted into any goblin encounter, and
being goblins themselves also work well with any of their typically allied
creatures. These are the encounters we get on the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 1: 1 goblin acolyte, 3 goblin warriors, 1 Lolthbound Goblin. It’s likely
the whole group are drow slaves, with the LBG being their leader. The level
math works out, but the LBG’s drow-related skills are wasted here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: 2 bugbear wardancers, 2 bugbear warriors, 1 barghest battle lord. A
warlord and their bodyguards.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: 1 fleshcarver, 3 hobgoblin soldiers, 2 dire wolves. A patrol with a
little extra kick to it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: 4 lolthbound goblin slaves, 1 drow priest, 2 blade spiders, 2 drow
warriors. Lots of poison being thrown around on this one, which makes the
minions more dangerous than their level would indicate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these new additions, because their stat blocks are interesting and their
associated lore fleshes goblin culture out a bit more. I like that they’re
complex enough to have multiple martial styles.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/goblin.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/goblin.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
