<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 22:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 22:09:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Colossus</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-colossus.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Brian Valenzuela. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw back in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/08/23/colossus.html&quot;&gt;Colossus entry for the Monster Manual&lt;/a&gt;, colossi are at
the top of the tech tree for traditional constructs, and only gods and
near-divine spellcasters have the power to create them. They’re the kind of
thing that was used as a weapon in the Dawn War. Well, here we learn that the
gods weren’t the only side of that war that could make colossi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the post linked above, I made a reference to the giant monsters from the
Shadow of the Colossus game. The primordial colossus we’re looking at here fits
them much better than the godforged variant from the first Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most primordial colossi were created at the time of the Dawn War, and being as
ageless as their creators they still exist today. Some roam the planes seeking
to fulfill the orders of their long-gone masters, but others lie dormant looking
for all the world like shattered ruins or broken parts of the landscape. When
someone approaches them, they rise and smash the intruder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magic that goes into a primordial colossus is a little wilder and less
controlled than the one that goes into the god-forged variant. The principles
behind it are such that a primordial colossus might be created &lt;em&gt;by accident&lt;/em&gt;
in any event that causes the release of a massive amount of elemental
energy. This includes the awakening or destruction of a mighty elemental
being. It’s also possible for an epic spellcaster to acquire and perform the
ritual to create one of these constructs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again we get a single stat block here, so let’s get right to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;primordial-colossus&quot;&gt;Primordial Colossus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This baby is a Huge Elemental Animate with the Construct keyword, and a Level 29
Elite Brute with 640 HP. It’s immune to disease, fear, poison and sleep, and has
a Variable Elemental Resistance 15 switchable 3 times per encounter. Its ground
speed is 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primordial colossi really lean into that mechanic for composite energy
damage. They have an &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Presence&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that deals 15 damage of the
“acid, cold, fire, lightning, and thunder” type to anyone caught inside. You
need resistance to all five types in order to not take full damage from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; do physical damage, but they likely prefer to use a
&lt;strong&gt;Colossal Slam&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (close blast 3 vs. AC), which does the same damage
over an area and triggers a secondary attack vs. Fortitude that does a bit of
extra five-type elemental damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy moves adjacent to the colossus, it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Reactive Kick&lt;/strong&gt; as
a reaction, targetting Fortitude, doing a good bit of five-type damage, pushing
the target 4 squares and knocking it prone. This recharges once the colossus is
first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staying away does you no good, since it can throw &lt;strong&gt;Primordial Stones&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged
20 vs. Reflex) that do only a bit less damage than the slam and have a secondary
area attack (Close Burst 5 vs. Fortitude) which does that sweet five-type
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two sample encounters have primordial colossi guarding ancient ruins
alongside other similarly powerful apotropaics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 26: 1 primordial colossus, 2 great flameskulls, 1 slaughterstone
hammerer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 27: 1 primordial colossus, 1 primordial naga.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe an epic adventure centered on Far Realm opposition could have some
horrible aberrant secret guarded by both godforged and primordial colossi -
something so terrible the gods and primordials actually joined forces to
protect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, I find those Big Balls of Elemental Damage in the colossus’ stat
block to be a lot of fun. It’s so hard to resist you’d get the same result by
just using straight physical damage, but describing it this way reinforces the
elemental nature of the creature… and you get to see the look on your players’
faces as you announce they took acid, cold, fire lightning and thunder damage.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/colossus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/colossus.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Cockatrice</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-cockatrice.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Art by Brian Valenzuela. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know both cockatrices and basilisks are based on the same vague lump
of medieval folklore about an animal that can turn you to stone. The exact name,
description and proportion of snake/lizard/chicken traits this animal has varies
in each specific story. D&amp;amp;D, of course, turned each possible name for the same
thing into a totally different monster. They’ve been in the game since at least
the days of BECMI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cockatrices are bird-like monsters whose bite can turn a victim to stone. Unlike
a lot of other deadly creatures, though, they don’t actually seem to be
predators. Their petrification powers are a defense mechanism, which they will
use while trying to run away from whatever enemy threatens them. So yeah, you
could say cockatrices are a bit chicken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, cockatrice lairs tend to have the little statue gardens common to
petrifying monsters, all likely made from predators who thought they could
handle it or from innocent creatures who had no idea whose lawn they were
stepping on. I imagine careful adventurers can just avoid the area entirely if
they see the statues, though there are reasons they would seek it out instead:
the freshly plucked feathers of a cockatrice can be used to brew a potion that
undoes petrification if applied within 24 hours. A single dose requires a whole
cockatrice’s worth of feathers, which in turn likely requires killing the beast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cockatrices are themselves immune to petrification, which makes them good pets
for medusas. The book also says other reptilians, like lizardfolk and yuan-ti,
also make use of them. They’re definitely easier to handle than a basilisk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only get a single stat block here, so let’s get right to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cockatrice&quot;&gt;Cockatrice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Small Natural Beast and a Level 5 Skirmisher with 63 HP and low-light
vision. It’s immune to petrification as discussed earlier, and has a ground
speed of 4 and a flight speed of 6 (clumsy). As a reminder, the Clumsy keyword
means the creature has a -4 to attacks when using that movement mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cockatrice’s basic attack is its &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which is kinda weak but triggers
a secondary attack vs. Fortitude. A hit there does no damage and slows the
victim (save ends). This worsens to Immobilized on the first failed save, and to
“permanent until cured” petrification on the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an enemy moves adjacent to the cockatrice it can use &lt;strong&gt;Buffeting Wings&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 4-6) as an interrupt, which allows it to bite the triggering enemy and
shift 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given their low level, cockatrices are likely to be the first petrifying
monsters a party encounters. They’re simple, but their main attack is scary
enough to make up for that. They could be made into higher-level threats if, in
addition to leveling them up, you made them more mobile and gave them an extra
special attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 5: 2 cockatrices and a trio of lizardfolk using
them as attack animals.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/cockatrice.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/03/cockatrice.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Chaos Shard</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-chaos-shard.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any edition of D&amp;amp;D it’s easy to get obsessed with its fiend taxonomy, but
there are always some creatures that end up slipping through its cracks. Take
chaos shards, for example. They form spontaneously at the edges of the terrible
maelstrom that exists at the border between the Elemental Chaos and the Abyss,
when the energies of those two planes clash in a particular way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These crystalline entities are sapient, violent, and cruel. Since they don’t
have any biological needs to distract them, they’re quite content with roaming
around and blasting everything they see with elemental energies. I imagine they
give preference to targets that can scream and suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having themes tied to the Abyss, being Chaotic Evil, and even having
variable elemental resistance, these things are not demons. They do have some
sort of metaphysical connection to the Shard of Pure Evil at the bottom of the
Abyss, though. Legend has it that the most powerful chaos shards are splinters
of that legendary blight upon the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some wizards trap chaos shards for use as power sources, which I bet is not at
all dangerous or likely to result in death and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a handful of stat blocks for shards covering from the mid-Heroic to the
mid-Paragon tiers. All are Medium Elemental Magical Beasts. They have
Darkvision, immunities to disease and poison, and a variable elemental
resistance similar to that of demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re all Artillery monsters, and their movement is fairly slow, though they
do fly. Most are strongly aspected towards a specific element, and have damaging
auras that get a bit stronger if their enemies are suffering from some condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;storm-shard&quot;&gt;Storm Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 4 Artillery shard has 44 HP and aspected towards lightning and
thunder. Its ground and fly speeds are 3, and it projects a &lt;strong&gt;Static Storm&lt;/strong&gt;
aura (2) that deals 3 lightning and thunder damage to those enemies caught
inside. This rises to 5 if the enemy is immobilized. They have the standard
senses and immunities, and their variable resistance is 5 and can be switched
once per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fire &lt;strong&gt;Shock Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fortitude) that do some lightning damage and
“strongly incentivize” the target to move: if they don’t end their next turn at
least 4 squares away from their current position, they take lightning damage
roughly equal to triple that of the initial attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If forced into melee, the shard attacks with &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Strikes&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fortitude)
which deal thunder damage and knock the target prone if it’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When killed, storm shards explode! This &lt;strong&gt;Storm Shatter&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 3
vs. Fortitude) attack deals lightning and thunder damage, pushes the targets 3
squares, and deafens them (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note on damage types: the expression “lightning and thunder damage” above
denotes an attack with a single damage roll that is of both types at
once. Targets use the smallest of their relevant elemental resistances against
this damage. In this specific example, someone with Lightning Resistance 10 and
Thunder Resistance 5 would subtract only 5 from the rolled damage. Someone that
resists only one of the component types takes full damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;death-shard&quot;&gt;Death Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aspected towards necrotic energies, Death Shards are Level 8 Artillery with 71
HP. It has all the standard traits including Variable Resistance 5
(1/encounter), and also Necrotic Resistance 10. Its speed is 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thing projects a &lt;strong&gt;Death Shadow&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that deals necrotic damage to
enemies caught inside, which increases if the enemies are slowed. It fires
&lt;strong&gt;Death Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Fortitude) that deal necrotic damage and slow
(save ends). In melee, it cuts you with a &lt;strong&gt;Razor Shard&lt;/strong&gt;, a regular basic
attack dealing physical damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit less volatile than the Storm Shard, but still dangerous: when hit by
a critical, it reacts with a &lt;strong&gt;Critical Fracture&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2
vs. Fortitude), which deals necrotic damage and weakens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the death shard resists damage (i.e, if it’s hit with something covered by
its resistances), all of its attacks deal extra damage until the end of its next
turn. This trait is named &lt;strong&gt;Life to Death&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flame-shard&quot;&gt;Flame Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Level 12 Artillery monsters have an even 100 HP and are a bit more literal
about this whole artillery business than most of their compatriots. Their speed
is 4 and their variable resistance 10 (switchable twice per encounter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flame shard’s main ranged attack is &lt;strong&gt;Flame Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 2 within 10
vs. Reflex) which is basically like an at-will fireball, though its damage is
rather low. In melee it stabs people with a &lt;strong&gt;Burning Shard&lt;/strong&gt; that does fire
damage, and it projects a &lt;strong&gt;Heat Wave&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that deals fire damage and
inflicts a -2 penalty against ongoing fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When killed they explode in a final attack that’s much like a Flame Burst
centered on themselves, and which also does ongoing fire damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prismatic-shard&quot;&gt;Prismatic Shard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living proof that “Radiant” doesn’t always mean “Good”… it can also mean “evil
disco ball”! These are Level 16 Artillery monsters with 123 HP. To the standard
list of shard immunities they add an immunity to &lt;em&gt;radiant damage&lt;/em&gt;, making the
party’s divine characters very sad. Their variable resistance is 10 and can be
switched four times per encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their aura (2) is named &lt;strong&gt;Prismatic Corona&lt;/strong&gt;. It does radiant damage and
inflicts a -2 penalty to all saving throws during made during the affected
enemy’s turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the Prismatic Shard’s attacks do radiant damage. The melee &lt;strong&gt;Prism
Flare&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex) has nothing else going on for it. The &lt;strong&gt;Iridescent Bolt&lt;/strong&gt;
(ranged 20 vs. Will) also blinds for a turn. Its &lt;strong&gt;Flashing Colors&lt;/strong&gt; (close
burst 3 vs. Will; minor action) do no damage but daze (save ends). And the
&lt;strong&gt;Prismatic Shatter&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Will) attack it uses when it dies also
blinds (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, chaos shards don’t have frail organic bodies to worry about,
so they can live solely for the fun of seeing people explode from their
elemental blasts. They hang out with creatures who are equally appreciative of
this highly refined form of entertainment, including slaads, demons, and certain
types of Internet troll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also be summoned and controlled through elemental magic, which makes
them popular with certain spellcasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: 2 death shards, a bloodseep demon, and 2 evistros.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 17: 1 prismatic shard, 3 blue slaads, and 1 green slaad.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaos shards fulfill the important mechanical niche of providing artillery
support for demons and slaads, since these monster types are all about melee and
tend to lack ranged firepower. They also further confuse the taxonomy of “things
from the Abyss”, something which I’m finding more and more interesting as I
progress through these monster books.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/01/chaos-shard.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/06/01/chaos-shard.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Vault 2: Centipede</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-centipede.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monstrous centipedes have been in the game since the beginning, and are based on
real-world animals. Let’s see what 4e makes of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only recently realized D&amp;amp;D centipedes aren’t as fantastical as I always
thought. There are thousands of real-world centipede species, and the ones I was
familiar with were pretty small and generally not dangerous to people. However,
some species can reach up to 30cm (a foot!) in length, and have a poisonous bite
that might cause fever and chills in people. It’s possible for someone to be
allergic to centipede venom, and in that case their bite can cause anaphylatic
shock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the only fantastical thing about the D&amp;amp;D centipede in early editions of the
game was the fact that its venom was always save-or-die. Its size was realistic,
and so was its venom in later editions when it became less deadly. Of course,
the game also had truly giant centipedes which were entirely fantastical, and
this remains true here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centipedes can be found in woodlands, caves, and lots of other
environments. They’re ferocious predators and aggressive enough to attack much
larger creatures if they feel threatened. The larger specimens are of a scale
large enough to see humanoids as potential prey, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all this aggressiveness, it seems lots of sapient creatures are able to
keep them as pets and guard animals. I suspect magic might be
involved. Centipedes are particularly popular pets for Torog worshippers, who
consider them sacred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centipedes are Natural Beasts of varying size. The game gives them Darkvision,
though it might be more accurate to give them blindsight instead. The authors
didn’t consider a single foot-long centipede to be a worthy threat, so we get
stats for a swarm of them and for a giant specimen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centipede-swarm&quot;&gt;Centipede Swarm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Medium swarm is a Level 2 Brute with 44 HP. It has ground and climb speeds
of 6, with Spider Climb (which allows them to cling to ceilings). It has all
standard swarm traits, taking half damage from melee and ranged attacks, and 10
extra damage from close and area attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) deals 3 automatic damage to each enemy caught
inside, +2 per centipede swarm adjacent to the enemy. This is deceptively
dangerous, particularly if you assume multiple swarm auras stack! An enemy
adjacent to a single swarm will take 5 damage at the start of their turn. An
enemy adjacent to 2 of them would take 14, or 7 if the auras don’t stack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The swarm’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Swarm of Mandibles&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Reflex), which deals a
little bit of physical damage, which increases by 1 with each adjacent centipede
swarm. A hit also deals ongoing 5 poison damage (save ends). If the enemy is
already taking ongoing poison damage, they’re weakened (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the swarm is hit by an area or close attack, their &lt;strong&gt;Survival Instinct&lt;/strong&gt;
causes them to shift 3 squares as a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting monster: despite being a brute, its attack is kinda weak. Most of
the damage comes from the swarm aura, particularly if you assume multiple
centipede swarm auras stack. You’ll never encounter just one swarm either -
there should be at least two in the group to enjoy those cool exponential
bonuses. More than two might be pushing a bit, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centipede-scuttler&quot;&gt;Centipede Scuttler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A proper giant, this is a single Medium individual. It’s a Level 4 Skirmisher
with 51 HP and both ground and climb speeds of 8. Can’t run away from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; targets AC and does a little more damage than the swarm’s, but has
the same riders. Against a weakened creature (which likely got that way from its
venom) it can &lt;strong&gt;Feed&lt;/strong&gt;, dealing roughly triple the damage of a basic bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an at-will move action, the Scuttler can, well, &lt;strong&gt;Scuttle&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it
to shift 4 squares. When it shifts into an ally’s space while scuttling, that
space doesn’t count as one of the 4 squares. Be sure to give it lots of
buddies when building the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 4: 1 ankheg, 2 bloodthorn vines, and 2 centipede swarms. What rotten
luck that all of them would be hanging out next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 5: 2 scuttlers, 1 gnoll huntmaster, 2 gnoll marauders. So they keep more
than hyenas as pets.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the old save-or-die centipedes and these feel properly scary as well,
while also being distinct from all the other giant creepy crawlies.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/30/centipede.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/30/centipede.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Centaur</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-centaur.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centaurs are inspired by Greek myth, in which they were The Worst (with rare
exceptions). They’ve been in D&amp;amp;D since at least the days of BECMI, which even
had a supplement that made them playable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth Edition centaurs are a good deal nicer than their mythological
counterparts. Their culture venerates nature in its wilder aspects, and they
have an extensive martial tradition. In other words: they’re quite rowdy and
love a good fight. Kord and Melora are a lot more popular with them than
Corellon, who is otherwise the go-to fey deity. I don’t know if the lore of the
primal spirits had been finalized at this point, but centaurs also work great as
primal spirit worshippers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centaurs like to live in areas that contain vast plains or steppes, but they
like to build their settlements on hills or inside caves. The combination gives
them a defensible position surrounded by clear sight lines all around, and also
gives them the large space they need to run around and to grow their food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centaurs are not typically evil, but they’re territorial, mistrustful of
strangers, and hate people who despoil nature. Dealing with them peacefully
requires careful diplomacy that begins beyond arrow range. The prospective
ambassador should spend great effort making their approach both obvious and
obviously non-threatening. Once the centaurs recognize you for a friend, though,
they can become steadfast allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most centaur settlements are located in the Feywild, though there are some in
the world bordering elven forests. Centaur law is simple, and most crimes carry
banishment and exile as their punishment. Exiled centaur criminals could easily
end up working with other villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centaurs are Large Fey Humanoids, with low-light vision and a ground speed
of 8. They have two signature abilities. The first is that their basic attacks
do an extra die of damage when used in a charge. The other is a reaction called
&lt;strong&gt;Quick Kick&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to make a free kick attack against an enemy
who moves into a position that flanks the centaur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centaur-hunter&quot;&gt;Centaur Hunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this was a PC, it would be a Twin Strike-spamming ranger. Hunters are Level
12 Artillery with 96 HP and all standard centaur traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with classic horse archer tactics, using their superior mobility to
keep away and fire on the move. Their main ranged attack is &lt;strong&gt;Lightning-Fast
Arrows&lt;/strong&gt; (range 25/50 vs. AC), a standard action that allows them to shoot
twice. Though each individual arrow has low damage, the two combined almost line
up with MM3 math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Charge Arrow&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 25/50 vs. Fortitude) to
do a bit more single-arrow damage, push the target 3 squares, and knock it
prone. I’d say it’s not worth it unless the target is near a cliff or the hunter
has melee buddies that would benefit from a prone enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter the hunter can speed up even more and deliver a &lt;strong&gt;Triple
Shot&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 25/50 vs. AC), making three attacks whose individual damage is
a bit higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone does manage to engage the hunter in melee, it can defend itself with
a &lt;strong&gt;bastard sword&lt;/strong&gt;… but it doesn’t really need to, since the &lt;strong&gt;Close-Combat
Archer&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes it not provoke opportunity attacks from the targets of its
shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centaur-ravager&quot;&gt;Centaur Ravager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most likely melee buddy for the hunter, this is a barbarian-type. Ravagers
are Level 12 Brutes with 150 HP and all standard centaur traits. They fight in
melee with their &lt;strong&gt;bastard swords&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Berserk Rush&lt;/strong&gt; (melee
1 vs. Fortitude; recharges when first bloodied) to do even more damage on a
charge, push the target 2 squares, and knock them prone. When first bloodied,
they also use &lt;strong&gt;Brash Retaliation&lt;/strong&gt;, a free action attack that does high damage
and pushes the targets 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this suggests shock cavalry tactics: charge, fight in place for a bit,
then move away and charge again. Though I guess ravagers have no problem staying
in the thick of it either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centaur-mystic&quot;&gt;Centaur Mystic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wise primal or divine spellcaster, the mystic takes a priestly role in centaur
culture and advises the community on its duties towards nature and the
spirits. In combat they use plant- and earth-themed magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mystics are Level 13 Controllers with 132 HP and all standard centaur
traits. They wield Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaffs&lt;/strong&gt; which also acts as implements for
their magic. The mainstay here is &lt;strong&gt;Rootwhip Staff&lt;/strong&gt;, a melee spell that targets
Reflex and does the same damage as a basic staff attack, but also slides the
target 3 squares and slows it (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystic’s ranged options are big guns with limited ammo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancestral Chargers&lt;/strong&gt; is a Close Blast 5 that presumably summons ancestors
spirits and has funky mechanics. It targets both Fortitude and Will: you make a
single attack roll against both defenses. If the attack beats the target’s Will,
they take high psychic damage; if it beats the target’s Fortitude they’re
knocked prone and pushed 2 squares. This spell recharges when a friendly centaur
within 10 squares drops to 0 hit points, which implies the recharge comes from
summoning their recently departed spirit for one last strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biting Earth&lt;/strong&gt; (Area Burst 2 within 10; recharges when first bloodied) creates
a zone that lasts for a turn and can be sustained with standard actions. The
biting earth zone immobilizes all enemies within. These enemies can choose to
take 3d8 damage to save against the effect as a free action. There’s no regular
save, so if the enemy doesn’t want to take damage they’re stuck in place while
the zone lasts. When the zone is sustained, the mystic can choose to move it up
to 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Mystic Resonance&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action), which
affects all allies within 10 squares. It heals them for 10 HP and allows them to
roll a save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like you want to open with Ancestral Chargers here, and then use Biting
Earth to try and hold the PCs in place for the ravagers and hunters to do their
stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centaur-fey-charger&quot;&gt;Centaur Fey Charger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fey chargers are significantly more powerful than the other centaurs we saw up
until now, being better fighters and having a host of storm-themed powers. This
would fit a warden or a paladin of Kord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re level 18 Soldiers with 172 HP and all standard centaur traits. They wear
mail and carry a shield in addition to the traditional centaur bastard sword,
none of which slows them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can fire &lt;strong&gt;Stabs of Lightning&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex) do to lighthning
damage at range while closing in, but the main event is the melee. Once an
opening presents itself they close in with a &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Charge&lt;/strong&gt;, a strong attack
that does a mix of physical and lightning damage and carries a secondary Close
Burst 2 attack that targets Fortitude, does thunder damage, knocks prone and
marks for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once engaged, their &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; attacks mark for a turn, and they can use
&lt;strong&gt;Thunder Hooves&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Fortitude) as a reaction to attack anyone who
ignores the mark and do thunder damage to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;centaur-campaigner&quot;&gt;Centaur Campaigner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A legendary commander and champion of the centaur people with decades of
military experience. The campaigner is a Level 25 Soldier (Leader) with all
standard centaur traits and a good deal of supernatural wind- and storm-themed
abilities. It wears plate, and carries a shield and a longsword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bonus charge damage of the &lt;strong&gt;longsword&lt;/strong&gt; attack is thunder, and the
Campaigner is all about that glorious impossible charge. Its &lt;strong&gt;Light Hoof&lt;/strong&gt;
trait allows it to ignore all difficult terrain, and &lt;strong&gt;Sky Bound&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will free
action) allows it to fly for the duration of its next move, though it must land
at the end. If that isn’t possible the centaur will gently float down to the
floor, so it doesn’t take fall damage but you might say its momentum gets kinda
ruined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the campaigner’s charge hits it can use &lt;strong&gt;Three Thunder Assault&lt;/strong&gt; to allow
two allies within 10 squares of itself to charge as a free action. These charges
deal a bit of bonus thunder damage as well. Combine this with other centaurs
(maybe even other campaigners), and you have an instant massive cavalry charge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once engaged, &lt;strong&gt;Shock Trooper&lt;/strong&gt; gives the campaigner a small bonus to damage
while it’s adjacent to more than one foe. It can also use a maneuver called
&lt;strong&gt;Hoofed Tornado&lt;/strong&gt; to perform strong attacks on all enemies in a Close Burst 1,
knocking them prone on a hit and marking them for a turn as an effect. This
recharges when it’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centaurs might be found as members of most fey-themed encounter groups, working
alongside elves, eladrin, satyrs, and so on. I imagine the nastier sort of
centaur might also work alongside shady customers such as banshrae, hags, or
fomorians. For some of those you might want to do some level adjustment either
of the centaurs themselves or their associates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want your party to meet centaurs early, knocking 10 levels from the
centaur hunter, ravager and mystic would be a good start, making them
early-heroic NPCs/enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter we get is Level 23: a centaur campaigner plus two eladrin
ghaeles of winter mounted on fell wyverns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these centaurs! They can be either friend or foe depending on how they’re
treated, and in any case the PCs might find a way to talk to them instead of
fighting right away. They’re exactly what I look for in a NPC humanoid
species. Their stat blocks also work well at giving the impression of a people
for whom infantry tactics and cavalry tactics are the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/29/centaur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/29/centaur.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Streamlined Melee Mastery for GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In GURPS, the Trained by a Master advantage allows a character to perform
martial feats on par with those seen in kung fu movies and other similar
stories. The Weapon Master advantage does basically the same in a slightly
different way. They overlap so much that I’m not sure if they were meant to
exist in the same campaign!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think both advantages are fairly priced on their own, but I don’t think both
of them combined are worth 75 points. Choosing to only allow one of them in your
campaign is a fairly simple matter, but what if you want to allow both,
potentially on the same character?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the differences between the two traits are fiddly matters of skill
coverage. Sweeping those aside leaves us with the remaining elephant in the
room, the Weapon Master damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elephant-examination-the-damage-bonus&quot;&gt;Elephant Examination: The Damage Bonus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the damage bonus is the biggest game changer in the entire WM
package. Even if a Weapon Master never learns a supernatural skill and never
attacks or parries more than once per turn, they’re still going to feel like an
entirely different character from someone who has the exact same stats but lacks
the advantage. It feels a bit unfair to me that this bonus is not available to
characters that focus on unarmed strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS uses realistic assumptions as a base for its rules, and under those
assumptions a combatant with a weapon always has a big advantage over one
without. The unarmed fighter risks limb injury on every parry and strike. The
armed one has greater reach and much better damage from using swing attacks or
simply from doing a better damage type than crushing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unarmed fighter with Trained By a Master can approach that by taking other
traits… But then they’ve spent 60 points and bought a Hard combat skill to be
on par with someone who bought an Average skill and took Weapon Master (single
weapon) for 20 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t feel a need to keep this “effectiveness gap” between armed and unarmed
skills when we’re dealing with a campaign that allows “mastery” advantages in
the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-traits&quot;&gt;New Traits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solution to the above situation is to rejigger the existing traits. The new
and altered traits below are available in any campaign that also allows both
Trained by a Master and Weapon Master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;true-master-50-points&quot;&gt;True Master (50 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through either decades of dedication or being some sort of war god, you have
mastered all forms of “archaic” combat. You gain &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the benefits from having
both Trained by a Master and the full version of Weapon Master. Your unarmed
strikes enjoy the same damage bonus described under Weapon Master. This bonus
&lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; stack with other bonuses from high striking skills and from traits like
Claws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those two advantages still exist, and represent a slightly less comprehensive
form of mastery. You can upgrade from any of them to True Master by spending the
difference between their point value and 50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iron-limbs-10-points&quot;&gt;Iron Limbs (10 points)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your limbs are immune to incidental injury during unarmed combat. Enemies can’t
damage your limbs when they parry your unarmed attacks with a weapon, nor can
they switch targets and damage your limbs when you fail to parry their
attacks. You also don’t hurt yourself when hitting armored opponents with
unarmed strikes. Your limbs can still be deliberately targeted by enemy attacks,
however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trait replaces Unarmed Master, as it is basically Unarmed Master without
the damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like those two traits, though as of this writing I still need to actually
field-test them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns that use these two new advantages, an unarmed specialist &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt;
turn their limbs into Strikers. That’s what Unarmed Master did, and we did away
with it. IF the specialist in question happens to belong to a non-human species
that has natural Strikers, though, &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; would stack with True Master. Beware
of boxing crab-people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron Limbs doesn’t have any prerequisites: you could buy it without having any
of the “mastery” advantages. This allows it to be used to represent an extremely
focused blessing, or a creature whose limbs are naturally hard to hurt or even
naturally made of metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you feel 10 points for Iron Limbs is too expensive for someone who
is already a True Master, you could try rolling it into True Master at no extra
cost, and eliminating the separate Iron Limbs advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/27/masterful-combat.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Bullywugs</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=left&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-bullywug.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullywugs first appeared in the AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition Fiend Folio, and featured
heavily in the D&amp;amp;D cartoon of the 80’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullywugs are frog-people who claim they were created by the original
primordials, not by the gods, and that by living lives of cruelty and violence
they can reincarnate as slaads. They also believe the world itself hates them,
which they sense as a constant paranoid feeling that everyone is out to get
them. And indeed, nature itself seems to breathe in relief when a bullywug is
slain in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullywug culture places no value in conservation: they move into an area
(preferrably a swampy one) and exhaust its resources as quickly as
possible. Anything they can’t use they might very well end up destroying. When
there’s nothing left, they might resort to cannibalism. Because of this
behavior, and possibly because of the divine curse alluded to above, bullywug
territory eventually becomes a barren and dismal echo of what it once was. By
the book, they’re typically Chaotic Evil with an Int score of 6 and speak
Primordial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned several times in the past, I’m not really a fan of Universally
Evil Humanoids, so I’d say it’s possible for there to be bullywugs who aren’t
Captain Planet villains and who can coexist more peacefully with their
neighbors. Who knows, maybe they could be the diplomatic bridge between the
humans over in the fields and the lizardfolk deeper in the swamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullywugs are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Aquatic keyword, which allows
them to breathe underwater and gives them combat bonuses while submerged. They
have ground speeds of 6 with Swamp Walk, ignoring swamp-flavored difficult
terrain. They also have Swim speeds of 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bullywug signature abilities all come from that divine curse. &lt;strong&gt;Rancid Air&lt;/strong&gt;
is an aura (2) which causes enemies to become weakened until the end of their
next turn if they spend a healing surge while inside. &lt;strong&gt;Nature’s Release&lt;/strong&gt;
triggers when the bullywug is killed by a critical hit, and restores a handful
of HP to their slayer. Our theoretical non-evil froggy people would lack either
of these traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bullywug-mucker&quot;&gt;Bullywug Mucker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 1 Brute with 34 HP likely makes up the rank-and-file of a bullywug
force. It wields a &lt;strong&gt;spear&lt;/strong&gt; in combat, and has a &lt;strong&gt;Bully&lt;/strong&gt; trait that makes it
cause extra damage to prone targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can make targets prone with &lt;strong&gt;Bullywug Rush&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Fortitude;
recharge 5-6), a charge attack that deals more damage and knocks the target
prone. A miss here deals 3 damage to the Mucker and knocks &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; prone. I’m
starting to feel sorry for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bullywug-twitcher&quot;&gt;Bullywug Twitcher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 2 Skirmisher with 34 HP, who fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Javelin&lt;/strong&gt; either in
melee or at range. Once per encounter the twitching intensifies and it can
perform a &lt;strong&gt;Spasmodic Hop&lt;/strong&gt;, ending any marks on it, shifting 4 squares, and
making an enhanced javelin attack at the end that also inflicts a -4 attack
penalty on the target for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This power is Reliable, which means it’s not spent if the attack misses. On the
other hand, the Twitcher has no other special movement powers. So ironically, it
becomes less mobile once it lands its special attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bullywug-croaker&quot;&gt;Bullywug Croaker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weak and flabby specimen that uses its remarkably bad breath to make up for
its lack of strength. It’s a Level 3 Minion Brute that attacks with &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;
and with a &lt;strong&gt;Foul Croak&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Blast 2 vs. Fortitude) that does poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bullywug-mud-lord&quot;&gt;Bullywug Mud Lord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spellcaster that makes me think that whole business about emulating slaads
being a path to power might have some truth to it. Much smarter than the average
bullywug, mud lords often end up in leadership positions, and they have
absolutely no qualms about sacrificing their pathetic underlings to ensure their
own survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re Level 3 Artillery with 39 HP. Their ranged spells all cover an area, and
appear to be more vomited than cast. &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Croak&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within 20
vs. Reflex) does fire and thunder damage, and &lt;strong&gt;Electric Reflux&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3
vs. Reflex; recharge 6) does cold and lightning damage, half on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither of these attacks are selective. In fact, if they include at least one
ally in their area, &lt;strong&gt;Necessary Sacrifices&lt;/strong&gt; grants the mud lord a +2 attack
bonus. Okay, this dude isn’t pathetic, he’s despicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 1: 1 bloodthorn vine, 2 croakers, 2 muckers, and a twitcher.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: A mud lord, 3 twitchers, 3 ettercap fang guards and 1 ettercap
webspinner.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear whether the vine or the ettercaps are working with the bullywugs or
not. Their lore doesn’t make me think they’d work well with anyone. In fact,
they’d probably be in conflict with any other sapients who live in the same
swamp as them. If you want to set up a good old-fashioned swamp crawl where the
PC can meddle with several factions, a bullywug-goblin-kobold-lizardfolk
four-way conflict is an excellent starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/23/bullywug.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/23/bullywug.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Beholder</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beholders appeared in the first Monster Manual, and I covered them
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/05/27/beholder.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The Monster Manual 2 brings us a few more varieties, including some
that also made it into the Monster Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the three beholder varieties here gets its own bit of lore, so let’s
combine that with their numbers below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, beholders are Aberrant Magical Beasts. They have All-Around Vision
and Darkvision, and a variable fly speed with hover capability. In general their
attacks consist of a very weak bite and a whole bunch of thematic ranged attacks
from their eye stalks and central eye. Beholder eye rays are Ranged, but don’t
provoke opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beholder-gauth&quot;&gt;Beholder Gauth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one appeared in the Monster Vault, and so we discussed them a bit
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/05/27/beholder.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Gauths are the least of their kind, but they’re still as unpleasant
and power-hungry as any beholder. Their relative weakness means they often don’t
end up on the top of whatever evil org chart they join, and so they are
constantly scheming to rise in its ranks. They’re the most Starscream-like of
beholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gauths also like to capitalize on the fearsome reputation of their larger
relatives, so people who don’t know better might confuse them for the more
dangerous varieties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already covered the Monster Vault version of gauths in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/05/27/beholder.html&quot;&gt;post on MM1
beholders&lt;/a&gt;. The Monster Manual 2 is pretty much identical, except it suffers
from the damage bug and has a remarkably weak bite. Just use the MV stats for
this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beholder-eye-of-frost&quot;&gt;Beholder Eye of Frost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-beholder-eye-of-frost.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A counterpart to the MM1’s &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/05/27/beholder.html&quot;&gt;Eye of Flame&lt;/a&gt;, this is a beholder with a great
affinity for elemental ice. It prefers to dwell in very cold climates in the
world and Elemental Chaos, where it keeps company such as ice archons, frost
giants, and oni. Since eyes of frost aren’t that much stronger than these other
ice monsters, they often end up in the same narrative position as gauths,
scheming to gain the power and respect they feel is due to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyes of Frost are Large and have a fly speed of 6. They’re Level 14 Elite
Artillery with 222 HP. When first bloodied they coat themselves in &lt;strong&gt;Ice
Armor&lt;/strong&gt;, increasing their AC and Fortitude by 2 for the remainder of the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is super weak: 2d6 damage. You’d need to triple this to get it in
line with the new math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more interesting are the eye beams. The &lt;strong&gt;Central Eye&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 8
vs. Reflex; minor action 1/round) weakens on a hit (save ends). If a target
weakened by this power would become slowed, they become immobilized instead, and
this lasts until they’re no longer weakened!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Eye of Frost has access to 3 &lt;strong&gt;Eye Rays&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Eyes of the Beholder&lt;/strong&gt;
allows it to use one of them as a free action against any enemy that starts its
turn within 5 squares of the beholder. That enemy also gains Vulnerable 5 Cold
until the end of the beholder’s next turn. A ray attack can also be done with a
standard action, of course, further increasing the beholder’s rate of fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rays have Range 10, and have the following effects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Freeze Ray&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude, deals cold damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Telekinesis&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude, slides 6 squares.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ice Ray&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude, deals less cold damage than the freeze ray but
also deals ongoing cold damage and immobilizes (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cold resistance on the PCs will go a long way towards making the eye of frost
less dangerous, though its control effects will still be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beholder-eye-of-chaos&quot;&gt;Beholder Eye of Chaos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-beholder-eye-of-chaos.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, there was a beholder &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/05/27/beholder.html&quot;&gt;Eye Tyrant&lt;/a&gt; who dove into the Abyss
in search of the Shard of Ultimate Evil wielded by Tharizdun. Though the
creature never found the shard, it nevertheless emerged from the experience
infused with all sorts of demonic energies, which increased its power and warped
its body and mind. This stat block could represent that individual or one of its
descendants, or perhaps another beholder who thought he could do it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eyes of Chaos are still quite capable of concocting complex schemes and
directing armies of underlings… only now those underlings tend to be demons
more often than not, and those schemes end up having widespread destruction and
bloodshed as either their main goals or as desirable side effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This twisted thing is Large, and Level 25 Elite Artillery. It has a pretty
impressive fly speed of 8, which makes it a lot zoomier than your average
beholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is once again nothing to write home about, despite all those lovely
teeth. The &lt;strong&gt;Central Eye&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 20 vs. Fortitude) has the traditional
antimagic/enervation effect that forbits the target from using encounter or
daily powers until the end of the beholder’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that we get the six &lt;strong&gt;eye rays&lt;/strong&gt;, all Ranged 10:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Telekinesis&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude, does physical damage and slides 6 squares.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blinding&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Reflex, does physical damage and blinds (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confounding&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Will, does psychic damage, slides 6 squares, and dazes
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maddening&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Will, does psychic damage and dominates until the end of
the beholder’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Will, does psychic damage and forces the target to move its
speed away from the beholder by the safest route possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teleporting&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Reflex, does physical damage and teleports 10 squares.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual &lt;strong&gt;Eyes of the Beholder&lt;/strong&gt; trait means anyone starting their turn within
5 squares of the beholder gets hit with a random eye ray. When the monster is
first bloodied it releases a &lt;strong&gt;Ripple of Chaos&lt;/strong&gt; that allows it to target every
enemy within 5 squares with a random eye ray and then teleport 6 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda want to make a random roll even for the standard-action eye rays with
this critter. For all the randomness, though, it seems the eye ray effects are
actually a bit less exciting than those of a “normal” beholder, since there are
no sudden death effects here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;beholder-ultimate-tyrant&quot;&gt;Beholder Ultimate Tyrant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-beholder-ultimate-tyrant.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you manage to talk to the Ultimate Tyrant, it will tell you that it has the
most valid of reasons for hating all other beholders: they’re a bunch of
posers. They were born in the world or otherwise went native, but the Ultimate
Tyrant is part of the original generation that came directly from the Far Realm
and still keeps its connection to that place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the particulars of your campaign it might even be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; original
beholder. If not, it’s at least among the first to arrive in the world. Perhaps
the only creature that might dispute its claims of OG-ness is the Gibbering Orb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ultimate Tyrant is Huge, and a Level 29 Solo Artillary menace with 1080
HP. This can even make it suitable as a final boss for a campaign that ends in
the mid-epic levels. Its fly speed is 8, again making it a lot faster than the
MM1 beholders. The damage for all of this beholder’s attacks is quite low, and
should likely be at least doubled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, and there’s the stuff you’ll actually be using. The
&lt;strong&gt;Central Eye&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 30 vs. Fortitude; minor action 1/round) does no damage
but dazes and slows on a hit (save ends both). This worsens to a full Stun on
the first failed save. A miss still slows the target (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eyes of the Beholder&lt;/strong&gt; works as usual, and &lt;strong&gt;Spasmodic Rays&lt;/strong&gt; makes it so the
beholder attacks every enemy within 10 squares with an eye ray when it’s first
bloodied and again when it dies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;eye rays&lt;/strong&gt; themselves are quite scary. Instead of simple ranged attacks,
all of them are Area Burst 1 Within 10, and they still don’t provoke opportunity
attacks. If the standard Eye Tyrant is a slow-moving battleship, the Ultimate
Tyrant is a hyper-mobile orbital laser cannon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Madness&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Will; does psychic damage and forces the target to make a
basic attack against its nearest ally.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unraveling&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude; does physical damage and 10 ongoing damage
(save ends). The first failed save causes an additional 1d10 damage; the
second an additional 2d10; the third causes an additional 3d10 and
automatically ends the effect. So if you fail all of your saves, you’ll be
taking a total of 6d10+30 damage over those three turns.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Withering&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude. Does immediate and ongoing necrotic damage
(save ends), with the first failed save also weakening the target. There’s a
(save ends) after the weakening effect, so I’m guessing that’s a separate
save from the ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burning&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Reflex. Does immediate and ongoing fire damage, and also
inflicts a -2 attack penalty (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Telekinesis&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude. Slides the target 8 squares and knocks it
prone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frost&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Reflex. Cold damage, and a -2 penalty to saves until the end
of the beholder’s next turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Petrifying&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude. Causes slowness (save ends), which worsens to
immobilization (save ends) with the first failed save and with petrification
with the second. Petrification is permanent until cured.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disintegrate&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Fortitude. Physical damage, and ongoing 15 physical
damage (save ends). There’s also an ongoing 10 damage after-effect, so in
practice passing that first save only reduces the ongoing damage a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attraction&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Reflex; -5 penalty to all defenses, and at the start of
the target’s turn the beholder pulls it 2 squares (save ends). There’s also a
-2 penalty to defenses as an after-effect (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repulsion&lt;/strong&gt;: vs. Reflex. -2 penalty to Reflex, and at the start of the
target’s turn the beholder pushes it 6 squares (save ends). As an after
effect, the target gets pushed 3 squares in the same way (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the Ultimate Tyrant only has one outright deadly effect among its ray
selection, it has a few other very interesting effects: the increasing ongoing
damage from the Unraveling Ray, the extra-sticky ongoing damage from
Disintegrate, and the first instances I’ve seen of ongoing forced movement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It bears repeating that &lt;em&gt;all of these are area attacks&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, even the
free-action ones from Eye of the Beholder and Spasmodic Ray. This thing is an
army-killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get a total of four sample encounters here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 5: A gauth, 2 barghest savagers, and a goblin underboss. The gauth is
likely the leader here, making the goblins think it’s a fully powered
beholder.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: An Eye of Frost, an oni mage and two wyverns. What haunts the cold
mountain at night.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 24: An Eye of Chaos and a Chaos Hydra. That enough chaos for you?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 29: The Ultimate Tyrant and 2 Slaughterstone Hammerers. What if the
kaiju teamed up with the giant robots?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love beholders and it’s always good to have more. The Eye of Frost feels
weirdly limited in what it can do, like is fiery counterpart in the first MM,
but the Ultimate Tyrant is an absolute unit.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/21/beholder.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/21/beholder.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Behir</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-behir.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behirs first appear in AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, and are one of the game’s many
“not-quite-dragon” monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behirs are giant reptilian creatures with serpentine bodies, many legs (8 or 12,
depending on edition), and innate electrical powers. They’re sapient but
anti-social and uninterested in the trappings of civilization. They don’t even
tolerate each other’s presence for longer than absolutely necessary. A behir
mother will eject her young from the lair shortly after they’re born, forcing
them to fend for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though a behir makes lairs in pretty much the same places you’d expect to find
dragons, it accumulates neither treasure nor servants. All it wants is to hunt
and be left alone. Like a lot of D&amp;amp;D super-predators it doesn’t usually care
about the sapience of its victims, but it &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be reasoned with or bribed if
you can get it to listen to you. Behirs can communicate both in Common and
Draconic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that some people try to recruit behirs into service. Though this can
end badly if the behir’s terms are not met, a successful negotiation will allow
the foolhardy employer to obtain the services of a formidable monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behirs are Huge Natural Magical Beasts, and have Tremorsense 10 and Resist
Lightning 15. They fight with a combination of natural weapons and lightning
attacks, which vary per stat block. They’re Unaligned, and have a typical Int
score of 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;behir&quot;&gt;Behir&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This represents the typical specimen found in the wild. It’s a Level 14 Solo
Soldier with 564 HP. Their ground speed is 7, and they have a climb speed
of 5. In combat they project a &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Storm&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that causes 5
lightning damage to anyone caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The behir fights with its &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which are Reach 3 and
do the same damage. The claw is a basic attack, and the bite does a mix of
physical and lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also &lt;strong&gt;Devour&lt;/strong&gt; a Medium or smaller victim (Reach 3 vs AC), doing bite
damage and swallowing it whole. This counts as a grab! While it lasts the victim
only has line of sight and effect to the behir, and no one else has line of
sight or effect to the victim. A creature can escape the grab by the usual
means, appearing adjacent to he behir, and can also automatically crawl out of a
dead behir as a move action. With a minor action, the behir can sustain the grab
and deal an automatic 15 damage to the victim. Only one victim at a time fits in
its gizzard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monster can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Reflex;
recharge 5-6), which does “high” lightning damage and dazes (save ends), and
does half damage on a miss.  Its &lt;strong&gt;Thunderleg Stomp&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3
vs. Fortitude) does “low” physical damage and knocks targets prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The damage on all of these is too low due to the math bugs: the basic attacks do
an average of 15 damage when they should be doing 22. The tactics section says
behirs begin by swallowing a squishy even if they have to eat a few opportunity
attacks to do it, and then favoring their area attacks unless sorely pressed by
a single character. With a damage upgrade across the board, these tactics are
quite sound, since the Stomp becomes a more viable option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being solo monsters, behirs have a neat initiative trick: they don’t roll
initiative at all! Instead, &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Reflexes&lt;/strong&gt; gives them three turns per
combat round at initiative counts 30, 20, and 10. This means that the poor
swallowed victim might be looking at 45 automatic damage per round if they fail
to escape the grab on their own turn. Using that first action on Swallow is
definitely a worthy investiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;behir-bolter-whelp&quot;&gt;Behir Bolter Whelp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A young specimen, not yet fully grown. It’s merely Large, and a Level 8 Solo
Soldier with 352 HP and Resist 10 Lightning. It’s standard damage is 12, and it
should be around 16 with the update. It has a ground speed of 8 and a climb
speed of 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bolter is going to start the fight by targetting a squishy &lt;strong&gt;Knockdown
Rush&lt;/strong&gt; (Reach 2 vs. AC; minor action; recharge 4-6), which allows it to charge
and knock the target prone on a hit. Then, since this was a minor action, it’s
going to follow that up with a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which work the same as the
adult’s with smaller numbers and Reach 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the PCs inevitably surround it, the bolder will emit a &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Shock&lt;/strong&gt;
pulse (close burst 2 vs. Reflex; recharge 5-6 and when first bloodied) which
does “high” lightning damage, half on a miss. When hit by a melee attack, it can
respond with a claw as a reaction (&lt;strong&gt;Rip-Claw Response&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being young, the bolter already displays &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Reflexes&lt;/strong&gt;, acting
on initiative counts 20, 15, and 5, so with enough luck on those recharge rolls
it can keep bouncing between PCs for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;behir-stormsteed&quot;&gt;Behir Stormsteed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “domesticated” behir was recruited and trained as a mount by storm
giants. It’s a Level 24 Soldier with 229 HP. It has Resisnt Lightning 15, a
ground speed of 8, and replaces the usual climb speed with a Fly speed of 8
(hover). This is explained as the creature having the ability to walk on the
lightning it generates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The math bug affects the stormsteed particularly hard since it’s an epic
creature. Its standard damage is a woeful 18, and it should be 32!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does a mix of physical and lightning damage,
and it can also use its &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Breath&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3 vs. Reflex, recharge
4-6) to deal lightning damage all around itself. I wonder if that was meant to
be a blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When mounted, the stormsteed can use &lt;strong&gt;Ride The Lightning&lt;/strong&gt;, which grants the
rider a +2 to attack with lightning powers, and allows the steed itself to use
Lightning Breath once per turn as a minor action indepentently of the recharge
counter. Perfect for storm giants or someone like a bluespawn godslayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two sample encounters: a level 8 one with a bolter whelp and three
bugbear wardancers, and a level 14 one with an adult, a medusa, and a yuan-ti
incanter. If something even remotely looks like a snake, Zehir has an interest
in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behirs are one of those monsters I never really got into in previous edition. A
closer reading of this MM2 entry does give me a few ideas of how to use them,
but I still can’t say I’m pumped about them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/19/behir.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/19/behir.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Barghest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Barghests have been in the game since AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, though I don’t
think I have the book in which they first appear. Their exact nature has changed
a bit between editions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you described a barghest as a “goblin werewolf”, you’d get the general idea
across while being almost completely wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barghests are born randomly in goblinoid populations. The event is rare, and
usually seen as a blessing from Bane. As a result of this reputation and their
own powers, barghests often rise to leadership positions in goblinoid society
when they grow up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barghests are shapeshifters, and possess two forms: one is a goblinoid (goblin,
hobgoblin or bugbear), and the other a wolf-like creature. You can’t really
mistake them for either normal goblinoids or wolves, though: the creature is
merely &lt;em&gt;wolf-like&lt;/em&gt;, and the other form always has a specific tell that remains
constant across forms. Locks of white hair or a single discolored eye are
common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barghests aren’t particularly vulnerable to silver nor are they affected by the
moon. They’re fairly smart and in full control of their actions in all
forms. And they have psionic powers, which usually manifest as some sort of
psychic vampirism they use to sap the minds and vitality of their foes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barghests are Small or Medium Natural Humanoids with the Shapechanger
keyword. They have low-light vision and a ground speed of 6 (8 in wolf
form). They can &lt;strong&gt;Change Shape&lt;/strong&gt; with a minor action once per round, and have
different basic attacks depending on what their current form is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have some form of harmful psychic power, which varies per stat
block. We have two here, both Medium:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;barghest-savager&quot;&gt;Barghest Savager&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-barghest-savager.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
   Illustration by Chippy. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a bugbear barghest whose love of violence is exceptional even for a
bugbear. As a leader, it tries to incite its troops to perform frequent raids on
any soft targets it can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savagers are Level 4 Brutes with 63 HP. They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;battleaxe&lt;/strong&gt; or with
their wolfish &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt;, and can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Jump Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5-6) with
either, shifting 3 squares before and after the attack and doing extra damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their mental powers manifest as the &lt;strong&gt;Power Feed&lt;/strong&gt; ability (melee 1 vs. Will;
Encounter; Reliable), usable only in wolf form. This does some psychic damage
and allows the barghest to use an encounter or daily power it has seen the
target use this encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack bonus for this will be the same as that of the monster’s other
attacks, but damage and other effects will be as if the power had been used by
the original PC. This would make the ability worth using on high-damage powers,
or those with interesting side effects. When the wizard proclaimed his Sleep
spell would end the fight, this was probably not what he had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reliable keyword means the power isn’t spent if the attack misses, so odds
are the monster will be able to use this successfully at least once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;barghest-battle-lord&quot;&gt;Barghest Battle Lord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-barghest-battle-lord.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustration by Steve Ellis. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hobgoblin barghest has the makings of a legendary general, commanding his
troops with great tactical acumen and preferring to bait his enemies into
traps. He’s a Level 7 Controller with 82 HP, fighting with a greatsword in
humanoid form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wolf form’s &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; knock the target prone on a hit, and the
&lt;strong&gt;greatsword&lt;/strong&gt; makes the battle lord invisible to the target for a turn. In
either form he can use a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Howl&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Will) which does
psychic damage, dazes for a turn, and inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks as an
aftereffect (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He can also use &lt;strong&gt;Life Feed&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude; encounter) in wolf
form, which does a little bit of necrotic damage and inflicts 5 ongoing necrotic
damage (save ends). Whenever the targets take that ongoing damage, the battle
lord heals 5 HP. So if four PCs are hit the battle lord will heal at the start
of each of their turns, totalling 20 HP per round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, as a reaction to being hit by a melee attack, the battle
lord can &lt;strong&gt;Get Some Distance&lt;/strong&gt;, shifting 2 squares away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barghests can be added to any goblin encounter that you think needs an extra
kick. The first few times it happens it might catch the PCs by surprise, but it
will be interesting to find out if they learn to spot the tells. As mentioned in
the lore, barghests will usually occupy leadership positions in whatever group
of goblins they hang out with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember barghests had an extremely complicated backstory in previous
editions, being fiends from the Neutral Evil plane who happened to be able to
shapeshift into goblins and who had a whole complicated hierarchy back home
based on how many souls they had devoured. All of that is gone here, which I
think is for the best in the end. Some goblins can just wolf out and break your
mind with their psychic powers. It’s one of those things that happens.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/18/barghest.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/05/18/barghest.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
