<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 19:46:32 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 19:46:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Giant, Hill</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-giant-hill.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another entry that that adds extra stat blocks to complement the existing MM1
and upcoming Monster Vault monsters. This one is for hill giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new lore here is minimal or restates things we saw elsewhere. Hill Giant
bands are usually small and consist of a single family group - they’re too
anti-social to form more complex organizations. Every once in a while a larger
group will manage to hold together for an extented period of time. Their leaders
style themselves kings, and the log fortresses they build are known as
steadings. You might have heard about a famous adventure with the words
“Steading”, “Hill Giant” and “King” in its title, wink wink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, Hill Giants are Large Natural Humanoids (Giants), with a basic speed
of 8. All of the ones here look like the iconic club-swinging D&amp;amp;D giant, with
the big difference being in how they fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hill-giant-smashers&quot;&gt;Hill Giant Smashers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Smasher is pretty much a “Hill Giant Lite”. It’s slightly weaker than a
standard MV giant, and doesn’t throw rocks. To compensate, it’s more mobile and
has a few more tricks in melee. This is the stat block you use for those lone
mercenary giants that get hired as living tanks by smaller evil humanoids like
hobgoblins, bugbears, or gnolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smashers are Level 11 Brutes with 137 HP. They have a passive &lt;strong&gt;Mobility&lt;/strong&gt; trait
which allows them to roll saves against being slowed, immobilized, or restrained
at the start of their turns instead of at the end. This also works for any
save-ends effect that includes these conditions, like “ongoing 5 damage and
slowed (save ends both)”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all giants in this entry they wield Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt;, and their basic
attack deals a bit of automatic splash damage to a secondary target on a
hit. Once per encounter they can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Crush&lt;/strong&gt; to attack everyone
in a close burst 2, and they can also perform a &lt;strong&gt;Brutal Smash&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
double damage and recharges on a miss. So they’ll keep trying that one until
they hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hill-giant-rockthrower&quot;&gt;Hill Giant Rockthrower&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM1 and MV give us an artillery giant that uses big javelins. But if you
want your giants to throw rocks and nothing but rocks, the Rockthrower is for
you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockthrowers are Level 12 Artillery with 97 HP. As artillery monsters, their
&lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; attacks are kinda weak, but their basic ranged attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;Knockdown Throw&lt;/strong&gt; that does a bit more damage, pushes the target 2 squares,
and knocks them prone. They can also throw with a bit more force for a
&lt;strong&gt;Shattering Rockburst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which deals damage in an area and dazes
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use the same tactics as a catapult: seek high ground, rain death from
above. I imagine hiring a bunch of rockthrowers is quite a bit cheaper than
maintaining your own siege engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hill-giant-avalancher&quot;&gt;Hill Giant Avalancher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avalanchers are the heroic prodigies of their people. They’re much smarter than
your typical hill giant, and often end up as leaders or kings. They get their
name from their clever rock-throwing tricks and from their brutal charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Avalancher is a Level 14 Skirmisher with 139 HP. They can make basic
&lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; attacks and perform &lt;strong&gt;Crushing Charges&lt;/strong&gt; that do the same amount
of damage and knock targets prone. From a distance they can throw &lt;strong&gt;Rolling
Rocks&lt;/strong&gt;, which in addition to doing damage on a hit slide the target 4 squares,
knock them prone, and gather no moss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After they knocked a bunch of PCs prone, Avalanchers will move using &lt;strong&gt;Stomping
Shifts&lt;/strong&gt;, which allow them to shift 4 squares and pass through prone enemies’
spaces. They deal an automatic 8 damage to a prone enemy when they pass through
their spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avalanchers will always try to use their Crushing Charge if possible, and will
make use of Stomping Shift to position themselves for a new charge and to deal
additional damage to prone enemies. They use Rolling Rocks to break up tricky PC
formations and to return fire against ranged attackers they can’t charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s more hill giants, which it’s okay because I like hill giants. I like that
the Smasher is explicitly meant to be included as the “surprise bruiser” in a
lower-leveled humanoid group. A smasher and its humanoid employers work well as
a boss battle for a group of level 8-10 PCs, depending on how many other
monsters you add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Avalancher gives you an interesting option for a leader type who is not a
titan.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/12/giant-hill.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/12/giant-hill.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Giant, Frost</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-giant-frost.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know the drill by now - Frost Giants appeared in the MM1 and were about to
get rewritten with new math on the Monster Vault. The MM3 brings in an
assortment of them that can complement the “basic” entries in the MV. You can
look at those basic entries &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/04/frost-giants.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frost giant lore remains the same. They’re plus-sized asshole vikings who like
to live in cold regions, fight with a variety of axes, and use lots of ice
magic. Some think this behavior is in service of a greater plan laid down by
their primordial masters, but that might be reaching a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frost Giants are Large Elemental Humanoids with the Cold and Giant
keywords. Their signature trait remains &lt;strong&gt;Icebound Footing&lt;/strong&gt;, which reduces any
forced movement imposed on them by 2 squares and can reduce it to 0. They can
also roll a save to avoid being knocked prone. They have Resist 15 Cold, and
their ground speed is 8 with Ice Walk, which allows them to ignore ice or
snow-based difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frost-giant-berserker&quot;&gt;Frost Giant Berserker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d expect someone with “Berserker” in its name to be a Brute, but these are
Level 16 Skirmishers with 157 HP. The book describes them as those hot-headed
youngsters who are too undisciplined to fight like proper brutes and instead
keep running around the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Freezing Greataxes&lt;/strong&gt;, which do a mix of physical and cold
damage. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Storm Charge&lt;/strong&gt; that doesn’t provoke opportunity
attacks from its movement and deals heavy physical damage. Once per encounter,
the berserker can use its &lt;strong&gt;Primordial Rage&lt;/strong&gt; to shift its speed and make three
basic attacks along the way, each against a different target. A bit more often
(recharge 4+) they can take a &lt;strong&gt;Giant Stride&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 6 squares and move
through enemy spaces while doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These giants are perfect for running right past the party’s defenders and
harassing their squishies. For extra annoyance, stage the fight in a map full of
ice-based difficult terrain, which doesn’t affect frost giants but makes it
harder for those defenders to reposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frost-giant-shield-bearer&quot;&gt;Frost Giant Shield Bearer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shield bearers are the opposite of berserkers. They’re the hardened veterans who
get the best gear and the best training. This makes them suitable to form the
core of a raiding party, or a lord’s honor guard. They’re huscarls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shield bearers are Level 18 Soldiers with 174 HP. They’re heavily armored and,
as the name implies, are just about the only frost giants who carry
shields. They still wield axes, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Coordinated Attack&lt;/strong&gt; ability gives them combat advantage against any
enemy that has another shield bearer adjacent to them, no flanking
required. Their &lt;strong&gt;Icy Battleaxes&lt;/strong&gt; do cold damage and mark for a turn. Once per
encounter they can enhance an attack and turn it into a &lt;strong&gt;Protective Strike&lt;/strong&gt;,
which deals 10 extra cold damage and grants 25 temporary HP to an ally within 10
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Defensive Stand&lt;/strong&gt; allows them spend a minor action to choose an enemy
within 10 squares. If that enemy moves within reach before the end of the shield
bearer’s next turn, the shield bearer gets a free attack against that
enemy. It’s not an opportunity attack, so it should work with shifts or other
forms of movement too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re all set up to fight in tight formations and hold ground, which means
they go well with artillery and ranged controllers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frost-giant-chieftain&quot;&gt;Frost Giant Chieftain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any frost giant community not led by a titan will likely be led by one of
these. This chieftain is a Level 20 Controller with 190 HP. He has an
&lt;strong&gt;Emanating Cold&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that makes enemies inside grant combat advantage to
cold creatures (i.e, frost giants and any monsters that are likely to tag along
with them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chieftain fights with an &lt;strong&gt;Icy Greataxe&lt;/strong&gt; that does cold damage, and can
attack at range with a &lt;strong&gt;Eye of the Storm&lt;/strong&gt; spell that does immediate and
ongoing cold damage in addition to slowing the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the chieftan can create a Medium or Large &lt;strong&gt;Pillar of Ice&lt;/strong&gt;
within ten squares. The pillar lasts for a turn and “occupies” its space,
meaning no one can move through. It blocks line of sight and slows anyone who
starts their turn next to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chieftain can also cast a spell named &lt;strong&gt;Grip of Winter&lt;/strong&gt; that creates a zone
that slows and deals cold damage to those inside. The zone lasts for the whole
encounter and the power recharges once the chieftain is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s your ranged controller to go with the shield bearers. Chieftains should
stay behind a line of their bodyguards, making the already difficult terrain of
the icy battlefield even worse with ice pillars and slowing attacks. Then you
release the berserkers to step over all that and hit the PC’s back ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like giants in general, so I like these MM3 giant entries even though they
don’t include much new lore. The trio presented here has nice mechanical synergy
and should also be fun to use with the frost giants from the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/10/giant-frost.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/10/giant-frost.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Giant, Fire</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-giant-fire.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the ghouls we just covered, fire giants are classic monsters that appeared
both in the original Monster Manual, and who would appear again in the upcoming
Monster Vault. The MM3 gives a selection of fire giant stat blocks that
complements that of the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore for fire giants remains pretty much the same as it was &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/06/fire-giants.html&quot;&gt;in the
MM/MV&lt;/a&gt;. The new bits here add that the ancient fire giant empire had close
contact with the efreets of the Elemental chaos, and that their many volcano
fortresses were linked to each other and to the City of Brass via teleportation
circles and portals. Most of these portals are deactivated in the present day,
though the giants labor to reignite them wherever they find one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, fire giants love to team up with other fire creatures, preferrably
ones they can dominate and command. Some of them end up in the service of more
powerful masters like efreets or the older red dragons, but since fire giants
always think they should be the ones in charge they make for untrustworthy
subordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Giants are Large Elemental Humanoids with the Giant keyword. They have a
ground speed of 8 and Resist 15 Fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-giant-lavamaster&quot;&gt;Fire Giant Lavamaster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a name that looks like it came from the writer’s 8-year-old
child. Lavamasters are… masters of lava! Their magic allows them to control
magma and use it both as a weapon, and to heal their allies. Lavamasters are
Level 17 Controllers with 164 HP and the Leader tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They project an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Hearthflames&lt;/strong&gt; that hurts enemies and bolsters
allies. Enemies caught inside take 10 fire damage; bloodied allies recover 10 HP
when they start their turns inside the aura. This is not any kind of “drain”
effect. Allies recover HP regardless of whether there are enemies to damage or
not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lavamaster attacks with a &lt;strong&gt;Molten Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that deals fire damage, and can
also use several spells. &lt;strong&gt;Magma Lash&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack that deals a bit more
fire damage than the sword, and pulls the target 4 squares. If the target ends
up adjacent to the lavamaster, the giant grabs them. The spell recharges when
the giant has no target grabbed. &lt;strong&gt;Magma Burst&lt;/strong&gt; is like an at-will
mini-fireball that leaves a fiery zone in its affected area. The zone lasts for
a turn, counts as difficult terrain, and deals fire damage to enemies inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the lavamaster has an enemy grabbed, &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Vendetta&lt;/strong&gt; allows the lavamaster
itself or one of its allies to make a free attack against that enemy whenever
the enemy attacks the lavamaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good tactic here is to keep away and repeatedly fireball the enemy, grabbing
anyone who gets too close. Keep a Brute or two nearby as bodyguards so they can
make free attacks against the grabbed victim and benefit from that healing aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-giant-flamedancer&quot;&gt;Fire Giant Flamedancer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This martial artist is trained in an ancient style developed by the efreets. It
combines mobile spear fighting with fire-based teleportation magic. Flamedancers
are Level 18 Skirmishers with 174 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Nimble Reaction&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them +4 to AC vs. Opportunity Attacks, and
their &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Spear&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack deals fire damage and allows them to shift
2 squares on a hit. They can also make at-will &lt;strong&gt;double attacks&lt;/strong&gt;, which must be
against different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can make a &lt;strong&gt;Flameburst Leap&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action,
teleporting 8 squares and dealing automatic fire damage to any enemies adjacent
to them at the starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t expect a giant to be this agile! The same stat block can be used
for a slightly lower-level efreet without much issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-giant-smokecaller&quot;&gt;Fire Giant Smokecaller&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smokecallers are what passes for a “subtle” fire giant spellcaster. They
surround themselves in clouds of volcanic smoke, and attack by turning that
smoke into a pyroclastic cloud aimed at their enemies. It’s “subtle” without
necessarily being “stealthy”, unless you’re already in an environment naturally
choked with sulphurous smoke. Which is… actually a common situation when
you’re fighting fire giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smokecallers are Level 19 Lurkers with 140 HP and a nice speed of 10. They fight
with a &lt;strong&gt;Smoldering Whip&lt;/strong&gt; that has a fantastic reach of 5. It targets Reflex,
does fire damage, and pulls up to 3 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its main tactic consists of two abilities: &lt;strong&gt;Smokecloud&lt;/strong&gt; creates a zone of
smoke in a Close Burst 3 that lasts for a turn. It blocks line of sight for all
creatures except the smokecaller. While inside this zone, the smokecaller can
use &lt;strong&gt;Cindersmoke&lt;/strong&gt; to attack all enemies in a Close Blast 5. This deals fire
damage on a hit, and it ends the smokecloud immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both are standard actions, which means the lurkery routine here is Smokecloud
followed by Cindersmoke on the next turn. Cindersmoke does the same damage as a
whip attack to each target. This means the whip is only worth it if its forced
movement component would synergize with something. An example is when you have
multiple smokecallers and one of them wants to pull a PC into its buddy’s
upcoming Cindersmoke area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the ghoul entry, this one feels like it was designed to fit together with
the (upcoming, at the time) Monster Vault. The giants here all use the same
improved math as the ones that would appear on the MV, and they fill roles which
the more “classic” MV lineup does not. Combining the two gives you enough
ready-made stat blocks to make a dungeon inhabited solely by fire giants, though
you might also want to sprinkle in some hell hounds, elementals, and enslaved
azer that just need that final push to revolt.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/giant-fire.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/giant-fire.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Magic Item: The Coffee Machine From Hell</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I dreamed about this thing today, and what use is a blog if I can’t use it to
write about the weird things I dream up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like a chunky, tabletop coffee machine of the sort that can be made
at TL8, and which might be found in an office. It’s self-contained, with
internal reservoirs for beans and plastic cups. An authorized technician
supposedly refills those after working hours, but employees who stay late never
see this technician, no matter how late they stay. And yet, the machine never
seems to run out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The device bears the name of a company that does indeed make this type of
appliance, though instead of their usual logo it has an upside-down star with a
smiley face. It has no model name or other contact information printed anywhere
on its body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coffee Machine From Hell has a counter-intuitive control panel. Several
button presses are required to tell it what you want, but that’s just bad
interface design. The Machine’s true curse is more insidious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As its name implies, the Coffee Machine From Hell is literally a torment device
built by demons. It will do its nominal job of producing cups of shitty office
coffee, but only if the user is making one for themselves (i.e, being
self-serving) or is thinking hostile or hateful thoughts about the intended
recipient of the drink. Someone who’s genuinely trying to help, or even just
being neutral about it, will find the machine seizes up or behaves
unpredictably. Even if all buttons are pressed correctly, it will spit mangled
cups, spill hot liquid on the countertop, make the wrong drink, and generally go
out of its way to make user experience a nightmare and to never ever produce
whatever it is the third party ordered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placed in an office where “making a coffee for someone else” is an accepted part
of the culture, the Machine will soon turn it into a nest of hate and
resentment. This is accelerated if the “someone else” is always the
boss. Unlucky interns and employees will cause mess after mess until they start
to truly hate the boss. The boss, in turn, will be frustrated that no one else
seems to be able to operate this “simple” machine that always works for them and
will come to hate their underlings in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics&quot;&gt;Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its shitty interface, no roll is required to operate the Machine. It
does however read the operator’s mind to see if it should trigger the curse, in
which case it behaves as if a critical failure had been rolled. This will either
result in a humiliating mess, or in a normal-looking but undrinkable cup of
coffee that’s sure to cause inflict a nasty surprise on its intended recipient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who is wise to the curse can try to trick the device into operating
normally with a successful &lt;strong&gt;Mind Block&lt;/strong&gt; roll, or through any powers they have
that can shield their thoughts from telepathy. This roll can me made at the
usual &lt;strong&gt;Will-5&lt;/strong&gt; default if the character lacks the skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The machine’s infernal nature can be detected by any power or spell that detects
evil or infernal powers. It can be “cleansed” through &lt;strong&gt;Exorcism&lt;/strong&gt; or equivalent
powers, like a more typical cursed artifact. Its greatest defense against
detection and exorcism is that neither of these abilities are common in the
settings in which it appears. Its true nature can’t be detected by purely
scientific means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-it-in-a-game&quot;&gt;How to use it in a game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coffee Machine From Hell is a perfect addition to any oppressive office your
PCs must infiltrate for a while, particularly if they’re undercover as
interns. It’s something of a trap in that case: If everyone else already hates
each others’ guts, the PCs will be the only ones who trigger the curse, and this
will draw undue attention to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, every office &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Hell has one of these, but it can also be present
on Earthly companies under demonic influence, or just wind up in an otherwise
normal company without any explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs on an infiltration mission will most likely need to trick the
machine. Exorcism attempts are too obvious and will likely blow their cover,
especially if they are actually infiltrating Hell. In an infiltration scenario
where the office is weird or evil in other ways, the machine is unlikely to be
the only obstacle they face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a campaign centered on paranormal investigation or monster hunting, the PCs
might be hired to find the problem behind a supernaturally toxic work
environment. If they have supernatural means of detecting evil, they’ll be able
to easily find the Machine, but in those cases it might be only one of the
sources of trouble. If they must rely only scientific instruments, then finding
the Machine is considerably harder even if they can easily use Exorcism to
cleanse it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/coffee-machine-from-hell.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/coffee-machine-from-hell.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>items</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Ghoul</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-ghoul.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As classic monsters, Ghouls had their 4e debut on the first Monster Manual, and
would end up making it into the Monster Vault as well. Here, the Monster Manual
3 gives us a few specialized ghoul variants that can compliment the ones on the
MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic lore for ghouls remains the same. You can check out a description of
it on my post about &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/20/ghoul.html&quot;&gt;ghouls in the MM/MV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM3 emphasizes that ghouls are creatures of pure evil, since they used to be
individuals who practiced cannibalism or did other equally horrible things in
life. It adds that they are not only driven by a hunger for flesh, but are also
drawn to places where evil is powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghouls will spontaneously show up at the home bases of evil cults, especially
those who worship Orcus or one of his exarchs. These villains often secure the
ghouls’ services by paying in live captives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghouls will also seek out ruins and dungeons where great evil is entombed,
sometimes digging for miles to reach these places if they happen to be deep
underground. This attraction handily explains why the ghouls that live in these
places prefer to hang out there rather than terrorizing the countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some adventurers like to use these ghoul tunnels and warrens as a way to reach
their dungeons or the Underdark, but this is a risky proposition as any ghouls
living in the tunnels will have a terrain advantage against the interlopers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three different varieties of Ghoul here, none of which seem to be
reprinted in the MV. They’re all Medium Natural Humanoids with the Undead
tag. They have Darkvision, Immunity to disease and poison, Resist 10 Necrotic,
and Vulnerable 5 Radiant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghoul-flesh-seeker&quot;&gt;Ghoul Flesh Seeker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cultist of Orcus who has undergone a voluntary transformation into a
ghoul. I guess the origin could be applied to any stat block, but this specific
entry describes a stealthy bastitch. They sometimes hunt in civilized
settlements, disguising themselves with heavy robes. When accompanying other
monsters, they like to strike from ambush while the PCs are busy with their less
stealthy buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flesh Seekers are Level 4 Lurkers with 45 HP. Their ground speed is an excellent
8, and their &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Skulk&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows them to roll Stealth to hide in
combat when they have partial cover or concealment (normally you need full cover
or concealment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and immobilizes (save ends) on a
hit. They don’t have abilities to exploit this directly, but “standard” ghouls
do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have two “lurker”-y special attacks. The first is &lt;strong&gt;Prepare For
Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt;, which they can use against a creature from which they were hidden
at the start of their turn. It does more damage than the claw attack, and on a
hit the flesh seeker knocks the target prone and grabs it. The target can escape
using the normal rules (Athletics DC 14 or Acrobatics DC 16) but takes a -2
penalty on the escape test and can’t stand up until the grab ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Render Unto Orcus&lt;/strong&gt;, and it can only be used on a
target grabbed by the flesh seeker. No special riders here, just a massive chunk
of damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactics write themselves: Ambush -&amp;gt; Prepare For Sacrifice -&amp;gt; Render Unto
Orcus. If someone pries you off your victim, hide and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adept-of-orcus&quot;&gt;Adept of Orcus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cannibal priest of Orcus who died and returned as a ghoul. This one retains
its memories, but since it already behaved like a ghoul in life the only way you
can tell it’s because it can use magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adepts are Level 6 Controllers with the Leader tag and 71 HP. Their speed
is 8. They project an &lt;strong&gt;Uneasy Grave&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5). Any non-minion ghoul ally that
dies inside this aura comes back as a zombie rotter (a minion) at the start of
its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adept’s &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; damages and immobilizes, as typical for ghouls. It also has
three spells, all ranged attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Grave Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will) does no damage and
restrains (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Call to Feast&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) immobilizes (save ends)
and allows a ghoul ally adjacent to the target to make a free basic attack
against them. And &lt;strong&gt;Grave Dust Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is an area spell that does
necrotic damage and creates a zone that does 5 necrotic damage to any enemy who
enters it or ends their turn inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things are extremely dangerous when paired with traditional ghouls, since
they can paralyze from a distance and allow their buddies to do huge damage
right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghast&quot;&gt;Ghast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghasts are a monster as traditional as the ghoul. Basically, they’re stronger
and stinkier ghouls. The MM and MV had Abyssal Ghouls to fill this role, but
they were level 16. This official Ghast entry is appropriate for mixing in with
standard ghouls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghasts are what happens when a ghoul goes for too long without eating the flesh
of the living. Instead of starving, they rot from the inside and become even
more desperate and voracious. This rot is what gives them their horrible stench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghasts are Level 6 Brutes with 85 HP. They’re a bit slower at speed 6, and their
&lt;strong&gt;Stench of Death&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) slows any living creatures that start their turns
inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and immobilizes for a turn. They
can use a &lt;strong&gt;Devouring Bite&lt;/strong&gt; against an immobilized creature, which does huge
damage and keeps recharging until they hit with it. After the bite hits and is
spent, they can use their &lt;strong&gt;Rabid Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, to make two melee attacks against
immobilized creatures. Each one does slightly less damage than the basic bite,
but if the two hit they hurt more overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new ghoul types can fit into the same types of encounter group as the ones
from the MM/MV, which means they pair well with Orcus cultists and other
undead. And now you have enough ghoul stat blocks to make a large variety of
all-ghoul encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for my impressions… I like ghouls as opponents, and I would like to repeat
my warning from the original article to prefer the MV ghouls over the MM1
ones. The ones from this book pair well with the MV versions.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/05/ghoul.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/05/ghoul.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merging GURPS Weapon Skills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Peter V. Dell’Orto made a post in his blog Dungeon Fantastic about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/07/possible-weapon-skill-mergers-for-gurps.html&quot;&gt;merging GURPS weapon skills&lt;/a&gt;. I really, really like the idea, so I thought
about writing about how I’d do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dell’Orto’s post is specific to Dungeon Fantasy and to his own Felltower
campaign. Mine is a bit more generic since I don’t have an active campaign
going, and I tend to kind of mix up Dungeon Fantasy and default GURPS rules in
my head. Consider it an addition to my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/12/18/df-house-style.html&quot;&gt;House Style&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for doing this is also pretty well-covered by this &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/08/why-all-merging.html&quot;&gt;follow-up Dungeon
Fantastic Post&lt;/a&gt;: having too many fine distinctions between spells and skills
in a cinematic campaign can serve as a bit of a damper on the pacing and
excitement of the campaign. My usual players tend to have a certain resistance
to trying stuff that’s not on their character sheets, especially in a complex
system like GURPS, so having broader traits would allow them to experiment a bit
more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-skills&quot;&gt;The Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns where this post is in effect, I’m going to use the following list
of weapon skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Axe/Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This skill is a combination of the original &lt;strong&gt;Axe/Mace&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt;. When
using a flail, the character suffers a -1 skill penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games that use Techniques, &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt; is a new Hard technique that defaults to
Skill-1 and has a maximum level equal to Skill. This means you can buy the -1
penalty off for 2 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fencing-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Fencing (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new skill merges &lt;strong&gt;Rapier&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Saber&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Smallsword&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows you to
use not only these three “titular” weapons, but also any other weapon that would
fall under those skills, such as the jian (Rapier) or the light stick
(Smallsword).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the normal rules for fencing weapons apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;force-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Force Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-3, One-Handed Sword-3, Two-handed Sword-3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should I ever play a science fiction game with force swords, this gets merged
with &lt;strong&gt;Force Saber&lt;/strong&gt;. Whether you get fencing parries or not depends on the stat
line of the weapon you’re using. The “Fencing parries for everyone!” option is
also valid in a more explicitly Star Warsy game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;knife-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Knife (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges the original &lt;strong&gt;Knife&lt;/strong&gt; skill with &lt;strong&gt;Jitte/Sai&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Main-Gauche&lt;/strong&gt;. Any weapon that could be used with either of these can be used
with the new skill. Weapons use their Main-Gauche profiles for this, meaning
there’s no penalty for using the off hand and the user gets fencing parries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, “knife expert” PCs always went for Main-Gauche anyway. People
who dropped a point in Knife as a back-up skill almost never ended up using it,
so they can just drop a point in this one instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jutte and the Sai get both a +2 for disarm attempts and fencing parries
without any special stance switches required. They are rare enough in my games
that I don’t believe it will be a problem. And by “rare” I mean no one has taken
these weapons and no one has tried a disarm yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;One-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4, Two-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the skill used for all one-handed swords, merging both &lt;strong&gt;Broadsword&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Shortsword&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blade length is an important consideration in real life, but it’s below the
level of granularity I prefer. This also broadens the range of really cool magic
swords your sword-wielding players can find and immediately use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pole-weapons-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Pole Weapons (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Sword-5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges &lt;strong&gt;Polearm&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Staff&lt;/strong&gt;. The Form Mastery perk is
redundant for these weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about that sweet Staff parry bonus? If it’s in your weapon’s stat line
under Staff, you get it. If it’s not, you don’t. The only exception to this are
balanced two-handed spears, which I feel should have the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Axe-Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Axe/Mace, but for two-handed weapons. The same rules apply for two-handed
flails, including the existence of a Hard technique to buy the -1 penalty off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much the same skill as the original, with a suitably altered list
of defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-all-the-other-skills&quot;&gt;What about all the other skills?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the more exotic weapon skills, like Whip, Kusari, and Tonfa, remain the
same. I might change my mind in the future and come back to this, but I haven’t
actually used any of them in my games, so it makes no difference for them to
stay as-is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-rule-weapon-familiarity&quot;&gt;Optional Rule: Weapon Familiarity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like how these skills are merged, but still feel a staff user shouldn’t
be able to pick up a halberd and wield it just as proficiently right away, then
you can use a version of the Familiarity rules from the GURPS core book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs are considered familiar with any weapons they acquire during character
creation. If they pick up a weapon that would be used with a different skill
under the standard rules, they have a -2 penalty to use that weapon until they
can spend a few hours practicing with it. This takes time but costs no money or
points. In effect, it can only happen when the PCs have a significant amount of
downtime (such as when returning to town from a dungeon in DF). After this, the
PC is considered familiar with that weapon type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this up as an option, but it’s not one I’ll use myself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Gargoyle</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-gargoyle.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gargoyles made their 4e debut in the first Monster Manual. I wrote about them
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/12/gargoyle.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Though that article includes a whole bunch of gargoyles, most of them
are from the Monster Vault. When the MM3 was published, we still only had the
two originals from the MM1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry adds a lot more variety, and it doesn’t actually overlap with the
later MV gargoyles, so we’re going to be looking at all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gargoyle lore remains basically the same, and you can read it &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/12/gargoyle.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. We get
two new bits in this entry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that efreets love to train packs of gargoyles to hunt sapients for
sport. The elemental lords are endlessly amused by their pets’ penchant for
sadism when hunting. In the world, cultists of the Elder Elemental Eye
frequently recruit and train gargoyles to guard their temples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is that while gargoyles have a fearsome reputation in the world, they
tend to be viewed as weak in their native Elemental Chaos. There, they are more
often the prey than the hunter. Gargoyle packs skulk in caves and other secluded
locations, and only attack when they greatly outnumber their target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All gargoyles in this entry are Medium Elemental Humanoids with the Earth
keyword. They have Darkvision, a ground speed of 6, and a flight speed
of 8. They’re immune to petrification, and all but one of them have a passive
trait called &lt;strong&gt;Lurking Presence&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives them a +10 bonus to Stealth
against enemies’ passive Perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also interesting to note that none of the gargoyles in this entry have the
Lurker role - with these and the ones from the MV, you can build varied
all-gargoyle encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ironstone-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Ironstone Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identified by the rust-red streaks covering their bodies, Ironstone Gargoyles
behave like their “default” cousins, hanging out in mountain passes and ruins
waiting to raid unsuspecting passers-by. They wait in ambush but fight in a more
aggressive and mobile way than usual once combat starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironstone Gargoyles are Level 7 Skirmishers with 80 HP and the traits outlined
above. They use &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; to fight, and have a special attack named &lt;strong&gt;Crashing
Stride&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+). This allows them to shift 4 squares and make claw
attacks against two targets at any point along the shift. If they hit, they also
slide the target 1 square and knock it prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When surrounded, a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping Glide&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will move action) allows them to fly 4
squares without provoking opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hornstone-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Hornstone Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This robust specimen is distinguished by its large horns, which it uses to gore,
impale and drag victims in combat. It’s a Level 8 Brute with 107 HP and all
standard traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those horns can be used in an &lt;strong&gt;Impaling Charge&lt;/strong&gt;, an attack which must be used
as part of a charge. It does heavy damage and grabs the target by impaling them
in the gargoyle’s horns. The target takes 5 ongoing damage while the grab
lasts. Escaping uses the standard rules (Athletics DC 22 or Acrobatics DC 19).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gargoyle can use &lt;strong&gt;Skewering Drag&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action to move half its speed
and automatically pull the grabbed victim along with it. Neither provokes
opportunity attacks from the other during this movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the basic &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack for last because it interacts with the above
abilities: aside from doing the usual heavy damage of a Brute, it allows the
monster to use Skewering Drag as a free action. Attacking the grabbed victim is
a perfectly valid choice, mind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat they’ll do their best to impale and drag an enemy away. If the charge
fails they prefer to fly away and try again rather than stand and fight with
basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;obsidian-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Obsidian Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obsidian gargoyles are kinda brittle, but also covered in sharp edges. Massive
flocks of these things darken the skies of the Elemental Chaos, and they’re the
preferred variant of Elemental Eye cultists. They’re Level 8 Minion Soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks are nothing special, but they also have a &lt;strong&gt;Cruel Claws&lt;/strong&gt;
passive that deals 4 damage to an enemy who leaves a square adjacent to the
gargoyle. That’s not a lot, but it triggers on a shift and &lt;em&gt;stacks&lt;/em&gt;. Surround a
PC with these beasts. Leave only one way out. Dare them to take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;runic-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Runic Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an &lt;em&gt;artificial&lt;/em&gt; gargoyle variant, originally created to serve the Elder
Elemental Eye. Their skin looks like white marble covered in arcane runes, and
they are a lot smarter than your average gargoyle. Some of them have since
broken out of their servitude and found jobs with different groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Runic Gargoyles are Level 8 Soldiers with 87 HP and all standard traits &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt;
for Lurking Presence, since they don’t really have natural camouflage. They were
made to be bodyguards, and their runes can be configured to bind them to a
designated “master”. I guess “client” might be a better word for free runic
gargoyles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack marks the target for a turn. They can also use an
&lt;strong&gt;Avenging Claws&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that dazes instead of marking. This recharges when
they’re first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action, they can teleport &lt;strong&gt;To the Master&lt;/strong&gt;, appearing in a space
within 2 squares of the client. There is &lt;em&gt;no range limit&lt;/em&gt; on this, and it allows
you to have a cool scene where the boss snaps his fingers and a gang of gargoyle
guards teleports in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the gargoyle is adjacent to its client and the client takes damage, it can
use &lt;strong&gt;Shielding Wings&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt to take the damage instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters&quot;&gt;Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same encounter building tips for MM1/MV gargoyles also apply here. The
efreet and Elder Eye angles are new and just as valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inter-gargoyle synergy is highest between the gargoyles from this entry. You
have a couple of variants who are excellent at inflicting forced movement, and a
minion who deals damage to enemies who move away from it. And since all of them
fly, they also pair well with pits and other floor-based hazards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks in this entry don’t really change my general opinion of
gargoyles. They might be &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; iconic, as the exceptional case in a D&amp;amp;D
adventure is meeting an inanimate gargoyle statue who &lt;em&gt;won’t&lt;/em&gt; come to life and
try to kill you. For this reason, you don’t want to use them too much in your
actual game. Still, by combining the MM3 and the MV you have enough variants to
make that one gargoyle encounter truly memorable.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/02/gargoyle.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/02/gargoyle.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Frog</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-frog.jpg&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Not a D&amp;D illustration.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every individual roleplayer has a set of D&amp;amp;D monsters they consider “iconic”,
regardless of what the publisher has to say about it. Years ago, I remember one
such player saying that to him “giant fucking frogs” were the most iconic D&amp;amp;D
monster. It’s not D&amp;amp;D if you don’t fight a huge-ass frog at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that criterion we can shut the grognards up for good now. Here is the moment
when 4e finally becomes D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real-world frogs are usually quite useful creatures. Most species are harmless
to humans and eat disease-spreading insects. Some consider them cute and, if
nothing else, they can be tasty when properly prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In typical D&amp;amp;D fashion, this book calls such creatures “pests” because they’re
not fuzzy wabbits. And then it moves on to focus on monstrous frogs, who are big
and aggressive enough to eat people. They live in surface swamps and on
underground lakes in “natural” caves or in the shallow Underdark. There are
several different species, and the book implies they’re atavistic survivors from
the world’s prehistory, like sharks and crocodiles in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monstrous frog won’t usually leave its home territory to hunt people, but it
will eat anyone foolish enough to wander through that territory. “Beware of
Frog” signs are a common sight in villages close to the borders of their
habitat. Frog attacks are a potential hazard for PCs traveling through marshy
terrain, and the book suggests they could be hired by a wealthy family to
retrieve some heirloom from the belly of a frog who ate its former bearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All frogs shown here are Medium Natural Beasts, though you could probably
home-brew larger specimens if you want. They’re Aquatic, which lets them breathe
underwater and gives them bonuses against non-aquatic enemies in underwater
combat. They also have good Swim speeds and low-light vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thornskin-frog&quot;&gt;Thornskin Frog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These frogs have brown skin covered in thick spines. The spines are not
effective in combat but give them a distinctive look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thornskins are Level 1 Brutes with 35 HP. They have a ground speed of 4 and a
swim speed of 6. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and they can also &lt;strong&gt;pounce&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+). This lets them shift their speed, deald more damage than a bite
and knocks the target prone. As a minor action they can use a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue
Grab&lt;/strong&gt; that pulls a target 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, these critters do everything you could expect from a classic giant
frog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sporeback-frog&quot;&gt;Sporeback Frog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-sporeback.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sporebacks are the laziest hunters imaginable. They pick a spot and wait there
for prey to wander into the reach of their barbed tongues. They move so little
that mushrooms often grow on their backs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most creatures smart enough to pose a threat to these monsters have long since
learned to avoid them. As a result, sporebacks never expect their chosen prey to
put up a fight, and don’t usually run away unless they’re very close to death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sporebacks are Level 2 Controllers with 42 HP. Their ground speed is a pitiful
3, and their swim speed is 5. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and
slows, and their Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Barbed Tongues&lt;/strong&gt; damage, pull the target 2 squares,
and knock it prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they die, the mushrooms on their back burst and perform a &lt;strong&gt;Spore
Release&lt;/strong&gt;, a close burst 2 attack that deals poison damage and inflicts a -2
attack penalty (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For extra nastiness, have the sporebacks in your encounter group stay
&lt;em&gt;underwater&lt;/em&gt; and use their tongues to drag PCs there. This works even better if
all of Team Monster has the Aquatic keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;murklord-frog&quot;&gt;Murklord Frog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murklords are entirely black, and have two parallel bio-luminescent stripes
running down their backs. These flare up when the frog is startled or feels
threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These beautiful creatures are the opposite of sporebacks when it comes to
attacking prey. They perform darting strikes from the muddy margins of their
watery homes, and grow even more frantic and ferocious when wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murklords are Level 2 Skirmishers with 39 HP. They have ground and swim speeds
of 6. Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and they can also perform a
&lt;strong&gt;Leapfrog&lt;/strong&gt; attack (recharge 4+) that deals more damage and allows them to
shift 3 squares both before and after making the attack. Perfect for leaping out
of the water, taking a bite, and returning before the PCs can react.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, it can also perform a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue Lash&lt;/strong&gt; that does no
damage but slides the target 1 square on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The murklord’s attacks use d6s as their damage dice: 1d6+4 for the bite, 2d6+4
for the limited-use Leapfrog. After the frog is first bloodied, though, those
d6s become d12s, significantly increasing its damage potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters&quot;&gt;Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goblins, kobolds and bullywugs commonly employ trained monstrous frogs as mounts
and war beasts. Only the bullywugs have succeeded in &lt;em&gt;domesticating&lt;/em&gt; them,
though - the others must capture wild frogs and train those. When bullywugs make
alliances or trade agreements, they commonly make a gift of trained war frogs to
their new partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with no access to trained frogs can still use them by keeping them
captive and releasing a bunch of angry half-starved frogs in the general
direction of the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I’d go as far as calling huge-ass frogs “iconic D&amp;amp;D monsters”,
but they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; cool. These ones are properly froggy in their mechanics, and you
can probably extend their usefulness by giving them additional levels,
increasing their size, and giving them a Swallow attack.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/01/frog.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/01/frog.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Foulspawn</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-foulspawn.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foulspawn had their 4e debut in the first Monster Manual. If you read the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/09/foulspawn.html&quot;&gt;post I wrote&lt;/a&gt; about them, you’ll see that MM1 Foulspawn were plagued by some
design flaws, but you could speculate from their lore that they were the end
state of mortal Far Realm cultists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore in this entry is mostly a re-statement of the original foulspawn
lore. They’re more actively inimical to the natural world than most other Far
Realm denizens, and cross over where the barrier between dimensions is thin to
attack mortal settlements. They drag some of their victims back with them, and
those unfortunates eventually become foulspawn themselves after having their
bodies and minds warped by the Far Realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still plenty of room for you to portray foulspawn as the “end state” for
a lot of mortal cultists who worship cthulhoid entities - they’re the ones who
step into the portal willingly. If all you had to go with were the MM1 entries,
this was kind of an ironic fate, as the foulspawn there were kinda weak. Let’s
see if this is still true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foulspawn are Aberrant Humanoids with a ground speed of 6 and a teleport speed
of 3. They mix physical attacks with powers that warp space and damage enemy
minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;foulspawn-wretch&quot;&gt;Foulspawn Wretch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most unwilling victims probably turn into these. Wretches are Small Level 7
Minion Skirmishers with low-light vision and the standard traits listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have a &lt;strong&gt;Ceaseless Murmurs&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait that inflicts a -2 penalty to
the Will of any PC adjacent to two or more wretches. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack
deals a bit of damage and allows another wretch within 6 squares to teleport
adjacent to the target. And when they die, their &lt;strong&gt;Screaming Echo&lt;/strong&gt; ability
teleports a non-minion ally within 6 squares to the position previously
occupied by the dead wretch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wretches are made to use standard “monster wave” tactics - use a lot of them and
have them crowd around the PCs. Try to get them adjacent to the PC’s squishies
on the back line, so that when they die they teleport your front-line bruisers
there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;foulspawn-mockery&quot;&gt;Foulspawn Mockery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spellcaster with a raven skull for a head. Mockeries use mind-bending magic to
force the PCs close together and then hit them with area attacks. They’re Medium
Level 10 Controllers with 104 HP, low-light vision, and the standard traits
outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; which is actually stronger than almost any
attack from a MM1 fouslpawn simply because it uses the correct math. They attack
at range with a &lt;strong&gt;Mind Harrier&lt;/strong&gt; spell that deals psychic damage and imposes one
of those interesting custom effects. If a target hit by Mind Harrier is not
adjacent to any of its allies by the end of its next turn, it takes an extra 10
psychic damage and 10 ongoing psychic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the mockery has used Mind Harrier to push the PCs together, it can hit them
all with a &lt;strong&gt;Maddening Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which deals psychic damage and
dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;foulspawn-warpcaller&quot;&gt;Foulspawn Warpcaller&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are like aberrant bards, or those things that keep dancing around Azatoth
playing flutes and pipes. They’re Medium Level 12 Controllers (Leaders) with 126
HP, Darkvision, and the standard traits outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Droning Pipes&lt;/strong&gt; act as an aura (3) that makes enemies inside Vulnerable
5 to Psychic damage. This is important because Psychic is pretty much the
signature damage type for foulspawn and other aberrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warpcallers can &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; in melee for good damage, but their magic is the star
of the show here. &lt;strong&gt;Warped Sending&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will ranged attack that deals
psychic damage and teleports a foulspawn ally within 5 squares of the target to
a space adjacent to the target. &lt;strong&gt;Twisted Dismissal&lt;/strong&gt; does the same damage,
immobilizes the target (save ends) and teleports it 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Warpmind Field&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a fireball-sized area attack that
deals psychic damage and creates a zone that lasts for a turn and can be
sustained with a minor action. Enemies who enter the zone or end their turns
there take 10 psychic damage. An enemy inside the zone can’t target anyone
further than 5 squares away. And the warpcaller can spend its move action to
move the zone up to 4 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warpmind Field is an excellent fight opener if you drop it on the party’s
archers. If they move outside the zone to fire on their turn, Twisted Dismissal
can push them back inside and keep them there, possibly combined with a move
action spent moving the zone closer. And Warped Sending is another handy way to
teleport your brutes past the PC’s defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;friends-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Friends and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foulspawn usually only work with other foulspawn, though if you’re using the
ones from the MM1 you really, really need to fix their math. Other appropriate
company includes gibbering mouthers and other aberrant creatures that deal
psychic damage. And according to the book they also sometimes work with cultists
of Tharizdun and Demogorgon - the kind of person who wants to wreck the world
but doesn’t care how it happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore remains the same, but the mechanics on these foulspawn are quite a bit
better. I’m not just talking raw numbers either - the MM1 foulspawn rarely did
more than spam basic melee attacks. These have a lot more variety.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/28/foulspawn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/28/foulspawn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Forsaken</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later monster books in a D&amp;amp;D edition are usually where you find those monsters
from previous editions who weren’t “iconic” enough to appear earlier, but
sometimes they’re also where you can find some truly ambitious entries. After
all, the authors have pages to fill and most of the classics have already been
done. The Forsaken are one of the most ambitious new monsters presented by the
MM3. Or at least they &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; new. If a monster by this name existed earlier it
was likely completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dawn War saw the death of many gods. In most such occasions, the dead god’s
essence dispersed across the Astral Sea. However, a few gods were slain while
physically present in the world, and their essence could not escape. Instead, it
deposited itself in some of the mortal sapients that inhabited the world even
back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the gods in question were dead and gone, these new vessels of their power
acquired a memory of what it felt like to be immortal. This memory became a
source of torment, for their owners were themselves mortal. They remembered and
missed something they never had, and could never have. Overwhelmed by these
feelings, these people ritually removed their own eyes so they would never have
to gaze upon the mortal world again, and vowed to destroy and absorb the
essences of the remaining gods so that they could steal their divinity for
themselves. They called themselves the Forsaken, and they are still known by
that name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our narrative present there are several different Forsaken tribes, each with
their own approach to their grand design. They travel through all the universe
in search of mystical secrets that will increase their power and allow them to
become gods. They tangle and skirmish with Vecna worshippers, inflitrate astral
dominions, and even journey the Hells. Some set up elaborate networks of
followers and co-conspirators in the mortal realms. Some make plans to trap and
devour a god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forsaken are epic-level threats. They’re Medium Natural Humanoids with the Blind
keyword and Blindsight 20. This means they can’t be affected by the “blinded”
status and they’re immune to gaze attacks and most vision-based impairments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Fragment of Immortality&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when they
hit 0 HP. It clears all effects from them, removes them from play and returns
them a turn later with about 25% of their HP restored, in a space within 5
squares of their last location. The fragment allows them to cling to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their other abilities come from training and vary per stat block. They
tend to have some vague similarities to PC divine classes, but any divine power
would come from the Forsaken themselves rather than from a deity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-fearwrack&quot;&gt;Forsaken Fearwrack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-forsaken-fearwrack.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearwracks are spellcasters who delve deep into the mysteries of fear and death,
confronting that which most scares the forsaken and inflicting it on
others. There’s an enclave of them in the outer shores of Celestia, and though
the inhabitants of that dominion very much want to see them gone, they fear
meeting their final death at the hands of the Forsaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearwracks are Level 26 Artillery with 150 HP. They &lt;strong&gt;Inspire Fear&lt;/strong&gt;, which acts
as an aura (1) that inflicts a -2 penalty to all enemy defenses against fear
attacks. Almost all of their attacks have the Fear keyword, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wield rods as implements, which I guess makes them a bit similar to PC
invokers in look and feel. Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Fear Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that
targets Will, deals psychic damage, and forces the target to move its speed away
from the invoker. The invoker chooses the path, but each square must be further
away than the previous one. Why is this different from a push? Because the
victim can provoke opportunity attacks during this movement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range they fire &lt;strong&gt;Terror Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; which do the same amount of psychic damage
and allow an ally adjacent to the target to make a melee basic attack against
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often they can also employ a &lt;strong&gt;Curse of Mortality&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), which
targets Fortitude and inflicts 20 ongoing damage (save ends). The target has a
-2 penalty to save against this, and each failed save increases the ongoing
damage by 5 to a maximum of 30. I guess the damage looks like rapid aging, and
since there’s no exception in the text it works even on beings who do not
normally age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from Fragment of Immortality, fearwracks have another reaction power in
the form of &lt;strong&gt;Cleansing Wounds&lt;/strong&gt;, which clears all enemy effects from them when
they first become bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An all-fearwrack group has a surprising amount of synergy. If the PCs close to
melee with one of them, others can target the PC with Terror Bolt to open them
up to a free Fear Strike. This causes the PC to run away and potentially get hit
with &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; Fear Strikes. The fearwrack choses the victim’s path and there’s
nothing forbidding them from walking them into traps or pits either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are occasions where the fearwrack &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; the PC to stay close, though -
their aura makes the Curse of Mortality even harder to resist with a total -4
save penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forkaken-infiltrators&quot;&gt;Forkaken Infiltrators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infiltrators have an amazing talent for long-term impersonation. Some believe
they inherited it from the deity whose essence initially infused them. They join
up with churches and cults of all types of deity, from Pelor to Vecna, with the
goal of reaching a high post in their hierarchy. From that lofty perch they gain
access to all sorts of restricted divine secrets, and can abuse their authority
to sabotage the cult from within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infiltrators are Level 27 Skirmishers with 200 HP. They wield a kophesh in one
hand and a hand crossbow in the other, and they use the classic strategy of
moving around to gain combat advantage while discouraging the PCs from making
opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they have &lt;strong&gt;Combat Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; against a target, any attack they hit also
immobilized the target and allows the infiltrator to shift 2
squares. &lt;strong&gt;Punishing Response&lt;/strong&gt; is a mighty discouragement indeed: when an enemy
hits the infiltrator with an opportunity attack, the enemy takes the same damage
dealt to the infiltrator plus 5!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Khopesh&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Hand Crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; are accurate and do solid damage, but have
no built-in riders. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Careful Attack&lt;/strong&gt; with the sword that
deals about 25% less damage but gives the infiltrator a +2 bonus to defenses for
a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No combat-time shapeshifting powers here, so I guess any transformations either
take more time, or are just the fruit of epic-level tradecraft rather than
shape-shifting magic. Infiltrators do get training in all the social skills plus
Stealth, and their high level means they’re better at those than most mortals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-loreseeker&quot;&gt;Forsaken Loreseeker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loreseekers are the rank and file of the Forsaken spying operation, tasked with
actively breaking into libraries, vaults, and minds to steal the knowledge
contained within. I guess a big part of the big-I Infiltrator’s mission is to
open the way for loreseekers. Some believe they can steal all the memories of a
creature they kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loreseekers are Level 27 Minion Soldiers, which tells me they’re not really
meant to engage in combat most of the time and/or that they work in large
teams. When forced to fight, they use weapons similar to those of the
Infiltrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Hand Crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; attack marks for a turn, and their melee attack also
performs a &lt;strong&gt;Theft of Memory&lt;/strong&gt;. During the target next turn, all enemies except
the attacking Loreseeker are invisible to the victim. Memory erasure in real
time! The loreseeker loses this ability after it uses Fragment of
Immortality. Yes, despite being a minion they also have this ability, so you
need to hit them twice to defeat them for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-slaughterer&quot;&gt;Forsaken Slaughterer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-forsaken-slaughterer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some Forsaken find the memory of immortality a weight too great to bear. It eats
at their sanity until their mind snaps, and they’re consumed by rage and
grief. The other forsaken keep these unfortunate individuals in reserve for use
as living weapons. They’re more sensitive to divine power, you see, and tend to
fly into a murderous frenzy when they sense some. It wouldn’t do to waste that
kind of god-killing potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaugheterers are Level 28 Brutes, which means they can indeed challenge
demigods and other things of that nature when backed up by a team of similar
level. They have 253 HP, and the other standard Forsaken traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaughterers have a couple of interesting passive traits: &lt;strong&gt;Relentless
Slaughter&lt;/strong&gt; is an aura (1) that halves the benefits of healing for any enemy
inside; and &lt;strong&gt;Proximal Resistance&lt;/strong&gt; gives them Resist 10 against all ranged and
area attacks if no enemies are adjacent to them. This makes them very capable of
charging through an open field to engage PCs in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with paired khopesh swords, and their basic &lt;strong&gt;Khopesh&lt;/strong&gt; attack does a
nice chunk of damage - almost as much as a Balor’s sword, with the main
difference being the lack of the High-Crit property. They can also use an
&lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable Cut&lt;/strong&gt; that splits that damage between two adjacent targets. This
isn’t a multi-attack - if the first target gets hit, the second takes damage
automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all Forsaken, slaughterers have Fragment of Immortality as a triggered
action. They also have another very interesting one called &lt;strong&gt;Blood for
Blood&lt;/strong&gt;. It triggers when they’re first bloodied, and consists of a Close Burst
1 attack against all enemies that does damage equal to each target’s healing
surge value. That’s 25% of their HP, and it’s likely to bloody them since it
will go off a ways into the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaughterers are offensive brutes - you want them to charge past the defenders
and attack your squishies. They’ll be particularly eager to target divine
characters like clerics and invokers, so having a paladin with you is probably
the best way to make them stop and fight your defenders. Otherwise they’ll
definitely risk opportunity attacks and mark punishments to break through, with
Blood for Blood working as a nasty surprise for those PCs who prove adept at
hurting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-mastermind&quot;&gt;Forsaken Mastermind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forsaken Masterminds are strategists. They run operations whose scope
encompasses an entire region, sitting at the center of a web of different cells
and agents that include several other Forsaken as well as their mortal
pawns. Their goals tend to involve heavy stuff like interfering with the designs
of the gods themselves, or those of their direct servants. A mastermind should
only enter combat directly if all of their other plans have been thwarted by
meddlesome adventurers, but they’re far from defenseless if it comes to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masterminds are Level 29 Controllers with 213 HP and the Leader keyword. They’re
masterful warriors, and also employ some magic focused on disrupting divine
powers. They’re surrounded by an &lt;strong&gt;Inspire Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5), which grants
an extra 40 temporary HP to any forsaken ally who uses Fragment of Immortality
within it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;khopesh&lt;/strong&gt; attack makes the target marked by one of the
mastermind’s allies within 5 squares! So it forces the PC to target that ally
instead of the mastermind itself, and allows the ally to use any mark-related
abilities it may have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also use a &lt;strong&gt;hand crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; that can make a solid ranged basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main spell is &lt;strong&gt;Tainted Wave&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will Close Blast 3 attack that
targets enemies, deals untyped damage, and makes those it hits lose &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
temporary HP and become unable to regain HP for a turn. It targets Fortitude, so
most defenders might have a good shot at resisting it, but if it hits they’re in
trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often (recharge 5+), they can use &lt;strong&gt;Delayed Retribution&lt;/strong&gt;, an area spell
that targets enemies’ Reflex. Those it hits take some damage and, more
importantly, will become stunned for a turn if they attack the mastermind during
their next action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone uses a divine power within 10 squares of the mastermind, it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the Forsaken&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This ends all negative effects on an
ally within 10 squares, and allows them to make an immediate recharge roll to
recover an expended power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quite like these guys. Their lore feels epic and horrific at the same time,
and their mechanics are cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do wonder how the Forsaken perpetuate themselves, as they’ve been around since
the Dawn War and are very explicitly not immortal. Perhaps they’re still
&lt;em&gt;unaging&lt;/em&gt;, or maybe there is a procedure for exposing a mortal victim to the
fragment of immortality that belonged to a deceased Forsaken, bringing them back
in a new form Go’auld style.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/25/forsaken.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/25/forsaken.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
