<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 15:37:05 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 15:37:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Wyvern</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-wyvern.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyverns have been in the game since its beginnings (or at least since
BECMI). Here, they are present only on the Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyverns are the most famous “not-quite-dragons” of D&amp;amp;D, and the ones most likely
to be confused with real dragons from a distance. The most obvious visual
difference is that wyverns lack front legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are others, too, which become more evident when you interact more closely
with them. Unlike dragons, wyverns are non-sapient animals, and they also lack
magical breath weapons. Instead, they have a stinger at the tip of their tails
that can inject prey with a potent venom. They’re not as relentlessly voracious
as some of the other fantastic predators described in this book, but I imagine
they still might put a strain on any herds on their chosen territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, wyverns live in small groups called “flights”, which roost in high
places like mountains and hunt the surrounding region together. If you see a
flight of wyverns up close, it’s because they’re trying to eat you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyverns can be tamed, but the process has to start shortly after they’re
born. As you might expect, there’s a market for eggs and hatchlings, and sapient
opponents might bring their pet wyverns to the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for two species of wyverns here. Both are Large Beasts with the
Reptile keyword, and fight with their natural weapons: a bite, claws, and the
stinger. Wyverns are good fliers and much more agile in the air than on the
ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that wyvern damage as written is notoriously weak. Fixing this to use the
updated math should be a priority before you include them in an encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wyvern&quot;&gt;Wyvern&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more common variety is a Large Natural Beast with the Reptile and Mount
Keywords, and a Level 10 Skirmisher with 106 HP. Their land speed is 4, and
their flight speed is 8 with Hover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyverns have two basic attacks: a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; with no special effects beyond
damage, and a slightly weaker attack with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which can only be
done from the air and knocks prone on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to fly
their speed and make one of these attacks at any point along the way without
drawing opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also &lt;strong&gt;sting&lt;/strong&gt;, of course, which does a little less damage than the
claw and triggers a secondary attack vs. Fortitude that deals ongoing poison
damage on a hit (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If used as a mount, the wyvern’s &lt;strong&gt;aerial agility&lt;/strong&gt; gives its rider +2 to all
defenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m guessing the wyvern doesn’t bite very often. It’s going to use flyby attacks
to knock people prone, or sting if that’s not practical. Only a prone, poisoned
target will get the bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-wyvern&quot;&gt;Fell Wyvern&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A larger species which originated in the Shadowfell but is also present in
places where that plane intersects with the world. It’s a Large Shadow Beast and
a Level 24 Skirmisher with 228 HP. Despite not being undead, it has Resist 10
Necrotic and Vulnerable 5 Radiant. Its land speed is 6, and its fly speed is 12
with Hover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fell Wyverns fight mostly like wyverns with bigger numbers, and have all the
same attacks. Their venom causes “necrotic and poison” damage, so it’s harder to
resist. They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;pestilent breath&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude;
recharge 5-6) that does immediate and ongoing necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a single sample encounter: level 10, an ettin marauder, a basilisk, and
2 wyverns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also imagine either wyvern is a pretty close fit to those fell beasts the
Ringwraiths rode in Lord of the Rings, though their actual level would depend on
how high-powered you view that story as.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that wyverns can be mounts, the most clichéd use for them would be to have
them as the “hostile humanoid” flying mount of choice, to have proper aerial
fights against human gryphon cavalry.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/21/wyvern.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/21/wyvern.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Worg</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I see the name “Worg” is in the AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition Monster Manual,
where it was synonymous with “dire wolf”. The word itself comes from the Lord of
the Rings, I think. In Fourth Edition, they’re only on the Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worgs are not wolves, though they might be distantly related. Even dire wolves
are just animals, but worgs are sapient and evil. They also have some distinctly
un-wolf-like physical traits when you look at them from up close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worgs like the taste of sapient flesh and prefer it over any other prey. They
live in mazelike warrens, which they decorate with trophies of their
victims. Worgs on the hunt act as a group, but don’t cooperate very well, since
each individual is only interested in satisfying its own thirst for murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worgs willingly ally with other sapient creatures that have a disposition as
nasty as their own, often carrying these allies into battle as mounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and the worg also has a larger and meaner relative: the elephant-sized
gulvoorg, which looks nothing like a wolf even from very far away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m guessing you won’t find both worgs and normal wolves in the same wilderness
region - worgs are beefy enough to overpower even dire wolves in direct
fights. They’d enjoy it, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both “strains” of worg are Natural Magical Beasts. They have trained Perception
and Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worg&quot;&gt;Worg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-worg.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is Large and a Level 9 Brute with 120 HP. It has a speed of 8
and its &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Growls&lt;/strong&gt; act as an aura (3) that gives enemies a -1 attack
penalty and allies a +1 attack bonus. Their only attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; which also
does ongoing damage on a hit (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess the main benefit of riding a worg into battle is that you’re always in
range of its aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gulvoorg&quot;&gt;Gulvoorg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-gulvorg.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These monsters are Huge, and Level 16 Elite Brutes with 384 HP. Their speed is
9, and they still have trained Perception and Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gulvoorg &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; are Reach 2, and always knock prone on a hit. They can
perform Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;tail slams&lt;/strong&gt;, which are also considered basic attacks. On a
hit, they both knock prone and daze (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a standard action they can use &lt;strong&gt;Gulvoorg Fury&lt;/strong&gt; to make both a bite and a
slam attack, against different targets and with a -2 attack penalty. That
penalty is completely unnecessary, since we’re talking about an elite monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book gives us two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: 3 worgs, 2 razorclaw stalker shifters, and 1 oni night haunter. An
oni and its evil henchthings.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 17: 2 gulvoorgs and 2 cyclops hewers. It’s even possible the cyclopes
are riding the gulvoorgs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conceptually, I like worgs a lot more than I like dire wolves, and wouldn’t be
opposed to merging the two again. That way you get sapient evil worgs with the
interesting mechanical bits of dire wolves. Maybe add some wind powers so they
can huff, puff, and blow your house down.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/19/worg.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/19/worg.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Wolves</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-wolf.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolves are real animals and have been part of the game since its
beginnings. Here, they are both in the Monster Manual and in the Monster Vault’s
animal appendix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real-world wolves are pack hunters, and the ancestors of modern dogs. If I
recall correctly they mostly stay away from people and only attack when cornered
or really desperate. There are enough stories about wolves attacking sheep and
other farm animals that it must have happened in the past, but it’s not really a
common occurrence any more. And that’s partly because there are very few wolves
left in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D wolves are of course a lot more common and a lot more willing to attack
people, since a pack of wolves is a classic low-level wilderness encounter. They
can be found across a wide variety of climates and terrains. Mountains? Check!
Forests? Check! Plains? Check! Deserts? Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This being D&amp;amp;D, there might be some natural landscapes where your reasonably
realistic grey wolf might have trouble competing with the more fantastical and
powerful monsters common to the game. Instead, these places might feature dire
wolves, which are a larger, smarter and more dangerous variety. As of 3e,
they’re also spikier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to being found in the wild, both common and dire wolves might be
trained by humanoids such as goblins or shifters, who have a knack for taming
wolves directly without having to spend centuries turning them into dogs. Other
creatures might also control large packs of them through magic: vampires are
famous for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolves are obviously Natural Beasts, even the dire variety. They have low-light
vision, and their other acute senses are represented by Trained Perception. They
run at speed 8, attack with &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; and usually do something interesting when
they have combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gray-wolf-both&quot;&gt;Gray Wolf (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray wolves are Medium, and Level 2 Skirmishers with 38 HP. As far as natural
wolves go, it seems to me these would be on the large end of the scale, which
might explain why they’re more eager to attack humans than you’d expect a
mundane wolf to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their sole attack is the &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which does extra damage against prone
targets. The bite in the MV version also allows the wolf to shift 4 squares &lt;em&gt;as
an effect&lt;/em&gt;, so these critters will never stay still if they can help it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a wolf has &lt;strong&gt;Combat Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; against a target, its bite will also knock
the target prone on a hit. This means a group of wolves has a lot of incentive
to flank a specific PC. One of them knocks the victim prone with its first bite,
the others pile on with that bonus bite damage. All of them keep moving around
with those free shifts. And now you know why they call this “wolf-pack tactics”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dire-wolf-both&quot;&gt;Dire Wolf (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire wolves are Large, which means each is roughly horse-sized. They’re Level 5
Skirmishers with the Mount keyword and 67 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire wolf &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; have larger numbers due to them being higher level, and also
do increased damage to prone targets. They also knock the target prone if the
wolf has &lt;strong&gt;combat advantage&lt;/strong&gt; against the target, and the monsters have more
ways to get that other than plain old flanking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text for “combat advantage” in the MM version says the dire wolf has CA
against any target who has at least one other ally adjacent to it. No flanking
required. This could be interpreted to mean that a dire wolf with a rider always
has CA against any enemy adjacent to it! The MV version of this trait, named
&lt;strong&gt;Pack Harrier&lt;/strong&gt;, says it only works when the wolf has two or more allies
adjacent to the enemy. So the rider still counts, but you need a second ally to
get the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a trait called &lt;strong&gt;Pack Hunter&lt;/strong&gt;, which grants their &lt;em&gt;rider&lt;/em&gt; combat
advantage if an ally other than the mount is adjacent to the target. So if you
go with the MV text, the rider would get CA whenever the wolf got it, and
vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m guessing that the MV version is the “correct” one in all aspects
here. A wolf that got permanent combat advantage against everyone would be a
little overpowered due to that knockdown effect on the bite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two sample encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 3: 3 gray wolves, 2 hobgoblin archers, and 1 hobgoblin warcaster. Your
standard hunting party.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 5: 3 dire wolves, and 2 longtooth shifter hunters. A mounted hunting
party.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Werewolves are also quite likely to be leading dire wolf packs, and Count Strahd
in the original Ravenloft module quite famously commanded a literal army of dire
wolves he could send after the PCs every night until they entered his castle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dire wolf-riding goblins are also a classic image, though the levels are a
little mismatched as printed. It would be easy enough to level the goblins up or
the dire wolves down, and it’s quite plausible for the Small goblins to be
riding Medium gray wolves instead of the Large dire ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days “you’re attacked by a pack of wolves while on the road” strikes me as
a little uninspired, though I think they’re OK when used as muscle by sapient
opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/13/wolves.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/13/wolves.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Wight</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-wight.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wights have been in the game since its beginnings, part of the original Undead
Power Ladder. Here, they are present only on the Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might have touched upon this before, but in the implied D&amp;amp;D setting mortal
beings are composed of three main metaphysical “pieces”: the body, the soul, and
the will. The will is also known by sages as the “animus”, and is the “glue”
that holds body and soul together. This is also quite similar to Exalted’s
division of the body, “higher soul” and “lower soul”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What usually happens when someone dies is that the soul separates from the body,
and the animus disintegrates. You get undead when something intereferes with
this process and the animus sticks around, or when someone introduces an
artificial animus into the equation via necromancy. What &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; of undead you
get depends on the final configuration of post-mortem body, soul and animus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the soul departs but the animus sticks to the body, you get a wight. Wights
are intelligent, since they retain the use of their brain-meats, but they’re not
really the same person they were in life. In place of a soul they have this
gaping void, which they are compelled to fill by slaying the living and drinking
their life force. A wight doesn’t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to do this in order to keep existing,
though, so they hang around for a long time in their haunts waiting for a victim
to wander by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wights typically inhabit the places where they died, though they are not really
bound to them. More ambitious wights might take over catacombs and crypts and go
about finding victims (and treasure!) in a more proactive way. These can find
themselves commanding lesser undead, or perhaps acting as lieutenants for more
powerful villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wights are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Undead keyword. As such they’re
immune to disease and poison, and have tier-based necrotic resistance and
radiant vulnerability. They also have darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wights are famously able to drain the life energy of others with a touch. In
previous editions this meant they drained levels (in AD&amp;amp;D) or inflicted
“negative levels” (in 3e). Here this means they eat your healing surges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you can still get them back via a long rest, this does significantly
impact your resources, which is a real bummer in those instances where you can’t
just plop down and rest for six hours whenever the fancy strikes you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deathlock-wight&quot;&gt;Deathlock Wight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one was either a necromancer in life, or learned how to be one after it
died. It’s a Level 4 Controller with 54 HP and all standard wight traits. Its
speed is 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deathlock wight’s basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack does necrotic damage, and causes the
target to lose a healing surge. Their &lt;strong&gt;Grave Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20 vs. Reflex) is a
much better attack, dealing necrotic damage and immobilizing (save ends). Their
magically-enhanced &lt;strong&gt;Horrific Visage&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Will; recharge 4-6)
does untyped damage and pushes victims 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can &lt;strong&gt;Reanimate&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10; minor action) a fallen
non-minion undead ally. The target stands back up with 25% of its HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM stat block for deathlock wights has pitifully low damage all
around. Fixing this is a priority if you want to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wight&quot;&gt;Wight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard model is a Level 5 Skirmisher with 62 HP and all standard wight
traits. Its speed is 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic wight’s only attack are its life-draining &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which do necrotic
damage, eat a healing surge, and allow it to shift up to 3 squares on a
hit. It’s simple, but the shift and the life-draining make it quite dangerous
since it can reach your squishies and ruin their day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battle-wight&quot;&gt;Battle Wight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wight with more formal combat training. It wears plate, and wields a sword and
shield. It’s a level 9 Soldier with 98 HP and all standard wight traits, plus
speed 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle wight has learned to channel its dark powers through the sword, and
so its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Souldraining Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; that does necrotic damage,
eats a healing surge and immobilizes (save ends). It can also attack at range
with &lt;strong&gt;Soul Reaping&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Fortitude; recharge 5-6). This only affects
immobilized targets, but deals high necrotic damage and heals the wight for 10
HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battle-wight-commander&quot;&gt;Battle Wight Commander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A smarter and more powerful version of the Battle Wight, this one is a Level 12
Soldier (Leader) with 106 HP and all wight traits. It has the same gear as the
basic battle wight, and speed 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commander’s &lt;strong&gt;Souldraining Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; does everything the battle wight’s
does, and also weakens on a hit. A save ends both the immobilization and the
weakness. Soul Reaping gets upgraded to &lt;strong&gt;Soul Harvest&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5
vs. fortitude; recharge 4-6) which works the same but heals both the commander
and 2 undead allies within 10 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slaughter-wight&quot;&gt;Slaughter Wight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the basic wight, this one is a monstrosity in rags that attacks with
its claws. It’s just a whole lot stronger and tougher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaughter wights are Level 18 Brutes with 182 HP, all standard wight traits, and
speed 7. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; do necrotic damage and have a lot of riders: eat a
healing surge, weaken (save ends), heal the wight for 15 HP, and a partrige in a
pear tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When killed, these monsters emit a &lt;strong&gt;Death Wail&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5 vs. Fortitude),
which does necrotic damage to enemies in the area, and allows undead allies in
the area to make a basic attack as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get several encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 3: 1 deathlock wight, 3 zombies, and 6 zombie rotters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 11: 1 battle wight commander, 4 battle wights, 1 shadar-kai witch, 2
shadar-kai chainfighters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 18: 2 slaughter wights, 3 abyssal ghouls, 1 nabassu gargoyle.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wights are a very distinctly D&amp;amp;D monster, but at the same time they kinda get
lost amid all the other similar undead in the game. This might explain why they
were left out of the Monster Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/11/wight.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/11/wight.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Warforged</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-warforged.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged are a 3e creation, first appearing as a playable option in the Eberron
campaign setting. In 4e they would also become playable characters, but their
first appearance was in the Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warforged lore given to us by the Monster Manual has been stripped of all
Eberron-specific information, which means it’s extremely terse and generic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged are living constructs created by magic. The “living” part means
they’re gifted with true sapience, and with souls. It also means they’re a
little less tough than a golem, but they make up for that with their large
numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged are created in magical factories called Creation Forges. They’re
sexless and can’t reproduce in any other way. As their name implies, the
original purpose of the warforged was to serve as an army. In peacetime,
individual warforged often end up working as bodyguards and mercenaries for
people who share their individual ideals and disposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Eberron, the secret of building and operating creation forges belonged
exclusively to House Cannith, who sold warforged armies to all five sides of the
Last War but whose main customer was the nation of Cyre. The treaty that ended
the War (signed after Cyre got swallowed by a magical disaster) freed all
existing warforged from servitude, and I think it also tightly regulated their
creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most warforged PCs from Eberron are going to be veterans of the Last War, which
is like a combination between our Hundred Years War and World War One. However,
in the ruins of Cyre, a powerful warforged supremacist named the Lord of Blades
controls a fully working creation forge and is using it to build an army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged in the 4e implied setting might have been alive to see the fall of
Nerath. They could also have been built more recently by someone operating an
Nerathian creation forge, or even assembled by hand by an isolated artificer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warforged are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Living Construct
keyword. Monster Manual warforged have several signature traits: they get a +2
to saves against ongoing damage, they employ &lt;strong&gt;Battlefield Tactics&lt;/strong&gt; that grant
them a +1 bonus to melee attack if any ally is adjacen to the target, and they
can use the &lt;strong&gt;Warforged Resolve&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power as a minor action when
bloodied to recover a healing surge’s worth of HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playable Warforged would appear in the Eberron Player’s Guide: they’d get the
save bonus against ongoing damage and a modified form of &lt;strong&gt;Warforged Resolve&lt;/strong&gt;,
along with a few other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;warforged-soldier&quot;&gt;Warforged Soldier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 4 Soldier with 56 HP and all standard warforged traits. It wears
plate, and wields a longsword and a shield. Its ground speed is 5, and it’s
trained in Endurance and Intimidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soldier’s basic (and only) attack is the &lt;strong&gt;longsword&lt;/strong&gt;, which does average
damage for its level and marks for a turn. Its &lt;strong&gt;Warforged Resolve&lt;/strong&gt; heals it
for 14 HP when used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warforged isn’t too different from a human fighter, but its racial traits
give significantly more staying power. You can slap them onto any human stat
block to get the warforged version. If you use them in a tight formation then
most of them will get the +1 Battlefield Tactics bonus all the time when
attacking targets directly in front of the formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;warforged-captain&quot;&gt;Warforged Captain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 6 Soldier (Leader) with 72 HP and all common warforged
traits. Its speed is 5 due to armor and its Warforged Resolve heals it for 18 HP
when used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captains fight with a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;glaive&lt;/strong&gt;, which does average damage and marks for a
turn. It can use this weapon to performa &lt;strong&gt;Tactical Switch&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver (recharge
4-6), in which it makes a basic attack that also slides the target 1 square. If
this hits, the captain or an ally within 10 squares can also shift 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captains excel at fighting from the back row of that warforged soldier
formation, since they have a reach weapon. Tactical Switch is good for
disrupting enemy formations, or interrrupting flanking attempts by individual
strikers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a single sample encounter: Level 4, three human guards, 1 warforged
soldier, and 1 warforged captain. A mixed force that makes it look like
warforged make up the command and elite in this particular army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, these Monster Manual warforged are very simple and present little
in the way of exciting surprises other than the fact that they
will. Not. Stay. Down. If I’m being honest the book might have done without them
entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I absolutely love the &lt;em&gt;concept&lt;/em&gt; of warforged, both as player characters
and as NPCs. I love them so much I adapted them to GURPS &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/09/17/dfrpg-warforged.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I understand
why the first MM included these: the Eberron books were still a little ways
away, and the authors might have felt its fans needed a little reassurance.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/07/warforged.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/02/07/warforged.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Vine Horror</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-vine-horror.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2012 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the many plant monsters of D&amp;amp;D, I’m not sure where vine horrors first
appeared. They look like a 3e thing but could have been in a supplement for an
earlier edition. Here, they’re only on the Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like shambling mounds, vine horrors are created “naturally” through an unlikely
sequence of events. If an evil person dies in an area touched by the Shadowfell,
their blood might end up soaking the earth and infusing the local plant life,
which animates as a new vine horror. They’re undead-adjacent, but not undead
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vine horrors are humanoid plant masses who bear a vague resemblance to the dead
person whose blood gave them life. Some times they even display some of that
person’s abilities: for example, a vine horror who rises from a wizard might be
able to cast a few spells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personality-wise, they display human level intelligence and tend to be cruel
serial killers. The books say they like to ambush and kill passing sapients, but
doesn’t make any mention of them &lt;em&gt;needing&lt;/em&gt; to do it. It would make sense if they
needed to keep draining blood to live, but it also fits to say that a vine
horror feeds on soil and sunlight just like any other plant and just kills
people because it likes to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vine horrors are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Plant keyword. They have
blindsight, a land speed of 6 with both swamp and forest walk, and a swim speed
of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vine horror’s humanoid shape isn’t a constant - they’re &lt;strong&gt;Malleable&lt;/strong&gt; enough
to squeeze into any 1-inch or wider opening without slowing down at all. They
have &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, and can also partially uncoil to strike their victims with vines
whose exact effects vary by stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vine-horror&quot;&gt;Vine Horror&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 5 Controller with 67 HP. Aside from its basic
&lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, it can use its &lt;strong&gt;Vicious Vines&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter. This Close Burst
5 vs. Reflex restrains and does 10 ongoing damage on a hit (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its Stealth training, varied movement modes and malleability ensure the horror
will be a in a good position to use Vicious Vines as a fight-opener. After that,
it and its buddies can go to town on the weakened party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vine-horror-spellfiend&quot;&gt;Vine Horror Spellfiend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a wizard-derived horror who can cast some spells. It’s Level 7
Artillery and has 65 HP. It can only use &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, but has a lot of
ranged options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shock Orb&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10 vs. Reflex) does lightning damage. &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Vine of
Dread&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Reflex; fear) does physical damage and pushes the target 5
squares on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Caustic Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within 10 vs. Fortitude) does
immediate and ongoing acid damage, and also blinds (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like spellfiends pair wonderfully with shambling mounds, since their
at-will lightning powers can heal the mounds. They can also use their fear vines
to herd the party into position for Caustic Cloud, a process that’s a lot
quicker if you have a pair of spellfiends in the encounter group instead of just
one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book does mention the possible shambling mound partnerships, but the example
encounter it gives is a little less synergistic: Level 9, 2 spellfiends, 1 bog
hag, and 2 trolls. A clever party might be able to turn those caustic clouds to
their advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Story-wise vine horrors don’t do much for me. They’re just one creepy plant
monster among many others. Mechanically, I’d like to see how an encounter
featuring spellfiends and shambling mounds would go.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/28/vine-horror.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/28/vine-horror.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Vampire</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-vampire.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2012 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legend has it that vampires were an even earlier addition to D&amp;amp;D than the cleric
class - the first cleric was designed specifically to counter Sir Fang, a
vampire PC. As monsters, they were the second most powerful rung in the Undead
Power Ladder, below liches. As expected of a creature with such a long history,
they are present in both the Monster Manual and the Monster Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vampires in media and folklore are an incredibly varied lot. Each source has a
slightly different type of vampire than the rest, including D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Monster Vault says, vampires “rule the night”. They’re powerful sapient
undead with an insatiable hunger for the blood of the living, which gives them a
big incentive to interact with the living often. A lich will stay in its lair
and perform experiments for years on end. A ghoul is content to squat in its
hole and brood hungrily until someone wanders by. A vampire has to hunt. A
particularly ambitious vampire will get itself a “flock” to rule over, and
extract blood as tribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that the scholars who study the subject always argue over whether a
vampire is the same person it was in life. They retain their memories and
intelligence, and they answer to the same name; however, the baroque curse that
propels them also makes them wholly evil, no matter what they were like when
alive. And while it also imbues them with great and terrible power, it takes
away some of the abilities they had in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are as many superstitions surrounding vampires in D&amp;amp;D’s implied setting as
there are in the real world, and very few people know which are true and which
are not. You know all of them: garlic, running water, fear of holy symbols, and
so on. Aside from a vulnerability to sunlight (and other radiant damage, to a
lesser extent), most of these are fake. Perhaps these falsehoods are even spread
by the vampires themselves. The good news is that you can still fight and even
kill them with the usual adventurer arsenal of weapons and magic, it’s just
really hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other true vampire fact is that they’re tied to their grave or place of
death. Vampires need to rest during the day, and they must do so either inside
their coffins or crypts, or under the earth of the place where they died if they
didn’t get a formal burial. A vampire who’s prevented from resting in this way
will become less and less rational as the days pass, until it enters a
self-destructive feeding frenzy that lasts until it’s either slain or finally
manages to get some shuteye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above applies to what Fourth Edition calls vampire &lt;em&gt;lords&lt;/em&gt;, which are
the typical sophisticated vampires of editions past. You also have vampire
&lt;em&gt;spawn&lt;/em&gt;, which tend to be weaker and have a personality that can be summed up as
“angry and snarly”. Spawn are created when a vampire spawn drains someone dry -
the corpse rises a day later as a spawn under the complete control of its
sire. A victim incapacitated by blood drain but not killed will enter a coma and
rise as a spawn in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating another vampire lord requires an elaborate magic ritual. This ritual is
named “Dark Gift of the Undying”, and must be performed by a vampire lord on a
mortal victim. There’s an exchange of blood before the victim is killed, and
then the corpse must be buried and numerous prayers and invocations to Orcus
recited over it. A day later, the victim will rise as a new vampire lord. This
process is draining for the sire, so it’s not done lightly. The MV adds that
it’s also possible, but rare, for someone who would rise as a spawn to become a
full vampire instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases, the turning can be prevented with a casting of Raise Dead before
that one-day interval has elapsed. If the victim is merely comatose instead of
dead, Remove Affliction will also work to prevent the transformation and allow
the victim to be healed normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of vampire player characters has enjoyed enduring popularity ever
since a certain other game introduced it in the early 90’s. So when Heroes of
Shadow came out late in Fourth Edition it added like three or four different
ways to play a PC who could call themselves a vampire (including a full Vampire
class). Unlike the Monster Manual/Monster Vault varieties, these didn’t have to
be evil. I’d be inclined to say the Orcus-worshipping ritual described here only
produces evil vampires, so the non-evil ones in your setting are likely to have
other origins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monster Manual Vampires are built using templates, in a way similar to death
knights and liches. By the time of the monster vault the concept of rigid
monster templates had been dropped, so vampires there are built from scratch
following similar guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both types of vampire are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Undead keyword. They
have Darkvision and the usual undead traits: immunity to disease and poison and
resistance to necrotic damage (10). Most also have some vulnerability to radiant
damage as well. They also tend to have a high running speed, and a climb speed
with Spider Climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s fun to point out that back in the AD&amp;amp;D days, vampires didn’t
actually drink blood, or even bite. Instead, they drained your life energy by
punching you in the face. Around the time the Ravenloft setting became popular,
they published a variant that behaved more like you’d expect from a horror movie
vampire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the Monster Manual vampires do explicitly drain your blood, but this isn’t
described as a bite in their stat block. The Monster Vault vampires eliminate
this remaining ambiguity, and have bite attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vampire-spawn-fleshripper-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Vampire Spawn Fleshripper (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Level 5 Minion Skirmishers are fairly basic. They have the usual undead
immunities and resistances, darkvision, a speed of 7, and a climb speed
of 4. They attack with a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does necrotic damage, with a small damage
bonus against bloodied targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re also &lt;strong&gt;Destroyed by Sunlight&lt;/strong&gt;: a spawn that starts its turn in sunlight
can only perform a single move action that turn. If this isn’t enough to get
them out of the light, they are destroyed at the end of that same turn. So you
get a dramatic slow death out of them instead of having them pop like soap
bubbles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM also has a &lt;strong&gt;Vampire Spawn Bloodhunter&lt;/strong&gt; which is level 10 and exactly
the same with bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-vampire-spawn-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Elder Vampire Spawn (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 10 Minion Soldier is a little more interesting than the MM spawns. It
has everything they have, but its attacks are a little different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; does physical damage and grabs on a hit (escape DC 18). The spawn
can then &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; the grabbed victim. A hit does more damage than the claw and
dazes the target until the grab ends - and bites against a dazed target hit
automatically. So after the first bite hits, there’s no need to make another
attack roll for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vampire-night-witch-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Vampire Night Witch (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Monster Vault vampire, the Night Witch is built from scratch and doesn’t
use the template rules. It’s a Level 10 Controller with 98 HP and all common
vampire traits, plus Vulnerable 5 Radiant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all non-minion vampires, the night witch is &lt;strong&gt;Burned by Sunlight&lt;/strong&gt;, taking
5 radiant damage whenever she starts her turn exposed to direct sunlight. Does
the vulnerability get added on top of this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night witch fights with &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; that also slide the target 3 squares on a
hit. She can also cast a &lt;strong&gt;Dream Lure&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Will) to do psychic damage
at range, daze the target, and pull them 3 squares. Against dazed or similarly
impaired targets (stunned, unconscious, dominated) she can &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which does
high physical damage and heals her for 15 HP on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, when the night witch takes damage while bloodied, she can
&lt;strong&gt;vanish into shadow&lt;/strong&gt;, becoming invisible until the &lt;em&gt;end of the encounter&lt;/em&gt; or
until she attacks. This is a nice escape hatch and can allow the night witch to
be a recurring opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vampire-lord-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Vampire Lord (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Built using the template rules, this is a Level 11 Elite Lurker with 186 HP who
used to be a human rogue. It has all the vampire traits mentioned in the Numbers
intro, plus Vulnerable 10 Radiant and Regeneration 10 that doesn’t work while
the vampire is exposed to direct sunlight. Sunlight exposure &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; harm it
further than this. Its speed is 8, and it has Spider Climb 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blood-sucking rogue deals extra damage with all of his attacks when he has
combat advantage. He fights with a &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt;, and what is probably a
printing error has also given him a &lt;strong&gt;spiked chain&lt;/strong&gt;. He also has a couple of
rogue powers; &lt;strong&gt;Deft Strike&lt;/strong&gt; allows him to move up to 2 squares and make a
melee basic attack. &lt;strong&gt;Imperiling Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that does a bit
more damage than the basic sword and inflicts a -3 penalty to all of the
target’s defenses for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that come the template powers. &lt;strong&gt;Blood Drain&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Fortitude)
requires combat advantage, does more damage than any of the “rogue” attacks, and
heals the vampire for 46 HP. It recharges whenever an adjacent creature becomes
bloodied. &lt;strong&gt;Dominating Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Will) does no damage but dominates
on a hit, (save at -2 ends). As an after-effect, the target is dazed (save
ends). Fortunately only one creature can be dominated at a time. And finally,
&lt;strong&gt;Mist Form&lt;/strong&gt; is an encounter power that does what the name implies. In mist
form, the vampire is insubstantial and has a fly speed of 12, but can’t
attack. It lasts for 1 hour or until the vampire ends the effect as a minor
action, so it’s another “escape hatch” power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any vampire built using the template is going to have all three powers in the
preceding paragraph. This one also has a &lt;strong&gt;Second Wind&lt;/strong&gt; that works like the
player version, and recovers 46 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;master-vampire-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Master Vampire (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Level 12 Lurker with 98 HP, this monster follows the same concept as the
Vampire Lord. It has all standard vampire traits, with &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; radiant
vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s still a vampire and is still &lt;strong&gt;Burned by Sunlight&lt;/strong&gt;, taking 10
damage on any turn it starts exposed to it. It also has &lt;strong&gt;Regeneration&lt;/strong&gt; 10,
which shuts down for a turn if the vampire takes radiant damage (from sunlight
or any other source).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The master vampire fights with &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; like a proper monster, and has a
&lt;strong&gt;Dominating Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. will) that dominates for a turn. Its &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;
is like that of the Night Witch but heals it for 20 HP instead of 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has the Vampire Lord’s &lt;strong&gt;Mist Form&lt;/strong&gt; power, and it can also turn into a
&lt;strong&gt;Cloud of Bats&lt;/strong&gt; (though not at the same time). That last ability is at-will,
and works very similarly to Mist Form with the following differences: it only
lasts for a turn, the fly speed is only 8, and the vampire gains a +5 bonus to
Stealth in this form. This is clearly what it uses to “lurk”, though it doesn’t
gain extra bonuses beyond CA when it attacks from hiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 12 and has 1 vampire lord along with an entire
undead retinue: 1 battle wight commander, 3 battle wights, and 6 vampire spawn
bloodhunters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like vampires as monsters. Looks like the vampire lord/master vampire is tough
to put down even in its Monster Vault incarnation, where it has both
Regeneration and a draining bite. It’s the MM variant that easily crosses over
into “annoying” territory, since Blood Drain heals a lot more &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; it has
Second Wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5e makes a huuuge deal out of Count Strahd, the game’s Dracula expy, but in his
original incarnation he was explicitly described as a vampire who was only a bit
more powerful and clever than what’s average for these monsters. You could
easily stat him up in 4e by making him an Elite or Solo Controller with the
Vampire Master’s gaze, bite, and transformation powers, plus a strong claw/slam
attack and some necromancy-themed powers or rituals. He should be part of an
encounter of the party’s level +3 or +4, suitable as a final boss battle.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/25/vampire.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/25/vampire.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Unicorn</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-unicorn.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicorns are actually one of the creatures I associate most strongly with D&amp;amp;D,
since my first contact of any sort with it was the 80’s cartoon with its
adorable unicorn mascot. They’ve been in the game since at least BECMI, and
likely since it’s beginnings. Here, they are only present in the Monster Manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicorns are horse-like creatures that originate in the Feywild, though some of
them also live in the world. Lots of depictions of them tend to take a horse and
stick the famous spiral horn on its forehead, but mythological unicorns had
other fantastical traits: their hooves are split like a goat’s and not uniform
like a horse’s, and their tail is a bit lion-like with a small tuft at the
tip. They also sometimes had goat-like beards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The illustration here nails most of those details, though it still has a
horse-like tail. And its horn is not a cute and delicate spiral at all, but
rather something built to split a fool from crotch to sternum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicorns are sapient and very intelligent, and have a similar relationship to
their natural habitats as that of dryads or treants. They also have an extra
reason to distrust mortal intruders, as their horns are widely reputed to
contain potent mystical and healing properties. This makes them frequent targets
of hunting expeditions financed by Cocaine Wizards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your typical unicorn has a light-colored coat and mane, but sometimes you get
what is known as a Dusk Unicorn. They’re dark-colored, have black horns, and are
all-around stronger and more majestic. The birth of a dusk unicorn is considered
a portentous omen among the fey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get stats for “standard” and Dusk unicorns. Both are Large Fey Magical
Beasts, with low-light vision and a high land speed from their horselike
build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unicorn&quot;&gt;Unicorn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 9 Skirmisher with the Leader keyword and 93 HP. It
projects an aura of &lt;strong&gt;Fey Warding&lt;/strong&gt; (2) that grants allies within a +2 bonus to
all defenses. Its land speed is 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicorns attack with their &lt;strong&gt;hooves&lt;/strong&gt; up close, but if they have a running start
they’ll instead use a &lt;strong&gt;Piercing Charge&lt;/strong&gt;, which as you might guess counts as a
charge. A hit does roughly double the damage of a basic kick, pushes the target
1 square, and knocks them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicorns can also channel magic through their horns and produce a variety of
effects. &lt;strong&gt;Fey Beguiling&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5 vs. Will) is a charm spell that forbids the
victim from attacking the unicorn and forces them to make opportunity attacks
with a +2 bonus against anyone in reach who attacks the unicorn (save ends). So
remember all those legends of people whose purity charms unicorns and turns them
into friends? It’s actually the other way around! The power can only be used if
the unicorn doesn’t have a currently charmed victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creature’s other powers are a &lt;strong&gt;Fey Step&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power that works
exactly like the eladrin version, and a &lt;strong&gt;Horn Touch&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power that
allows the touched ally to spend a healing surge or roll a save against an
effect a save can end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dusk-unicorn&quot;&gt;Dusk Unicorn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These magnificent specimens are Level 12 Elite Controllers with the Leader
keyword, 236 HP, and speed 9. Dusk Unicorns work exactly like the basic model,
but with bigger numbers and a couple of different powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of Fey Beguiling they have &lt;strong&gt;Fey Wisp&lt;/strong&gt; (Area Burst 5 within 10
vs. Will; at-will; no damage), which creates dancing lights in the burst’s
origin squares and pulls any enemies it hits 3 squares towards the lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in addition to Fey Step, they have &lt;strong&gt;Twilight Teleport&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 5;
encounter) which affects only willing allies within range and teleports them to
somewhere else within the dusk unicorns’ line of sight. Yes, only the starting
square has to be within range - the end point can be anywhere visible!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you could have something cheesy like a dusk unicorn scrying the party or
looking through a scope, and using that to teleport a bunch of allies right on
top of them. Or you could have this power be the centerpiece of an heroic
sacrifice, as the unicorn transports is allies to safety before being
overwhelmed by the enemy. That works better if the teleported allies are the
PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is short and to the point: 1 dusk unicorn and 3 banshrae
warriors. Either the unicorn is a psychopath, or the banshrae are unusually
nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like unicorns! These follow the 4e maxim of being potentially usable in a
fight against Good PCs, since they are Unaligned and might have goals that
conflict with those of the party. In previous editions, if you’re fighting a
unicorn it means something went horribly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically it seems they have so many signature traits (horn and hoof attacks,
Fey Step, Horn Touch, Fey Warding) that it might be easier to make custom
unicorns by adjusting their level and messing with the minor secondary magic
powers.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/24/unicorn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/24/unicorn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Umber Hulk</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-umber-hulk.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umber Hulks have been in the game since at least AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition. Here, they’re
present in both the Monster Manual and the Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umber Hulks are insectoid predators native to the Underdark, through which they
roam by digging tunnels with their powerful claws. Tunneling is slow and hungry
work, so they need a lot of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umber Hulk are curious explorers and their tunnels are stable, so they end up
being an important part of the Underdark’s ecosystem. While Purple Worm tunnels
form the “avenues” and “highways” of that subterranean realm, hulk tunnels form
its side roads and streets, linking larger passages and caves together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lacking in both natural stealth or speed, umber hulks like to hunt by tunneling
until they’re about to break through into a larger space, and using their
tremorsense to wait for approaching prey. Then they finish bursting through the
wall and enter combat. Once engaged, they use the psychic powers granted by
their peculiar second set of eyes to attack their victim’s mind, making then an
easier target for their claws. Contrary to what it might seem, the psychic eyes
are the large faceted pair, not the tiny, beady one. Those they use to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hulks are sapient and Unaligned, but not very smart at Int 5. They can’t speak,
but can understand Deep Speech, so it’s possible for PCs to negotiate with them
and avoid violence if they know the language and think to do
that. Unfortunately, they’re another one of those creatures that often gets
enslaved by the evil empires of the Underdark, and avoiding violence with those
is a little trickier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umber Hulks are Large Natural Magical Beasts, with Darkvision and
Tremorsense 5. They usually have a speed of 5, and a burrowing speed of 2 with
the Tunneling enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with their big claws and their psychic gaze, though the exact effects
of those vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;umber-hulk-both&quot;&gt;Umber Hulk (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 12 Elite Soldier with 248 HP. Its gaze confuses
victims and makes them wander around aimlessly, making them easy prey for its
large, grabby, rending claws. The two books model this a bit differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases, the hulk’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;, and it can make a &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt; with it. If both attacks hit, the hulk grabs the target. The Monster
Vault escape DC is a generous 20, but the MM DC is either the hulk’s Fortitude
of 33 or its Reflex of 28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference lies in what happens after the monster grabs a victim. The
Monster Manual version (with the higher escape DCs) does ongoing 10 damage to
the grabbed victim. The Monster Vault umber hulk can instead use a standard
action to &lt;strong&gt;Rend&lt;/strong&gt; the victim and do an automatic 40 damage to it, which is like
an automatic hit of its usual double attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their gaze works the same in both versions: It’s a Close Blast 5 vs. Will,
targetting enemies in the area. It does no damage, but slides the targets 5
squares and dazes them (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;umber-hulk-tunneler-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Umber Hulk Tunneler (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This specimen is a Level 15 Skirmisher with 148 HP. Since it’s not as beefy as
the basic model, it relies on snatching a chosen victim and running away with
it, using its gaze to keep the victim’s friends at bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack is a bit weak, but the tunneler can use &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt; to make two of them against the same target. If both hit, the tunneler
can shift up to 5 squares and pull the victim along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its eyes can cast a &lt;strong&gt;Rebuffing Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Will). The targets it
hits take 2d6 damage whenever they enter a square closer to the hulk during
their next turn. So it’s more of a disincentive to move closer than a
prohibition, and an PC who’s feeling lucky can risk taking up to 10d6 damage
to charge in anyway. At levels 12-15, this is significant but not necessarily
lethal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;umber-hulk-bewilderer-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Umber Hulk Bewilderer (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This variant relies on its psychic powers more than on its claws. It’s a Level
15 Controller with 148 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack is once again kinda weak, but it does double damage
against stunned targets. The bewilderer can employ a &lt;strong&gt;Stunning Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (close
blast 5 vs. Will; recharge 5-6) as a standard action to stun those enemies it hits for a turn,
and it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Staggering Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Will) as 1/round minor
action to do a bit of psychic damage and slide the target 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bewilderers can punch above their weight class if they focus on a single PC, and
if you have more than one such umber hulk they multiply each other’s
firepower. I’d say include at least two in an encounter group where you want
them to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deep-hulk-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Deep Hulk (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an umber hulk from way deeper into the Underdark - it’s a stronger
version of the basic model, a Level 17 Elite Brute with 404 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Umber Hulk but more” describes this creature perfectly. Most of its attacks are
versions of those from the MV basic hulk with bigger numbers: the claw, the
grabby double attack, and the rending (which does 60 damage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Deep Hulk’s gaze gets upgraded to a &lt;strong&gt;Maddening Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5
vs. Will). This attacks every enemy in the blast, as usual. Those that get hit
must spend a standard action on their next turn making a basic attack against an
ally in range. If there’s no ally in range, they must charge the closest ally. I
guess it’s a “maddening” gaze because it will make your players pretty mad even
though it only lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, the gaze is an at-will attack, so a deep hulk can open the fight with it,
spend the next turn clawing a PC, and from them on alternate the gaze with the
claws (or the rending). It won’t even give up too much damage potential if the
party includes lots of people with good basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shadow-hulk-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Shadow Hulk (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of this monster is the same behind the Deep Hulk: a bigger, badder
Umber Hulk from deeper in the Underdark. The implementation is quite different,
however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadow Hulks are Huge Shadow Magical Beasts, which hints that they might have
been mutated by magical leaks from the Shadowfell somewhere down there. They’re
Level 17 Solo Soldiers with 860 HP. Their land speed is 6, their burrowing speed
4, and they have &lt;em&gt;phasing&lt;/em&gt;, which means they might not actually burrow much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadow Hulks attack with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, have the grabby &lt;strong&gt;double attack&lt;/strong&gt;, and
bite the grabbed victim for 15 ongoing damage. While bloodied, they can also
make &lt;strong&gt;claw frenzy&lt;/strong&gt; attacks (close burst 3 vs. AC; recharge 6) which do the
same damage of the basic attack over an area. They also have the Deep Hulk’s
&lt;strong&gt;Madening Gaze&lt;/strong&gt;, which they can use as an &lt;em&gt;at-will minor action 1/round&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I get why we got the Deep Hulk in the Monster Vault instead of a more
direct conversion. Fighting 860 HP of umber hulk with higher AC and accuracy
than normal, and who can both claw &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; use a maddening gaze every round, is a
bit much. Still, if your players are cocky, you can update the Shadow Hulk and
throw it at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 13, 2 umber hulks and 2 drow warriors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hulks from the Monster Vault are much better than the ones from the Monster
Manual. If you have the Vault, you can disregard the MM versions entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like Umber Hulks! They’re a big dumb brute monster with some really
interesting tricks to go with he usual physical attacks. Fighting them requires
a bit more thought because of that.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/20/umber-hulk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/20/umber-hulk.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual/Vault: Troll</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm-4e-troll.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2008 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D Trolls are inspired by the writings of Poul Anderson and have been in the
game since the beginning. Here, they are present in both the Monster Manual and
the Vault. I’m telling you in advance: I’m not gonna make jokes about rude
Internet posters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls are large humanoid creatures with amazing regenerative powers, able to
survive just about anything and thrive just about anywhere. This same remarkable
metabolism makes it so trolls are always hungry and in search of food. They’ll
eat anything that’s smaller than themselves and made of meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only things that can temporarily overwhelm a troll’s regeneration are fire
and acid. One of these is required to kill a troll permanently - it can come
back from anything else. This makes them pretty much fearless in combat. Trolls
attack even when they’re outnumbered and when the enemies seem strong, because
they’re confident in their survival. Even the presence of fire and acid doesn’t
get them to back off right away, though in this case they might retreat if they
get too hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine this made trolls into dangerous puzzle monsters back when they were
new, but now pretty much any D&amp;amp;D veteran is going to know about their
weaknesses. Many arcane characters have easy sources of fire or acid at hand,
and other “caster” types might have an encounter power or two that deal those
types of damage. If your wizard is one of those charop types that went all in on
psychic and force spells, though, you’re in for a tought fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have no other source of fire you can “kill” the troll with
conventional weapons and stick a lit torch in it to finish the job, but even
that is easier said than done. And adventurers these days tend to prefer those
alchemical glow-sticks as light sources, so they might not even have torches
available if they don’t know a troll is around!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls are sapient, but not very smart. Still smarter than ogres,
though. Tricking the typical troll is easy, provided you can get it to talk to
you instead of immediately ripping you apart and eating the pieces. All sorts of
villains and tyrants like to recruit trolls into their forces, since they’ll
readily work for a bit of money and a lot of food. Such trolls are all too glad
to receive additional training and gear from their bosses, and though they make
for undisciplined and rowdy soldiers, they’re deadly in a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evil wizards also love trolls, for a different reason. They can survive all
sorts of disturbing magical experiments, which tend to result in weird mutants
much stronger and much less mentally stable than a standard troll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s perfectly possible for there to be trolls who aren’t evil and who don’t eat
other sapients, though even them they’d have a hard time coexisting with those
sapients since they require large hunting areas to sustain themselves. Even nice
trolls are likely to make their home in the wilderness far away from any
settlements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls are Large Natural Humanoids, and their signature traits are
&lt;strong&gt;Regeneration&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Troll Healing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I explained in a previous entry, 4e Regeneration is more or less equivalent
to 3e’s Fast Healing: the monster recovers the specified amount of hit points at
the start of its turn as long as it has at least 1 HP remaining. For MM trolls,
this is either 10 or 15 depending on the stat block. For MV trolls, this is 5
across the board. Troll regeneration stops working for a turn if the monster
takes fire or acid damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Troll Healing is what makes them immortal: if a troll is reduced to 0 HP by
anything other than fire or acid damage, it recovers the specified amount of HP
and rises again at the start of its next turn. It can still be killed before it
rises if it takes fire or acid damage while down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these, they can usually do something interesting when their basic
attack bloodies a target. Being Large creatures, all their attacks have
Reach 2. They only speak Giant, which is another barrier to nonviolent
communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;troll-both&quot;&gt;Troll (Both)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model is a Level 9 Brute with 100 HP. The MV version has regeneration
10 and troll healing 10, while the MV version has regeneration 5 and troll
healing 15. Both have speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trolls attack with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, and if their basic attack bloodies the
target they get to make another one against it as a free action. They have no
other special abilities, being quintessential brutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battle-troll-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Battle Troll (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A troll who received extra training and equipment from its patrons. It’s a Level
12 Soldier with 124 HP. Its speed is reduced to 7 by armor, and its
regeneration/troll healing values are 5/15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The battle troll wears scale and fights with a &lt;strong&gt;broadsword&lt;/strong&gt;, which marks the
target for a turn. If a broadsword attack bloodies the target, the troll can
make another free attack against it. It can also use the sword to make
&lt;strong&gt;sweeping strikes&lt;/strong&gt; which hit in a Close Blast 2 and knock targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bladerager-troll-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Bladerager Troll (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product of twisted Cocaine Wizard experiments, this is a troll who had tons
of sharp blades implanted all over its body. It’s a Level 12 Brute with 151 HP,
Speed 7, and Regeneration 5 &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; Troll Healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bladerager attacks with its augmented &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which can also perform a
&lt;strong&gt;Bladerager Rend&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter for massive immediate damage and ongoing
10 damage (save ends). A miss does half the immediate and ongoing damage. If the
basic claw attack bloodies a target, the Rend recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the bladerager reaches 0 HP, it explodes into a cloud of shrapnel! This
&lt;strong&gt;Death Burst&lt;/strong&gt; targets affects a Close Burst 2 around the troll, doing a bit
less damage than the rend to everyone caught by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghost-troll-render-monster-vault&quot;&gt;Ghost Troll Render (Monster Vault)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This troll died but didn’t even notice. It’ll still try to eat you. You can make
any regular troll into an elite of sorts by having one of these rise up from its
corpse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost Trolls are Level 13 Brutes with 161 HP and the Undead keyword. They have a
flight speed of 7 with Hover and Phasing, and are immune to disease and
poison. Lacking a body, they no longer regenerate and are instead
Insubstantial. This means they take half damage from anything but force
attacks. Getting hit by a radiant, fire or acid attack makes them substantial
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Spirit Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Reflex, and they can
perform a &lt;strong&gt;Terror Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. Will) that does a massive amount of
psychic damage and slows on a hit (save ends). The first failed save turns that
slowed status into unconsciousness, which ends on a sucessful save or if the
victim takes damage. This is an encounter power that recharges if it misses, so
chances are the ghost &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; scare someone this way during the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;war-troll-monster-manual&quot;&gt;War Troll (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An earlier but slightly more flexible version of the MV Battle Troll. This one
is a Level 14 Soldier with 110 HP. It wears plate, wields a greatsword, but also
carries a longbow and a quiver full of arrows. Its speed is 7 and its
regeneration/troll healing values are 10/15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has the same &lt;strong&gt;greatsword&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sweeping strike&lt;/strong&gt; attacks of the Battle
Troll, and it also has &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt; (2) and can use &lt;strong&gt;Blood Pursuit&lt;/strong&gt;
as a reaction to shift 1 square closer to a bloodied enemy within 2 squares who
shifts. It can also fight at range with its &lt;strong&gt;Longbow&lt;/strong&gt;, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fell-troll-monster-manual&quot;&gt;Fell Troll (Monster Manual)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest and baddest among trolls. They’re Huge, and Level 20 Elite Brutes
with 360 HP. Their speed is 10, their regeneration/troll healing values are
10/20, and they gain a +1 to attacks and a +2 to damage against bloodied
enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;, and they can use Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;backhand
slams&lt;/strong&gt; as a 1/round minor action for extra damage and to push fools up to 4
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it’s possible for a game to call itself D&amp;amp;D without including
green regenerating trolls in its bestiary. Non-D&amp;amp;D games can still have them, of
course: GURPS Dungeon Fantasy does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual has three sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 9: 3 trolls and 2 destrachans. The destrachans are slightly smarter than
the trolls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 16: 2 war trolls, 1 night hag, 5 grimlock minions, a drow priest, and a
drow blademaster. A group so diverse it could be an evil adventuring party.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: 1 fell troll, 2 enormous carrion crawlers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War and battle trolls can be found alongside anyone who is willing to pay
them. The others would be found with more trolls, and with creatures they might
have decided to keep as pets. Mechanically, they need that company to make for
more interesting fights, because their abilities aren’t very varied on their
own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding some trolls to a “wilderness” region you’re populating might work as a
fine explanation for why all those other deadly monsters don’t spill out and
overwhelm nearby “points of light”. If anyone would hunt and eat bullettes, dire
boars, roaming gricks and maybe even the occasional drow scouting party, it’s a
bunch of trolls.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/09/troll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/01/09/troll.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
