<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>Octopus Carnival posts categorized as "GURPS"</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.gurps.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 00:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 00:42:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shadowrun: Goncharov</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently read about a fun Tumblr meme. It’s about Goncharov, a 1973 Martin
Scorcese movie that never existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It began when someone posted a picture of these bootleg boots they bought
somewhere. The brand label had one of those word salads copied from somewhere
and edited by someone not too familiar with the target language. In this case,
it was copied from a poster for Gomorrah, a real movie. And it read “Martin
Scorcese presents Goncharov”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tumblr &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tumblr.com/hussyknee/701454778540146688/im-so-confused-rn-can-you-explain-the-goncharov&quot;&gt;kinda ran with it&lt;/a&gt;, so now you have a lot of people making things up about
the movie and fabricating screenshots, posters, bits of soundtrack, talking
about all of this as if it was a real cinematic masterpiece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone in a Discord server I frequent suggested Goncharov should become a
standard name for someone who doesn’t exist, the opposite of John Doe. And this
got me thinking about Shadowrun again. Here are two uses for the name Goncharov
in a Shadowrun-like setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mundane&quot;&gt;The Mundane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Shadowrun, “Mr. Johnson” is shadowrunner slang for a person who hires
shadowrunners. The stereotypical Mr. Johnson is a shady fuck in a suit who talks
in vague businesslike terms&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but it can be anyone who is willing to be the
“client” for a runner group. That’s an established part of the game already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how about we say Goncharov is the “reverse” term? Goncharov is Johnson code
for shadowrunners! Sure “shadowrunners” is canon and also works well, but you
can’t really write “shadowrunner payoff” in your official corporate ledger, can
you? So instead you write “payment to Goncharov for services rendered”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just like no self-respecting mysterious client calls themselves Mr. Johnson,
no self-respecting runner calls themselves Goncharov. Someone who takes that as
their handle or even as an alias is telling the whole world they’re a clueless
poser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little bit of culture works well in the Shadowrun setting itself, and on
any other setting that has stylish urban mercenaries as characters, including a
lot of GURPS Action or GURPS Cyberpunk campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numinous&quot;&gt;The Numinous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go a bit further, shall we? Here’s a mystical explanation that’s a bit
more mystical than even Shadowrun’s default setting allows for&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and is a bit
closer to Exalted’s take on spirits and magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goncharov is the Small God of Shadowrunners. He started out as an abstraction,
as above, but at some point became a real part of shadowrunning culture. Either
an existing spirit took on the mantle, or folk belief made him real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real&lt;/em&gt; runners, those who are more than amoral assholes doing horrible things
for money, they have an understanding with Goncharov. They never forget the
corps and the big syndicates are the enemy even when circumstances force them to
work for these groups. They never sell out. They know who their community and
friends are, and they look out for them. And after every successful job, they
give Goncharov his cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goncharov looks like a fit but somewhat scuffed up man in a nice but somewhat
scuffed up suit. The details vary, but he never looks overly fancy or
arrogant. In other words, he might look like John Wick after a fight or three,
but never like the Continental Hotel guy - that’s the god of Mr. Johnsons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magicians can take Goncharov as a mentor spirit. He provides bonuses to combat
spells and Spirits of Man, whatever form those bonuses take in your edition of
choice. Non-magicians can also have “an understanding” with him for a slightly
cheaper price. This gives them access to the Goncharov’s Cut rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goncharovs-cut&quot;&gt;Goncharov’s Cut&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who have an understanding with the god of Shadowrunners, and keep to his
code, can gain extra Karma for giving him his cut. This includes magicians who
take him as a mentor spirit, or any character who spends points to buy a
slightly cheaper Edge representing the covenant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the Karma for Cash rule in your game, such characters gain an
extra point of Karma when using the rule, if they would already gain at least
one point normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s not a general campaign rule, such characters still gain access to it,
becoming able to exchange money for a single point of Karma after every run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases the money goes to support and improve the runner’s community, or
to help out fellow shadowrunners in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-gurps&quot;&gt;In GURPS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a GURPS Action or Cyberpunk campaign with supernatural elements, The
Understanding is a -10-point Code of Honor, since it’s informal but applies to
interactions with people who are not your peers. Give Goncharov his cut and use
it to support your community and fellow runners; hunt down and punish any who
betray them&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;; never sell out; even if you need to do a job for a corp or a
crime syndicate, never forget they’re the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code can work as a “pact” limitation for supernatural or cinematic traits
related to being stealthy, discreet, or good at combat (yes, even Gunslinger or
a talent like Smooth Operator). It would provide a 10% discount on their price,
as normal, and would make these abilities unavailable until atonement if the PC
breaks the attached code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monetary value of Goncharov’s cut is 10% of any earnings from
“shadowrun”-like missions. GMs and players who don’t want to bother with
accounting can just remove it from the PC when it’s given, and assume it gets
spent properly. In games where more detailed tracking is important, the PC
doesn’t need to spend the money immediately, just set it aside for use when
necessary. Using it for personal benefit after it’s been set aside is a
violation of the Code, though. If the protected community has its own
organization stats, the player might want to consider transferring this money
from the PC to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the code might also lead to acquiring traits such as positive
reputation among your community or fellow runners, or Enemies in the form of
traitorous villains and amoral mercenaries who think you’re weak for having a
conscience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atonement from breaking the code usually takes the form of a dangerous mission
to aid an oppressed community or fellow runner in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;And who betrays you at the end. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Though I understand it was kinda moving in this direction in its latest
editions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, you are totally following the code if you track Clockwork down and
shoot him in the head after telling him “Goncharov says hi”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/22/goncharov.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/22/goncharov.html</guid>
        
        <category>shadowrun</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 01</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been playing a lot of Wolfenstein games these past few days. There’s
something cathartic about unapologetically fighting Nazis. I first did it to
de-stress, and then to celebrate the results of our most recent election (go
Lula!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since I do occasionally want to post something here that’s not Let’s Read
the Monster Manual, I decided to talk a bit about the various guns you use to
kill Nazis in all of these games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re dealing with two separate continuities here: one that starts with Return
to Castle Wolfenstein (2001) and another that starts with Wolfenstein: The New
Order (2014). You could, if you’re so inclined, include both of them in the
GURPS Infinite Worlds framework. I’d call then Wolfenstein-1 and Wolfenstein-2
respectively, though I guess Infinity might call the latter Reich-6 at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we’ll cover the stuff that appears in Return to Castle
Wolfenstein (2001), AKA the Wolfenstein-1 setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-overview&quot;&gt;Game Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a flashier remake of Wolfenstein 3D, the game that more or less started
the FPS genre back in 1992. It’s the first game in the franchise to have a more
fleshed out story wrapped around its gameplay, with voiced dialogue and
cutscenes elaborating on the simpler “you must escape the castle and kill Nazis”
plot of the 1992 game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game takes place in a pulpier version of WWII, where the Nazis are working
on a large variety of scary secret projects and the OSA (a joint Allied spy
agency) is sending agents to stop them from hitting the field. The player
character, as always, is William “B. J.” Blazkowicz. He gets sent along with a
British agent to Castle Wolfenstein to find more about these projects, they get
captured, and the game starts with Blazko’s escape attempt and moves on to
thwarting those projects to the Allies can win the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two sinister things going on here: an attempt by the Thule society to
resurrect ancient evil undead knights, and a mad science lab working to build
cyborg supersoldiers. The final boss is, of course, a bunch of cyborg
supersoldiers possessed by the spirits of ancient evil undead knights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-weapons&quot;&gt;Historical Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolfenstein-1 is mostly a pulpier version of WWII, so a lot of the weapons we
see are historical and present on GURPS High-Tech. Though sometimes you’ll start
a level with some Allied weapons issued by the OSA, the vast majority of the
time you’ll be using captured German hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OSA-issue weapons include the &lt;strong&gt;Colt M1911A1&lt;/strong&gt; pistol (p. HT99), the &lt;strong&gt;Thompson
M1&lt;/strong&gt; submachine gun (p. HT122), and the &lt;strong&gt;Enfield Sten Mk IIS&lt;/strong&gt; submachine gun
(p. HT 125). The integral suppressor of the Sten works according to cinematic
principles here, making it completely silent to enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, one of the “elite guard” units you face in the game also
uses Stens, because they’re meant to be sneaky and the Sten is the only
suppressed SMG in the game. The other OSA weapons are used exclusively by the
player character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;German weapons include the &lt;strong&gt;Luger P08&lt;/strong&gt; pistol, (p. HT98), the &lt;strong&gt;ERMA MP40&lt;/strong&gt;
SMG (p. HT 124), the &lt;strong&gt;Mauser Kar98K&lt;/strong&gt; rifle (p. HT111), the &lt;strong&gt;Rheinmetall
FG42&lt;/strong&gt; battle rifle (p. HT 115) and the &lt;strong&gt;Panzerfaust&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT147). The player
also uses these extensively, since every enemy drops ammo for one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FG42 is the signature weapon of the other “elite guard” unit in the game,
and has the scope described in its High-Tech entry. It’s also possible to find a
suppressor for the Luger and a variable-power scope for the Mauser, which you
can stat up using the generic rules in p. HT 156 and p. HT 158.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can occasionally also find a few &lt;strong&gt;MG42&lt;/strong&gt; machine gun (p. HT 134)
emplacements in the game. There is also a flamethrower similar to the &lt;strong&gt;M2-2&lt;/strong&gt;
(p. HT179), though this is probably the German equivalent rather than the
American version in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grenades also see use, with most of them being the German &lt;strong&gt;Stielhandgranate
24&lt;/strong&gt;, and the rest American &lt;strong&gt;AMC Mk II&lt;/strong&gt; models. Both are on p. HT190-191.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fictional-weapons&quot;&gt;Fictional Weapons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of pulpy arms research going on here on both sides, so we also get
to see some weapons that don’t exist in reality. We’ll cover these in a bit more
detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;snooper-rifle&quot;&gt;Snooper Rifle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a prototype sniper rifle issued to Blazkowicz by the OSA early in the
second mission of the game. You also find captured rifles later on while
breaking into one of the games’ many secret lab facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Snooper is the most down-to-earth of the experimental weapons here, being an
exaggerated version of the &lt;strong&gt;M3 Carbine&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT113). Even the fancy infrared
sight is real! The biggest changes are the addition of a cinematic integral
suppressor that makes the gun completely silent, and making the infrared sight
more advanced than it really was. The one in the game has variable magnification
and requires no external batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venom-machine-gun&quot;&gt;Venom Machine Gun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first entirely fictional weapon we encounter in the game, and the
second most unrealistic one. It’s a portable, six-barreled, belt-fed minigun. It
has relatively short barrels, a shoulder stock and rifle-style grips. There’s an
in-game document that describes it as firing 7.92mm saboted armor piercing
rounds, but the ammo for it is labeled as “12.7mm” in game. You first find the
Venom as a prototype in one of the secret labs that make up the game’s levels,
and after that it starts appearing in the hands of some enemy human
soldiers. Most of the cyborg supersoldiers you meet towards the end of the game
also carry one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll need custom stats for this one! Let’s go with the assumption that it fires
7.92mm ammo, to make it minimally plausible for it to be portable. To make it a
little easier on the user, we can further say it fires the 7.92x33mm Kurz round,
instead of the longer 7.92x57mm Mauser round from the Kar98K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The in-game Venom takes up to 500 rounds. These would probably be in a
disintegrating belt inside a metal can that can be worn as a backpack. The whole
thing weights around 16kg, more than the weapon itself. More reasonable 200 and
100 round belts with their smaller containers might weight in at 8 and 4kg
respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll actually base the stats for it on the Minigun from page 138 of GURPS
Ultra-Tech, making the Venom a TL 7+2 weapon. The one on the table fires APDS
ammo, which is also TL 7+2 in this caliber, and has a 500-round belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d+2(2) pi-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000/4000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15kg/16kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25!&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Venom requires Guns (LMG) to operate, or Guns (Longarm) with the Burst-Fire
technique if using the alternate gun skill rules from Pyramid #3/65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tesla-gun&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weapon used by the advanced cyborg supersoldiers you meet at the very end of
the game. Unlike the Venom this doesn’t bear even the tiniest resemblance to any
real gun. Pull the trigger and it fires a stream of lightning until you release
it or until it runs out of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tesla Gun draws power from a superscience backpack battery equivalent to a
TL 9 D cell, but four times heavier. Its damage follows the same rules as the
Lightning spell: metal armor only provides DR 1, and the target must make a HT
roll with a penalty of -1 for every 2 points of injury taken from it. Failure
means they’re stunned, and must attempt an HT roll every turn in order to
recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d+2 burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;600/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;35kg/10kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50 (5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;18M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tesla Gun requires Gunner (Beam) to operate, even when carried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-for-these-fancy-guns&quot;&gt;How much for these fancy guns?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that I ommitted any price information for the Venom and the Tesla
Gun above. That’s because in Wolfenstein-1 they’re secret prototypes with very
limited production runs. You don’t buy them, you pry them from the hands of dead
Nazi assholes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use them on a different setting where they are available for
purchase, use the following costs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom MG&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$12.500&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom Ammo (100-round belt, APDS)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$180&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Venom Ammo (100-round belt, solid)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$60&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Gun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$60.000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Tesla Battery&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;$400&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are for a setting with a tech level of 7+2. If you’re in a “plain” TL9
setting you might want to use the Minigun and Semi-Portable Electrolaser from
Ultra-tech, which have slightly better stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your setting is like Wolfenstein-1, where the overall TL is a plain 7 and
these are secret superscience prototypes, multiply all prices by 4.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Orchard of Time</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had an interesting dream recently that gave me what I think is a neat idea for
a dungeon location: The Orchard of Time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s started out as your standard divine orchard, a bit like the Garden of the
Hesperides. It was owned and operated by a powerful spirit or minor deity, and
its trees gave fruit that ranged from “mundane but high-quality” to “outright
miraculous” the further in you went. If you got to the very center, you could
harvest the Peaches of Immortality or something equally awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something happened to the Orchard’s original owners and they left, abandoning
the place. Monstrous fauna from the surrounding regions moved in and either
overwhelmed the previous guardians or entered some sort of symbiosis with
them. These new monsters found ample food in the trees of the Orchard, whose
energies mutated them to be larger and stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, a powerful arch-wizard found the Orchard’s location and decided to go
for the Peaches. This extremely arrogant individual was sure he would succeed
where all others have failed. After all, the others weren’t him! He armed
himself with his best spells and his best magic items, and teleported to the
Orchard’s entrance (can’t teleport into it from outside). Then he boldly strode
past the gate, and cast his most powerful magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a custom spell that would stop time everywhere in the Orchard except
for an area five meters or so in radius around the wizard himself. The idea was
that, with time stoped, the archmage could just walk up to the really good trees
in the center while dodging the place’s many inhabitants. If he needed to remove
any of them, he could bring them into the “active time” circle and use his other
magic to handle them one individual or small group at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the wizard’s hubris got the better of him at exactly the worst
time. Maybe he had miscalculated when creating the spell, or maybe he made a
critical error when casting it. The fact is that our wizard just
kinda… exploded, leaving behind only his ornate metal staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the spell itself worked exactly as planned. Even better in fact, as
the same error that deleted our wizard made it last forever. It’s centered on
the wizard’s staff, which stands planted on the ground just inside the Orchard’s
entrance gate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;layout-and-hazards&quot;&gt;Layout and Hazards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orchard is located in a hidden valley and is bordered by tall forested
mountains. The climate can range from temperate to tropical depending on what
kind of fruit you want it to contain. As mentioned above, vestigial divine wards
prevent people from finding it with divination or from teleporting into it from
outside. It can still be found via good old-fashioned research, as its location
is recorded in ancient religious texts and in the unfortunate wizard’s own
notes. The wizard has also helpfully dispelled any magical defenses that
prevented people from just walking through the main gate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Orchard of Time was a little overgrown from its period of abandonment, but
still retains its characteristic layout. There are many trees but they’re spaced
far apart. Cobbled paths wind their way among them. Grass and other wild plants
reach up to a human’s knees between the trees and paths. This space used to be
taken up by a lawn and flower beds, but these have been overwhelmed by native
plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that despite covering a very large area, the Orchard has excellent
sight lines and a clearly navigable layout. You can see a good deal of its
significant landmarks from the entrance gate and it’s impossible to get lost
inside. These excellent sight lines work against intruders such as the PCs,
because they allow the many, many monsters and guardians that live here to see
them from far away. These creatures are all hostile, territorial, and generally
incapable of dialogue either because they have animal intellect or because
they’re some sort of construct. In the dream I had these monsters definitely
included a variety of Rodents of Unusual Size. There are almost more monsters
than there are fruit, and they all more or less converge on the location of any
intruders they can perceive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or they &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt;, if time hadn’t stopped inside. The wizard’s staff is just
inside the entrance, and it projects a field of “normal time” in a 5-meter
radius around itself. Everything outside this bubble and inside the orchard’s
outer walls is frozen in time, and has been for a long time (decades?
centuries?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs who want to succeed where the arrogant wizard failed need to carry the staff
with them. Getting close enough to a monster that it enters the “bubble” will
unfreeze the creature, and it will imediately attack. There might be a route
that allows them to avoid most of the creatures, but not all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the copious monsters, the permanent time stop might have created
hazardous areas inside the Orchard, where space or time itself behave in harmful
ways. These might be almost impossible to detect until they’re inside the active
time bubble, which would make them reveal themselves in a dramatic fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-go-there&quot;&gt;Why go there?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious reason to delve the Orchard of Time is to get its most awesome
fruits from the big trees at the center, like the wizard wanted to do. The
Orchard might also contain buildings of interest (such as libraries or treasure
vaults), along with the bodies of ancient adventurers who tried to delve the
place before the ill-fated wizard. Some of these might be legendary themselves,
and have died carrying their equally legendary gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slightly alternate Orchard would have been invaded by the wizard while it was
still operational! In this case it’s going to be in pristine condition, with all
of its original guardians and security systems still in place. Even its &lt;em&gt;owners&lt;/em&gt;
will still be around, frozen in time like flies in amber. Freeing them is an
excellent goal for more heroic sorts, or at least for sorts who need the
specific help whose divine entities are able to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since those owners are frozen in time, they’re still going to be under
the impression that they’re being invaded by a cheeky wizard. And look at you,
carrying his staff around like that. Better talk fast!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/10/23/orchard-of-time.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/10/23/orchard-of-time.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Hell's Rebels Adventure 03, Part 01</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go to the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/hells-rebels/&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt; to see all entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite a while since I posted an article on this series! There are
several reasons for this, both real-world and blog-related. One of the latter
ones was that these adventures were getting &lt;em&gt;bigger&lt;/em&gt;. The detailed approach I
took on Adventure 02 was meant to kinda be a stealth GURPS adaptation, but it
probably wasn’t as helpful as I thought and it left me kinda burned out on
Hell’s Rebels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to take a more condensed approach on Adventure 03, &lt;strong&gt;Dance of the
Damned&lt;/strong&gt;, and leave the detailed conversion bits for their own post. This one
feels even bigger than Adventure 02, as it has three “dungeons” and a number of
social encounters as well. I’ll try to cover them all with one post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that happened over the hiatus is that I ran the first
adventure and most of the second for a group of my friends, over roll20 and
using GURPS. So you can expect &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; conversion notes in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the previous adventure, the PCs had secured a permanent
headquarters under the ruins of the Lucky Bones casino and completed several
high profile missions that increased their fame and notoriety within the city of
Kintargo. Even Barzilai Thrune, ruler of Kintargo and the campaign’s Big Bad,
was forced to congratulate them on their “civic-mindedness” after they get rid
of a dangerous serial killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrune unwittingly helps them further by increasing the Bleakbridge toll to 2gp
per crossing (or 10 for a day pass). This a trivial amount for the PCs by this
point, but it’s prohibitive for a lot of the civilian population. You see,
Kintargo is split into northern and southern halves by a river, and this bridge
is the only crossing. Plus D&amp;amp;D sets the daily wage of a common laborer at about
1gp. So yeah, dick move on Barzilai’s part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people set up illegal ferry operations in response to this, at first
charging just a few coppers and then doing it for free just to stick it to the
Man. It’s quite possible the Silver Raven PCs themselves have already done this
after the first couple of increases in previous adventures (like my group
did). If they did that, they’re sure to gain a massive reputation boost. Even if
they didn’t anti-Thrune sentiment should still help them gather supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rebellion poised to grow so much, it’s time to begin thinking bigger,
and this is what Adventure 03 is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, the book also mentions that the PCs might want to begin thinking about
improving the Lucky Bones’ defenses. It doesn’t get attacked during &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;
adventure, but there’s a high chance that will happen in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1-the-silver-council&quot;&gt;Chapter 1: The Silver Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs aren’t yet regularly meeting with the key NPC allies they’ve been
making along the way, then one of these allies will suggest they begin doing so
now. The book calls this group the Silver Council. It will at the very least be
composed of Laria Longroad and Rexus from Adventure 01 plus Hetamon Haace from
Adventure 02, and will also contain any other such allies the group makes in
your game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silver Council’s first order of business in this adventure is an alliance
proposal by Lady Mialari Docur, one of Haace’s good friends. She runs Lady
Docur’s School for Girls, which is a real school but also a front for the
closest thing Kintargo has to a functioning thieves’ guild. The offer is
genuine, the numeric and political benefits are great, and the alliance is more
or less automatic unless the PCs go out of their way to be assholes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After these pleasantries are concluded it’s time to discuss the next big
steps in the rebellion’s progression. They have plenty of citizen support, but
they should still secure official alliances with Kintargo’s noble houses. And
even beyond that, they should gather &lt;em&gt;regional&lt;/em&gt; support and prevent Thrune from
doing the same. Kintargo is not the only city in the duchy of Ravounel, after
all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;noble-alliances&quot;&gt;Noble Alliances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kintargo’s eight remaining noble houses are a bit more similar to Renaissance
families than to feudal ones. Their fortunes come from varied commercial
interests in the duchy. We get a list of houses, a short stat line for their
leaders, their political allegiance, the requirement for an alliance, and its
mechanical benefits to the rebellion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political allegiance can be either to Kintargo or to Thrune. Houses whose
allegiance lies with Kintargo can be persuaded to support the rebellion if the
PCs can impress their leaders and convince them the city would be better off if
it declares independence from Cheliax. Failure to do so results in them staying
neutral. Thrune-aligned houses can’t be convinced to ally with the
Ravens. They’re also a bunch of evil slave traders, so we don’t want then on
our side anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four of the houses are Kintargo-aligned, three are Thrune-aligned, and one is
undecided. This last one is House Aulorian, which will only ally with the Ravens
if the PCs undo their good deed from Adventure 02 and return Marquel to them. I
don’t imagine many groups will go for this, but the option is there. Unless this
happens, they flip to Thrune when the chips are down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regional-hot-spots&quot;&gt;Regional Hot Spots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kintargo is the capital of the duchy of Ravounel, but it’s not its only
city. The duchy is cut off from central Cheliax by an imposing mountain chain
with a single pass through it. Most trade comes via sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three important places related to the goal of gathering regional
support in Ravounel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The aquatic elf village of Acisazi, whose inhabitants can do a lot to defend
Kintargo from Chelish naval actions. The PCs rescued scouts from this
community in the previous adventure, which should give them an “in” with the
local rulers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The city of Vyre, a mostly independent “vice city” that’s a preferred vacation
spot for the country’s nobility. The Chelish government wants to keep good
relations to them because it loves its vacations; they want to keep good
relations to Kintargo because they don’t have a decent sea port. Securing an
alliance with Vyre would help with keeping Cheliax away.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Menador Gap, that one mountain pass to Central Cheliax.  If the pass is
closed, it will prevent Chelish troops from marching directly into the
province. They’d have to take the long way around and march through
neighboring nations, which will be at the very least much harder.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these is its own chapter (or “Part”) in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rumors&quot;&gt;Rumors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We close with a round of rumors where the GM can insert the ones they like. The
book notes two important ones: a reminder that the former Mayor of Kintargo is
still missing, and the news that Barzilai Thrune is organizing a grand gala to
assure the city everything is fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gala, named the Ruby Masquerade, will be the adventure’s climax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes-and-impressions&quot;&gt;Notes and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is where the Adventure Path format hurt the actual adventure a
bit. Both Lady Docur and the noble houses feel like things that could have been
introduced way back in Aventure 01.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early introduction to Lady Docur give the PCs a good starting bonus on the
“strategic layer” of the campaign, and allows her to act as the “face” of
Kintargo’s black market when the PCs need to buy gear. I did that when I GMed
Adventure 01 and had a lot of fun inserting Little Witch Academia characters as
students / guild members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noble houses also benefit from an early introduction. Securing alliances
with them requires a lot of personal interactions with their leaders, so PCs who
like the tradecraft and roleplaying aspects could have a good time researching
their habits, arranging meetings, and negotiating with them. It also gives a
little more weight to the decision of whether to rescue Marquel in the first
place or not. Rescuing him still the right thing to do, IMHO, but it feels more
organic to have it be inserted in a political context from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-2-dead-in-the-deep&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: Dead In the Deep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ravounel has a northern coast that’s mostly dominated by a huge tangle of reefs
known as the Dismal Nitch. There are charted routes through this, but Kintargo
is pretty much the only decent sea port in the region. The Acisazi village is
located in the Nitch, and its sea elf inhabitants can easily swim all through
it. They can do wonders to block those sea routes if they don’t like the people
trying to sail through. The PCs should make sure they dislike Thrune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs saved the sea elf scouts from Adventure 02, they’re going to have a
&lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier time here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-situation&quot;&gt;The Situation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Acisazi village has a submerged district and a coastal one, where its
half-elf inhabitants live. It’s located near an underwater shaft called The
Drowned Eye, a cursed place whose evil was contained by Acisazi wards. Back
around the start of Adventure 01, though, these wards failed, and a strange
malady began affecting the village’s inhabitants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the spoilerific truth: the wards failed because they were destroyed by
Menotheguro, an aboleth necromancer who moved in around the time Adventure 01
was getting started. He’s working on focusing the Drowned Eye’s cursed energy
into the creation of an epic undead creature called a “sea bonze” (i.e, an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umib%C5%8Dzu&quot;&gt;Umibozu&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To protect himself, he’s raized an entire sunken ship’s crew as draugr, and a
huge great white shark as a zombie. He also secretly placed Nerrenn, the
village’s main protector, under long-term mental domination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Menotheguro’s draugr have been raiding the village and taking prisoners below
the waves to serve as sacrifices in his magical workings. The elf scouts came to
Kintargo to ask for Shensen’s help - she was a long-time friend of theirs. With
her missing, though, the PCs are their only hope. If the scouts survive
Adventure 02, their leader Aava can tell the PCs about the malady, the draugr
raids, and that they serve someone named “Menotheguro”. She doesn’t know the
rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;negotiation&quot;&gt;Negotiation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting into the village is going to be hard even if the PCs bring the sea elf
scouts with them. Nerrenn will receive them at the head of a crowd of hesitant
half-elves. Acting as the village’s interim leader, he will deny then entry
citing all sorts of paranoid reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs good at Diplomacy or Intimidation might convince him to allow an audience
with the village’s Speaker. Otherwise there’s going to be a fight. Whether he’s
browbeaten or just plain beaten up, Nerrenn will rush to his master’s side after
this encounter. Perceptive PCs might realize he’s dominated, and might think to
restrain him and try to dispel or suppress the effect. If they succeed at it,
Nerrenn will spill the whole truth outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is an audience with the village’s true leader, Speaker Athannah. This aged
half-elf druid is close to death due to the curse. She will be an instant friend
of the PCs if they brought the scouts back or revealed Nerrenn’s
domination. Otherwise winning her over will require some more diplomacy on the
PCs’ part. In either case, her condition for a formal alliance is the same:
break the curse of the Drowned Eye and save the village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dungeon-the-drowned-eye&quot;&gt;Dungeon: The Drowned Eye&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Drowned Eye is a deep pit in the ocean floor near a particularly treacherous
set of reefs. Its “curse” comes from the fact that a lot of ships sunk and fell
into it over the years, saturating the place with a death aura. Menotheguro is
at the bottom, protected by his guardians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a “dungeon” only in the sense that it’s a location with monsters. The
layout is entirely linear, and the PCs will run through every encounter in the
order listed. The biggest environmental complication is that it’s all
underwater. By this point the PCs should have some experience with underwater
combat, since it was a good bit of Adventure 02’s final dungeon. Acisazi Village
should have more than enough water-breathing magic available even if they didn’t
come prepared for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the PCs approach the vincinity of the hole, they’re going to be attacked by
half of Menotheguro’s draugr contingent. If they haven’t yet dropped underwater,
they’re going to have a surprise because the undead will surely try to sink
their boat and/or drag then under.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dropping down into the Eye itself, the PCs are going to fight the zombie white
shark on the way down. There is no ground, and their opponent is aquatic, making
this fight extra-tricky even though the shark’s numbers aren’t particularly
scary against the whole party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom has the other half of the draugr, including their captain, and an
entrance to Menotheguro’s cave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s almost guaranteed that the aboleth will notice the fight just outside his
door. If that happens he’ll try to trick the PCs with an illusion after they
deal with the draugr, claiming to be the ghost of a druid named “Menotha” who
needs a cleansing ritual performed by a living druid so she can finally rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the PCs don’t fall for the illusion, the aboleth fights them immediately. If
they &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;, he will wait for them to bring Athannah down here, dominate her and
&lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; fight the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Menotheguro himself only has 3 levels of Necromancer, but those are stacked on
top of an aboleth stat block so he’s certainly boss material. If Nerrenn escaped
the surface he will be here at full health ready to fight alongside his
master. He’s considerably more dangerous here because he has terrain advantage
and has his shark animal companion with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fight the PCs can destroy the runes etched in the cave’s wall to ruin
Menotheguro’s ritual and cleanse the Eye. Then they can loot the pile of
treasure in the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the aboleth destroyed and the curse lifted, the PCs secure an alliance from
Acisazi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes-and-impressions-1&quot;&gt;Notes and Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is by far the most “side-trekky” part of the adventure. It does have a
connection to the overall campaign and its story is kinda interesting, which is
good. On the other hand, its ends in an underwater “dungeon” featuring exactly a
day’s worth of combat encounters placed in a straight line one after the
other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is enough to make skipping this chapter altogether a reasonable
decision. In that case you can say Acisazi is actually fine, that Aava was a
relative of the Speaker, and that rescuing her back in Adventure 02 is enough to
secure the alliance. Escorting her back home is something one of the rebellion’s
NPC teams might do, freeing the PCs up for the other scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up: a feast and a fort.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/25/hells-rebels-3-part-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/25/hells-rebels-3-part-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merging Shield Skills in GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is kind of an addendum to my earlier post on &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html&quot;&gt;Merging Weapon Skills in
GURPS&lt;/a&gt;, which occurred to me after reading this other post in &lt;a href=&quot;https://aftertheogre.blogspot.com/2022/08/df-novices-merging-weapon-skills.html&quot;&gt;After the
Ogre&lt;/a&gt;. I realized I hadn’t mentioned Shield skills, but I had been merging
them for so long I had forgotten that wasn’t the standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my GURPS games, there is only one shield skill:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shield-dxe&quot;&gt;Shield (DX/E)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This skill merges &lt;strong&gt;Shield&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Shield (Buckler)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Force
Shield&lt;/strong&gt;. There is still a mechanical difference between a shield that’s held in
the hand and one that’s strapped to the arm, but both of them use the same
skill and there is no familiarity penalty from switching between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the optional rules for Familiarity Penalties in the previous
post, such a penalty would definitely apply when someone used to traditional
shields wields a weightless force shield, and vice-versa. As a reminder, that’s
a -2 penalty to Shield that goes away after a few hours of practice during
downtime, at no point cost.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/20/merging-shield-skills.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/20/merging-shield-skills.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Magic Item: The Coffee Machine From Hell</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I dreamed about this thing today, and what use is a blog if I can’t use it to
write about the weird things I dream up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like a chunky, tabletop coffee machine of the sort that can be made
at TL8, and which might be found in an office. It’s self-contained, with
internal reservoirs for beans and plastic cups. An authorized technician
supposedly refills those after working hours, but employees who stay late never
see this technician, no matter how late they stay. And yet, the machine never
seems to run out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The device bears the name of a company that does indeed make this type of
appliance, though instead of their usual logo it has an upside-down star with a
smiley face. It has no model name or other contact information printed anywhere
on its body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coffee Machine From Hell has a counter-intuitive control panel. Several
button presses are required to tell it what you want, but that’s just bad
interface design. The Machine’s true curse is more insidious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As its name implies, the Coffee Machine From Hell is literally a torment device
built by demons. It will do its nominal job of producing cups of shitty office
coffee, but only if the user is making one for themselves (i.e, being
self-serving) or is thinking hostile or hateful thoughts about the intended
recipient of the drink. Someone who’s genuinely trying to help, or even just
being neutral about it, will find the machine seizes up or behaves
unpredictably. Even if all buttons are pressed correctly, it will spit mangled
cups, spill hot liquid on the countertop, make the wrong drink, and generally go
out of its way to make user experience a nightmare and to never ever produce
whatever it is the third party ordered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placed in an office where “making a coffee for someone else” is an accepted part
of the culture, the Machine will soon turn it into a nest of hate and
resentment. This is accelerated if the “someone else” is always the
boss. Unlucky interns and employees will cause mess after mess until they start
to truly hate the boss. The boss, in turn, will be frustrated that no one else
seems to be able to operate this “simple” machine that always works for them and
will come to hate their underlings in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics&quot;&gt;Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its shitty interface, no roll is required to operate the Machine. It
does however read the operator’s mind to see if it should trigger the curse, in
which case it behaves as if a critical failure had been rolled. This will either
result in a humiliating mess, or in a normal-looking but undrinkable cup of
coffee that’s sure to cause inflict a nasty surprise on its intended recipient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who is wise to the curse can try to trick the device into operating
normally with a successful &lt;strong&gt;Mind Block&lt;/strong&gt; roll, or through any powers they have
that can shield their thoughts from telepathy. This roll can me made at the
usual &lt;strong&gt;Will-5&lt;/strong&gt; default if the character lacks the skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The machine’s infernal nature can be detected by any power or spell that detects
evil or infernal powers. It can be “cleansed” through &lt;strong&gt;Exorcism&lt;/strong&gt; or equivalent
powers, like a more typical cursed artifact. Its greatest defense against
detection and exorcism is that neither of these abilities are common in the
settings in which it appears. Its true nature can’t be detected by purely
scientific means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-it-in-a-game&quot;&gt;How to use it in a game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coffee Machine From Hell is a perfect addition to any oppressive office your
PCs must infiltrate for a while, particularly if they’re undercover as
interns. It’s something of a trap in that case: If everyone else already hates
each others’ guts, the PCs will be the only ones who trigger the curse, and this
will draw undue attention to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, every office &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Hell has one of these, but it can also be present
on Earthly companies under demonic influence, or just wind up in an otherwise
normal company without any explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs on an infiltration mission will most likely need to trick the
machine. Exorcism attempts are too obvious and will likely blow their cover,
especially if they are actually infiltrating Hell. In an infiltration scenario
where the office is weird or evil in other ways, the machine is unlikely to be
the only obstacle they face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a campaign centered on paranormal investigation or monster hunting, the PCs
might be hired to find the problem behind a supernaturally toxic work
environment. If they have supernatural means of detecting evil, they’ll be able
to easily find the Machine, but in those cases it might be only one of the
sources of trouble. If they must rely only scientific instruments, then finding
the Machine is considerably harder even if they can easily use Exorcism to
cleanse it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/coffee-machine-from-hell.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/coffee-machine-from-hell.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>items</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merging GURPS Weapon Skills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Peter V. Dell’Orto made a post in his blog Dungeon Fantastic about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/07/possible-weapon-skill-mergers-for-gurps.html&quot;&gt;merging GURPS weapon skills&lt;/a&gt;. I really, really like the idea, so I thought
about writing about how I’d do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dell’Orto’s post is specific to Dungeon Fantasy and to his own Felltower
campaign. Mine is a bit more generic since I don’t have an active campaign
going, and I tend to kind of mix up Dungeon Fantasy and default GURPS rules in
my head. Consider it an addition to my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/12/18/df-house-style.html&quot;&gt;House Style&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for doing this is also pretty well-covered by this &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/08/why-all-merging.html&quot;&gt;follow-up Dungeon
Fantastic Post&lt;/a&gt;: having too many fine distinctions between spells and skills
in a cinematic campaign can serve as a bit of a damper on the pacing and
excitement of the campaign. My usual players tend to have a certain resistance
to trying stuff that’s not on their character sheets, especially in a complex
system like GURPS, so having broader traits would allow them to experiment a bit
more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-skills&quot;&gt;The Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns where this post is in effect, I’m going to use the following list
of weapon skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Axe/Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This skill is a combination of the original &lt;strong&gt;Axe/Mace&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt;. When
using a flail, the character suffers a -1 skill penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games that use Techniques, &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt; is a new Hard technique that defaults to
Skill-1 and has a maximum level equal to Skill. This means you can buy the -1
penalty off for 2 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fencing-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Fencing (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new skill merges &lt;strong&gt;Rapier&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Saber&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Smallsword&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows you to
use not only these three “titular” weapons, but also any other weapon that would
fall under those skills, such as the jian (Rapier) or the light stick
(Smallsword).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the normal rules for fencing weapons apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;force-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Force Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-3, One-Handed Sword-3, Two-handed Sword-3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should I ever play a science fiction game with force swords, this gets merged
with &lt;strong&gt;Force Saber&lt;/strong&gt;. Whether you get fencing parries or not depends on the stat
line of the weapon you’re using. The “Fencing parries for everyone!” option is
also valid in a more explicitly Star Warsy game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;knife-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Knife (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges the original &lt;strong&gt;Knife&lt;/strong&gt; skill with &lt;strong&gt;Jitte/Sai&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Main-Gauche&lt;/strong&gt;. Any weapon that could be used with either of these can be used
with the new skill. Weapons use their Main-Gauche profiles for this, meaning
there’s no penalty for using the off hand and the user gets fencing parries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, “knife expert” PCs always went for Main-Gauche anyway. People
who dropped a point in Knife as a back-up skill almost never ended up using it,
so they can just drop a point in this one instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jutte and the Sai get both a +2 for disarm attempts and fencing parries
without any special stance switches required. They are rare enough in my games
that I don’t believe it will be a problem. And by “rare” I mean no one has taken
these weapons and no one has tried a disarm yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;One-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4, Two-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the skill used for all one-handed swords, merging both &lt;strong&gt;Broadsword&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Shortsword&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blade length is an important consideration in real life, but it’s below the
level of granularity I prefer. This also broadens the range of really cool magic
swords your sword-wielding players can find and immediately use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pole-weapons-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Pole Weapons (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Sword-5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges &lt;strong&gt;Polearm&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Staff&lt;/strong&gt;. The Form Mastery perk is
redundant for these weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about that sweet Staff parry bonus? If it’s in your weapon’s stat line
under Staff, you get it. If it’s not, you don’t. The only exception to this are
balanced two-handed spears, which I feel should have the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Axe-Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Axe/Mace, but for two-handed weapons. The same rules apply for two-handed
flails, including the existence of a Hard technique to buy the -1 penalty off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much the same skill as the original, with a suitably altered list
of defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-all-the-other-skills&quot;&gt;What about all the other skills?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the more exotic weapon skills, like Whip, Kusari, and Tonfa, remain the
same. I might change my mind in the future and come back to this, but I haven’t
actually used any of them in my games, so it makes no difference for them to
stay as-is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-rule-weapon-familiarity&quot;&gt;Optional Rule: Weapon Familiarity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like how these skills are merged, but still feel a staff user shouldn’t
be able to pick up a halberd and wield it just as proficiently right away, then
you can use a version of the Familiarity rules from the GURPS core book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs are considered familiar with any weapons they acquire during character
creation. If they pick up a weapon that would be used with a different skill
under the standard rules, they have a -2 penalty to use that weapon until they
can spend a few hours practicing with it. This takes time but costs no money or
points. In effect, it can only happen when the PCs have a significant amount of
downtime (such as when returning to town from a dungeon in DF). After this, the
PC is considered familiar with that weapon type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this up as an option, but it’s not one I’ll use myself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Star Wars RPGs and The Force: A Thought</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/Princess-Leia-Shirt.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heruniverse.com/product/star-wars-princess-leia-self-rescuing-princess-t-shirt/10920417.html&quot;&gt;
     Image source.
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t part of a series or anything, but it’s a random though I’ve been
having and I feel it’s worth turning into a post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-thought&quot;&gt;The Thought&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I ever to a Star Wars adaptation, it’s going to be one where everybody is
Force-sensitive. Let’s do away with the absolutist “magic/no-magic” divide
inspired by D&amp;amp;D that all the official RPGs so far have used. If the Force is
described in the source material as being in everyone, then it should &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; in in
everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players would not be forced to play Jedi - rather, the badassitude of their PCs
would be explained by their connection to the Force. No more of that nonsense
about how “you can still be cool even though you’re blind to the Force”. No,
you’re cool because you opened yourself to it. It’s everywhere, and getting past
a certain threshold of skill at any endeavor means becoming attuned to the
Force. By definition, any character who is PC material in the sort of heroic
story Star Wars favors is past that threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, yeah, you can still be a Jedi who throws stuff around telekinetically and
parries blaster bolts with a lightsaber, but you can also be an amazing
gunfighter from the slums of Coruscant who can &lt;em&gt;dodge&lt;/em&gt; blasters, react to stuff
before it happens, and make shots that ricochet from five different surfaces
before hitting some impossibly small target. And maybe both of you can jump
really high because that’s always useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a set of Force-based mechanics that all PCs gets access to, even if they
have the least mystical background possible. They can use it to perform
impossible feats of skill and luck. They can have intuitions and
premonitions. Maybe they can study a mystical tradition to do more overtly
supernatural stuff, but that’s not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe one of the reasons the Dark Side and the Empire are evil is that
they’re the ones who believe that only a select few elites should be given
access to the Force.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/14/star-wars.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/14/star-wars.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>star-wars</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Post Cyberpunk!</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/800517c403ee40194b3e22356dfe823a.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=https://www.deviantart.com/hidrico/art/Style-Over-Substance-Cyberpunk-2077-802599843&gt;
      By Hidrico on DeviantArt
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned back in my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/05/19/cp-red-review.html&quot;&gt;Cyberpunk RED review&lt;/a&gt;, I felt the game didn’t
quite clear my “Threshold of GURPS”. This particular term is new but the idea
itself is almost exactly 5 years old now. I first mentioned it in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/21/to-gurps-or-not-to-gurps.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;, where I discussed what makes me want to reach for GURPS in an
adaptation and what makes me look for other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CP RED’s native system is fine! The reason I say it didn’t “clear the threshold”
is that it’s exactly the sort of system and setting described in the “When to
GURPS” section of that 2017 post. It worries about modeling specific concrete
actions, and it worries about the details of how they’re executed. In addition
to this, the system itself doesn’t have any mechanical novelties that aren’t
reproducible in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, while I’d happily play the native system in a one-shot or something
like that, given enough time to prepare I’d prefer to adapt its setting to
GURPS. Talking about how I’d do it is an excellent excuse for an Octopus
Carnival post. It helps that “Cyberpunk” has been one of the genres GURPS set
out to support since its beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-1-high-concept&quot;&gt;Part 1: High Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk-the-setting is actually a fairly broad place that supports a large
variety of campaigns… but most people seem to be fans of that fairly narrow
slice of stylish street mercs pulling heists for money and/or personal
reasons. I’m not gonna lie, I’m like most people in that regard and so I’m going
to focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the setting has three distinct “eras” now, they all look and feel mostly
the same. The main changes are to the map of Night City and the specific reason
why Johnny Silverhand is raiding Arasaka Tower this time. I think we might be
able to condense that long timeline down a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to mix in my personal preferences: I believe cyberpunk doesn’t
&lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be a dystopia. This is something you might have gathered from my
previous posts on the subject. I find a lot of cyberpunk settings tend to
confuse “things are bad” with “things can never get better”, and I don’t want to
do that here. For Cyberpunk Red specifically, this ends up resulting into a game
that tells players simple survival is the most they can expect in the same book
where it touts the epic exploits of Bartmoss and Silverhand. I want to treat
them as “iconic” characters in the modern sense, which means that if those
clowns can do all this, so can the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we are: a game about stylish street mercs in the neon-lit future, living
in the fictional Night City. They get into noir-ish situations for money, and
see them through for personal reasons. Hostile factions are mostly corporations,
crime syndicates, or violent themed gangs with corporate ties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though PCs often fight for personal stakes they can still end up having a big
impact in the setting&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. PCs who are smart about it and make use of collective
action can make big, lasting, positive change, but even more traditional “band
of badasses” actions will still do something. Not every campaign has to be about
this, but the play style should be possible and supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-2-time-and-place&quot;&gt;Part 2: Time and Place&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, it’s Night City in the neon-lit cyber future. Feel free to
use the present date that suits you best. Set it in one of the official dates of
the original game. Set it in 2100 just to spite Transhuman Space. Make it 20XX,
21XX, 22XX, whatever. Or be like William Gibson and never even mention calendar
years. The backstory follows the same general lines of the original, using
relative dates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifty-something years ago the US government descended further into fascist
stupidity than ever before&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Over the next few decades its economy and
environment crashed big time, the entire West Coast seceded, and the government
was either powerless to stop the rise of the megacorps or was actively helping
them along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-something years ago Johhny Silverhand performed his one and only raid on
Arasaka Tower, which is more or less a combination of the events from the 2013
and 2023 raids in the original chronology. Arasaka’s nuke blows up, and the
political and literal fallout from this causes heavy backlash against megacorps
in general all over the world. Though many are still around, they can no longer
do whatever the fuck they want without fear of consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our narrative present is a blend of CP RED and 2077. Night city rebuilt enough
to leave “survival mode”, but it’s still something of a crime capital where the
corps have lots of influence and habitually pay those themed gangs to do their
dirty work. It also has a relatively large “edgerunner” culture with its own
honor codes and a surprisingly large propensity to take jobs from people who are
neither corp- nor gang- affiliated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of past wars to be a veteran of. The most recent one was
the Corp War that finally died down let’s say 5 years ago. It featured lots of
big corps going at each other, and lots of governments cracking down on them for
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberware is common enough that most people sport at least a bit of
“fashionware” from their late teens onwards. Most people won’t cut off healthy
limbs in order to replace them, but there are plenty of maimed veterans and
victims of disease for whom cybernetic replacements are an appealing
prospect. Implanted augmentations are somewhat more common, with the most
popular by far being a GitS-style “cyberbrain” implanted computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guns and armored clothing are common and relatively easy to get in Night
City. This is not generally a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; thing, and contributes to the city’s still
dismal violence statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertisements are nowhere near as aggressive and explicit as they are in
CP 2077. The real world is bad enough on that front that you don’t need to
further “enhance” it to make a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rache Bartmoss did not “destroy” the NET, because we don’t need to justify rules
changes with an in-setting event. Feral AI gods running on mutated data centers
is too good an image to pass up, though, so those are still there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-3-characters-and-their-stuff&quot;&gt;Part 3: Characters and Their Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of our rules is going to be GURPS Action, because this is a game about
action heroes. The default is that players get to build their PCs using the
250-point archetypes from GURPS Action 1. This makes them experienced
edgerunners. Greenhorns would use the lower-point templates from Specialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our default ruleset is the one from GURPS Action 2, with the main changes to
that being due to the science fiction elements we’re introducing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gear-and-cyberware&quot;&gt;Gear and Cyberware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base tech level is 9, though TL8 gear is still widely available. We’re
either not that far into the future or it’s simply easier to print at home than
the more advanced stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers and biotech are at TL10. You can run a mind emulation from a
portable system, and miraculous speed-healing drugs are available. Implants are
drawn from Ultra-Tech and Bio-Tech and are mostly TL9, though some TL10 things
that appear in the CP books would also be available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberware &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; inherently erode your humanity. Not even if you replace
your healthy bits with chrome that’s better than human standard. We use the
usual GURPS mechanics of making implants cost character points at character
creation and both points and money afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any template can spend its discretionary points on cyberware from Ultra-Tech or
implants from Bio-Tech. This means most PCs might have one or two implants to
start with, though having none is also a valid choice. Campaigns where the PCs
are meant to start out chromed to the gills might give them 25 or 50 extra
points to spend on starting cyberware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;netrunning&quot;&gt;Netrunning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hacking, I want a streamlined system. The one from Pyramid #3/21 is a good
start, since one of its goals is to prevent the isolation from the classic
“dungeon crawl” system of CP 2020. However, I want to rely even less on virtual
reality and be more like Ghost in the Shell or CP 2077.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prospective hacker needs a Neural Interface Implant of some sort (UT,
p. 216). A &lt;em&gt;cyberdeck&lt;/em&gt; is either a Computer Implant (Complexity 5, UT p. 215) or
a small computer (Complexity 6, UT p. 22) with a cable jack and a tiny radio
communicator, but without any built-in terminal. The “default” interface tier is
“Augmented Reality”, where the hacker sees the necessary interfaces alongside
the physical world. It’s possible to go “Full Immersion”, which is faster but
leaves the character effectively unconscious in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters running AR have a -2 penalty in opposed tests against characters
running Full Immersion. This is the only game effect, so it’s only worth giving
up your physical senses when you run into an immersed enemy hacker or an enemy
AI (which always counts as immersed). Programs and skills are the same as in the
Pyramid article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest change from the Pyramid article is in level design. Generally
speaking, “interesting” hackable servers and networks are not directly connected
to the public Internet, and the hacker PC must be on-site to access them. The
smallest and most common target is a single device with a basic firewall,
usually something like a security camera or an automatic door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sites with better security link their devices into a slightly larger
network. This is a bit more similar to the design examples of the Pyramid
article, but remember not to make them too large. Such a network might encompass
all security devices in a given floor. No connecting through a megacorp’s
top-secret research server through the vending machines in the lobby!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;People&lt;/em&gt; might also be a valid target for hacking, if they have those
nearly-ubiquitous computer implants. The implant can have any defenses that
could be installed in a computer of the same Complexity and usually contains at
least a basic firewall. Overcoming those defenses might allow netrunners to
“jam” the target’s senses with spurious sensory data or even run the Damage
program. Savvier opposition might link their internal computers into a more
secure network overseen by a friendly hacker, or just turn the their wi-fi off
entirely if it doesn’t confer any combat benefit to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. That’s enough to play your classic edgerunners in the
Cyberpunk 2020/RED/2077 setting. Any of the Screamsheets from 2020 or RED should
be readily adaptable, since they have little in the way of stats to begin
with. The gigs and side jobs from 2077 also provide plentiful inspiration and
material for tabletop adventures, and that game’s main plot gives you an idea of
what the sort of “high impact” adventure that leaves a crater looks like. You
might need a bit more thought to devise adventures about organizing collective
action, but they’re also quite possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Possibly leaving a big crater. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you’re using a 2077 date, that’s Trump’s thankfully fictional second
mandate starting in 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/23/one-post-cyberpunk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/23/one-post-cyberpunk.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Exalted Martial Arts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There’s this post on Mailanka’s Musings that talks about two different ways of
modeling martial arts in RPGs. The first is something he calls “Move-Based”, and
the second “Skill-Based”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based martial arts is how most RPGs in the 90’s did it. You bought a style,
and that gave you access to a series of “moves” that were essentially special
powers with individual rules for what they did. Some systems made you buy each
individual move as well, usually as a way to model your progression in the
style - advanced practitioners know more moves. Your move set is as or more
important than your raw skill level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skill-based martial arts are what GURPS does. Everyone uses the same skills to
fight, and knowing one style or another is mostly a matter of flavor with a few
minor mechanical bonuses thrown in. What really matters are your skill levels:
people with different style familiarities but similar skill levels are equally
effective. The same applies to someone who “knows” a style and someone who just
has the combat skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move-based rules might allow you to emulate some classic kung-fu stories that
are all about how some styles are objectively superior to others, or how there’s
a secret style or ultimate technique that’s jealously guarded by a cranky old
master. Skill-based rules are closer to Bruce Lee’s philosophy, or modern views
of martial arts in general, where individual skill is more important and the
“ultimate power” is learning from multiple sources and combining everything into
something that works for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer skill-based rules, largely due to my exposure to GURPS
Martial Arts for Fourth edition. Everything it introduces can be done by someone
who isn’t using the style rules. It covers styles from the whole world without
treating any of them as inherently superior, and it acknowledges that basically
any organized system of fighting counts as a “style”. The “generic swings” other
systems describe as the standard form of fighting only happen if you’re
completely untrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this preference, it comes as no surprise that I have a few weirdly
specific hangups about how Exalted handles its martial arts. Let’s talk about
them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exalteds-martial-arts&quot;&gt;Exalted’s Martial Arts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exalted’s &lt;em&gt;whole system&lt;/em&gt; is entirely move-based. Every PC has a large set
of “Charms” that are usually linked to skills, and represent magic techniques
they can use to enhance uses of that skill. Getting to the maximum possible
skill level is trivial, and it’s your Charms that make the difference when going
against similarly supernatural opposition. This goes even for non-combat skills,
though the fighty bits tend to take up a lot of attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martial Arts are part of this system, but the game still takes pains to make
them extra-special, even as it struggles to explain what makes them different
from standard combat powers. Exalted First Edition had a separate Martial Arts
skill, whose associated Charms were structured as “Martial Arts Styles”. They
didn’t really “mix” with charms of other skills. As a result, a lot of each
style’s Charms end up duplicating the effect of basic combat Charms in different
ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second Edition merged “standard” unarmed combat and Martial Arts, and made it a
little easier to mix and match charms from a few different styles. Third Edition
doubled down on the original position and made it so each style had its own
separate skill, thus coming full circle on the ‘martial arts cost more because
they are exotic and special’ trope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-id-do-it&quot;&gt;How I’d Do It&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had I been writing these rules, I’d probably take them in a different direction
entirely, and more towards the way GURPS sees things. There would be no Martial
Arts skill. Each style is associated with a single standard combat skill, and
consists of exactly three Charms representing its advanced or iconic
techniques. The basic stuff is already covered by the standard skill and
standard Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Charms I’d reuse the “lotus” metaphor, so they would be the Root, Bulb
and Blossom Charms. You learn them in this order. Each has the previous one as a
prerequisite, and probably an increasing Essence score. They’re meant to be
combined with the standard Charms for that skill, relying on them for the basic
dice-adding mechanics and such. If you know Charms of multiple styles you can
explicitly combine them as long as the combination is otherwise rules-legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who learns to fight is a martial artist, even if they never pick up
style Charms. Every martial artist ultimately develops their own personal style
by learning from as many sources as possible and keeping what works for
them. And you can certainly describe the way your kung-fu looks as being a
certain style even if you don’t have the Charms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example-snake-style&quot;&gt;Example: Snake Style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t originally plan on doing this, but what the heck, let’s go! Snake Style
has traditionally been the main corebook style, so let’s see how it would look
in this format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what the lore says about it: it’s a style focused on speed and
precision, aiming to take down better armed and armored opponents before they
have time to act. It uses two-fingered strikes to hit pressure points and
exposed tendons. Masters of the style can “pierce through armor”, “paralyze
opponents with pressure point strikes”, and “deliver poisonous Essence through
their fingertips”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of what to keep in our new format is pretty easy - each of the things
masters of the style can do references a specific Charm. We want those. All the
others increase basic numbers in different ways and can be replaced by standard
charms from Brawl and other trees. Want to dodge like a snake? Take Dodge
Charms. Want the “tough scales” effect? Take Resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So our new Snake Style is an unarmed style linked to Brawl. Our Root Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Crippling Pressure Point Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (Ex3 p. 428). Our Bulb Charm is
&lt;strong&gt;Armor-Penetrating Fang Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Our Blossom Charm is &lt;strong&gt;Essence Venom
Strike&lt;/strong&gt;. Their skill level and Essence prerequisites remain the same, but read
Brawl in place of Martial Arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quick and dirty sketch, and some additional work would be
required. Essence Venom Strike needs to be rewritten a bit, since half of its
effects reference Charms we’ve eliminated. We might also want to rewrite some of
the base Brawl charms, though I haven’t looked at them in much depth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/03/29/on-martial-arts.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>exalted</category>
        
        <category>martial-arts</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
