<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 16:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 16:13:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Drakes</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-drakes.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drakes make their debut on the first 4e Monster Manual, and this entry brings us
a few more of them. They remain a popular choice of animal for domestication but
the intro text mentions they retain a wild side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bloodseeker-drake&quot;&gt;Bloodseeker Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These expert trackers were included in the Monster Vault, so we already looked
at them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/01/drakes.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;horned-drake&quot;&gt;Horned Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the wild, horned drakes are pack predators who spend most of the day sleeping
and basking in the sun, going out to hunt at night. They have an excellent
instinct for teamwork, and a pack of them is able to take down much larger prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that, when domesticated, they make stronger alternatives to the
bog-standard guard drake, treating their handlers as part of the pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horned Drakes are Medium Natural Beasts and Level 5 Skirmishers with 63 HP. They
have low-light vision and a speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This drake’s basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does standard physical damage and
allows the creature to shift 2 squares on a hit. The &lt;strong&gt;Pack Movement&lt;/strong&gt; reaction
also allows them to shift 2 squares when an enemy adjacent to them is hit by a
melee attack. This makes them great a setting up flanks with their fellow drakes
or with their handlers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drake can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Goring Horns&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which does high physical
damage and knocks prone on a hit. It also has a +1 attack bonus over the basic
attack, which indicates to me that it’s meant to be a charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, these drakes are set up charge an enemy, then surround and run circles
around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scytheclaw-drake&quot;&gt;Scytheclaw Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another species of pack predator, scytheclaws inhabit forests and
grasslands. They are known for their cunning and for their devious tactics. If
you see one scytheclaw, odds are there are two or three others approaching you
from behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, they’re Jurassic Park raptors!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scytheclaws are Medium Natural Beasts and Level 10 Skirmishers with 105 HP,
which explains why the Jurassic Park protagonists had such trouble with
them. Their ground speed is an amazing 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is the titular &lt;strong&gt;Scytheclaw&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals physical damage
and knocks the target prone. If used against an already prone target, it hits
harder and inflicts 5 ongoing damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the drake hits with its basic attack, it can immediately use &lt;strong&gt;Springing
Step&lt;/strong&gt; (free action; recharge 4-6), which allows it to jump 8 squares and attack
someone else at the end of the jump. This doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks
from the target of the original attack, making it safe to move away from most
PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a prone enemy within reach tries to get up, its &lt;strong&gt;Overwhelming Attacker&lt;/strong&gt;
trait allows it to make an opportunity attack against that enemy. If this hits,
the target remains prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scytheclaws are therefore set up to bounce between PCs while knocking them
prone, and they will absolutely kick you when you’re down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fang-titan-drake&quot;&gt;Fang Titan Drake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you include the Raptors, you almost certainly have to include the T-Rex as
well. And sure enough, here it is. The largest species of drake, few creatures
other than dragons can pose much of a treat to them. Mostly solitary, they claim
large territories and chase away all other big predators, so ironically
creatures beneath the fang titan’s notice end up enjoying a measure of
protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most settings, such a creature would be impossible to domesticate, but in
D&amp;amp;D’s implied setting some sapients such as giants can manage it due to not
being that much smaller than them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-2&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fang Titans are Huge Natural Animals and Level 18 Elite Controllers with 348
HP. Their ground speed is 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a humongous &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that can target one or two creatures,
dealing physical damage and dazing them (save ends). They can also grab one of
the targets on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs. Reflex; recharge
4-6) that does high physical damage and knocks prone. Their &lt;strong&gt;Furious Roar&lt;/strong&gt;
works exactly like a dragon’s Frightful Presence, and when they’re bloodied they
recharge it and use it immediately as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters And Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two sample drake encounters in this entry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 3: A lizardfolk hunting party with a pair of bloodseeker drakes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: A quartet of fire giants and their pet fang titan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned during my reading of the MM/MV, I love drakes and more of them
are always welcome. For many of them, it’s also easy to “de-skin” them as
dinosaurs if you’re so inclined, but making them a distinct type of creature
also frees the authors (and you!) from having to adhere to best paleontological
practices.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/04/drakes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/04/drakes.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragon, Silver</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-silver.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons have been in the game since the days of AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition, as part
of the classic metallic dragon set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons are described by the book as “the knights-errant” of
dragonkind. They like to travel the world looking for “interesting conflicts”,
and then throwing themselves at the center of those. When not doing that, they
chill in their lairs, which are usually in cold mountain-tops or in cloud
castles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons are highly susceptible to flattery, but get angry when the people
talking to them behave in an arrogant or aggressive manner. They breathe ice,
but they prefer to mix it up in melee. They can fly, but their flight is slower
than that of most other dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this kinda make me think of the “Outrageous!” incarnation of Aquaman from
the “Batman: The Brave and The Bold” cartoon. A silver dragon patterned after
him would be a true ally of justice who travels in search of wrongs to make
right, and who is also really loud and boisterous about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can still have ambiguous or evil silver dragons without changing the written
text, though. Note that it doesn’t make any mention of which side in those
interesting conflicts a silver dragon prefers to join. So a villainous one could
be a mercenary who’s interested in chances to inflict violence and who joins
whoever pays him the most (and the villains almost always have more money in
these scenarios).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, a silver dragon will want to be where the fighting is
thickest. They’re all about beating people up in melee, and the more surrounded
they are the better their offense becomes. Their cold breath weapon isn’t their
most damaging attack, but it makes enemies vulnerable to damage from other
sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silver dragons are Solo Brutes. They have darkvision, and cold resistance that
starts at 15 and increases by 5 in each subsequent age category. Their ground
speed starts at 6, increases to 8 at Adult, and to 10 at Ancient. Their flight
speed is always equal to the ground speed, making them indeed slower than other
dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their size progression is pretty standard: starts at Large, grows to Huge at
Elder and Gargantuan at Ancient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are Level 8 with 376 HP. They have the usual Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; as basic attacks, doing Brute-level damage. &lt;strong&gt;Dragon Onslaught&lt;/strong&gt;
allows them to make a claw attack against every enemy in range in a single
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude; Recharge 5-6) does light
cold damage and makes targets vulnerable 5 to all damage (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied
Breath&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; work as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s reaction skill is &lt;strong&gt;Wing Slice&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when it’s hit by
an attack from an enemy flanking it. It makes an attack vs. AC dealing light
physical damage to both the attacker and the other enemy flanking the dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults are level 15 with 608 HP. They have all the abilities of youngsters with
some upgrades and additions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dragon Onslaught&lt;/strong&gt; adds an extra bite attack, so it’s a claw against everyone
in reach and a bite against a target of the dragon’s choice. They also gain
&lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing them to make opportunity attacks against anyone
they can reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elders-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Elders Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Level 22 with 840 HP. They’re Huge, but their melee reach remains
at 2. They have bigger numbers and all the abilities of adults, with the
following two additions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tail Slam&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. AC) does high physical damage and dazes (save
ends). It’s also an at-will action!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable&lt;/strong&gt; is a passive trait that allows the dragon to roll extra saves
against ongoing damage at the start of its turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-silver-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Silver Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancients are Level 29 with 1072 HP. It has all the abilities of an Elder, with
bigger numbers. It doesn’t gain new abilities, but its bite reach increases to
3, which benefits from Threatening Reach and also improves Dragon Onslaught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters play up the goodly tendencies of a silver dragon, pairing
it up with similarly “righteous” creatures. There’s a Level 8 encounter with a
young’un and 2 eladrin twilight incanters, and a level 17 one with an adult and
2 daeva zealots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other likely companions include dwarves, dragonborn, and angels. Mechanically,
you want monsters that can benefit from being shielded by a big brute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outrageous! I now totally want to include Arthur the Boisterous Heroic Silver
Dragon in my next game.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/02/dragon-silver.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/02/dragon-silver.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Iron Dragon</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-iron.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron Dragons were bit players in 3e, appearing in Dragon Magazine #356 seemingly
as part of an effort to make a dragon for each element in the periodic table. In
4e, they are promoted to the Monster Manual 2 alongside adamantine dragons to
replace the bronze &amp;amp; brass duo that was removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron dragons are kind of the black sheep of the metallic family, since unlike
most of their relatives they’re surly, anti-social, and underhanded. They lair
in isolated places and prefer terrain that contains plenty of hills, forests,
and other features that provide plenty of hiding spots for large predators such
as themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They still gather followers and henchthings with the promise of generous pay
and/or loot, but they see those as expendable dupes. They’ll send those
followers first to intercept any intruders, and will only join the fight
themselves if doing so looks like it will bring victory. If the hench-people are
severely outmatched, the dragon will get away and leave them to their fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have gathered, iron dragons are sneaky and prefer to attack from
ambush. They breathe lightning, and their metallic scales become tougher the
older they get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron dragons are Solo Lurkers, and have Darkvision like all other
dragons. They’re not actually very lurkery aside from a basic level of
sneakiness (Stealth training). Their abilities focus on damage mitigation with a
side order of control, all on top of the standard dragon loadout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young’uns start out Large, growing to Huge at Elder and Gargantuan at
Ancient. They have Resist Lightning 15, increasing by 5 per age category beyond
Young. Their speed starts out at 8 both in the ground and in the air, growing to
9/9 at Elder and 9/10 at Gargantuan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young iron dragons are Level 5 with 268 HP. They have a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does a mix
of lightning and physical damage, and a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does about half that in
physical damage. The usual &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to claw twice, allowing
them to spread some damage around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; does lightning damage, as described earlier, and also
pulls 3 squares on a hit. Maybe it magnetizes the dragon for a moment?
&lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; are here and work as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also &lt;strong&gt;Wing Block&lt;/strong&gt;, an interrupt with triggers when the dragon is hit
by a melee attack. This gives the dragon Resist 5 against that attack, and
allows it to make a melee attack dealing light physical damage against the
attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is Level 11 with 472 HP and all the traits of a youngster with bigger
numbers. No new abilities appear at this level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Elder Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Level 19 and have 740 HP. They have all of the adult’s abilities,
again with bigger numbers all around. Their Double Attack turns into a &lt;strong&gt;Triple
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing for three claw swipes with a single action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also gain &lt;strong&gt;Wing Defense&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action; recharge 5-6), which grants the
dragon a +2 bonus to all defenses for a turn. As long as it keep recharging,
they can keep using it every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-iron-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Iron Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancients are Level 26 with 992 HP. They have all of the elder’s abilities and
gain two new ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predator’s Response&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that triggers when the dragon is hit by a
melee or close attack. It allows the dragon to make a claw attack against the
triggering enemy and shift 2 squares. I now notice the dragon’s reach remains 2
even though it’s now Gargantuan. Either their limbs and neck are comparatively
tiny, or you should increase the reach for the Elder to 3 and the Ancient to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iron Wing Shroud&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action; recharge 6) allows them to make a close
burst 3 vs. AC attack dealing physical damage, and gain resist 15 to all damage
until the start of its next turn. While the damage resistance is active, the
dragon can’t make any attacks. I guess this represents the dragon hiding behind
its wings and catching surrounding enemies in the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shroud’s “can’t make attacks” clause is less of a disadvantage than it
seems - an ancient iron dragon can make all of its attacks for the turn and use
the Shroud ability as its last minor action. It will lose access to opportunity
attacks and Predator’s Response, but will be able to act normally when its next
turn rolls around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 7: A young iron dragon and 3 dwarf hammerers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: 1 adult iron dragon and 2 minotaur warriors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of them would follow the standard pattern I described in the Lore section,
with the lackeys being mercenaries lured by the promise of treasure, only to be
abandoned by their boss when the fight begins to go sideways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iron dragons are the ones who least fit the classic metallic dragon stereotype,
which makes sense given their origins as an obscure magazine-only 3.x
dragon. Also I guess it’s hard to make a draconic Lurker who doesn’t sound shady
as fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I like that they’re here. That shadiness is one point in favor of them as
far as their utility in a story goes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/01/dragon-iron.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/01/dragon-iron.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragon, Gold</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-gold.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons are the original metallics and have been around since the beginning
of D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons are among the most powerful children of Io, with the oldest being
among the most dangerous creatures in existence. And yet they’re among the
dragons who most enjoy the company of mortals. I guess a lot of the “scholarly
metallic dragon” stereotype comes from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their preferred terrain are plains or rolling hills, but that’s a secondary
concern. Proximity to a sapient society, or to some great source of magic, are
much more important. Gold dragons like to rule, but it seems they don’t need to
make much of a fuss about it like the other dragons. It just happens! Any
community or society located in gold dragon territory will soon find itself
being heavily influenced or ruled outright by that dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons are usually honest and fortright in their dealings, but the more
selfish ones don’t really care about the concerns of “lesser beings”. These
individuals tend to shape the societies under their influence to suit their own
long-term plans regardless of what the actual people who live there might
want. And of course, you can still find more traditionally “Good” gold dragons
out there as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons breathe fire, and as they age they gain more affinity with radiant
energy as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, we get a stat block for each significant age category of gold
dragon. They’re all Solo Controllers, and have Darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young dragons start at size Large, with 15 fire resistance, a ground speed of 8,
and a flight speed of 10 with Hover. They gain another 5 fire resistance with
each subsequent age category, and their flight speed increases to 12 at
Elder. They grow to size Huge at Elder, and Gargantuan at Ancient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young Golds are Level 9 Solo Controllers with 380 HP. Their melee reach is 2,
and their basic attacks are a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that does a mix of physical and fire
damage, and a weaker &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to claw twice in a
single action, bringing claw damage almost to parity with the bite. I guess it’s
good if they want to spread damage around rather than concentrate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an adjacent creature hits the dragon, it can hit back with a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Wing
Riposte&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1 vs. Fortitude), which pushes the impudent mortal 5 squares
and inflicts 5 ongoing fire damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Reflex; recharge 5-6) does fire
damage and weakens (save ends), or half damage on a miss. &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; work as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults are Level 17 with 652 HP. As usual they have all the attacks of a
youngster with bigger numbers. This includes the ongoing damage from the
Riposte, which is now 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also gain a new ability: &lt;strong&gt;Burning Tomb&lt;/strong&gt; (area burst 1 within 20
vs. Reflex; recharge 6) is a spell that does the same fire damage as the breath
weapon, immobilizes (save ends), and creates a zone that does 15 fire damage to
anyone who starts their turn inside and can be sustained with minor actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Elder Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Level 24 with a cool 888 HP. They have all the abilities of adults
with bigger numbers. Their Melee Reach increases to 3 due to their Huge size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is at the age where their radiance begins to have a game effect, giving
them a new ability: &lt;strong&gt;Beguiling Glow&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 8 vs. Will; enemies only;
recharge 5-6) is a minor-action attack that does no damage and pulls targets 5
squares on a hit, nicely setting them up for Burning Tomb or the breath weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also project an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Weakening Flames&lt;/strong&gt;, which forces enemies
caught inside to choose between taking 15 fire damage or being weakened for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-gold-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Gold Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancient Gold Dragons are Gargantuan Level 30 Solo Controllers with 1088 HP. This
puts them on par with the friggin’ Tarrasque both in size and danger level. The
Tarrasque has more HP, but that’s before you apply the MM2 Solo HP fixes. And
the dragon is much smarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have all the abilities of Elders with bigger numbers, including in reach,
aura size and damage, and ongoing damage from Riposte. Double Attack becomes
&lt;strong&gt;Triple Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing three claw swipes in one action. Their new
“capstone” skill is &lt;strong&gt;Ancient Radiance&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 4 vs. Fortitude; enemies
only; recharge 6) which does radiant damage and dazes for a turn. After the daze
clears, the target gains Vulnerable 10 Radiant (save ends). This is important
because the dragon’s &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; now does “fire and radiant” damage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold dragons surround themselves with allies and subjects that match their
individual dispositions. The evil ones employ beings such as evil minotaurs,
ogres and trolls as dumb disposable muscle. The good ones have a variety of
willing allies acting as guards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: a young gold dragon and 2 angels of valor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: an adult gold dragon and 3 savage minotaurs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Level-wise, these are certainly the most powerful of dragons. The Ancient is a
match for the Tarrasque and could put up a decent fight against beings such as
demon lords or other “campaign end bosses”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do have the same problem as the Tarrasque in that they lack strong
condition mitigation powers - that +5 to saves from being a solo might not be
enough to prevent stun-locking by an epic party. They also wouldn’t do so well
on their own against Demogorgon, so if you want to have a kaiju fight you might
want to use the dragon as an ally of the PCs instead of sending it in alone.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/31/dragon-gold.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/31/dragon-gold.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragon, Copper</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-copper.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are part of the classic set and have been in the game at least
since the AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition Monster Manual. Here, they are the only remaining
members of the “sorta orange-ish metal trio”, which used to feature bronze and
brass dragons as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are highly sociable creatures, but they’re also among the
greediest metallic dragons. They’re not likely to resort to outright robbery
like your typical red dragon, but they’re almost always looking for a way to
profit from their interactions with others. PCs can usually walk up to a copper
dragon and ask it for information or instruction. The dragon will be most happy
to give it to them… for a price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are quite protective of their hoards. They like to make their
lairs in rocky terrain like hilly badlands or mountains, which they can easily
patrol from the air but which restrict the mobility of land-bound intruders. If
they see the need to fight, they’ll do so by harassing their enemies with highly
mobile aerial attacks over an extended period of time. They breathe acid, and
prefer to recruit allies that can keep up with their high mobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like it that the illustrations for copper dragons give then verdigris
streaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are Unaligned, Natural Magical Beasts with the Dragon Keyword. We
get stat blocks for the usual four age categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their size starts at Large when young, and increases to Huge at Elder. They
never reach Gargantuan size, which I guess means they’re a bit smaller than the
others in general. They have trained Perception, Darkvision, and Acid Resistance
that starts at 15 when Young and increases by 5 per age category. Their speed is
quite high, starting at 8 (fly 12) and reaching 10 (fly 14) at Elder and
older. They also have Overland Flight 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-copper-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Copper Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young copper dragons are Level 6 Solo Skirmishers with 296 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;
allows them to shift 2 squares both before and after the attack, and deals a mix
of physical and acid damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; are a simple basic attack, but
&lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to claw twice and then shift 2 squares. Looks like
choosing between a bite and a double attack is a meaningful tactical decision!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s most frequent attack is likely to be a &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, where it
flies its speed and makes a melee basic attack at any point during the
movement. This does not provoke opportunity attacks from the target of the
attack. The bite is the clear best choice here, since it’s stronger and has
built-in shifts which I think would happen even in the midst of the Flyby
Attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Reflex; recharge 5-6) does acid damage
and slows (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; are also
here and work as described in earlier posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, &lt;strong&gt;Cutwing Step&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that triggers when someone moves to
a position that flanks the dragon. It’s an attack vs. AC that does light
physical damage and allows the dragon to shift 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-copper-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Copper Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adult Copper Dragons are Level 13 Solo Skirmishers with 528 HP. They have all
the abilities of a young specimen with correspondingly bigger numbers. All
attacks that allowed shifts other than the bite have the shift amount increased
to 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also add a new passive trait: &lt;strong&gt;Unfettered Wings&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to roll
saves against the Immobilized, Slowrd and Restrained conditions at the start of
their turns in addition to the normal end-of-turn rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-and-ancient-copper-dragons&quot;&gt;Elder and Ancient Copper Dragons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Elder grows to size Huge as previously mentioned, and is a Level 20 Solo
Skirmisher with 760 HP. It has bigger numbers than the Adult due to its higher
level, but its suite of abilities is otherwise identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ancient is a Level 27 Solo Skirmisher with an even 1000 HP. It has all of
the Elder’s abilities, and its &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt; upgrades to a &lt;strong&gt;Double Flyby
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it to attack two different targets during its strafing
run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounters are against all-skimmisher teams. There’s a Level 8 one
with a young copper dragon and 3 hippogriffs, and a level 14 one with an adult
and 2 dragonborn raiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper dragons are really flexible in the dramatic roles they can occupy even
when you stick to their written description. It all depends on which part of the
“sociable but greedy” stereotype you want to emphasize. I also like that most of
their illustrations in this book have their coppery hides shot through with
veins of verdigris.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/30/dragon-copper.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/30/dragon-copper.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragon, Adamantine</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dragon-adamantine.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adamantine dragons are the first metallics we’ll cover. I finally found a wiki
with publication histories for monsters, so I can say that that they first
appeared in a Monstrous Compendium for AD&amp;amp;D 2nd Edition, and in a Dragon article
for 3.x. This means they had a minor presence in the game until their first
proper Monster Manual appearance here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adamantine dragons like to lair in huge underground caverns, and can be found in
any sort of climate. They consider everyone else living in their claimed
territory to be their subjects, from whom they demand loyalty, respect, and
tribute. The flip-side of this is that adamantine dragons feel a genuine sense
of &lt;em&gt;noblesse oblige&lt;/em&gt; towards these subjects, and will protect them with all
their might.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their claws and fangs are made of their titular metal, so their attacks slice
through armor as if it wasn’t there. Their roars are powerful, and their breath
weapon is a focused sonic attack. In combat, they’re cool-headed and
tactical. If alone, they try to isolate weaker foes and focus fire on them. If
accompanied by allies, they’ll charge to the front line and attract the brunt of
enemy attacks to allow their allies more opportunities to damage the
opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, we get stat blocks representing four age categories: Young, Adult,
Elder, and Ancient. All are Natural Magical Beasts with the Dragon keyword. All
stat blocks are Unaligned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adamantine dragons start at size Large, growing to Huge at Elder and Gargantuan
at Ancient. They have trained Perception, Darkvision, and Thunder Resistance
that starts at 15 and goes up by 5 on each subsequent age category. Their ground
speed starts at 6 and rises to 8 on Adult and older. Their flight speed starts
at 8 and rises to 10 on Adult and 12 on Ancient. They also have Overland
Flight 15, which is the speed you use when calculating how much distance they
cover over extended times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-adamantine-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Adamantine Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 7 Solo Soldier with 332 HP and the traits described above. Its
basic attacks are a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which target Reflex instead
of AC because they’re adamantine. The bite is a little stronger, &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows the dragon to claw twice in a single action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Breath Weapon&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5 vs. Fortitude; recharge 5-6) does thunder
damage and knocks the targets prone on a hit. It replaces the usual “half damage
on a miss” with a much more interesting Effect: at the start of the dragon’s
next turn, it gives a thunderous roar that deals automatic thunder damage to
everyone in a close burst 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Presence&lt;/strong&gt; are here, and they work as
outlined in the intro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wing Buffet&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 2 vs. Fortitude) is a reaction that triggers when an
enemy enters or leaves an adjacent square. On a hit it deals light physical
damage and knocks prone. This is better than a standard opportunity attack
because it also triggers on a shift or other forms or movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adult-adamantine-dragon&quot;&gt;Adult Adamantine Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults are Level 14 Solo Soldiers with 564 HP. Their numbers are of course all
larger, but they are almost identical to young dragons in what they can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been a few additions: the bite now also inflicts ongoing damage (save
ends), and Double Attack is replaced by &lt;strong&gt;Draconic Fury&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows them to
make three claw attacks &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; bite a different target in a single action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elder-adamantine-dragon&quot;&gt;Elder Adamantine Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders are Level 21 Solo Soldiers with 796 HP. They have everything adults have,
with a few additions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Draconic Fury&lt;/strong&gt; gains another claw attack, for a total of four claws and
a bite. They also gain a new attack named &lt;strong&gt;Painful Resonance&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 20
vs. Fortitude; minor action; recharge 6) that inflicts ongoing thunder damage
and dazes (save ends). Since this is a minor action, it can be used in the same
turn as Draconic Fury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ancient-adamantine-dragon&quot;&gt;Ancient Adamantine Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ancients are Level 28 Solo Soldiers with 1020 HP. This puts makes them a match
for a pair of primordial colossi. They have everything elders have, plus their
melee reach increases to 4 and the area of their Breath Weapon’s follow-up roar
increases to 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also gain a new trait named &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Resilience&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives them
Resist 10 to all damage while they are bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book doesn’t even pretend you’re going to fight these solos by themselves,
though that of course is an option depending on what you want. Since adamantine
dragons place themselves in the front line, they favor allies who can benefit
from the distraction to rain ranged damage or control upon the enemy, or give
the PCs the run-around and hit their squishies. And they’re going to think of
party composition in these terms, since they’re tacticians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 15, an adult adamantine dragon and 2 banshrae
warriors.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/29/dragon-adamantine.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/29/dragon-adamantine.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dragons</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Woohoo, more dragons. The first Monster Manual (and the Vault) focused on
chromatic dragons, which are the classic draconic opponents, and now the second
one talks about the metallics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest metallic dragons were the Golds, who appeared alongside the
chromatic set in AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition and might have been around even earlier than
that. Here, we’re going to look at a slightly different set. This is an
introductory post, with the next handful of them each covering a different
“color” of dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In editions past, metallic dragons used to be various shades of Good, something
which settings like Dragonlance really leaned into. Things are a bit more
complex here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metallics still venerate Bahamut in his role as the Platinum Dragon. They’re
more likely to interact peacefully with PCs and other sapients, but they can
still be quite full of themselves and are very protective of their territory and
treasure. If they perceive someone as a threat, they won’t hesitate to crush
that someone. And just like you can have friendly chromatics, you can also have
villainous metallics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In either case they tend to have a scholarly temperament. They prefer lairs that
have some cultural or academic significance in addition to the usual
requirements of isolation and defensibility and their treasure hoards are
curated like museum collections. The typical metallic dragon loves engaging in
learned discourse, and has a keen ability to sense lies. They deal very harshly
with people who try to fool or, gods forbid, steal from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all dragons they see very few other creatures as their peers, but will
allow a group of “lessers” to gather around themselves. They tend to see these
as students and wards, instead of slaves and worshippers. A metallic dragon is
not going to set itself up as a god, but as a &lt;em&gt;university professor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry has five dragon types: Adamantine, Copper, Gold, Iron and
Silver. From what I gather, Adamantine and Iron dragons made it into the main
metallic lineup in 4e to replace bronze and brass dragons, which weren’t
distinct enough from Copper dragons at a glance. I think I agree with that
reasoning. While I’m sure these dragons have their own mechanical distinctions,
I sure can’t recall what they were just from looking at their names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual for dragons, the ones we get here are all solos, and each has several
stat blocks representing different age categories: Young, Adult, Elder and
Ancient. Young dragons only have the most basic versions of their powers, and
both improve them and gain new ones as they age. Their mechanical design is
closer to that of the first Monster Manual than to the one from the Vault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All dragons have darkvision, resistance to the same element they breathe, and
both combat and overland flight speeds. All of them get a different &lt;strong&gt;Breath
Weapon&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as the &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Breath&lt;/strong&gt; trait and the &lt;strong&gt;Frightful
Presence&lt;/strong&gt; attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bloodied Breath works as usual: when the dragon is first bloodied, its breath
weapon recharges and it uses it immediately as a free action. Frightful Presence
is a Close Burst 10 vs. Will encounter power that does no damage but stuns for a
turn and has a -2 attack penalty (save ends) as an after-effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll begin discussing the dragon types individually in the next few posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/28/dragon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/28/dragon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Djinn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djinns are inspired by the same real world Arabic folklore that inspired
efreets, and they’ve been in the game since at least BECMI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djinns are some of the most ancient sapient elementals, on par with efreets
(which we saw in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/11/efreet.html&quot;&gt;first Monster Manual/Vault Let’s Read&lt;/a&gt;). They’re
aspected to Air, and in the book’s own words, are “Ingenious Engineers of the
Fabulous”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in the day, the djinn built entire civilizations in the Elemental
Chaos. Theirs were shining palaces filled with treasure beyond mortal
comprehension, and great gleaming cities built on mobile floating
platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Dawn War came, the djinns chose to side with the primordials, which I
suppose they saw as the pragmatic choice. After all, their own empire was
outside the world, and the stronger primordials looked like they had a better
chance of winning. In the end, though, they chose wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gods scattered the djinns as punishment for their deeds in the war, and
imprisoned many of them in objects such as rings, lamps, or other artifacts. The
ones that remained free had their powers severely reduced. Over the ages a lot
of those artifacts and a lot of djinn relics made their way to other planes and
to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, it’s totally possible for a PC to find the proverbial magic lamp. It’s
up to the GM whether the magic that binds the djinn inside forces it to serve
the bearer, though. If it does, then these relics are super-powerful! Even if
the djinn can’t grant wishes like in the stories, it’s still an epic-level
creature full of magic powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The djinns who remained free, and those who freed themselves over the ages,
mostly busy themselves with roaming the planes looking for the remains of their
ancient civilization, with the goal of rebuilding it. I would guess they had
some success in that, but that it’s still nowhere up to its former heights of
glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The djinns presented here are all Unaligned, which implies that as a people they
are mostly interested in picking up the pieces of their civilization than in
going a-conquering or enslaving others. They can still get into conflict with
PCs who (knowingly or not) keep those pieces from returning to their original
owners. Hold on to that lamp for too long and its inhabitant’s friends will show
up at your door with some very pointed questions. I can’t say they’d be wrong to
do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djinns are Large Elemental Humanoids with the Air keyword. They have Blindsight
10, an immunity to disease and poison, Resist 15 Thunder, a ground speed of 6
and a flight speed of 8. The least intelligent djinn in this entry nas an Int of
19, so the ingenious engineers are also geniuses. Their level range covers the
early-to-mid Epic tier, making them only slightly weaker than efreets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most djinn powers have an air or storm theme, but they vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;djinn-thunderer&quot;&gt;Djinn Thunderer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-djinn-thunderer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thunderers are Level 20 Artillery with 146 HP and all djinn traits. They wield
jeweled scepters and strong air magic in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Scepter&lt;/strong&gt; mostly acts as an implement, but can be used as a Reach 2 basic
melee attack in a pinch. Their main ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Thunderburst&lt;/strong&gt; (area
burst 2 within 20 vs. Fortitude), which does thunder damage and dazes for a
turn. Once per encounter they can use &lt;strong&gt;Imperious Thunder&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets
Reflex and which has the same area and damage but instead of dazing causes 10
ongoing thunder damage (save ends) &lt;em&gt;even when it misses&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thunderer can avoid getting boxed in with &lt;strong&gt;Zephyr Step&lt;/strong&gt; (minor; recharge
6), which allows it to teleport 20 squares. If it takes damage from a critical
hit, it will respond with &lt;strong&gt;Rage of Storms&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs. Reflex; free
action, encounter). This does high thunder damage, pushes hit targets 5 squares,
and gives the djinn 1 action point as an effect, which it can use normally later
on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;djinn-windbow&quot;&gt;Djinn Windbow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-djinn-windbow.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windbows are Level 22 Skirmishers with 204 HP and all standard djinn
traits. They wield bows that fire arrows made out of wind, and this might lead
PCs to think they’re artillery. However, they’re equally good at melee and
ranged combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic ranged attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Windbow&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 10/20), and their basic
melee attack the &lt;strong&gt;Slash of Thunder&lt;/strong&gt;. Both do about the same amount of damage,
which is thunder for the Slash and physical for the bow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The djinn can cause one of their arrows to turn into a &lt;strong&gt;Brutal Zephyr&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged
30 vs. Reflex), which does thunder damage and is a bit stronger than the usual
attack. If this misses, the windbow gets to choose a different target within 10
squares of the original one and re-roll the attack against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If damaged by a critical hit they can use &lt;strong&gt;Blowback&lt;/strong&gt;, which works exactly like
the Thunderer’s Rage of Storms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;djinn-stormsword&quot;&gt;Djinn Stormsword&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-djinn-stormsword.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stormswords fight with scimitars and train to form whirlwinds that pull enemies
towards their blades. They’re Level 24 Soldiers with 222 HP and all standard
djinn traits, plus Resist 15 Lightning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Scimitars&lt;/strong&gt; are Reach 2, high-crit weapons that mark for a turn on a
hit. Their printed critical damage is 9d10+33, and it would be even higher with
a math fix. They can also use a technique named &lt;strong&gt;Whirlwind Dervish&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2
vs. AC; encounter) which does heavy thunder and lightning damage and recharges
when they’re critically hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stormswords can drag targets into range with &lt;strong&gt;Come To Me&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 5
vs. Fortitude; minor action), which does no damage but pulls the targets 5
squares. They can sometimes intensify that into a &lt;strong&gt;Spinning Vortex&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 5
vs. Reflex; recharge 6), which does heavy cold and thunder damage, and
immobilizes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;djinn-skylord&quot;&gt;Djinn Skylord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-djinn-skylord.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skylords are djinn spell-casters, specializing in sky- and weather-themed
magic. They’re Level 25 Controllers with the Leader keyword and 236 HP along
with all standard djinn traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main weapon/implement is the &lt;strong&gt;Storm Staff&lt;/strong&gt; (reach 2 vs. AC), which does
physical damage and allows the djinn to shift 2 squares or make an extra
recharge roll for &lt;strong&gt;Storm Shout&lt;/strong&gt;. This, in turn, is a Close Blast 5 vs. Will
that does heavy thunder damage, pushes 3 squares, and knocks prone. It recharges
on a 5-6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skylord’s main ranged attack is &lt;strong&gt;Mystic Hail&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20 vs. Will), which
does psychic damage and makes the target grant combat advantage to the
djinn. This lasts until the target spends a standard action clearing their head,
which is a heavier cost than having to roll a save. This works as a nice setup
for &lt;strong&gt;Sandstorm&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 5 vs. Will), which does heavy physical damage and
creates a zone. Allies inside the zone gain concealment, and enemies starting
their turns inside are dazed for a turn. This can be sustained with a minor
action. And finally, the djinn can also use a minor action (1/round) to use
&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Command&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10), which always hits, does no damage, and slides
the target 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djinns are said to mostly hang out with their own kind, and the two sample
encounters (level 22 and 26) bear this out. They’re assorted djinn parties,
likely journeying after relics of their old empire. The first one has a couple
of rimefire griffon pets, the second has 2 storm gorgons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Djinns are cool, and I like that they’re presented as not necessarily
hostile. Unlike in previous edition they’re not in an eternal war against the
efreets, though I imagine they don’t often have friendly interactions all that
often either. It might also be interesting to take a page from Middle Eastern
folklore here and say that many djinn in the present are devout worshippers of
the gods.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/21/djinn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/21/djinn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Direguard</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-direguard.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard of direguards before, but some quick googling tells me they
first appeared in the Forgotten Realms Campaign Setting for AD&amp;amp;D 2nd Edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A direguard is a skeletal undead created by a specific ritual often known by
liches and death knights. The ritual requires willing subjects, who retain their
minds, combat skills, and powers. This comes at a price, however: in the book’s
own words, they must “meet a quota of killing”, or they’ll be destroyed. I don’t
know if this is a one time thing or if it’s more like “kill X people every
month”. And of course they’re bound to the will of their creator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their FR lore is all tangled up with the whole Bane/Cyric situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direguards are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Undead keyword. They have
darkvision and truesight 10, and are immune to disease and poison. The rest of
their traits varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direguard-deathbringer&quot;&gt;Direguard Deathbringer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deathbringers are Level 8 Elite Artillery with the Leader keyword and 134
HP. They have a ground speed of 7 and project a &lt;strong&gt;Command Aura&lt;/strong&gt; (4) that grants
a +2 attack bonus to all allies inside. They can also issue a &lt;strong&gt;Vile Command&lt;/strong&gt;
(close blast 3; recharge 5-6) that allows all affected allies to shift 2 squares
and make a basic attack as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fire &lt;strong&gt;Force Blasts&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 15 vs. Reflex) that do force damage and push
the target 3 squares. On a miss, they do no damage but slow the target for a
turn. &lt;strong&gt;Frightful Force&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4-6) allows them to fire three such blasts
against different targets in a single action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If forced into melee, the deathbringer’s &lt;strong&gt;Blazing Bone Claws&lt;/strong&gt; do force damage
as well. And when they’re first bloodied, they summon some &lt;strong&gt;Force Armor&lt;/strong&gt;
around themselves that grants a +4 bonus to AC and Reflex until they’re hit by
an attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d say deathbringers are at home just behind the front line, or further back
along with a cluster of artillery enemies with ranged basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direguard-assassin&quot;&gt;Direguard Assassin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assassins are Level 11 Skirmishers with 111 HP. They’re made of shadow as much
as they are made of bone, and fight with swords made of force magic. Their
ground speed is 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That &lt;strong&gt;Force Blade&lt;/strong&gt; deals force damage, as expected, and once per encounter
they can fling &lt;strong&gt;Dire Blades&lt;/strong&gt; to do the same amount of damage in a Close
Burst 1. &lt;strong&gt;Mobile Assault&lt;/strong&gt; gives them a +2 attack bonus if they move at least 4
squares before attacking, and &lt;strong&gt;Mist Walk&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to shift 2 squares and
gain Insubstantial and Phasing for a turn when missed by a melee attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no sample encounters here! I guess they could only spare one page for
direguards, so there was no room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t care for the FR bits of their lore, but Deathbringers work nicely as
commanders of mindless undead, and Assassins are good elite troops for someone
like a skull lord to order around.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/21/direguard.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/21/direguard.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Dimensional Marauder</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-dimensional-marauder.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the other entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dimensional marauders are a 3.x creation. I definitely remember that image,
though I don’t remember if they had a different name back then. It was probably
something like “Ethereal Marauder”, but 4e doesn’t have an ethereal plane
anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are plane-hopping predators who travel the planes and the world
in search of easy prey. And that’s all the book has to say about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s allow ourselves to speculate a bit. Dimensional marauders “travel the
planes”, and I guess that means they don’t have a fixed territory and follow
sources of food instead. If you look at their stat block you’ll see their level
is a lot lower than that of almost any creature they’re likely to find in the
planes. This means they’re &lt;em&gt;opportunistic&lt;/em&gt;, looking for creatures that have
already been weakened by some other hazard or who are busy fighting someone
else. Then they jump in and take a bite. If the meal is still kicking, they
might run away, otherwise they stay and finish it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary pressure has given then a rudimentary sapience, which aids them in
evaluating the strength of potential prey. It also often leads marauders to the
conclusion that the easiest prey can be found in the world, near population
centers filled with juicy non-combatants whom they might even be able to beat in
a fair fight. Not that they’ll fight fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dimensional Marauders are Medium Aberrant Magical Beasts, and Level 4 Lurkers
with 45 HP. They have low-light vision, a ground speed of 7 and a teleport speed
of 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; with that cool triangular jaw. They can also
use their standard action to assume a &lt;strong&gt;Planephase Form&lt;/strong&gt;, partially shifting to
some other plane. This gives them the Insubstantial and Phasing qualities for a
turn, or until they miss with an attack. They can also sustain this with a minor
action, but it ends immediately when they take psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in this state, the marauder can use a &lt;strong&gt;Reality Warp&lt;/strong&gt; attack (melee 1
vs. Reflex), which does light physical damage, teleports the target 3 squares,
and teleports the marauder itself to a square adjacent to the target. It will
use this to isolate its chosen victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the marauder is hit by a melee attack, it can use &lt;strong&gt;Planar Evasion&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 4-6) as a reaction, teleporting 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see them mostly staying in planephase form and using Reality Warp to isolate a
PC, which they’ll begin biting for more damage once they’re far away. The book
tactics start them out entirely physical and has them planephase after hit for
the first time in combat, but there’s no reason for them not to planephase
before the fight even starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, a group of sapients will convince a marauder to work with
them. Mostly, though, they just opportunistically jump into ongoing fights to
take a bite out of whoever seems weakest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter could represent either of these situations. It’s level 3,
with 2 marauders, 2 ettercap fang guards, and 1 gnome arcanist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the illustration is very cool and memorable, but I only found the
creature itself interesting because of all the aprocryphal lore I came up with
in this post. Mechanically, I almost think it would work better as a Controller,
since its abilities are more about knocking PCs out of position than dealing
increased damage. If you give it some bonus sneak attack damage, it does work as
a Lurker.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/21/dimensional-marauder.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/07/21/dimensional-marauder.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
