<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 03:22:57 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 03:22:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Slaughterstone Construct</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think Slaughterstone Constructs first appeared on the D&amp;amp;D Miniatures game in
late 3e. Their naming style marks them as a construct created after the
“(Material) Golem” namespace had been mostly exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach to an underground dwarf fortress usually consists of a number of
narrow tunnels, and that’s where most of the fighting happens when these places
are attacked. Tunnel fighting is a nasty affair, particularly when it’s two
large armies going at it. No place to run, no place to hide. Each inch of ground
is bought with lives, and when you advance you step on the bodies of foe and
friend alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaughterstone Constructs are the dwarven answer to this problem. They’re
defensive siege engines built for the singular purpose of making sure the only
ones who die are the invaders. Their intended usage is that you set them loose
on a tunel and watch them run through it while turning everyone inside into
chunky salsa. Their extreme toughness and strength means not many armies can
stand up to them even in a more open field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a proper slaughterstone construct is quite difficult. To sculpt the
body, you need a solid block of stone upon which the blood of a hero has been
shed. Even if you have that stone, only the very best dwarf artificers can turn
it into a construct. You’ll only find these things defending the largest and
wealthiest dwarven kingdoms, or other places that have good relationships with
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the blood requirement doesn’t mean you need to &lt;em&gt;sacrifice&lt;/em&gt; a hero on
the stone block. You could cut the stone from a cave or tunnel where that hero
has fought. Alternatively, if your GM likes this sort of technically correct
solution you could get yourself a brand new stone block and ask a certified war
hero to prick their finger and let a drop of blood fall on it. Neither of these
methods is easy (heroes don’t grow on trees!) but they’re far more ethical than
sapient sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have neither a master artisan nor a source of heroic blood but you still
want your blender tank, you can pay a middling craftsdwarf for a knockoff that’s
less reliable but still pretty strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three varieties of slaughterstone constructs here. Two “genuine” models
and a knockoff. All of them are Large Natural Animates with the Construct
keyword. They have darkvision, a ground speed of 6, and the ability to squeeze
into Medium passages without any penalties and without granting combat
advantage. They’re immune to poison, disease, and sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Int is 1, the worst possible score, but you don’t need more than that when
your only two functions are “walk forward” and “kill”. They probably respond to
commands of equivalent complexity like “stop killing” and “go back to your
garage”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slaughterstone-eviscerator&quot;&gt;Slaughterstone Eviscerator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-slaughterstone-eviscerator.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eviscerators are armed with a large number of whirling scythe blades, and look
a bit like super-edgy stone mantids. They’re Level 18 Brutes with 212 HP. The
blades never stop moving, and to model that they have a &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Blades&lt;/strong&gt; aura
(2) that deals 10 damage to anyone caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As weapons, those blades are are Reach 2 and have the High Crit property. Their
basic attack deals heavy damage to a single target, and they can also be used in
a &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Bladestorm&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) that hits everyone in a Close Burst 2
for average damage. This makes them as dangerous in the open as in a tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slaughterstone-hammerer&quot;&gt;Slaughterstone Hammerer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-slaughterstone-hammerer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are more robust than eviscerators and mount stone hammers instead of
blades. Once they reach you, it’s really hard to get away from them. Hammerers
are Level 25 Soldiers with 233 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They project a &lt;strong&gt;Thunder Step&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that slows those caught inside. The
hammers can be used in two different attacks: a basic &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
average damage and knocks prone, and a &lt;strong&gt;Hammerstrike&lt;/strong&gt; that deals the same
damage and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the hammerer’s skills mark enemies, but if you use them properly enemies
will have no option but to attack the hammerer anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;slaughterstone-slicer&quot;&gt;Slaughterstone Slicer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our “knockoff”, described as a less powerful version of a genuine
eviscerator. It’s a Level 11 Elite Brute with 276 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slicers have pretty much the same attacks and traits as eviscerators, with
smaller numbers due to the level difference. Their Bladestorm is supposed to be
an encounter power that recharges when the slicer is first bloodied, despite the
“at-will” tag on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also have a tendency to malfunction, becoming dazed for a turn after they
either deal or take a critical hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth Edition’s combat rules make these constructs even more dangerous than the
lore indicates. Both the lore and the rules say a construct “plugs” a tunnel and
prevents enemies from passing through. The rules also say that allies may freely
move and attack through each others’ spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means slaughterstone constructs pair really well with artillery monsters,
and with controllers that have good ranged attacks. They’re also pretty good
with skirmishers who can dart forward, attack, and move behind the construct
again. Even if they can’t do all that in the same turn, their exposure to the
PCs is still reduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our example encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 11: 1 duergar blasphemer, 2 duergar fleshtearers, 1 slaughterstone
slicers. Looks like it’s not just dwarves who build these.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 18: 2 Eldritch Giants, 1 Nothic Mindblight, 2 Slaughterstone
Eviscerators. Maybe they conquered a dwarf fortress and stole the constructs?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 25: 1 Beholder Eye of Chaos, 1 Oni Thunderer, 3 Slaughterstone
Hammerers. This is the “strong artillery”, “mobile skirmisher” setup I
mentioned, in its epic incarnation. You think you’re safe because the corridor
is 6 squares wide, and then you see three constructs side by side blocking all
of it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/16/slaughterstone-construct.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/16/slaughterstone-construct.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Slaad</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaads already made their 4e debut in the first Monster Manual, and you can
check out the post I wrote on them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/12/23/slaad.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This MM2 entry brings us a
lower-level, less-popular slaad type and an alternate mechanic for the horrific
slaad spawning cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flux-slaad&quot;&gt;Flux Slaad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-slaad-flux.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flux slaads seem to be the runts of the slaad family. They’re weaker and
stupider than their relatives, they can’t spawn, and their chaotic mutations are
at best a mixed blessing. Still, being weaker actually means they might have an
easier time slipping through a dimensional crack into the world, which they love
because it allows them to lord it over creatures even weaker than them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flux slaads who slip into the world often end up conquering bullywug tribes and
setting themselves up as their god-kings. Finding one of these on the throne
instead of the usual “slightly stronger frog-dude” can be an interesting
experience for cocky PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flux Slaads are Medium Elemental Humanoids, and Level 9 Skirmishers with 98
HP. They have low-light vision, a ground speed of 7, and a teleport speed
of 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;. They can use those in a &lt;strong&gt;Flux Rage&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver
that allows them to shift 2 squares and attack everyone they pass by during this
movement. This recharges when they’re first bloodied. When they take damage from
an attack, they can shift 1 square as a reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing special so far, but now we come to the part that gives these slaads
their names. &lt;strong&gt;Slaad Vulnerability Shift&lt;/strong&gt; should really have a name that
includes the word “flux” in it. This trait makes the slaad start out with random
vulnerability determined by a d6 roll: (1) cold, (2) fire, (3) lightning, (4)
necrotic, (5) psychic, (6) thunder. The slaad has Vulnerability 10 to that
damage type, but Resistance 5 to all the other table entries. Every time the
slaad takes damage from its current weakness, you roll the die again and
determine a new weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slaad-spawn&quot;&gt;Slaad Spawn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-slaad-spawner.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustration by Wayne England. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most slaads reproduce by infecting victims with a disease called Chaos Phage,
which causes slad tadpoles to gestate within the victim’s flesh. The tadpole
grows and eventually erupts from its host, running away to mature
elsewhere. This was covered in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/12/23/slaad.html&quot;&gt;MM entry&lt;/a&gt; for Slaads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of them are instead infected with a mutant strain of chaos phage, which
produces embryos in their &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; flesh. These slaads are covered in gross giant
boils that pop when they’re wounded, spawning miniature versions of
themselves. These spawn are both almost mindless and extremely aggressive, so
they often get used as weapons by their “parents”. Should they survive the
circumstances of their birth, the spawn develop quickly and begin exhibiting
powers similar to those of an adult within days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-numbers-1&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spawn are Small Elemental Humanoids, and Level 17 Minion Skirmishers. They have
low-light vision, a running speed of 5, and a teleport speed of 3. They attack
with &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; and can also pounce using a &lt;strong&gt;Chaotic Slam&lt;/strong&gt;. On a hit, they
damage and knock down the target. On a miss, they explode, dealing a bit of
damage in a Close Burst 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also get stats for an elite template named &lt;strong&gt;Slaad Spawner&lt;/strong&gt;, which can be
applied to any Large-sized regular slaad. This is turns the slaad into an elite
monster, and adds a &lt;strong&gt;Spawn Slaad&lt;/strong&gt; reaction power that creates a new slaad
spawn whenever the spawner is hit by an attack. The new spawn appears adjacent
to the spawner, and acts right after the spawner’s action. The template is
unusual in that it doesn’t add additional HP to the regular monster. It does
bring a new minion into play every round, so maybe they thought this was enough
to make up for their lower HP. The spawner is worth double the experience of the
original slaad, but the spawned minions aren’t worth any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flux slaad is kinda meh aside from its “weakness roulette” mechanic. The
roulette is interesting, but your party needs a lot of damage types (or a lot of
lucky d6 rolls) to keep it spinning. Otherwise it’s going to stop on a type they
can’t use, which means the slaad becomes resistant to the types they can. At
least you can always beat it up using physical damage, which means martial types
can end up being more effective against it than the casters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you could build a “puzzle boss” that had the same mechanic, plus some
way for the party to influence the result of the d6 roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaad spawn and the Spawner template bring another flavor of body horror to a
slaad fight. Since it seems spawn mature even faster than tadpoles, a spawner
presents an even nastier apocalyptic scenario than a normal slaad. It also
presents the GM with an excuse to throw lots of de-leveled slaads against a
heroic tier party, since those could be “immature” slaads that have grown past
the spawn stage but not developer all the way yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our two sample encounters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: A death shard, 3 flux slaads, and 2 slaad tadpoles. Likely brought to
the world by a small Elemental or Abyssal rift.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 17: 2 blue slaads, 1 green slaad, 8 slaad spawn. The blues and green are
likely minding their little siblings and doing a typical slaad job of it. Note
that the spawn are worth XP in this encounter, since they’re not “produced” by
an on-site spawner.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/05/slaad.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/01/05/slaad.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Skeleton</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-skeleton.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Illustration by Adam Gilespie. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual already included &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/12/13/skeleton.html&quot;&gt;plenty of skeletons&lt;/a&gt;, so this time
we just get a couple more of them. The basic lore remains the same and you can
see it in the link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonecrusher-skeleton&quot;&gt;Bonecrusher Skeleton&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Large-sized skeleton that used to belong to an ogre, minotaur, oni, or similar
creature. Not having to haul all that flesh around makes it surprisingly fast
for its size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Large Natural Animate with the Undead keyword, and a Level 7 Soldier
with 80 HP. It has all usual skeleton traits: darkvision, immunity to disease
and poison, resist 10 necrotic, vulnerable 5 radiant. It runs at speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skeleton wields a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;greatclub&lt;/strong&gt;, and it can use it to perform a
&lt;strong&gt;Crushing Blow&lt;/strong&gt; (reach 2; recharge 6+) that does more damage and knocks the
target prone. Its superb agility is expressed as &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach 2&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;skeletal-steed&quot;&gt;Skeletal Steed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A horse skeleton that can act as a fearless and tireless mount, proving that
mundane horses truly suck in 4e. Even a dead horse is better mount than a live
one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skeletal horses are Level 3 Skirmishers with 47 HP, darkvision, and immunity to
disease and poison. They don’t have resistance to necrotic damage or
vulnerability to radiant damage. Their ground speed of 8 and their fearless,
untiring nature make them highly desired as mounts by people who don’t mind the
whole skeleton thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If forced to fight the skeletal steed uses &lt;strong&gt;kicks&lt;/strong&gt; like a normal horse, and
they can also perform them as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Mobile Melee Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. You know the
drill on this one: the steed moves its speed, makes an attack at any point along
the way, and doesn’t draw opportunity attacks. It can also emit a &lt;strong&gt;Death
Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; (fear; close burst 3; recharge 5+) that does no damage and inflicts a
-2 attack penalty (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When used as a mount, the steed allows its rider to join in on the Mobile Melee
Attack. Either the rider makes a basic attack while still allowing the steed to
kick, or the steed gives up its attack to allow the rider to use a non-basic
power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new skeleton types rise in much the same way as the other ones. Most often
it’s because a necromancer intentionally animates them, but sometimes a freak
accident with necrotic energy can cause them to rise up as well. In such cases,
skeletal steeds tend to rise along with their former riders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two sample encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 5: 1 deathlock wight and 2 standard wights riding skeletal
steeds. Ancient horsemen riding again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: 1 orc eye of Gruumsh plus a zombie hulk and three bonecrusher
skeletons. Orc necromancer and his undead ogres.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/23/skeleton.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/23/skeleton.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Shark</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-shark.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustration by Jim Nelson. Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharks are are real-world animals, and this Monster Manual 2 entry is their
debut on D&amp;amp;D Fourth Edition. The &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/11/11/sahuagin.html&quot;&gt;Sahuagin&lt;/a&gt; entry from the first Monster
Manual mentioned them a lot but that book didn’t have shark stats. The Monster
Vault did have them, and we already looked at its take on sharks in the post
linked above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many species of real-world sharks, with very varied looks and
behavior. Rather than worry about any of that, the Monster Manual 2 gives us a
fantastic species based on our worst fears about sharks. Witness the horrible
might of the Fleshtearer Shark, the bullete of the sea!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleshtearer sharks seem to be kinda modeled on the shark from Jaws. They’re big,
they’re stupid, they’ll try to eat anything they can bite, and that can include
boats. These sharks can thrive anywhere, I do mean anywhere: not only can you
find them in oceans of any temperature, they sometimes live in rivers and lakes
and even swim in the Underdark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleshtearers can live for hundreds of years and never stop growing, which can
make those subterranean sharks even larger and stronger than the typical
specimen presented in this entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sahuagin and kuo-toa usually steer clear of fleshtearer sharks because they’re
too dangerous to tame, but sometimes a heroic trainer among them will manage the
feat. In this case, the “tame” flesh-tearer is used in raids against large
ships, eating anyone who falls overboard and biting holes in the hull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleshtearer sharks are Large Natural Beasts with the Aquatic keyword. They’re
Level 10 Brutes with 128 HP and low-light vision. They swim at speed 8, but can
only flop around at speed 1 on land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aquatic keyword gives the shark a +2 attack bonus against non-aquatic
opponents when both are in water, and it also has a custom &lt;strong&gt;Waterborne&lt;/strong&gt; trait
that stacks a +2 damage bonus on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is of course a &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt;, but they also have several special
maneuvers. &lt;strong&gt;Lockjaw Charge&lt;/strong&gt; is a charge attack that also grabs the
target. Grabbed targets are vulnerable to the shark’s &lt;strong&gt;shredding teeth&lt;/strong&gt;, which
always hit and deal heavy damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shark has no special ability to pull a grabbed victim along when it moves,
so it must use the standard rules for doing that (opposed Strength tests). It
can also choose to stay in place while it chews into the victim with Shredding
Teeth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fleshtearer shark will lurk out of detection range until it picks a target
(the tastiest-looking PC). It will then use Lockjaw charge on them, relying on
its toughness to weather any opportunity attacks. It will probably release the
grab and swim away for another pass rather than getting pinned down by the other
PCs, but it’s too obstinate to run and usually fights to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shark’s bloodlust often gets in the way of those tactics, which is
represented by a trait named &lt;strong&gt;Feeding Frenzy&lt;/strong&gt;. When the shark starts its turn
within 5 squares of a bloodied creature, it must make a bite attack against a
creature adjacent to itself, which will also make it release a grabbed victim if
it has one. “Creature” here means both allies and enemies can trigger the effect
and be valid targets for the bite attack. Even a “tame” shark is dangerous to
its allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a movie shark, doing movie shark things. If you’re adventuring on or under
water, you might run into it, otherwise it won’t usually impact your adventuring
life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make them Huge and level them up to represent Underdark sharks, in which
case they might make good thralls for Aboleths and for Mind Flayers who want to
fight Aboleths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get one sample encounter here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Level 10: 2 fleshtearer sharks, 1 sahuagin baron, 2 sahuagin priests. This is
likely the “command squad” for a bigger raid against a large ship or coastal
village. They’d stay a bit further away from the front lines, and engaging
them might be necessary to end the raid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/17/shark.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/17/shark.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Shadar-kai</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-shadar-kai.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already saw the basic lore of shadar-kai back in [Let’s Read the  Monster
Manual][2], and the Monster Manual 2 brings a few more stat blocks for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where they add the lore about Shadar-kai seeking extreme sensations to
stave off the soul-draining malaise of the Shadowfell. As I said in the original
post, I prefer to ignore this bit. If you want to add it in, the book also
mentions that offers of novel and/or intense experiences tend to be
well-received when one negotiates with shadar-kai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book we get paragon-tier Shadar-kai, which one can usually meet in the
Shadowfell proper. They retain the MM1 signature traits (low-light vision and
the Shadow Jaunt ability), and get a new gimmick in the form of a new status
effect they can inflict: &lt;em&gt;shrouded in gloom&lt;/em&gt;. A victim who is shrouded in gloom
takes a -2 penalty to attacks and gains only half the benefit from healing
effects. This seems to always be a “save ends” condition. Their ground speed is
7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the new stat blocks presented here were named by someone who decided
that simple descriptive names like the “Warrior” and “Witch” of the first book
weren’t nearly goth enough. Let’s check them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shadar-kai-blacksoul&quot;&gt;Shadar-kai Blacksoul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blacksouls are spellcasters specializing in harmful shadow-based magic. They’re
level 14 Controllers with 138 HP, and all their attacks are spells. &lt;strong&gt;Corrupting
Blackfire&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic melee attack that deals fire and necrotic damage;
&lt;strong&gt;Shadowbolt&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic ranged attack that deals necrotic damage; and
&lt;strong&gt;Shadowburst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) deals necrotic damage over a wide area. All three
also shroud the target in gloom on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blacksoul’s ultimate attack is &lt;strong&gt;Corrupt Soul&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Will and
dominates (save ends). It can only target victims who are shrouded in gloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shadar-kai-dawnkiller&quot;&gt;Shadar-kai Dawnkiller&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This absurd edgelord is a Level 14 Lurker with 106 HP. They carry a pair of
&lt;strong&gt;kukris&lt;/strong&gt; whose strikes shroud the target in gloom and can also be used to
perform a &lt;strong&gt;shade strike&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage and blinds instead. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Shadows of the Raven Queen&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them bonus damage against targets who
can’t see them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dawnkillers likely alternate shade strikes and basic attacks, focusing on a
single PC. They pair really well with the spellcasters from this entry,
providing an extra source of “shrouded in gloom” so their buddies can use their
ultimate attacks earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shadar-kai-gloom-lord&quot;&gt;Shadar-kai Gloom Lord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gloom Lords are spellcasters of the same tradition as blacksouls, with a
slightly different spell selection. They’re Level 14 Artillery with 108 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attacks are the same, and their special technique is named
&lt;strong&gt;Shadowcage&lt;/strong&gt;. This is an at-will ranged attack that targets the Reflex of a
creature shrouded in gloom. It deals necrotic damage, restrains the target, and
prevents it from moving more than 2 squares away from its original position
until it passes a save to clear all of these effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sharar-kai-painbearer&quot;&gt;Sharar-kai Painbearer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re not in pain, they bring the pain to you. Painbearers are Level 15
Skirmishers with the Leader keyword and 144 hP. They wear leather and wield
spiked chains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is named &lt;strong&gt;shadow chain&lt;/strong&gt;, which does damage and shrouds in
gloom as usual. They can also perform a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Dance&lt;/strong&gt; that allows them to
shift their speed and make three shadow chain attacks against different targets
along the way. Each attack after the first deals an extra 2d6 damage for every
previous attack that hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the Skirmisher part. The Leader part comes from two other abilities. The
first is a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Weft&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that allows shadar-kai allies within to
shift 1 square after they hit with a melee attack. The second is &lt;strong&gt;Shadow
Boon&lt;/strong&gt;, a reaction that allows an ally within 10 squares to re-roll an attack
they just missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m surprised we didn’t get a stat block that was literally named Shadar-kai
Edgelord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical shadar-kai combat encounters will be either agains the villainous sort
that consorts with undead, or the morally ambigious yet antagonistic sort that
swears fealty to the Raven Queen. A more complex encounter might find the PCs
aiding the latter against the former. Either sort of shadar-kai might be riding
nightmares, because of course they would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two sample encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: two dawnkillers and a painbearer accompanied by a
bodak. Undead-loving villains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 14: A blacksoul, 2 gloom lords and 2 painbearers. A team where every
member is a brooding loner, Kamen Rider-style.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/17/shadar-kai.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/17/shadar-kai.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Retriever</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrievers first appeared in the Fiend Folio for AD&amp;amp;D 1st Edition. They make
their 4e debut here in the Monster Manual 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-retriever.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrievers are powerful constructs shaped like giant spiders, built by the
primordials themselves during the Dawn War to carry out kidnappings, thefts, and
assassinations. They’re not smart enough to do anything outside their intended
function, but when it comes to their mission there’s no one better in existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once given a target, a retriever can track it from anywhere in the multiverse
and teleport to its location instantly. If they’re retrieving, they can grab the
target and skedaddle. If they’re assassinating, they can count on their huge
size, bladed legs, and multi-directional eye rays to flatten almost any
opposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primordials can really build things to last when they care to. A significant
number of retrievers survived the War and is still active today, which is very
bad news for the world because some demons have learned how to command
them. Back in the days of AD&amp;amp;D, retrievers were linked to Demogorgon in
particular, but now they could be found in the service of any demon lord or
other entity of similar power. Perhaps some of them still act at the behest of a
primordial, and Lolth is spidery enough to want a bunch of them working for
her. Make any of them angry enough and a few retrievers might show up at your
home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrievers are Huge Elemental Animates, but though they are described as
constructs they lack the Construct keyword. They’re Level 27 Soldiers with 248
HP, immunity to Charm and Fear, and Resist 5 to all damage. They run at speed 8,
but have no climb speed despite looking like spiders. Their special senses
include darkvision and truesight 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A retriever has Reach 3 and two basic attacks: a standard &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; strike and
&lt;strong&gt;Retrieve&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Fortitude, deals claw damage and grabs the
target. A retriever can move its grabbed victim without needing to make Strength
tests, so they can easily “grab and go”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also has access to four different &lt;strong&gt;eye rays&lt;/strong&gt;, each pairing a type of
elemental damage with a different rider: acid and blindness, cold and
immobilization, fire and ongoing damage, thunder and stun. The creature can fire
all four in the same action, but must target a different creature with each. At
the start of each turn, a random ray recharges. This means a second full blast
takes a while, but it can fire a partial one if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the retriever is hard-pressed it can take an action to engage in
&lt;strong&gt;Self-Repair&lt;/strong&gt;, recovering 20 HP and gaining a +4 bonus to AC for a turn. This
recharges once it’s first bloodied. Might be a good thing to do when it manages
to run away with its victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally we have the power that makes it truly fearsome: &lt;strong&gt;Unerring
Accuracy&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it to sense the approximate location of its target and
teleport to within 10 squares of it &lt;em&gt;from anywhere in the
multiverse&lt;/em&gt;. Demogorgon is pissed at you, gives your name to a retriever in his
throne room and bam, giant spider mech bursting through your bedroom wall. This
is a daily power, so I guess a retriever on a kidnapping mission needs at least
a few hours before it can return to its master. That’s your window to rescue
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The order doesn’t even have to be very specific. “Bring me an elf” will allow it
to teleport to the location of the nearest elf, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being an epic spider mech, the retriever is a Regular, which means it
will usually be found as part of a group. This can mean “multiple retrievers”,
or it can mean other epic assassin-types who hitch a ride on the teleport. Maybe
they’re riding a howdah atop the spider body - it’d be the perfect place for
some epic artillery or controller monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, they might be found under the command of a less sophisticated
type of demon who prefers to use them as bodyguards and extra muscle in a more
straightforward combat scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter could belong to either type: a marilith with an entourage
composed of an abyssal rotfiend and 2 retrievers (level 26).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/retriever.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/retriever.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Remorhaz</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered remorhazes in the 3e Monster Manual, though I guess they’ve
been around since AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remorhazes are yet another example of the dangerous megafauna that plagues D&amp;amp;D
worlds: gigantic predators with a somewhat centipede-like appearance that
inhabit the colder reaches of the world. They’re also one of those gotcha
monsters, because despite living in cold biomes their powers are heat-based. A
remorhaz can heat its carapace up to an extremely high temperature, which really
ruins the day of the usually-weak-to-fire creatures it feeds on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remorhaz is big enough to swallow a frost giant or adult dragon whole, and
while it use that as a combat maneuver it prefers to do it when the prey in
question is no longer fighting back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frost giants sometimes risk training these creatures. A few of them even
succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-remorhaz.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remorhazes are Huge Elemental Beasts, and Level 21 Elite Brutes with 480 HP. It
has low-light vision and projects an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Blistering Heat&lt;/strong&gt; that does
10 fire damage to any creature caught inside. It runs at speed 6 and burrows at
speed 4 with Tunneling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and grabs on a hit. After
grabbing a creature they can spend a minor action to try to &lt;strong&gt;Swallow&lt;/strong&gt; it (an
attack vs. Fortitude). The beast’s insides deal 10 physical and 10 fire damage
to swallowed victims at the start of its turn. The victim is considered
restrained, with line of sight and effect only to the remorhaz itself. It can
use only melee or close attacks (with penalties from the Restrained condition),
and if it manages to deal 30 damage the remorhaz will spit them out. Killing the
creature also allows the victim to escape, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an oversight here, I think, because the ability doesn’t list a size
limit for which creatures can be swallowed. I’d say Large or smaller is a good
value for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remorhaz can also &lt;strong&gt;Trample&lt;/strong&gt;, moving its speed, crossing enemy spaces, and
making a physical attack that damages and knocks prone against each enemy whose
space it moves through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That heated carapace can do more than project an aura, too. It can flare up in
an &lt;strong&gt;Immolating Carapace&lt;/strong&gt; attack (close burst 1 vs. Reflex; recharge 6) that
deals fire damage and inflicts ongoing fire damage that lasts while the targets
are adjacent to the beast. Yes, this stacks with the aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the remorhaz is bloodied, it can also use &lt;strong&gt;Enraged Heat&lt;/strong&gt; to deal
automatic fire damage to someone who hits it in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good tactic for them seems to be to bite and swallow a PC who can’t put up
much of a fight from the inside, and then run around trampling and roasting the
rest with Immolating Carapace to prevent them from surrounding the remorhaz. An
individual who’s only interested in a quick meal might even try to swallow a PC
and run away to digest them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remorhazes being used as attack beasts by giants will be more ready to fight a
battle to the end, and in that case they might wait to swallow a PC who falls to
0 HP. The others would need to kill the creature in order to heal their
buddy. Welcome to epic level!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sample-encounter-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounter and Final Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 18: A frost giant acting as a beastmaster of
sorts, accompanied by a remorhaz and a rime hound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I had a bit of a hard time distinguishing between a remorhaz and
a behir in earlier editions. The distinction is clearer to me now, but only
because I spent some time studying their entries in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/remorhaz.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/13/remorhaz.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Phoelarch</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-phoelarch.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Go &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm2-4e/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seem to remember phoelarches appearing in one of the late Monster Manuals for
3e. I don’t know if they appeared before that. Their 4e debut is here in the
MM2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Phoelarch is a fiery humanoid native to the Elemental Chaos. Their orange skin
and fiery hair makes them look kinda like a human-like version of the azer, or a
slightly differerent fire genasi. They’re typically nomadic and adventurous, and
so could be found wandering anywhere in the universe. But when you see a
phoelarch you’re seeing just half the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soul of every phoelarch is connected to that of a &lt;em&gt;phoera&lt;/em&gt;, a fire bird
that’s pretty much a mini-phoenix. Phoeras soar through the skies of the
Elemental Chaos, living their bird lives. Though smaller than phoenixes, they’re
still giant territorial birds of prey and have quite a temper, so they can end
up attacking passing adventurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, a phoelarch doesn’t have a lot to do with their phoera and
vice-versa. They have a vague sense of each others’ personality and emotions,
but each lives their own life, and has thoughts and concerns that are utterly
alien to the other. It’s quite possible for them to never meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when one member of the pair is killed, the connection instantly summons
the other one, which will arrive knowing what happened and will be
understandably very angry at the perpetrators. Since phoelarches are more
widespread, the most common scenario likely has the PCs fighting them first and
then the phoera, but I suppose it could happen the other way around. As long as
one member of the pair survives, the other will eventually return to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoeras are Medium Elemental Magical Beasts with the Fire keyword. The two
phoelarches we get here are tagged as Medium Natural Humanoids, but I really
think they should be Elemental as well and have the Fire keyword. As sapient
humanoids, a lot of their abilities come from training, so we get two stat
blocks for them. They still tend to use a lot of fire, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the individual stat blocks here are regulars, but they’re really “disguised”
elites when you think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phoelarch-mage&quot;&gt;Phoelarch Mage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoelarch mages love fire magic, and travel the world looking for adventuresome
mentors who can teach them using practical lessons instead of classroom
work. Some seek out their linked phoeras in order to gain a deeper understanding
of their link and of fire magic in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Phoelarch Mage is Level 12 Artillery with 93 HP. They have Resist 10 Fire,
Vulnerable 5 Cold, and project an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Phoenix Heat&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals 5
damage to any creatures caught inside. That means you should be careful with
their formation if they’re partnering up with flammable allies. Their ground
speed is 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mage’s basic attacks are a &lt;strong&gt;burning dagger&lt;/strong&gt; and a Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;phoenix
ray&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which deal fire damage. They also know a spell named &lt;strong&gt;Flames of
the Phoenix&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which is pretty much your typical fireball: area
effect, fire damage, plus ongoing fire damage. Presumably they also know plenty
of non-combat rituals, but those don’t appear in stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the mage drops to 0 HP their &lt;strong&gt;Rise from the Ashes&lt;/strong&gt; ability triggers and
they explode. This deals heavy fire damage (vs. Reflex) in a Close Burst 2. It
also creates a zone of fire that lasts until the end of the encounter and
damages anyone caught inside. Finally, when the mage’s next turn comes up, a
phoera appears within the zone and joins the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phoelarch-warrior&quot;&gt;Phoelarch Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoelarch warriors are usually wandering mercenaries that seek to get hired as
independent skirmishers and special forces. While their moral outlook is as
varied as that of any sapient, even a dastardly warrior will usually refuse to
work for slavers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Warrior is a Level 12 Skirmisher with 114 HP. They have the same
resistances and aura as the mage, and a Speed of 7. Their main attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;burning falchion&lt;/strong&gt; that deals fire damage and is a High-Crit weapon. They also
have a &lt;strong&gt;Burning Step&lt;/strong&gt; trait that deals automatic fire damage to anyone who
hits them with an opportunity attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the mage, the warrior also explodes when dead, creating a fiery zone and
being replaced by their phoera in the next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phoera&quot;&gt;Phoera&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoeras are level 12 Skirmishers with 114 HP. As magical beasts they’re sapient
and can talk, but their toughts are usually a bit alien to your typical humanoid
and even to their linked phoelarch. They have Resist 15 Fire and Vulnerable 5
Cold, and a damaging fire aura (2) similar to that of the phoelarch, but
larger. They run at speed 6 and fly at speed 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phoeras fight with &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; that do physical and ongoing fire damage, and can
shoot &lt;strong&gt;feathers of flame&lt;/strong&gt; in a close blast 4 pattern. They can perform either
of those as part of a &lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack&lt;/strong&gt; as well, flying their speed without
provoking opportunity attacks and making the attack at any point in the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they die, they explode and leave a fiery zone just like a phoelarch. If
their phoelarch is already dead, that’s the end of it. If not, it’d make sense
for the phoelarch to appear in this zone next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is level 12: a phoelarch warrior who fell in with a briar
witch dryad and a few snaketongue cultists. Do mind your positioning on this
one, as all of the phoelarch’s allies are very flammable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the phoelarch/phoera gimmick! Without it, they’d be just another “generic
fire guy” alongside azers, genasi and salamanders.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/06/phoelarch.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/06/phoelarch.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nordlond Bestiary Kickstarter Campaign</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m a bit late to the promotion bandwagon for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;Nordlond Bestiary&lt;/a&gt;, since
there’s only a few days left in the project. But I’m still going to say it: go
back the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gamingballistic/nordlond-bestiary-and-enemies-book&quot;&gt;Nordlond Bestiary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is already funded. If you back the project, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; get your
reward, and you’ll be contributing to possibly making it &lt;em&gt;bigger&lt;/em&gt;. There’s a
chance it might make the first stretch goal, which means 16 extra pages full of
undead abominations for use in any GURPS campaign that needs monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the classic complaints of many new and veteran GURPS players is the lack
of a “proper monster book” for GURPS 4th Edition. Lots of books include a small
sample selection and tips on making more yourself, but there’s no official
“one-stop-shop” for ready-made critter stat blocks. And of course, this being
GURPS it’s kinda hard to make a truly generic monster book, since whether a
given monster is an impossible challenge or a mere speedbump depends on who your
PCs are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nordlond Bestiary is probably the closest we can get to that mythic book - a
chunky selection of creatures suitable for Dungeon Fantasy campaigns. DF has a
well-known starting point total and a known set of PC templates, you can easily
know how the monsters are callibrated. And it’s also the genre that’s more
likely to need a “monster book” anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book will be made for use with the DFRPG boxed set, but it’s also perfectly
usable with the GURPS core books if that’s what you have. And since you know
what sort of PC these monsters were made to fight, you can also adjust them for
your specific campaign more easily.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/02/nordlond-bestiary.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/12/02/nordlond-bestiary.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Ooze</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oozes have been in the game since the beginning, and as you can see in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/09/02/ooze.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt; the first 4e Monster Manual already featured a bunch of them. As I say
there, far more adventurers lost their lives to an ooze than to one of the
game’s titular dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the MM2 we get a few more oozes, some of which would go on to feature in
the Monster Vault. All of the oozes here have the Blind and Ooze keywords, which
make them immune to gaze attacks and particularly adept at squeezing through
small spaces. They also have BLindsight 10 and Tremorsense 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abolethic-skum&quot;&gt;Abolethic Skum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-ooze-skum.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we saw way back in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/01/04/aboleth.html&quot;&gt;Aboleth&lt;/a&gt; post, Aboleths can turn mortals into
servitors, a process which turns their skin into a layer of transparent
slime. Sometimes, though, this process goes awry and the victim’s form loses all
physical integrity. The resulting watery blobs full of organs are known as
“skum”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abolethic skums are barely sentient, but some memory of what they were remains
with them. This tangles up with residual fear and shame at what they have
become, so they tend to attack anyone who resembles their old form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skum are Level 18 Minion Brutes with the Aquatic keyword in addition to the
default ones. They emit a Psychic Dissonance aura (1) that inflicts Vulnerable 5
Psychic to every creature inside. They have Resist 20 Acid and crawl around at
Speed 2, but can swim at Speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; target Fortitude and do a flat 16 acid damage, which is in line
with Monster Vault math. And their &lt;strong&gt;Aqueous Form&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes them invisible
while in water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being described as failed experiments, a skum’s stats make it complement
its aboleth masters very well. If your PCs go into underwater Underdark
adventure (double the under for half the price!) make sure to place a psychic
aboleth in a room packed full of invisible skum. See how long it takes for your
PCs to figure out why they’re taking extra damage from the aboleth &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt;
dissolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;black-pudding&quot;&gt;Black Pudding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These also appear in the Monster Vault, so we covered them in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/09/02/ooze.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;. The MM2 version was their 4e debut, and it’s mostly identical (math
fixes aside). The only difference is that they lack the powerful &lt;strong&gt;melt&lt;/strong&gt; attack
and instead have a &lt;strong&gt;Mercurial Body&lt;/strong&gt; trait which allows them to ignore
difficult terrain and opportunity attacks when moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gray-ooze&quot;&gt;Gray Ooze&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray Oozes are another D&amp;amp;D classic. They’re about as runny as green slimes, but
more mobile, which means they have always been depicted as active
monsters. Their brand of slime is particularly good at dissolving bones, and
they feed on the resulting bone slurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they’re Level 2 Skirmishers with 43 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;stench&lt;/strong&gt; acts as
an aura (2) that inflicts a -2 attack penalty on creatues inside. They have 5
acid resistance, crawl with a Speed of 5, and climb with Speed 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is named &lt;strong&gt;Bone Melt&lt;/strong&gt;, targetting fortitude and dealing some
acid damage. Each hit also inflicts a cumulative -2 penalty to Fortitude, making
further hits likely. A successful save clears the entire penalty. They can also
shift 2 squares as a minor action, making them quite mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;green-slime&quot;&gt;Green Slime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another monster that appeared in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/09/02/ooze.html&quot;&gt;Monster Vault&lt;/a&gt;, the two versions are
more or less identical. The MV one is a bit simpler to use, though, so prefer
that one if you have the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oozes aren’t smart enough to understand the concept of alliances, but they’re
everywhere in the world of D&amp;amp;D. You don’t need any complex excuses to add an
ooze or three to any underground encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our example encounters for these entry are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 4: 2 green slimes and 2 gray oozes lounging around a lone ankheg’s lair.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: 2 black puddings and a darkmantle enveloper in accidental
cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: An aboleth overseer and two lashers with an entourage of 10
skum. This is that packed room I told you about.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/24/ooze.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/11/24/ooze.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
