<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:14:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Mekillot</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-mekillot.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A mekillot, which looks like a hill-sized lizard/pillbug hybrid.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hill-sized cutie pies are a kind of drake, but they differ enough from
their elementally aligned relatives that they deserve their own entry. In the
wild, these giant armored beasts roam the wastes in small herds, eating plants
and the occasional small animal and laying their eggs near oases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mekillots are not voracious predators other drakes, but they’re still aggressive
and stubborn in the same way a real-life large herbivore like a rhino or hippo
can be. While their size and armor makes them prime beasts of burden and war,
they need to either be trained for these roles from birth or be kept under tight
psychic control at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sorcerer-kings and other defilers think the mekillot’s natural size and
aggressiveness isn’t lethal enough, and perform bioengineering rituals on their
unhatched eggs to make the resulting creature even bigger and stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mekillots are Natural Beasts with the Reptile and Mount tags. They have no
special senses or vulnerabilities. Everything else varies per stat block, and we
get two here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mekillot&quot;&gt;Mekillot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical member of the species is Huge, and has a ground speed of 7. It’s a
Level 10 Soldier with 108 HP. Its basic attack is a Reach 1 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
extra damage to grabbed targets. It can grab them with a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue
Lash&lt;/strong&gt;, which attacks Fortitude. On a hit it pulls the target 2 squares, damages
and grabs them. The mekillot can only have one target grabbed like this, but it
can keep biting them for increased damage as described above while the grab
lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mekillots used as mounts are trained to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Checking Charge&lt;/strong&gt;. This
lets them perform a charge that can go through enemy spaces, and each time they
do so they automatically push the enemy 1 square and knock them prone. At the
end of the charge, in addition to the usual attack from the mekillot, its rider
can also make a melee basic attack as a free action. This is an excellent fight
opener, since the push-and-knock-prone effect doesn’t require an attack. It lets
the mekillot and its rider go straight to the PC squishies in the back line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mekillot-dirk&quot;&gt;Mekillot Dirk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a mekillot mutated by defiling magic to be even bigger. It’s
Gargantuan in size, a little slower at Speed 6, and a Level 22 Elite Soldier
with 418 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dirk is big enough to have &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach 2&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as a &lt;strong&gt;Wide
Body&lt;/strong&gt; that lets other creatures enter and end their move in its space. This
means they’re standing on its back – and that the slope is gentle enough to not
require climbing checks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dirk’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; works just like that of the standard mekillot, though its
numbers are of course bigger. It can also attack with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which
target 1 or 2 creatures. On a hit they deal damage, pull the target 1 square,
and knock it prone. Its Tongue Lash has been upgraded to a Reach 4 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue
Chomp&lt;/strong&gt;, which works identically but also allows the creature to make a free
bite attack against the target after pulling it to an adjacent square. This
effectively makes this maneuver a double attack. The text says the tongue only
pulls the victim 1 square, but I think that’s an error: it should be 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checking Charge upgrades to &lt;strong&gt;Trample&lt;/strong&gt;, which doesn’t require a rider. This
lets the mekillot shift twice its speed, enter enemy spaces during the move, and
make free claw attacks against any enemy whose space it enters in this way. So
it’s not &lt;em&gt;guaranteed&lt;/em&gt; to knock the whole PC party prone any more, but those it
does knock prone will be worse off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re either going to meet a small herd of wild mekillot, 2-3 of them being
used as war mounts by humanoid soliers or brutes, or a mekillot dirk being used
as an armored personal carrier by epic-level artillery and controller villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their mechanics are workable enough, but what really endears mekillots to me is
this illustration. They look like marketable plushies even though they’re likely
to trample you to death.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/24/mekillot.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/24/mekillot.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 03: The New Order</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2025/08/04/guns-of-wolfenstein-02.html&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; of this series, we took a look at the guns that appear on
Wolfenstein: The Old Blood, whose timeline I named “Wolfenstein-2” for ease of
reference. The timeline from the 2001 game, whose guns I talked about [here][2],
was Wolfenstein-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we will take a look at the weapons that appear in Wolfenstein: The New
Order, a game that was published &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; The Old Blood (2014) but whose stories
starts right when The Old Blood ends. We’ll also make some mentions to the last
game in the trilogy, The New Colossus (from 2017) but the weapons that make
their debut in that game will be presented in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-order-plot-overview-contains-spoilers&quot;&gt;The New Order Plot Overview (Contains Spoilers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this game was launched a year earlier, its story starts off right after
The Old Blood ends, in 1946. After B. J. Blaskowicz returns to the Allies with
the location of General Deathshead’s secret hideout, they mount a massive attack
on that island fortress. This is a higher-budget version of the final chapters
of the 2001 game, which ended with Deathshead’s defeat, but things don’t that
well here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack is a disaster. Deathshead kills most of B.J.’s unit and leaves the
rest of them to die in a deathtrap. The survivors manage to escape just as the
room they’re in explodes, but the explosion buries a large piece of shrapnel in
Blazko’s brain. He washes ashore somewhere in Poland, catatonic, and since no
one knows who he is, gets sent to an asylum. He spends the next 14 years there
slowly recovering, with nearly no motor function, slipping in and out of comas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Nazi attack on the asylum in 1960 gives him the impulse he needs to complete
his recovery, and the first actual level of the game is escaping that situation
with a nurse named Anna, the other survivor of the place. They reach Anna’s
grandparents, where Blazko learns that the Nazis won the war in 1948, and that
as far as everyone knows the last members of the resistance had been captured
and sent to an “inescapable” prison in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the game is about freeing these prisoners, rebuilding the
resistance, and striking back at Deathshead through a series of daring
heists. These start with the rescue of good-guy super-scientist Seth Roth&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,
and proceed with the the capture of a giant enemy submarine, the recovery of its
nuclear launch codes from a Nazi base on the Moon, and finally an attack on
Deathshead’s fortress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blazko manages to kill Deathshead during the second attack on his fortress,
though the asshole manages to detonate a grenade as he dies. The game ends as
B. J., too wounded to evacuate, gives his allies the all-clear to launch the
nuke that will destroy this fortress for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guns&quot;&gt;The Guns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the guns here are, again, captured Nazi hardware. And
those, in turn, are “new and improved” versions of the guns we saw in The Old
Blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their actual mechanics and list of available weapons changes a bit between this
game and its sequel in ways that can be better explained by changes in artistic
and gameplay direction than by in-setting developments. The weapons presented
here are based partially on a melding of their two versions, and partially on
what I’d think would be more interesting for a GURPS Action game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post focuses on the weapons that make their first appearance in The New
Order. The next one will present the ones that first appear in The New Colossus,
using the same adaptation strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m omitting price information as usual. In a Wolfenstein-inspired game, PCs
will be picking these up from the corpses of their enemies. In other games, the
GM can figure out a price based on the prices of similar real-world weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pistols&quot;&gt;Pistols&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pistol-model-1960&quot;&gt;Pistol Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A direct descendant of the 1946 model, this one has a more futuristic look, a
double-stacked 20-round magazine, and the ability to fire 3-round bursts. It
still takes the same cinematic silencer. As before, it adds -1 to Bulk, makes
the gun cinematically silent, and also makes it only able to fire in semi-auto
mode (RoF 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If using standard GURPS skills, you need Guns (Pistol) to fire in semi-auto
mode, and Guns (SMG) to fire bursts. If using the optional skills from Pyramid
#3/65, you need Guns (Pistol), with the Burst-Fire technique for firing bursts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Pistol 1960&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;160/1800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1.4kg/0.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-arms&quot;&gt;Long Arms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the standard system, use the Guns skill that corresponds to their description
(SMG, Shotgun, Rifle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the alternate skills from Pyramid #3/65, they all use Guns (Long
Arm), of course. The Burst-Fire technique helps fire weapons at a RoF greater
than 3 without penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;american-submachine-gun&quot;&gt;American Submachine Gun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much a historical &lt;strong&gt;Thompson M1A1&lt;/strong&gt;, described in p. HT122. The
Allies mostly didn’t have access to superscience in this timeline and were
limited to historical equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allied soldiers are armed with this during the 1946 assault on Deathshead’s
compound, and the game expects you to use them for the handful of minutes
between the start of gameplay and the moment when you first grab an enemy
weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assault-rifle-model-1960&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evolution of the 1946 model, it’s lighter and uses a double-stacked 45 round
magazine, but still fires the same round. The biggest change here is an
underbarrel accessory rail that can take a mini-rocket launcher, which appears
as an upgrade midway through the game. This is detailed in the Launchers
section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-1960&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This semi-automatic rifle is about the same length as the AR, but fires a
heftier round (likely 7.92x57mm) from a 10-round magazine. It has an integral
scope. It’s a relatively rare find both in the hands of enemies and as
loot. Clearly the Nazis are bigger fans of the spray-and-pray approach to
marksmanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extended 30-round magazine is available: Shots 30+1(3), Weight becomes
6.2kg/1.05kg. The gun can also fire APHC rounds: Dam 6d+2(2) pi-.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shockhammer-model-1960&quot;&gt;Shockhammer Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another descendant of the gun from The Old Blood, this one uses a “snail drum”
magazine and a single barrel to achieve better performance than its
predecessor. The most commonly available shells for the weapon are standard
buckshot, and “shrapnel”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shrapnel shells fire red-hot fragments that ricochet off walls in a very
video-gamey way, allowing the player to hit enemies behind cover or around
corners by bouncing the shrapnel off the wall behind them. The shotgun can only
fire in semi-auto mode while using these shells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the GURPS version below, I’m treating shrapnel as Multi-Flechette shells
(High-Tech p. 174) with an incendiary effect. Damage becomes 1d+1 pi- inc; Range
becomes 100/1200; RoF becomes 3x20. GMs who wish to replicate the ricochet
effect can reduce the penalty for firing at targets behind cover when there are
suitable surfaces nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the GM’s discretion, any special shells listed in High Tech and Ultra-Tech
might also be available for this shotgun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;long-arms-table&quot;&gt;Long Arms Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Thompson M1A1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+1 pi+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;170/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.1kg/0.8kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;30+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;MP-61&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d pi-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;170/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.1kg/0.4kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;45+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/3100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;45+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;850/3750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg/0.35kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shockhammer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1d+1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.1kg/1.05kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6x9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-weapons&quot;&gt;Energy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a surprising amount of energy weapons in both games. All of these use
Beam Weapons (Rifle) unless noted otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laser weapons in this setting draw power from internal batteries that can’t be
removed without disassembling the weapon. The usual method of reloading them is
by using one of the highly dangerous industrial power outlets that seem to be
everywhere in Nazi-dominated cities and facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In The New Order, these use short-ranged wireless power transfer. In The New
Colossus, they use a thick cable with a plug that resembles a gas station
pump. I suggest picking an aesthethic and sticking to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wireless Charging&lt;/strong&gt;: The wielder must stay within 2 meters of the outlet
during the process, which causes lightning to arc between the outlet and the
weapon’s power receptors. Doing anything with the weapon other than holding it
steady will interrupt the recharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wired Charging&lt;/strong&gt;: The wielder must plug the cable into the weapon (1 Ready
Action), and then stay within 1 meter of the outlet. The weapon cannot be used
while charging. Once charging is done, it takes another Ready maneuver to unplug
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recharge time is listed for each weapon, and has more to do with the weapon’s
ability to absorb incoming power than with the outlet’s ability to provide it!
The later seems to be effectively limitless, at least on a personal scale. Yes,
these things are extremely unsafe. What happens if you stab someone with the
wired plug or intercept them with the arc of the wireless charger is left as an
exercise for the GM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some places you can also find portable batteries that can be used to top up a
weapon through a similar process. The GM will say how many shots from a weapon
an individual battery can recharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lunar-laser-rifle&quot;&gt;Lunar Laser Rifle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Moonbase level of The New Order, everyone carries a laser weapon with the
same external appearance as the Marksman Rifle. It lacks a scope, and can fire
in full-auto mode. Its performance seems to be about on par with the assault
rifle, though it is a lot better at dealing with heavily-armored
enemies. Industrial outlets recharge it at 3 shots per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being a laser weapon based on the Marksman Rifle, Nazi soldiers don’t
usually use Aim maneuvers with it, so they are no more accurate than usual when
wielding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t exist in The New Colossus, not even on Venus. Maybe it was a pet
project of Deathshead’s for the moon base, and got phased out when he died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-combined&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle (Combined)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you return to Earth after the Moonbase level, B.J.’s Marksman Rifle becomes
a combination gadget of sorts, with the scope on a hinged mount. With the mount
closed and the scope in place, it fires bullets as before. With the scope folded
away, it behaves like the Moonbase laser rifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This design is probably more of a video game quality of life decision than
something feasible in setting, but if you want to include it in your campaigns
you can treat it as a Combination Gadget per the rules on Ultra-Tech p. 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under those rules, Weight becomes 8kg/0.35kg (or 8.7/1.05 with the extended
mag). Switching modes requires a Ready maneuver, and the weapon uses the Damage,
Acc, Range, RoF, Shots and ST of whatever version is the currently active
one. Keep track of both ammo counts separately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;laserkraftwerk&quot;&gt;Laserkraftwerk&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an experimental laser weapon that B. J. “liberates” from a lab early in
The New Order. It’s about carbine-sized, and fires shots that are more powerful
than those of the lunar laser rifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LKW also has an alternate “laser cutter” module that’s useful for quietly
severing chains and cutting through chain-link fences and thin metal walls. This
does 2d(2) burn and can run continuously for half an hour on a full battery, if
it matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the game, the player can find several upgrades for the LKW,
including a scope, a double-capacity battery, and new internal parts that allow
it to fire more often or to fire a more powerful “charged” shot that’s better at
dealing with large and heavily armored opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Weapon Table below, you get stats both for the baseline version and the
fully-upgraded one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial outlets recharge the weapon at a rate of 1 shot per second with the
standard battery, or 2 shots per second with the expanded one. The final upgrade
in The New Order is an “ancient supertech” portable reactor that recharges the
weapon at a rate of 1 shot per 2 seconds whenever it’s not being fired,
regardless of its battery size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;energy-weapon-table&quot;&gt;Energy Weapon Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Marskman Rifle (Laser)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/1500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;28*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;LKW (baseline)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;LKW (fully upgraded)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12+2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;charged shot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6dx3(3) burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;**&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*: See description for recharge time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**: Drains power equivalent to 5 shots from the battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grenades-and-launchers&quot;&gt;Grenades and Launchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enemy soldiers are enthusiastic about using hand grenades in the The New Order,
and only a little less so in The New Colossus. Launcher weapons are much rarer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In The New Order, enemies use the same &lt;strong&gt;Hand Grenade&lt;/strong&gt; from the previous post
in the 1946 prologue. By 1960 they’ve switched to using Tesla grenades
exclusively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;tesla-grenade&quot;&gt;Tesla Grenade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like a modernized version of the Stick Hand Grenade used back
in 1946. Its explosive power is equivalent, but also releases an electromagnetic
pulse that can “stun” robotic and cybernetic enemies in a 4-meter radius from
the epicenter of the explosion. They must make a HT-8(2) roll or be knocked out
of action for seconds equal to their margin of failure. That (2) means that any
electromagnetic shielding that would provide a bonus to this roll only works at
half effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; applies to battery-powered weapons of any kind, which usually have
HT 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;underbarrel-rocket-launcher&quot;&gt;Underbarrel Rocket Launcher&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An accessory compatible with the 1960 Assault Rifle, this launcher fires 40mm
anti-armor rockets from a removable cylinder with a 4-round capacity. It’s
issued to soldiers that are expected to go against heavily-armored opposition,
and who are usually heavily-armored themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launcher can only be used if it’s attached to another weapon. By default
that’s the assault rifle, which has the rails to receive it, but players might
decide to get creative with their jury-rigging. It adds its weight to the
overall weight of the other weapon and worsens its Bulk by -1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the standard skill system, this uses the Guns (LAW) skill. In the alternate
one, it’s Guns (Long Arm) aided by the Payload Warhead technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hand-grenade-table&quot;&gt;Hand Grenade Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fuse&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tesla Grenade&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7d cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;linked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;HT-8(2) aff&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rocket-launcher-table&quot;&gt;Rocket Launcher Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Underbarrel Rocket Launcher&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5dx2(10) cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;–&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;linked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d cr ex [1d-1]&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heavy-weapons&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;laser-machine-gun&quot;&gt;Laser Machine Gun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old Venom machine gun from the war has been replaced with this energy weapon
in the Sixties. Like its predecessor, the Laser MG is found in fixed mounts, in
the hands of cybernetic supersoldiers, and mounted on the many models of giant
robot stomping around. It can fire for quite a bit before running dry. This can
look like either a sequence of rapid pulses or a continuous beam, but either
version uses the same stats. Enemies don’t like to aim with it either, improving
the players’ chances of survival when facing it. It’s heavy and bulky enough to
be only a “sometimes” gun for the player, used when found and quickly discarded
when empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial outlets reload it at a rate of 20 shots per second. When attached to
a fixed mount, the weapon’s Acc improves to 18, and it’s recharged as if
connected to an outlet when not firing. Attaching or detaching it takes 2 Ready
maneuvers. The weapon uses the Gunner (Beams) skill even when detached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;heavy-weapon-table&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapon Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Laser MG&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;200*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*: See description for recharge time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Seth belongs to the Da’at Yichud, an ancient society of engineers that had
been building superscience devices as a form of worship since before the
rest of humanity had organized religion. Deathshead’s inventions are all
copied from one of their vaults, which he found in the 40s. I’ve seen the
concept described as kinda problematic despite the designers’ best
intentions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/17/guns-of-wolfenstein-03.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/17/guns-of-wolfenstein-03.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Megapede</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-megapede.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A megapede, an enormous purple centipede with neon green highlights.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lore of the Megapede is fairly uncomplicated. They’re the logical endpoint
of the Giant Centipede Arms Race. The largest, strongest, Darkest and Sunniest
giant centipedes on Athas. And they’re also psychic, because of course they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Megapedes lair underground, in burrows or natural caves where they lay their
eggs. They hunt by tunneling through the sand, erupting from beneath their
prey, and fighting a battle of attrition they will likely win with their
venomous bite, hundreds of flailing legs, and corrosive psionics. Sometimes
unlucky travelers taking shelter in a cave might find it’s already occupied by a
megapede when it drops down from the ceiling on top of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, they’ll share their lair with a couple of wild cilopses, who are
their distant cousins, but they tend to just eat anything else, and no one has
ever managed to tame them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Megapedes are Huge Natural Beasts and Level 15 Elite Brutes with 368 HP. They
have Darkvision, a ground speed of 8, a burrow speed of 6 in loose earth, and a
climb speed of 8. Their overall power level is on par with that of an Athasian
drake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; attack has Reach 2 and does a potent blend of physical and
poison damage. Their most common at-will attack will be &lt;strong&gt;Legs of the
Megapede&lt;/strong&gt;, which attacks all enemies in a Close Burst 2 for similar damage
&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; lets the megapede bite someone for free as an effect. Its &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Body&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) works as a minor-action melee attack that does a little less
damage than the Legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the monster is also psychic! Once per encounter it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Psionic Erosion&lt;/strong&gt; to attack the Fortitude of enemies in a Close Blast 5. On a
hit, this deals immediate and ongoing psychic damage, which starts at 10 and
decreases to 5 after the first successful save. On a miss, it deals half
damage. Slightly more often, it can cause a &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Detonation&lt;/strong&gt; on an Area 1
Burst Within 5, which deals “psychic and force” damage and slides targets 3
squares. This recharges when it’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when it hits with either of its single-target physical attacks, the
megapede can use &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augmentation&lt;/strong&gt; to deal extra psychic damage on the
attack. This also recharges when it’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the most likely megapede encounters are against a mated pair
or against one of them plus 2-3 leveled-up cilopses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise this is basically a Giant-er Centipede, so I’m not all that excited
about them. If that’s your bag, tough, they’re awesome. Mechanically, you can
use a megapede anywhere you’d use an Athasian Drake - they’re about as powerful
and arguably a lot more common. You could also reskin their stat block as a
drake or other suitable giant creature.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/08/wir-dscc-megapede.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/08/wir-dscc-megapede.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Kirre</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-kirre.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A kirre, looking like a horned green tiger with eight legs.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirres manage to feel like exotic alien creatures both to us in the real world
and to characters in Athas. To us, it’s because they have eight legs and a pair
of horns. To Athasians, it’s because they’re fur-covered mammals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These felines live in Athas’ rare forests and jungles, such as the Crescent
Forest and the same Forest Ridge where halflings live. They gather in small
prides, and are clever and cautious hunters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of simply charging in, a kirre who isn’t desperately hungry will stalk
its prey for hours to evaluate its capabilities and behavior, and will adapt its
tactics to ensure their success. With some, they might be extra-sneaky and
attack when the prey’s guard is down. With others, they might harass and make
noises to scare the prey into making a foolish mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book entry mentions that kirres are only one of several species descended
from ancient great cats. Other names mentioned are tigones and “the reptilian
lirr”, though these two aren’t present in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only have one stat block here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kirre&quot;&gt;Kirre&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kirre is a Large Natural Magical Beast, and a Level 13 Skirmisher with 131
HP. It has a Speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has two basic attacks: a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a slightly weaker &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that slows
for a turn on a hit. The &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; at-will ability lets it make two claw
attacks in one action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Springing Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; lets the kirre bite, shift 4 squares, and bite again. This
becomes a nice fight opener when combined with the &lt;strong&gt;Scattering Leap&lt;/strong&gt;
move-action encounter power, which lets the beast jump 6 squares, push adjacent
enemies at the destination 2 squares, and then shift 2 squares to follow one of
those enemies. The Pounce recharges when the creature is bloodied, which also
makes it useful for escaping a dicey situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Forceful Roar&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks the
Fortitude of enemies in a Close Blast 3. On a hit it deals force damage, pushes
2 squares, and knocks prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy moves to a square where it flanks the kirre, it can use its
&lt;strong&gt;Barbed Tail&lt;/strong&gt; to fend then off, making a Reach 2 melee attack that knocks
prone and inflicts 10 ongoing damage (save ends) on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirres are smart enough to ally with creatures of other species, though they
demand that their allies be at least as smart as themselves. Those who aren’t
will be treated as prey instead. This is a low bar for other sapient creatures
to clear, which means they will sometimes even accept humanoids as pack
mates. They can be most often found in the company of halflings, though goliaths
and giths that live in greener areas are also known to ally with kirres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re regular monsters, but their spread of abilities means they fight like
elites! An encounter featuring a pair of kirres and a handful of humanoid allies
will give PCs quite a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/28/wir-dscc-kirre.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/28/wir-dscc-kirre.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4e</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Kestrekel</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-kestrekel.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A flock of kestrekels, who look like vultures with oversized serrated beaks.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kestrekels are not to be confused with kestrels, which might not even exist in
Athas. They’re basically Darker and Sunnier vultures, with a habit of gathering
around creatures that are about to die in the wastes. They’re a lot more
enthusiastic about hurrying the process along than their mundane counterpart,
and while a single kestrekel isn’t much of a threat a whole flock of them can be
very dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who want to turn the tables and hunt the birds instead might be able to
draw them closer by feigning injury, but this rarely works - they’re a bit too
clever for that tactic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kestrekels are Tiny Natural Beasts with a ground speed of 2 and a flight speed
of 6. We get two stat blocks here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kestrekel-carrion-eater&quot;&gt;Kestrekel Carrion Eater&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one represents a single individual. It’s drawn to movement, so even a
traveller who isn’t wounded or dying might find one or three of these staring at
them from a distance, and following them for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kestrekel is a Level 1 Minion Skirmisher. Its &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack is stronger
against bloodied targets, and its &lt;strong&gt;Darting Rake&lt;/strong&gt; at-will ability lets it shift
3 squares and make a claw attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kestrekel-blood-flock&quot;&gt;Kestrekel Blood Flock&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might get a whole flock like this one on battlefields and similar places,
where carrion abounds and its smell carries great distances. This is a Medium
swarm of kestrekels, counting as a Level 2 Controller with 35 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flock has all standard swarm traits: half damage from melee and ranged
attacks, vulnerable 5 to close and area attacks, can occupy enemy spaces, can
squeeze past any opening large enough for a Tiny creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its &lt;strong&gt;Swarm Attack&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) deals a bit of physical damage to enemies caught
inside, and also slows them for a turn when that happens. Its basic attack is a
swarm of &lt;strong&gt;Scrabbling Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which does standard physical damage with a small
bonus against bloodied targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flock’s sheer bloodlust is also a weapon: the &lt;strong&gt;Loathsome Feast&lt;/strong&gt; ability is
a psychic attack that can be used if the flock is adjacent to a bloodied
enemy. It attacks enemy Will in a close burst 3, deals psychic damage, and
pushes each target hit a number of squares equal to their speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re dealing with a few individuals or a whole flock, kestrekels are
very opportunistic. They’ll stay away and watch until they see their victim is
injured, sick, or dying. Then they dive in. Spilled blood also drives them into
a frenzy, so they’re sure to join in on any fight that they see starting, intent
on eating the combatants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things don’t exactly spark joy in me, but it feels like they’re an
interesting addition to any battlefield, where they’d be a constant hazard.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/22/wir-dscc-kestrekel.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/22/wir-dscc-kestrekel.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Kank</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-kank.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A jhakar, a stocky dog-lizard hybrid with a pug-like face.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kanks are giant, beetle-like hive insects. A wild hive will viciously attack
strangers and intruders, but they’re actually relatively easy to domesticate:
just start feeding them. After a while, the kanks will start seeing those who
bring them food as members of the hive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each hive has a queen that does little more than continuously lay eggs. The
larvae that hatch from these eggs can specialize in one of two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kank spitters are the hive’s workers. Their duty is to forage for any sort of
organic matter and process it into a nutritive nectar that is used to feed the
hive (and extracted to feed people). They can store the noxious byproducts of
this processing and spit them at intruders as a form of defense, hence their
name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kank soldiers are very straightforward: they’re big, they’re strong, they have
huge mandibles. Their duty is to protect spitters from threats. When properly
trained, they’re also extremely popular war mounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kank queens are too immobile to get combat stats, but we do get stats for the
other two types. Both are Natural Beasts with a ground speed of 8 and Resist 5
Acid and Poison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kank-spitter&quot;&gt;Kank Spitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spitters are Small but not defenseless. They’re Level 2 Artillery with 30
HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; do a mix of untyped and acid damage. Their &lt;strong&gt;Kank Spit&lt;/strong&gt; has
range 10. On a hit it does a little bit of physical damage, inflicts ongoing 5
acid damage, and slows (save ends). If the target was already slowed, it is
immobilized instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kank-soldier&quot;&gt;Kank Soldier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Large kanks are Level 4 Soldiers with 54 HP and the Mount tag. Their
&lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is rather weak to start with, but it grabs on a hit. Once the soldier
has a grabbed victim, it can only bite that victim, but its bite attack gains +2
to attack and +10 to damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soldier can instead choose to inject the victim with &lt;strong&gt;Kank Venom&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+), an attack that targets Fortitude, slows, and deals ongoing 10
poison damage (save ends both). After the first saved throw, this worsens to
immobilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If serving as a mount, their benefit is &lt;strong&gt;Grabbed Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;: this gives their
rider combat advantage against the kank’s grabbed victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kank soldiers don’t have marking mechanics, but they don’t need them. They’ll
focus on a victim and try to keep it grabbed by their mandibles, using the venom
as a parting shot if they have reason to release the grab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep hearing about kanks in other Dark Sun Let’s Reads, so it’s nice to
finally put a (bug) face to the name, so to speak. They feel more interesting to
me than crodlus, both because they’re beetles and because they have a use other
than “war mount” to their humanoid caretakers.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/19/wir-dscc-kank.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/19/wir-dscc-kank.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Jhakar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-jhakar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A jhakar, a stocky dog-lizard hybrid with a pug-like face.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Described as “small, squat, and pugnacious”, these round boys are reptilian dog
equivalents with keen senses and a vicious streak. On the wild they follow your
standard pack hunter structure, but they’re also frequently “tamed” by people
for use as combat, guard, and tracker animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tamed” is in quotes here because jhakars don’t form bonds of loyalty with their
handlers. They respect strength and pain, but they also nurse grudges. So the
process of training a jhakar is quite cruel and results in a creature that’s
likely to turn on their handler as soon as it sees a chance. Ironically, because
of this owning a trained jhakar is seen as a sign of strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jhakars are Small Natural Beasts with the Reptile tag. They have a ground speed
of 6 and Low-Light Vision. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Uncanny Senses&lt;/strong&gt;, which
makes their attacks ignore concealment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jhakars don’t have supernatural tracking abilities like some of the monsters we
saw before, but you can probably consider them as good at it as a trained
mundane hound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jhakar-tracker&quot;&gt;Jhakar Tracker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This specimen is a Level 1 Skirmisher with 28 HP and all standard jhakar
traits. As mentioned above, it’s probably as good at tracking as a mundane dog,
but its stat block focuses more on what it does once it finds its prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tracker’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; does standard damage with a sizable bonus against targets
granting combat advantage to it. The attack also lets the tracker shift 1 square
as an effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter the tracker can use an &lt;strong&gt;Opportunistic Chomp&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction
when an enemy ends its turn within 2 squares. It lets make a free bite attack
with the damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trackers are unlikely to stay in one place for very long. Their free shift with
a bite lets them move in, bite, and then dart away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jhakar-trapjaw&quot;&gt;Jhakar Trapjaw&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This beefier specimen is a Level 3 Soldier with 47 HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; is a bit
stronger, grabs on a hit, and lets the trapjaw make a secondary attack against
Fortitude. If that one hits, the grabbed victim takes 5 ongoing damage until
the grab ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trapjaw can also &lt;strong&gt;Drag Down&lt;/strong&gt; a grabbed victim, attacking their
Fortitude. If they hit, they deal heavy damage and knock the target prone. It
can’t get up until the grab ends either! This recharges when the creature is
first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike trackers, jhakar trapjaws are set up to choose a PC and make their day
extremely bad. They’ll do exactly that, positioning themselves as the center of
attention to let their quicker buddies attack the party while they’re
distracted. This works no matter who those allies are, so it’s appropriate for
both wild and domesticated jhakar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry is short and to the point, just like the creatures it
describes. You’ll never ever need to include normal dogs or wolves in our Dark
Sun Campaigns if this book has anything to say about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An encounter group of wild Jhakars will probably include one or two trapjaws
with trackers making up the rest of the numbers. And of course any of the other
doglike creatures in this or other books could be reskinned as a jhakar. They
also work in any mixed encounter as trained beasts, as they are fairly common in
that role.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/17/wir-dscc-jhakar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/17/wir-dscc-jhakar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Inix</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-inix.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An inix, a yellowish giant lizard with a brown beak and carapace.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most of the Athasian fauna we saw so far, these giant lizards are fairly
docile omnivores. They mostly eat plants and roots, though they’ll also feed on
carrion and small animals. They only attack people if directly
threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inixes are widely domesticated for use as mounts, draft animals, and
livestock. Some people like to keep juveniles as pets. In the wild, they roam in
small bands. Inix females lay eggs once a year, and are capable of producing
viable eggs even without a male.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inixes are Natural Beasts, with the Reptile tag. When forced to fight they
attack with bites and with swipes of their large and powerful tails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inix-juvenile&quot;&gt;Inix Juvenile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inix juveniles are only about half the size of adults, which means they’re
Medium. This slighter build makes them faster than adults. Juveniles also have
venom in their bites, which they lose as they grow up. They’re Level 4
Skirmishers with 57 HP and a speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is venomous, dealing a mix of physical and
poison damage. As a minor action they can attempt a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Trip&lt;/strong&gt;, which attacks
Fortitude. On a hit, the inix knocks the target prone and can shift 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inix-adult&quot;&gt;Inix Adult&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults are size Large, and Level 9 Brutes with 120 HP and a Speed of 6. They’ll
probably open the fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Slap&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks the Fortitude of
enemies in a Close Blast 2. On a hit it deals standard physical damage and
knocks the targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, it’s time for the &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals standard physical damage. When it
hits a prone target, the bite deals extra damage and grabs that target. The
victim can only try to stand up after the grab ends, and the inix can keep
making bite attacks against it (but not against others while the victim remains
grabbed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the inix is serving as a mount, it can use the &lt;strong&gt;Warding Tail&lt;/strong&gt; ability. This
triggers when the rider is hit by an opportunity attack provoked by making a
ranged or area attack, and lets the inix use Tail Slap against the triggering
creature as a free action. This makes them a fine mount for artillery monsters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short and sweet entry. It’s always good to see another member of the club of
Athasian creatures that are not suicidally aggressive predators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encounters with domesticated inixes tend to be much more interesting than those
with wild ones, as they can feature more varied encounter groups. As mentioned
above, adults are awesome mounts for artillery and controller riders. They’re
also fun to have as the draft animal for a “runaway wagon” scenario, as they
tend to be much harder to physically stop than horses.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/15/wir-dscc-inix.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/15/wir-dscc-inix.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Id Fiend</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-id-fiend.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An id fiend, a big toothy lizard, hanging out on a rock outcropping.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Id fiends are big toothy lizards with psionic powers of fear manipulation,
which they use to hunt their preferred prey. Which is, of course, people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As reasonably smart magical beasts, they are capable of making alliances with
other creatures, though these tend to be strained at best. More often, an id
fiend might craft fearful illusions to manipulate those creatures into helping
it attack others. When that happens, the best tactic is to focus on the id
fiend - when it dies, its control ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Id fiends are a major threat to civilians, but a favorite target of seasoned
monster hunters. The House of the Mind in Draj pays generously for live
specimens, whose fresh organs and fluids go into making alchemical potions meant
to awaken someone’s psychic potential. Many of those are dubious at best, but at
least some of them have real effects. The book mentions “terror ichor” by name -
this is a consumable reagent that can be used to enhance fear-based powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Fiends are Large Aberrant Magical Beasts with the Reptile tag. This probably
makes them the most mundane-looking aberrants we saw so far. Just a big lizard,
not a tentacle in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they end up filling the empty niche left by absence of low-level
dragons in Athas. They’re Level 1 Solo Controllers with 120 HP, Darkvision, a
Speed of 6, an immunity to Fear and Resist 5 Psychic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fiend can attack with a &lt;strong&gt;quick slash&lt;/strong&gt; of its claws, which deals light
physical damage and lets it shift 1 square; with a bite of its &lt;strong&gt;Snapping Jaws&lt;/strong&gt;
that deals more damage and slides the target 1 square; or with a &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt; that uses both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a breath weapon, it has the &lt;strong&gt;Manifest Fear&lt;/strong&gt; power (recharge 4+),
which affects enemies in a Close Burst 5. Those hit by it are dazed for a turn
as they see a vision of their worst fears becoming reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the fiend dazes a few enemies, it will use the &lt;strong&gt;Fearful Torment&lt;/strong&gt; power, a
minor-action ranged attack that targets one or two tazed creatures. A hit deals
psychic damage, immobilizes, and inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks for a turn. I
guess this means it makes the vision of fear worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the fiend is first bloodied, Manifest Fear recharges and it can use the
power immediately as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like id fiends prefer to use their fear powers to kill their victims if
possible, though they’re also perfectly capable of physical fighting as seen
above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single id fiend makes a fine boss battle for beginner PCs. Once they gain a
level or two, you can begin to add thralls enraptured by visions of fear, and
fooled into thinking the PCs are monsters to be slain. As the book says, killing
the fiend will likely free the thralls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an interesting monster, I think. Effectively a low-level dragon that
breathes fear. You can level it up a bit to make it more challenging for
mid-Heroic PCs, but I’d probably set that as the upper bound of their power.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/13/wir-dscc-id-fiend.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/13/wir-dscc-id-fiend.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Human</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I keep mentioning Mixed Groups of People as possible encounter
groups? How they can be anything, allied or hostile, made up of free or enslaved
individuals, working for any one of the setting’s factions or none at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s exactly the kind of description you get for humans in this entry. They
are the most numerous humanoid species on Athas, they are infinitely varied and
adaptable, and all the other stuff you have read about them a thousand times in
other places. What this tells me is that those Mixed Groups of People will be
mostly made up of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans in Athas are mechanically identical to humans elsewhere. Medium Natural
Humanoids with Speed 6, and with absolutely everything else determined by
training in each specific stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any of these stat blocks can easily be adjusted to represent a member of another
species by adding that species’ signature traits o it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-slave&quot;&gt;Human Slave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If humans make up the bulk of those Mixed Groups of People, then it’s logical to
assume they also make up the bulk of Athas’ enslaved population. You’ll see them
in large numbers while walking down the street of any of the sorcerer-kings’
city states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Human Slave is a Level 1 Minion Brute, armed with a &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt; that’s likely
improvised. They gain +1 bonus damage for each ally adjacent to their target,
and &lt;strong&gt;Laborer’s Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; make them stay up for an additional turn after
being reduced to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, they’re quite bad at fighting, and will likely only do so if
they have no other choice. Only their large numbers make them a threat to
PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-wasteland-raider&quot;&gt;Human Wasteland Raider&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a typical member of those hostile Mixed Groups of People who attack you
while you’re traveling the wastes, intent on either killing you, taking your
stuff, or both. They’re Level 2 Soldiers with 40 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most striking thing about this stat block is the big editing error right in
the middle, a &lt;strong&gt;barbed spear&lt;/strong&gt; attack that has no listed damage and should be
ignored. The raider’s actual weapon is a &lt;strong&gt;Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; that does standard physical
damage and can be used in a stronger &lt;strong&gt;Gutting Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; attack against someone
grabbed by the raider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the spear was supposed to be the attack that grabbed the target? As it is,
the raider has to use the default rules and perform a Grab action to do
it. My suggestion here would be to replace the &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack with a
&lt;strong&gt;Barbed Spear&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage, grabs on a hit, and cannot be used
against other targets while the raider has a target grabbed. Gutting Dagger
would then turn into Gutting Spear, with the same effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-dune-trader&quot;&gt;Human Dune Trader&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember disliking the emphasis the book put on elven traders being unreliable
and dishonest, but it looks like it doesn’t have much better to say about the
human ones. This one is described as being flanked by burly bodyguards as he
cheerfully lies about the price and quality of his goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune Traders are Level 4 Controllers with the Leader tag and 55 HP. They’re
armed with &lt;strong&gt;hatchets&lt;/strong&gt; that do physical damage and cause the target to grant
Combat Advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While unbloodied, they can spend minor actions on &lt;strong&gt;Goading Commands&lt;/strong&gt; that let
one ally within 6 squares move their speed as a free action. While bloodied,
this changes to a &lt;strong&gt;Furious Glare&lt;/strong&gt;, a standard action that attacks the Will of
enemies in a Close Blast 3. It does no damage, but immobilizes and makes the
targets grant combat advantage on a hit (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-gladiator-novice&quot;&gt;Human Gladiator Novice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those gladiators who managed to survive their first few fights can go on to
achieve fame and greatness… but this one is still figuring out the surviving
part. There are many like him on every arena. He’s a level 4 Soldier with 55 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gladiator novice fights with a &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and marks on a
hit, and can perform a &lt;strong&gt;hamstring cut&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage, knocks
prone, and slows (save ends). If an adjacent enemy stands up, the novice can
use &lt;strong&gt;Stay Down!&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to attack their Reflex and knock them back down
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book remarks that gladiators are one of the opponent types that have
in-character reasons for picking less than optimal combat options during a
fight, as long as they make for a better show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-overseer&quot;&gt;Human Overseer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first explicitly Evil stat block in this entry. The things they oversee are
the sale, transport, and daily (mis)treatment of slaves. Whether they display
malicious glee or banal apathy towards the cruelty that surrounds them, it
remains true that their job is to perpetuate it. They’re Level 9 Controllers
with the Leader tag and 96 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overseers are armed with &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Swords&lt;/strong&gt;, and they have extensive training
in psychic powers that assault and dominate the mind because of course they
do. They project a &lt;strong&gt;Mental Mire&lt;/strong&gt; around themselves (aura 2) that slows enemies
who starts their turns inside. &lt;strong&gt;Not So Fast!&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack that deals
psychic damage and pulls 3 squares. And &lt;strong&gt;Do My Bidding&lt;/strong&gt; targets one slowed
creature within 2 squares and dominates it for a turn on a hit. This one is
thankfully not at-will - it recharges when the overseer is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-slavehunter&quot;&gt;Human Slavehunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another Evil entry. Slavehunters do what it says on the tin, roaming both the
wilds and the streets looking for new people to enslave. Anyone who looks like
they’d fetch a good price and won’t put up much of a fight is fair game. They’re
Level 10 Skirmishers with 103 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This villain is armed with a &lt;strong&gt;Mace&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian-toothed Whip&lt;/strong&gt;. A hit
with the mace lets them shift 1 square. A hit with the whip pulls the target 1
square and knocks it prone. As minor actions, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Swift Pursuit&lt;/strong&gt; to
shift 3 squares (recharges when bloodied) or &lt;strong&gt;Cutting Lash&lt;/strong&gt; to inflict ongoing
10 damage (save ends) on a prone creature as an encounter power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book mentions a power named “Face Smash”, but this isn’t present on the stat
block. I guess there were some editing hiccups, and it was replaced by Cutting
Lash without any changes to the surrounding text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-templar-of-tyr&quot;&gt;Human Templar of Tyr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth Edition Dark Sun is set right after the sorcerer-king of Tyr was deposed
and killed in a violent revolution, and this book describes the city’s templars
as being “cast adrift” and only relying on “themselves and each other” to impose
their will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to me like a fancy way to say they immediately pivoted to being a
crime syndicate after losing their official authority, though I remember
something in the older 2e books about Tyr still having some templars in its
government. This stat block is Evil, so I’m guessing it represents a “loyalist”
templar who is now a mobster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This templar is a Level 10 Controller with 106 HP. It fights exclusively with
Force magic. Its basic melee attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Spear&lt;/strong&gt; that does force
damage and slides targets 1 square on a hit. The basic ranged attack is an
&lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same amount of force damage and pushes 2
squares. &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Cage&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is an Area Burst 2 spell that attacks
all creatures in the area. On a hit it restrains and deals 10 ongoing force
damage (save ends). The book says the templar is not shy about including some of
its own allies in the area if it will help them get more PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the templar’s powers explicitly mention defiling, but you could give
them a version of the next stat block’s passive trait if you wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-defiler&quot;&gt;Human Defiler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Athas, despoiling an already ravaged ecosystem is a big taboo that’s sure to
draw the ire of those who see you do it… unless you’re a sorcerer-king or a
templar, I guess. The defilers represented by this stat block are neither, but
they really want to be and think the scorn of the ignorant masses is a light
price to pay for Ultimate Cosmic Power. You could also uses these stats for a
higher-ranking templar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Human Defiler is Level 14 Artillery with 108 HP (and also Evil). It has the
&lt;strong&gt;Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait, which deals 5 necrotic damage to all enemies within
3 squares whenever the defiler uses an implement power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its only non-implement power is a &lt;strong&gt;staff&lt;/strong&gt; bonk that causes a mix of physical
and necrotic damage. The templar prefers to fight from a distance with lightning
spells. &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Lance&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic ranged attack that does lightning damage,
and &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Serpent&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that does a bit less lightning
damage but also inflicts ongoing 10 poison damage (save ends). Once per
encounter, the Defiler can use &lt;strong&gt;Dimension Door&lt;/strong&gt; to teleport 10 squares,
something it will probably use as an emergency escape measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy within 10 squares of the defiler spends a healing surge, it can
use &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Serpent&lt;/strong&gt; as a free action to regain HP equal to half the value
of the triggering surge and recharge Lightning Serpent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-mind-adept&quot;&gt;Human Mind Adept&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re out of the Evil Zone again. This is a powerful human telepath that can be
cast in any role, friendly or not: a Level 15 Controller with 145 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind adepts rely solely on their powers (and on their teammates, of course) for
defense. We start with an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Overwhelming Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt; that makes it so
any enemy that ends their turn inside cannot target the adept with an attack
until the end of their next turn. This means melee-based PCs will only be
attacking them every other turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much all of the adept’s attacks are psychic powers that target Will. For
melee, we have the &lt;strong&gt;Mind-Wracking Touch&lt;/strong&gt; dealing psychic damage and making the
target grant combat advantage for a turn. For greater ranges we have the at-will
&lt;strong&gt;Paralyzing Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5) which targets enemies, deals light psychic
damage, and immobilizes for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adept’s ultimate technique is &lt;strong&gt;Will of the Master&lt;/strong&gt;, a ranged attack that
deals no damage and dominates (save ends). While the target is dominated, it
emits harmful psychic waves: any enemy that starts their turn within 2 squares
of the target takes 5 psychic damage and is immobilized for a turn. This is an
encounter power that recharges whenever it misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the adept is reduced to 0 HP, it causes &lt;strong&gt;Mental Overload&lt;/strong&gt; in a Close
Burst 1. This targets enemies and on a hit deals psychic damage and stuns for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-blade-noble&quot;&gt;Human Blade Noble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-human-blade-noble.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A red-haired woman human wearing leather armor and holding a sheathed sword.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most powerful human in this entry is not a wizard or a psychic, but someone
who is Just That Good with a sword. Or in other words: Hello, Ms. Malenia! Fancy
meeting you here. This is a Level 17 Controller with 163 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blade noble has a trait named &lt;strong&gt;Unpredictable Flank&lt;/strong&gt; that gives them combat
advantage against any enemy adjacent to one of their allies. No need to setup a
by-the-book flanking position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Duelist’s Blade&lt;/strong&gt;, which given the context is probably one
of the few magical steel swords that still survive in Athas. Its basic attacks
do physical damage and slide the target 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dance of Blades&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rlnv_DCBEa8&quot;&gt;technique&lt;/a&gt; that reminded me of
Malenia: it attacks enemies in a Close Burst 2, deals the same damage as a basic
attack, immobilizes, and inflicts ongoing 5 damage (save ends). On a miss it
still does half damage, which is a rarity on a rechargeable attack. The noble
can shift 2 squares as an effect as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For triggered actions we have &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Parry&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that
triggers when an ally of the noble’s within 2 squares is hit by a melee or
ranged attack. As an interrupt, the noble shifts 2 squares to be adjacent to the
ally and rolls an attack using its standard bonus vs. AC. If that’s higher than
the triggering attack roll, the triggering attack misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The individual stat blocks are pretty cool, but the lore is your standard Humans
Are The Most Generic thing. In the end this ends up being a very ecletic set of
People that you can reskin as any species and any narrative role that best fits
your specific campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some more recent games have explicitly gone this route for pretty much
every humanoid NPC, giving us stat blocks based on narrative or mechanical role
(“Bandit”, “Guard”, “Brute”, “Wizard”) and then letting us assign any species as
necessary. D&amp;amp;D 4e wasn’t quite there yet, but ended up doing it by accident on
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/11/wir-dscc-human.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/11/wir-dscc-human.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
