<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 21:26:58 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 21:26:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Silk Wyrm</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-silk-wyrm.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A silk wyrm, which looks like a very large snake covered in a segmented
    green carapace, and whose grinning mouth is about three times as wide as its
    head.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silk Wyrms are snakelike monsters covered in chitinous carapaces. They’re gifted
with many natural weapons: bites laced with paralytic venom and the psionic
powers of flight, camouflage, and mesmerism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though incapable of communicating in humanoid languages they’re tenacious
endurance predators who employ clever hunting strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silk Wyrms will shadow their intended prey for days, looking for a time when its
guard is down. The book is not too specific about the nature of this prey. It
could be an adventuring party, a traveling caravan with humanoids and several
kinds of pack animal, or something like a pack of baazrags or other wild
animals. What matters is that the prey is easy to hunt and can be eaten “fresh”,
because silk wyrms apparently only eat their victims while they’re alive, and
abandon them when they die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When their intended targets are vulnerable, the silk wyrm will sneak in,
paralyze a chosen victim, and devour them on the spot. If it manages to
incapacitate more than one victim it will drag one of them to its nest, where it
will trap them in silk strands and eat them over the course of the next few days
while they’re still alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silk wyrms band together as hatchlings, but as soon as they reach the adult
stage their deeply antisocial instincts take over and they set off on their own
to become lone hunters. Only after many years do they become wise enough to
overcome this instinct and start allying with other creatures. Some manage to
lead bands of their own younger kin, while others can ally with those creatures
whose telepathy allows them to communicate with the wyrms and buy their service
with easy food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silk Wyrms are Natural Magical Beasts with the Reptile tag and Low-Light
Vision. All silk wyrms have a flight speed, but their flight is Clumsy, which
means they have a -4 penalty to attacks and defenses while on the air. This
means silk wyrms only fly to travel, but they prefer to fight on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll look at their other traits in each stat block below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silk-wyrm-hatchling&quot;&gt;Silk Wyrm Hatchling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too frail to set out on their own, hatchlings roam the wastes in bands,
spreading out to scout for prey and emitting a loud chirping noise when they
find it to call their clutch-mates. They’re Medium-sized Level 3 Minion
Skirmishers, with ground and flight speeds of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Blood Scent&lt;/strong&gt; trait means their attacks against bloodied creatures
ignore concealment. These will mostly be &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; that deal poison damage and
slow for a turn. When the hatchling hits 0 HP, they release &lt;strong&gt;Silk Strands&lt;/strong&gt; as
a last attack, which deal a bit of acid damage and restrain (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silk-wyrm-adult&quot;&gt;Silk Wyrm Adult&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their “lone hunter” phase, adults are Large-sized Level 3 Solo Skirmishers
with 174 HP. Their flight speed increases to 8, but remains clumsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults retain &lt;strong&gt;Blood Scent&lt;/strong&gt;, which works exactly the same way. They will
likely start the encounter in &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Form&lt;/strong&gt; (minor, recharges when first
bloodied), which makes Insubstantial with Phasing and gives them +5 to Stealth
while stopping it from attacking. It can get out of this with a free action, and
will do so shortly after springing its ambush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the wyrm appears in the middle of its targets, and again whenever the power
is charged, it will use &lt;strong&gt;Mesmerizing Dread&lt;/strong&gt; (minor, recharge 4+), which deals
psychic damage to enemies in a Close Burst 5, slides them 3 squares, and
inflicts a -2 penalty to all defenses for a turn. Then it’s bite time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bites&lt;/strong&gt; deal more poison damage, since they’re not minions, and their
venom becomes stronger. The target is slowed (save ends), which worsens to
immobilized (save ends) on the first save and to helpless (save ends) on the
second failure. &lt;strong&gt;Wyrm Strike&lt;/strong&gt; lets it bite two different targets with one
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helpless is a funny and very worrying condition. It’s funny because going
strictly by the book, you can move and act normally while Helpless. However
you’re never &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; Helpless. The most common way to get this condition is to be
unconscious. In this case, even on a strict reading you’ll still be Restrained
when you fail your second save and become Helpless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being Helpless is worrying because it makes the victim grant combat advantage,
and opens them up to the Coup de Grace action, which is an attack with any
applicable power that auto-crits and kills the target outright if it deals more
than their bloodied value in damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Silk Wyrm manages to get someone immobilized, restrained, or helpless, it
will &lt;strong&gt;Feed&lt;/strong&gt; on them, attacking their Fortitide eating one of their healing
surges, and healing 10 HP. There’s no damage other than this, apparently, which
makes this attack a lot more forgiving in a fight than it would otherwise seem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It someone hits the adult wyrm with a melee or close attack, it can respond with
&lt;strong&gt;Silk Strands&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This is a melee 3 attack vs. Reflex, dealing
acid damage and restraining on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silk-worm-elder&quot;&gt;Silk Worm Elder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elders have lived long enough to learn the value of teamwork despite or perhaps
&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of the loss of their ability to project silk strands in combat. They
band together with one another or with other powerful allies in order to survive
and keep eating. They’re Level 14 Skirmishers with 125 HP. Not being solos, they
don’t have a blanked +5 on all saves, but they still have that bonus on saves
against Immobilized or Slowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shadow Form&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Mesmerizing Dread&lt;/strong&gt; work exactly the same, with Shadow
Form just making the wyrm Weakened instead of preventing attacks entirely. They
can only &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; once per turn but their venom remains as potent as the
adult’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here is the damage: both Mesmerizing Dread and the basic bite do
exactly the same damage as the adult’s, which is way, way below what it should
be for a level 14 monster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feed&lt;/strong&gt;, on the other hand, does a huge chunk of physical damage (5d10+6) in
addition to deleting a healing surge. It recharges when first bloodied instead
of being at-will, but it no longer has any target restictions. They still really
want to use this in a helpless target if they can, because it’s going to kill
any helpless target with 112 maximum HP or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, outside of their one or two uses of Feed, elders are significantly less
scary. The venom is still a concern, particularly if they have heavy hitters
with them, but barring errata it seems to me elders were made to rush in, use
Feed once or twice, and escape the fight using Shadow Form and &lt;strong&gt;Serpent
Strike&lt;/strong&gt;, which they still have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the Lore section outlines possible silk wyrm encounters pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, the first two seem okay to me, but the elder is weird. The damage
of their bites and Mesmerizing stare needs a buff. It’d make them more
consistently dangerous despite making their Feed attack a little less impressive
in comparison (as its 28 average damage is not a lot higher than the 22 their
bites would need).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/10/04/wir-dscc-silk-wyrm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/10/04/wir-dscc-silk-wyrm.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Creature Catalog: Sand Bride</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-sand-bride.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A sand bride, which looks like a pretty lady lounging in an illusory oasis
    that hides a sandstorm.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wouldn’t be a proper D&amp;amp;D monster book without at least one vile seductress
that tries to lure in unsuspecting adventurers with her womanly wiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sand Brides are basically Darker and Sunnier Nymphs. More specifically, they are
the things this world’s surviving nymphs turned into when the ecosystem went to
shit and the Feywild was mostly destroyed. Like a lot of other Athasian fey,
they blame all intelligent natural creatures for their corrupted state, and try
to victimize them as an act of vengeance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their preferred tactic is to build traps and ambush spots out in the desert and
use their illusion powers to disguise them as safe places like oases, sheltering
ruins, or caravan rest stops. Then they disguise themselves as harmless
humanoids and try to lure their targets to the ambush. The illustration and some
of the descriptions imply these “harmless humanoids” are pretty ladies, but they
don’t have to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the victims are at the intended spot, the ambush is sprung, and the sand
bride will use her sand-bending powers and dehydrating touch to kill the
victims, leaving only dried husks behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sand Brides are Medium Fey Humanoids and Level 10 Elite Controllers with an even
200 HP. Despite being living beings they have Darkvision and are immune to
disease and poison, traits commonly found in undead. Their ground speed is 8,
and they have a burrow speed of 6. This &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; say it’s for loose earth only,
so they could theoretically tunnel through rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Sandform Body&lt;/strong&gt; lets them ignore all difficult terrain, tough they’re
less diffuse than the dune constructs we saw previously. They attack in melee
with a &lt;strong&gt;Dehydrating Touch&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic damage and inflicts -2 to all
defenses for a turn on a hit. At range, they use &lt;strong&gt;Sand Blasts&lt;/strong&gt; that deal
physical damage and push 4 squares. &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; lets them make two melee
attacks per action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also employ a &lt;strong&gt;Sand Drown&lt;/strong&gt; power (recharge 5+) if the PCs bunch up
too much. This is an Area 1 Within 10 attack, dealing heavy physical damage and
restraining on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its ability to create illusory terrain is weaponized as an &lt;strong&gt;Insidious Mirage&lt;/strong&gt;
(Encounter), which lets the Sand Bride create a zone 4 squares on a side that
lasts until the end of the encounter. This counts as difficult terrain for
enemies, lets the bride slide enemies who end their turns inside by up to 2
squares as a free action, and can be moved by up to 4 squares as minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally they have &lt;strong&gt;Deceptive Veil&lt;/strong&gt;, allowing them to appear as a humanoid
of any species. Piercing the illusion requires an Insight contest against the
bride’s Bluff skill of +15. This doesn’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be a pretty lady, but it’s
apparently traditional. The bride’s stats remain the same while disguised, and
she can attack without dropping the illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sand brides target groups of travelers The creatures are fairly social with each
other and will organize in groups. They can probably ally with other fey too, or
have some Athasian beasts under their control ready to attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not overly fond of vile seductress monsters but sand brides seem easy to
reskin into something less cliche while keeping the same tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/10/02/wir-dscc-sand-bride.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/10/02/wir-dscc-sand-bride.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Rampager</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-rampager.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A rampager, which look like a big green kaiju with a human-like face.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures were known as so-ut in olden times, but most people found that
name wasn’t very descriptive, so now they’re known as Rampagers. And they do
what it says on the tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True, that doesn’t narrow it down by a lot given that we just looked at
Nightmare Beasts, which are also big rampaging monsters. But there are some
important differences: Nightmare Beasts are hateful monsters twisted by the
energies of the Gray who hate all living things; Rampagers are hateful monsters
twisted by vengeful primal spirits who hate all artifice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, they’ll kill anything that gets in their way, but the thing they really
hate are buildings and other constructed signs of civilization. The cloud of
angry elementals that constantly surrounds these creatures fills them with rage
and drives them to seek these things out and utterly destroy them with their
acidic claws. Ruins or new buildings, it doesn’t matter. They will all be razed
to their foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who can’t take on a Rampager in direct combat (i.e, most Athasians) might
have a chance to avoid a deadly confrontation by placating the immaterial
spirits that surround the creature via rituals or diplomacy, convincing them to
direct their weapon elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Rampager is a Large Elemental Beast and a Level 21 Solo Brute with 800 HP. It
has Darkvision and a ground speed of 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The angry spirits surrounding the so-ut aren’t modeled as separate creatures and
cannot be targeted in combat, but I think they might be the source of its
&lt;strong&gt;Entropic Presence&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2), which &lt;em&gt;strips immunities and resistances&lt;/em&gt; from
all creatures and objects within. I believe that does include most of the
inherent immunities objects have (such as to poison and necrotic damage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rampager also has two other passive traits: &lt;strong&gt;Destruction’s Storm&lt;/strong&gt; boosts
its damage while bloodied, and &lt;strong&gt;Soul of Destruction&lt;/strong&gt; boosts it even more
against constructs, objects, and structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its active attacks start with acid-laced Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which deal a hearty
blend of physical and acid damage and penalize AC by -1 until the end of the
encounter on a hit. This accumulates to a maximum of -5. And to top it off they
have the High Crit property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; is Reach 2 and targets Reflex, and seems weak at first, but that’s
just the primary attack. If that hits, the creature makes a secondary attack
against the target’s Fortitude, which weakens and inflicts 30 ongoing poison
damage on a hit (save ends). Entropic Presence makes this as effective against
structures and objects as it would be against flesh and blood enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our last attack is the one that gives the Rampager its name: &lt;strong&gt;Destructive
Rampage&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will power that lets it make three claw and one bite attack
in any order. At most 2 attacks can be directed at the same target, and the
monster can shift 2 squares after each one as an effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Rampager is first bloodied, and again when it drops to 0 HP, it can use
Destructive Rampage as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I wasn’t as impressed by the Rampager’s lore since it comes right after
the Nightmare Beast and the Psurlon, but it’s very in theme for Athas. You could
also easily reskin it as a sort of tarrasque spawn, since both follow similar
themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, I think all the mechanics that combine to make it a menace against
constructs and structures are really cool. I can easily see an adventure where
PCs must somehow direct a rampager to fight something like the Dark Sun version
of the Wandering Tower (originally from Threats to the Nentir Vale). And of
course, if this thing ever meets a Nightmare Beast meet, they’re going to fight,
and while the Rampager as written might not win that one without PC help it can
serve as an important distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book clearly intends for Rampagers to be found alone, since as mentioned
above the spirit cloud is more of an special effect than a separate creature,
mechanically. Nothing stops you from adding some actual epic level elementals to
the encounter if your PCs are higher level, though.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/30/wir-dscc-rampager.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/30/wir-dscc-rampager.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Psurlon</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-psurlon.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A psurlon, which look like a gray-skinned centipede centaur with scythe-like
    forearms and a xenomorh-style head.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, in a world far, far away, there was a civilization whose
mastery of psionics was so complete they decided to merge their entire
population into a single collective god-mind. They failed, and the backlash
destroyed their planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survivors managed to escape to the Astral Sea, but only as disembodied
consciences. There, they came upon another world that radiated vast amounts of
psychic energy, comparable to their old home. The survivors were drawn to it
like moths to a flame, piercing the barriers that surrounded this new world and
taking over a species of worm that turned out to be particularly receptive to
their minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the following generations, these planar refugees would shape their hosts to
be more useful to their mysterious purposes, and would come to prefer their new
bodies over their old humanoid forms. And this is how the psurlons came to be,
though no one in Athas really knows the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some psurlons reside in the Gray, amid the graves of the gods. Many others live
in Athas itself, where they often take human form to infiltrate and spy on the
city-states of the sorcerer-kings, working towards some mysterious goal of their
own. Psurlons are an old people with long memories and extremely advanced
psionic skills, so sometimes they’ll be sought out by powerful psychics,
spellcasters, and historians willing to risk their lives to bargain for
knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psurlons are Medium Aberrant Magical Beasts. They have resistance to psychic
damage, a burrow speed, and Tremorsense, though the exact values on these traits
vary per stat block. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Armored Mind&lt;/strong&gt;, a passive
trait that lets them roll saves against domination both at the start and end of
their turns, even if the condition doesn’t normally end with a save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;psurlon-dustworm&quot;&gt;Psurlon Dustworm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dustworms are specialized infiltrators, disguising themselves as humanoids to
spy on the city-states and on the comings and goings of the
sorcerer-kings. They’re Level 17 Skirmishers with 164 HP. Their ground and
burrow speeds are 8, and they have 5 psychic resistance and Tremorsense 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dustworm can &lt;strong&gt;Change Shape&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action to appear as a
humanoid. Others need to pass a DC 36 Insight check to detect the
deception. Most dustworms encountered by PCs will start out disguised, and will
do their best to maintain cover until there is no other alternative. Then, they
take their natural shapes and fight, likely attempting to escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to Armored Mind, they also project a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Deadpool&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 5),
which inflicts -2 on enemy saves against ongoing psychic damage. They can attack
in melee with their &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which damage and deal ongoing 5 psychic damage
(save ends). At range, they fling &lt;strong&gt;Mindknives&lt;/strong&gt; which deal psychic damage and
forbid the target from making opportunity attacks for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these attacks can be boosted by &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augment&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers
after one of them hits and lets them deal an extra 2d6 psychic damage. This
recharges when the dustworm takes psychic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can use a &lt;strong&gt;Burrowing Attack&lt;/strong&gt; to burrow half their speed, attack someone
with a claw, and then burrow the other half of their speed. This is strangely
precise phrasing compared to the other “moving attack” skills we have seen so
far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;psurlon-warworm&quot;&gt;Psurlon Warworm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warworms cannot change shape, possibly because they’re Huge instead of
Medium. They defend psurlon settlements and stay hidden underground near
infiltrators, waiting to burst out when things go pear-shaped. They’re Level 18
Elite Brutes with 424 HP. Their ground and burrow speeds are 6, their
Tremorsense is 20, and their psychic resistance is 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; deals heavy damage and inflicts ongoing 5 psychic damage (save
ends), and &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; lets them bite twice per action. Once per
encounter, they can let out a &lt;strong&gt;Mind Scream&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks enemies in a Close
Burst 2. A hit deals heavy psychic damage and stuns for a turn. Nasty! A miss
deals half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;psurlon-mindworm&quot;&gt;Psurlon Mindworm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindworms are powerful seers, able to see many futures at once. They guide their
fellow psurlons to the ones most favorable to their secret objectives. Mindworms
are Level 19 Controllers with 181 HP. Their movement speed is 6, they have 10
Psychic resistance, and Tremorsense 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their additional passive is a &lt;strong&gt;Whispering Meme&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that lets the
mindworm slide enemies that start their turns within 1 square. I guess the
mysterious whispers of “this is fine” and “always has been” drive enemies to
distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mindworm will probably start the fight at range and attempt to use &lt;strong&gt;Ego
Control&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) on a PC. This deals a sizable chunk of psychic damage
and dominates on a hit (save ends). Then they’ll close in to melee range and
alternate between &lt;strong&gt;Referred Pain&lt;/strong&gt; and their &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Claws&lt;/strong&gt;. The first power
is a Close Burst 2 that deals psychic damage and slows for a turn; the other is
a basic attack that deals a mix of psychic and physical damage and inflicts -2
to AC for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindworms can also &lt;strong&gt;Change Shape&lt;/strong&gt; and use &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augment&lt;/strong&gt;, both of which
work just like the dustworm’s, but with higher numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot here that reminds me of mind flayers, but I think I actually like
psurlons better. With mind flayers, you know they want to eat your brain, and
most PCs will start drawing their weapons as soon as they spot one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psurlons have a much more mysterious goal, so they can more easily fill the
“mysterious but dangerous stranger” role instead of always being overtly
hostile. Heck, PCs might want to ally with them against a sorcerer-king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, they do employ a lot of the same tactics as flayers, including
keeping large groups of dominated thralls around to help compose mixed encounter
groups.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/28/wir-dscc-psurlon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/28/wir-dscc-psurlon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Nightmare Beast</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-nightmare-beast.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A rampaging nightmare beast with a doomed human spearman for scale. The
    spearman looks tiny.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nightmare Beasts are among the most feared horrors to walk the surface of Athas,
second only to the Dragon of Tyr itself. The mere presence of a nightmare beast
poisons the surrounding land and contaminates its water. This seems to be a
continuous defiling effect - and the beasts can defile further to fuel their
powers. The description also makes me think they might be &lt;em&gt;radioactive&lt;/em&gt;, if you
want to inject some science fantasy into your campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sages can only speculate as to their origin. The leading theory is that they
were summoned from the Gray by powerful defilers during an age in the distant
past where war raged all over the world. Fully grown beasts are solitary, but
smaller versions can be seen hanging out in packs with each other or with other
predatory animals. Those same sages theorize these are young beasts, born
through natural reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything about the preceding paragraph is wrong, however. Nightmare beasts
form when one of the many natural predators of Athas consumes too much prey from
areas tainted by the Gray or marked by heavy defiling. The creature begins to
slowly mutate. It acquires intelligence, power, and a hatred for all living
things, becoming a nightmare beast when the metamorphosis is complete. The
“spawn” are merely beasts whose transformation is still ongoing. Fully
transformed beasts are solitary. Partially-mutated spawn still display behaviors
reminiscent of their previous form, which is why they can be found in packs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nightmare beast lairs tend to be pretty obvious and imposing landmarks at the
center of a horribly corrupted region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nightmare Beasts are Shadow Magical Beasts with Darkvision. We get stat blocks
for both spawn and fully transformed specimens. Both can invade people’s dreams
and use magical black lightning as a weapon, in addition to having very large
and sharp tusks, but the effects of all of these vary per stat block. We’ll see
them from weaker to stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the GM’s option, beasts poison the area around them when they die. The area
within 10 squares of a full beast’s corpse become Defiled Terrain (a hazard
described at the end of the book). Spawn also do this, but the area is only 5
squares in radius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nightmare-beast-spawn&quot;&gt;Nightmare Beast Spawn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, “spawn” is a misleading name. This Large creature was
formerly a more mundane Athasian predator who is currently in the process of
mutating into a nightmare beast. It will kinda resemble the animal it once was,
but is already clearly unnatural. Spawn are Level 16 Elite Artillery with 244
HP. Their ground speed is 8 and they also have Burrow and Climb speeds
of 4. Maybe this was a megapede?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creature’s basic melee attack uses its &lt;strong&gt;Tusks&lt;/strong&gt; (Melee 2), which damage and
slide the target 2 squares on a hit. Its favorite tactic, however, is to hang
back and rain &lt;strong&gt;Black Lightning&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 20) upon its foes. This attack
vs. Reflex targets one or two victims. On a hit it deals “lightning and
necrotic” damage, and ongoing 5 necrotic damage (save ends). This worsens to 10
ongoing on the first failed save, and to &lt;em&gt;unconsciousness&lt;/em&gt; (save ends) on the
second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spawn can further torment its unconscious victims with &lt;strong&gt;Horrid Nightmares&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor action, recharge 6+, Ranged 10), which deal psychic damage and prevent
the target from rolling saves for a turn on a hit. Yeah the spawn can
potentially lock a PC down once they’re unconscious from Black Lightning. This
also works if they manage to sneak up on their victims while they sleep, though
the spawn might not yet be clever enough to think of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a target steps into the spawn’s melee reach, it can use its &lt;strong&gt;Barbed Tongue&lt;/strong&gt;
(Melee 3) as a reaction. This attack vs Fortitude deals necrotic damage on a hit
and prevents the target from regaining HP for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nightmare-beast&quot;&gt;Nightmare Beast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fully mutated beast is size Huge, and a Level 25 Solo Controller with 928
HP. In other words, it’s a kaiju. This specimen is stronger than the spawn in
every way, from physical weapons all the way to psychic and magical powers. Its
ground speed is just 6, though, with no other movement modes. It likes to use
its magic to torment its victims, but once it gets injured it will drop the mind
games and get physical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beast has no less than &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; basic attacks, all Melee 3 and each with a
different rider: &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; that slide 3 squares, &lt;strong&gt;Tusks&lt;/strong&gt; that knock prone, and
a &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; that grabs the target if the beast hasn’t grabbed anyone yet. Each of
those of course also does respectable damage. &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; lets the beast
pick any two of those to use on the same action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Fury&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) becomes available while the beast is
bloodied. It lets the creature move its speed and use a claw/claw/tusk/bite
combo at any point along the movement, using up to two attacks against each
target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the beast is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bloodied, it can instead use its &lt;strong&gt;Black Lightning&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 4+). This version targets 1 or 2 creatures in a Close Burst 5, and on
a hit inflicts ongoing &lt;em&gt;30&lt;/em&gt; lightning and necrotic damage (save ends). Each
creature adjacent to one of the targets takes 20 lightning and necrotic damage
when the target is hit, as well. The targets fall unconscious right on the first
failed saving throw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the beast misses a target while using Black Lightning, it can use its
&lt;strong&gt;Hideous Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; to attack every enemy in a Close Burst 2, dealing a chunk
of necrotic damage on a hit. A hit also allows it to reroll the missed Black
Lightning attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether bloodied or not, the beast can inflict &lt;strong&gt;Horrid Nightmares&lt;/strong&gt; on
unsconscious targets just like its less-developed counterpart, with better
damage. It can also use &lt;strong&gt;Dream Step&lt;/strong&gt; at will, teleporting 15 squares to a
space adjacent to an unconscious creature!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full beasts will usually be found alone, as they kill anything else they can
perceive. A GM who wishes to add more spice to this solo encounter could add
powerful undead minions. The beast might tolerate their presence since they
aren’t living creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spawn could be found in groups, either with each other or still hanging around
their packs as the transformation proceeds. Eventually the day comes when they
complete the transformation and slay their packmates.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/26/wir-dscc-nightmare-beast.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/26/wir-dscc-nightmare-beast.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Mul</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-mul.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A mul rebel about to bash some slaver&apos;s skull in with a rock.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text for this entry sounds really fucking racist. It can’t decide whether to
talk about muls as if they were non-sapient animals or whether to stick to the
old “stupid and brutal savage” cliches. Therefore, I’ll paraphrase and summarize
it more aggressively than I do most other entries, and also pull stuff from the
much more even-handed text in the Campaign Guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muls are half-dwarves, born from the union of a human and a dwarf. They’re
taller than humans on average, and combine dwarven strength and endurance with
human physical and mental agility. Most muls are born into slavery, as they were
originally a sorcerer-king eugenics project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muls resent slavery just as much as anyone else, and their strong wills and
bodies usually often put them in a position to do something about it. They often
rebel and turn on their oppressors, and you can find communities of free muls
making a life out in the wastes and organizing to strike back at the
sorcerer-kings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their aptitude for resistance, muls are popular as gladiators, which
means a lot of them receive combat training from their enslavers. Most muls the
PCs encounter will have some degree of skill at fighting, and free individuals
often go on to work as mercenaries and bodyguards because of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muls are Medium Natural Humanoids with a ground speed of 6. Their signature
trait is the same &lt;strong&gt;Incredible Toughness&lt;/strong&gt; mul PCs get. Once per encounter, at
the start of their turns, they can automatically end a ongoing damage effect or
the dazed, slowed, stunned, or weakened conditions. This applies both to (save
ends) effects, and to those that would last until the end of the turn, which
makes this ability really useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mul-gladiator&quot;&gt;Mul Gladiator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trained and forced to fight in the arena, the mul gladiator is head and
shoulders above his human rivals both literally and in terms of skill. He’s a
Level 4 Elite Soldier with 112 HP. He wields a &lt;strong&gt;warhammer&lt;/strong&gt; and can use a
&lt;strong&gt;Double Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver to attack twice in the same action, knocking the
target prone if both attacks hit. If an adjacent prone enemy stands up, the
gladiator can use a &lt;strong&gt;Pursuing Shove&lt;/strong&gt; to attack their Fortitude. On a hit, he
pushes the target 3 squares and shifts 3 squares to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mul-chainfighter&quot;&gt;Mul Chainfighter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could represent a more experienced gladiator or bodyguard, or a free
agent like a mercenary. It’s a Level 8 Brute with 106 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chainfighter wields a &lt;strong&gt;Cahulaks&lt;/strong&gt; as their main weapon. This is a Dark Sun
weapon introduced in the Campaign Guide: a length of chain with barbed
grappling hooks on either end. Its attacks have Reach 2, or Reach 1 if the
chainfighter has a creature grabbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grabs happen via the &lt;strong&gt;Ensnaring Tines&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver, a Reach 2 attack that pulls
the target 1 square and grabs them if they end up adjacent to the mul, who can
grab at most one victim at a time in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the grabbed victim attempts to escape and fails, the chainfighter can use
&lt;strong&gt;Wicked Ensnarement&lt;/strong&gt; (vs. Fortitude) as a reaction. On a hit, this deals a bit
of damage and knocks the target prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mul-savage&quot;&gt;Mul Savage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This unfortunately-named stat block is meant to represent a free mul that is
used to surviving in the wastes. It’s a Level 9 Brute with 120 HP and the Leader
tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tag is justified by the &lt;strong&gt;Furious Inspiration&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) projected by the
mul. Whenever an ally inside the aura becomes bloodied they can make a melee
basic attack as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This warrior fights with a &lt;strong&gt;Bone-Studded Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt;, whose attacks damage and
knock prone on a hit. When first bloodied, his &lt;strong&gt;Bloodied Fury&lt;/strong&gt; lets him make
the same attack against every enemy in a Close Burst 1, additionally pushing
them 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mul-champion&quot;&gt;Mul Champion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prominent figure in the rebel movements against the sorcerer-king, champions
inspire others to take up the fight through their deeds. Like the chainfighter,
the champion wields cahulaks, but they’re a lot more skilled with the
weapon. Champions are Level 17 Soldiers with 167 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Cahulaks&lt;/strong&gt; attack works exactly like the chainfighter’s, with
better numbers. Their &lt;strong&gt;Snagging Tines&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver is Reach 2 and grabs on a hit,
but it &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; pull: the champion can maintain a grab at up to
Reach 2. &lt;strong&gt;Swinging Hook&lt;/strong&gt; (Encounter) lets them slide a grabbed target 4
squares as an effect, maintaining the grab if the target is within 2 squares of
the champion at the end of the movement. At the end of the movement the champion
makes an attack both against the grabbed target and an enemy adjacent to that
target, damaging and knocking them prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the &lt;strong&gt;Champion’s Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; marks every enemy in a Close Burst 2
for a turn. If a marked enemy makes an attack that doesn’t target the champion,
they open themselves to a &lt;strong&gt;Wicked Parry&lt;/strong&gt;, a reach 2 interrupt that damages and
inflicts a -2 penalty to the triggering attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book completes its collection of fantasy racism cliches by stating that
neither humans nor dwarves like muls very much. Nevertheless, they can be found
in Mixed Groups of People as bodyguards, enforcers, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the stat blocks because they’re relatively simple and each has One Neat
Trick. Shame about the fluff, but as you saw it’s relatively easy to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/25/wir-dscc-mul.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/25/wir-dscc-mul.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Mekillot</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-mekillot.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A mekillot, which looks like a hill-sized lizard/pillbug hybrid.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hill-sized cutie pies are a kind of drake, but they differ enough from
their elementally aligned relatives that they deserve their own entry. In the
wild, these giant armored beasts roam the wastes in small herds, eating plants
and the occasional small animal and laying their eggs near oases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mekillots are not voracious predators other drakes, but they’re still aggressive
and stubborn in the same way a real-life large herbivore like a rhino or hippo
can be. While their size and armor makes them prime beasts of burden and war,
they need to either be trained for these roles from birth or be kept under tight
psychic control at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sorcerer-kings and other defilers think the mekillot’s natural size and
aggressiveness isn’t lethal enough, and perform bioengineering rituals on their
unhatched eggs to make the resulting creature even bigger and stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mekillots are Natural Beasts with the Reptile and Mount tags. They have no
special senses or vulnerabilities. Everything else varies per stat block, and we
get two here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mekillot&quot;&gt;Mekillot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical member of the species is Huge, and has a ground speed of 7. It’s a
Level 10 Soldier with 108 HP. Its basic attack is a Reach 1 &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
extra damage to grabbed targets. It can grab them with a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue
Lash&lt;/strong&gt;, which attacks Fortitude. On a hit it pulls the target 2 squares, damages
and grabs them. The mekillot can only have one target grabbed like this, but it
can keep biting them for increased damage as described above while the grab
lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mekillots used as mounts are trained to perform a &lt;strong&gt;Checking Charge&lt;/strong&gt;. This
lets them perform a charge that can go through enemy spaces, and each time they
do so they automatically push the enemy 1 square and knock them prone. At the
end of the charge, in addition to the usual attack from the mekillot, its rider
can also make a melee basic attack as a free action. This is an excellent fight
opener, since the push-and-knock-prone effect doesn’t require an attack. It lets
the mekillot and its rider go straight to the PC squishies in the back line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mekillot-dirk&quot;&gt;Mekillot Dirk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably a mekillot mutated by defiling magic to be even bigger. It’s
Gargantuan in size, a little slower at Speed 6, and a Level 22 Elite Soldier
with 418 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dirk is big enough to have &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Reach 2&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as a &lt;strong&gt;Wide
Body&lt;/strong&gt; that lets other creatures enter and end their move in its space. This
means they’re standing on its back – and that the slope is gentle enough to not
require climbing checks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dirk’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; works just like that of the standard mekillot, though its
numbers are of course bigger. It can also attack with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, which
target 1 or 2 creatures. On a hit they deal damage, pull the target 1 square,
and knock it prone. Its Tongue Lash has been upgraded to a Reach 4 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue
Chomp&lt;/strong&gt;, which works identically but also allows the creature to make a free
bite attack against the target after pulling it to an adjacent square. This
effectively makes this maneuver a double attack. The text says the tongue only
pulls the victim 1 square, but I think that’s an error: it should be 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checking Charge upgrades to &lt;strong&gt;Trample&lt;/strong&gt;, which doesn’t require a rider. This
lets the mekillot shift twice its speed, enter enemy spaces during the move, and
make free claw attacks against any enemy whose space it enters in this way. So
it’s not &lt;em&gt;guaranteed&lt;/em&gt; to knock the whole PC party prone any more, but those it
does knock prone will be worse off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re either going to meet a small herd of wild mekillot, 2-3 of them being
used as war mounts by humanoid soliers or brutes, or a mekillot dirk being used
as an armored personal carrier by epic-level artillery and controller villains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their mechanics are workable enough, but what really endears mekillots to me is
this illustration. They look like marketable plushies even though they’re likely
to trample you to death.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/24/mekillot.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/24/mekillot.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 03: The New Order</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2025/08/04/guns-of-wolfenstein-02.html&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; of this series, we took a look at the guns that appear on
Wolfenstein: The Old Blood, whose timeline I named “Wolfenstein-2” for ease of
reference. The timeline from the 2001 game, whose guns I talked about [here][2],
was Wolfenstein-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we will take a look at the weapons that appear in Wolfenstein: The New
Order, a game that was published &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; The Old Blood (2014) but whose stories
starts right when The Old Blood ends. We’ll also make some mentions to the last
game in the trilogy, The New Colossus (from 2017) but the weapons that make
their debut in that game will be presented in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-order-plot-overview-contains-spoilers&quot;&gt;The New Order Plot Overview (Contains Spoilers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this game was launched a year earlier, its story starts off right after
The Old Blood ends, in 1946. After B. J. Blaskowicz returns to the Allies with
the location of General Deathshead’s secret hideout, they mount a massive attack
on that island fortress. This is a higher-budget version of the final chapters
of the 2001 game, which ended with Deathshead’s defeat, but things don’t that
well here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack is a disaster. Deathshead kills most of B.J.’s unit and leaves the
rest of them to die in a deathtrap. The survivors manage to escape just as the
room they’re in explodes, but the explosion buries a large piece of shrapnel in
Blazko’s brain. He washes ashore somewhere in Poland, catatonic, and since no
one knows who he is, gets sent to an asylum. He spends the next 14 years there
slowly recovering, with nearly no motor function, slipping in and out of comas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Nazi attack on the asylum in 1960 gives him the impulse he needs to complete
his recovery, and the first actual level of the game is escaping that situation
with a nurse named Anna, the other survivor of the place. They reach Anna’s
grandparents, where Blazko learns that the Nazis won the war in 1948, and that
as far as everyone knows the last members of the resistance had been captured
and sent to an “inescapable” prison in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the game is about freeing these prisoners, rebuilding the
resistance, and striking back at Deathshead through a series of daring
heists. These start with the rescue of good-guy super-scientist Seth Roth&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,
and proceed with the the capture of a giant enemy submarine, the recovery of its
nuclear launch codes from a Nazi base on the Moon, and finally an attack on
Deathshead’s fortress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blazko manages to kill Deathshead during the second attack on his fortress,
though the asshole manages to detonate a grenade as he dies. The game ends as
B. J., too wounded to evacuate, gives his allies the all-clear to launch the
nuke that will destroy this fortress for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guns&quot;&gt;The Guns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the guns here are, again, captured Nazi hardware. And
those, in turn, are “new and improved” versions of the guns we saw in The Old
Blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their actual mechanics and list of available weapons changes a bit between this
game and its sequel in ways that can be better explained by changes in artistic
and gameplay direction than by in-setting developments. The weapons presented
here are based partially on a melding of their two versions, and partially on
what I’d think would be more interesting for a GURPS Action game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post focuses on the weapons that make their first appearance in The New
Order. The next one will present the ones that first appear in The New Colossus,
using the same adaptation strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m omitting price information as usual. In a Wolfenstein-inspired game, PCs
will be picking these up from the corpses of their enemies. In other games, the
GM can figure out a price based on the prices of similar real-world weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pistols&quot;&gt;Pistols&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pistol-model-1960&quot;&gt;Pistol Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A direct descendant of the 1946 model, this one has a more futuristic look, a
double-stacked 20-round magazine, and the ability to fire 3-round bursts. It
still takes the same cinematic silencer. As before, it adds -1 to Bulk, makes
the gun cinematically silent, and also makes it only able to fire in semi-auto
mode (RoF 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If using standard GURPS skills, you need Guns (Pistol) to fire in semi-auto
mode, and Guns (SMG) to fire bursts. If using the optional skills from Pyramid
#3/65, you need Guns (Pistol), with the Burst-Fire technique for firing bursts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Pistol 1960&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;160/1800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1.4kg/0.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-arms&quot;&gt;Long Arms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the standard system, use the Guns skill that corresponds to their description
(SMG, Shotgun, Rifle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using the alternate skills from Pyramid #3/65, they all use Guns (Long
Arm), of course. The Burst-Fire technique helps fire weapons at a RoF greater
than 3 without penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;american-submachine-gun&quot;&gt;American Submachine Gun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much a historical &lt;strong&gt;Thompson M1A1&lt;/strong&gt;, described in p. HT122. The
Allies mostly didn’t have access to superscience in this timeline and were
limited to historical equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allied soldiers are armed with this during the 1946 assault on Deathshead’s
compound, and the game expects you to use them for the handful of minutes
between the start of gameplay and the moment when you first grab an enemy
weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assault-rifle-model-1960&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evolution of the 1946 model, it’s lighter and uses a double-stacked 45 round
magazine, but still fires the same round. The biggest change here is an
underbarrel accessory rail that can take a mini-rocket launcher, which appears
as an upgrade midway through the game. This is detailed in the Launchers
section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-1960&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This semi-automatic rifle is about the same length as the AR, but fires a
heftier round (likely 7.92x57mm) from a 10-round magazine. It has an integral
scope. It’s a relatively rare find both in the hands of enemies and as
loot. Clearly the Nazis are bigger fans of the spray-and-pray approach to
marksmanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extended 30-round magazine is available: Shots 30+1(3), Weight becomes
6.2kg/1.05kg. The gun can also fire APHC rounds: Dam 6d+2(2) pi-.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shockhammer-model-1960&quot;&gt;Shockhammer Model 1960&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another descendant of the gun from The Old Blood, this one uses a “snail drum”
magazine and a single barrel to achieve better performance than its
predecessor. The most commonly available shells for the weapon are standard
buckshot, and “shrapnel”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shrapnel shells fire red-hot fragments that ricochet off walls in a very
video-gamey way, allowing the player to hit enemies behind cover or around
corners by bouncing the shrapnel off the wall behind them. The shotgun can only
fire in semi-auto mode while using these shells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the GURPS version below, I’m treating shrapnel as Multi-Flechette shells
(High-Tech p. 174) with an incendiary effect. Damage becomes 1d+1 pi- inc; Range
becomes 100/1200; RoF becomes 3x20. GMs who wish to replicate the ricochet
effect can reduce the penalty for firing at targets behind cover when there are
suitable surfaces nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the GM’s discretion, any special shells listed in High Tech and Ultra-Tech
might also be available for this shotgun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;long-arms-table&quot;&gt;Long Arms Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Thompson M1A1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+1 pi+&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;170/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.1kg/0.8kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;30+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;MP-61&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d pi-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;170/1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.1kg/0.4kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;45+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/3100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;45+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;850/3750&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg/0.35kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shockhammer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1d+1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.1kg/1.05kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6x9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;energy-weapons&quot;&gt;Energy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a surprising amount of energy weapons in both games. All of these use
Beam Weapons (Rifle) unless noted otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laser weapons in this setting draw power from internal batteries that can’t be
removed without disassembling the weapon. The usual method of reloading them is
by using one of the highly dangerous industrial power outlets that seem to be
everywhere in Nazi-dominated cities and facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In The New Order, these use short-ranged wireless power transfer. In The New
Colossus, they use a thick cable with a plug that resembles a gas station
pump. I suggest picking an aesthethic and sticking to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wireless Charging&lt;/strong&gt;: The wielder must stay within 2 meters of the outlet
during the process, which causes lightning to arc between the outlet and the
weapon’s power receptors. Doing anything with the weapon other than holding it
steady will interrupt the recharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wired Charging&lt;/strong&gt;: The wielder must plug the cable into the weapon (1 Ready
Action), and then stay within 1 meter of the outlet. The weapon cannot be used
while charging. Once charging is done, it takes another Ready maneuver to unplug
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recharge time is listed for each weapon, and has more to do with the weapon’s
ability to absorb incoming power than with the outlet’s ability to provide it!
The later seems to be effectively limitless, at least on a personal scale. Yes,
these things are extremely unsafe. What happens if you stab someone with the
wired plug or intercept them with the arc of the wireless charger is left as an
exercise for the GM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some places you can also find portable batteries that can be used to top up a
weapon through a similar process. The GM will say how many shots from a weapon
an individual battery can recharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;lunar-laser-rifle&quot;&gt;Lunar Laser Rifle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Moonbase level of The New Order, everyone carries a laser weapon with the
same external appearance as the Marksman Rifle. It lacks a scope, and can fire
in full-auto mode. Its performance seems to be about on par with the assault
rifle, though it is a lot better at dealing with heavily-armored
enemies. Industrial outlets recharge it at 3 shots per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite being a laser weapon based on the Marksman Rifle, Nazi soldiers don’t
usually use Aim maneuvers with it, so they are no more accurate than usual when
wielding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t exist in The New Colossus, not even on Venus. Maybe it was a pet
project of Deathshead’s for the moon base, and got phased out when he died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-combined&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle (Combined)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you return to Earth after the Moonbase level, B.J.’s Marksman Rifle becomes
a combination gadget of sorts, with the scope on a hinged mount. With the mount
closed and the scope in place, it fires bullets as before. With the scope folded
away, it behaves like the Moonbase laser rifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This design is probably more of a video game quality of life decision than
something feasible in setting, but if you want to include it in your campaigns
you can treat it as a Combination Gadget per the rules on Ultra-Tech p. 16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under those rules, Weight becomes 8kg/0.35kg (or 8.7/1.05 with the extended
mag). Switching modes requires a Ready maneuver, and the weapon uses the Damage,
Acc, Range, RoF, Shots and ST of whatever version is the currently active
one. Keep track of both ammo counts separately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;laserkraftwerk&quot;&gt;Laserkraftwerk&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an experimental laser weapon that B. J. “liberates” from a lab early in
The New Order. It’s about carbine-sized, and fires shots that are more powerful
than those of the lunar laser rifle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LKW also has an alternate “laser cutter” module that’s useful for quietly
severing chains and cutting through chain-link fences and thin metal walls. This
does 2d(2) burn and can run continuously for half an hour on a full battery, if
it matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the game, the player can find several upgrades for the LKW,
including a scope, a double-capacity battery, and new internal parts that allow
it to fire more often or to fire a more powerful “charged” shot that’s better at
dealing with large and heavily armored opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Weapon Table below, you get stats both for the baseline version and the
fully-upgraded one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial outlets recharge the weapon at a rate of 1 shot per second with the
standard battery, or 2 shots per second with the expanded one. The final upgrade
in The New Order is an “ancient supertech” portable reactor that recharges the
weapon at a rate of 1 shot per 2 seconds whenever it’s not being fired,
regardless of its battery size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;energy-weapon-table&quot;&gt;Energy Weapon Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Marskman Rifle (Laser)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/1500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;28*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;LKW (baseline)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;LKW (fully upgraded)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12+2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;charged shot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6dx3(3) burn sur&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;**&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*: See description for recharge time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**: Drains power equivalent to 5 shots from the battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grenades-and-launchers&quot;&gt;Grenades and Launchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enemy soldiers are enthusiastic about using hand grenades in the The New Order,
and only a little less so in The New Colossus. Launcher weapons are much rarer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In The New Order, enemies use the same &lt;strong&gt;Hand Grenade&lt;/strong&gt; from the previous post
in the 1946 prologue. By 1960 they’ve switched to using Tesla grenades
exclusively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;tesla-grenade&quot;&gt;Tesla Grenade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like a modernized version of the Stick Hand Grenade used back
in 1946. Its explosive power is equivalent, but also releases an electromagnetic
pulse that can “stun” robotic and cybernetic enemies in a 4-meter radius from
the epicenter of the explosion. They must make a HT-8(2) roll or be knocked out
of action for seconds equal to their margin of failure. That (2) means that any
electromagnetic shielding that would provide a bonus to this roll only works at
half effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; applies to battery-powered weapons of any kind, which usually have
HT 12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;underbarrel-rocket-launcher&quot;&gt;Underbarrel Rocket Launcher&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An accessory compatible with the 1960 Assault Rifle, this launcher fires 40mm
anti-armor rockets from a removable cylinder with a 4-round capacity. It’s
issued to soldiers that are expected to go against heavily-armored opposition,
and who are usually heavily-armored themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launcher can only be used if it’s attached to another weapon. By default
that’s the assault rifle, which has the rails to receive it, but players might
decide to get creative with their jury-rigging. It adds its weight to the
overall weight of the other weapon and worsens its Bulk by -1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the standard skill system, this uses the Guns (LAW) skill. In the alternate
one, it’s Guns (Long Arm) aided by the Payload Warhead technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hand-grenade-table&quot;&gt;Hand Grenade Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fuse&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tesla Grenade&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7d cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.7kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;linked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;HT-8(2) aff&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rocket-launcher-table&quot;&gt;Rocket Launcher Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Underbarrel Rocket Launcher&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5dx2(10) cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1900&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;–&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;linked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d cr ex [1d-1]&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heavy-weapons&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;laser-machine-gun&quot;&gt;Laser Machine Gun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old Venom machine gun from the war has been replaced with this energy weapon
in the Sixties. Like its predecessor, the Laser MG is found in fixed mounts, in
the hands of cybernetic supersoldiers, and mounted on the many models of giant
robot stomping around. It can fire for quite a bit before running dry. This can
look like either a sequence of rapid pulses or a continuous beam, but either
version uses the same stats. Enemies don’t like to aim with it either, improving
the players’ chances of survival when facing it. It’s heavy and bulky enough to
be only a “sometimes” gun for the player, used when found and quickly discarded
when empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial outlets reload it at a rate of 20 shots per second. When attached to
a fixed mount, the weapon’s Acc improves to 18, and it’s recharged as if
connected to an outlet when not firing. Attaching or detaching it takes 2 Ready
maneuvers. The weapon uses the Gunner (Beams) skill even when detached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;heavy-weapon-table&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapon Table&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8+2^&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Laser MG&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6d(2) burn&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;700/2100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;25kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;200*&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15M&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*: See description for recharge time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Seth belongs to the Da’at Yichud, an ancient society of engineers that had
been building superscience devices as a form of worship since before the
rest of humanity had organized religion. Deathshead’s inventions are all
copied from one of their vaults, which he found in the 40s. I’ve seen the
concept described as kinda problematic despite the designers’ best
intentions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/17/guns-of-wolfenstein-03.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/17/guns-of-wolfenstein-03.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Megapede</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-megapede.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A megapede, an enormous purple centipede with neon green highlights.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lore of the Megapede is fairly uncomplicated. They’re the logical endpoint
of the Giant Centipede Arms Race. The largest, strongest, Darkest and Sunniest
giant centipedes on Athas. And they’re also psychic, because of course they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Megapedes lair underground, in burrows or natural caves where they lay their
eggs. They hunt by tunneling through the sand, erupting from beneath their
prey, and fighting a battle of attrition they will likely win with their
venomous bite, hundreds of flailing legs, and corrosive psionics. Sometimes
unlucky travelers taking shelter in a cave might find it’s already occupied by a
megapede when it drops down from the ceiling on top of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, they’ll share their lair with a couple of wild cilopses, who are
their distant cousins, but they tend to just eat anything else, and no one has
ever managed to tame them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Megapedes are Huge Natural Beasts and Level 15 Elite Brutes with 368 HP. They
have Darkvision, a ground speed of 8, a burrow speed of 6 in loose earth, and a
climb speed of 8. Their overall power level is on par with that of an Athasian
drake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; attack has Reach 2 and does a potent blend of physical and
poison damage. Their most common at-will attack will be &lt;strong&gt;Legs of the
Megapede&lt;/strong&gt;, which attacks all enemies in a Close Burst 2 for similar damage
&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; lets the megapede bite someone for free as an effect. Its &lt;strong&gt;Lashing Body&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) works as a minor-action melee attack that does a little less
damage than the Legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the monster is also psychic! Once per encounter it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Psionic Erosion&lt;/strong&gt; to attack the Fortitude of enemies in a Close Blast 5. On a
hit, this deals immediate and ongoing psychic damage, which starts at 10 and
decreases to 5 after the first successful save. On a miss, it deals half
damage. Slightly more often, it can cause a &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Detonation&lt;/strong&gt; on an Area 1
Burst Within 5, which deals “psychic and force” damage and slides targets 3
squares. This recharges when it’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when it hits with either of its single-target physical attacks, the
megapede can use &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augmentation&lt;/strong&gt; to deal extra psychic damage on the
attack. This also recharges when it’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the most likely megapede encounters are against a mated pair
or against one of them plus 2-3 leveled-up cilopses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise this is basically a Giant-er Centipede, so I’m not all that excited
about them. If that’s your bag, tough, they’re awesome. Mechanically, you can
use a megapede anywhere you’d use an Athasian Drake - they’re about as powerful
and arguably a lot more common. You could also reskin their stat block as a
drake or other suitable giant creature.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/08/wir-dscc-megapede.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/09/08/wir-dscc-megapede.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Kirre</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-kirre.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A kirre, looking like a horned green tiger with eight legs.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirres manage to feel like exotic alien creatures both to us in the real world
and to characters in Athas. To us, it’s because they have eight legs and a pair
of horns. To Athasians, it’s because they’re fur-covered mammals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These felines live in Athas’ rare forests and jungles, such as the Crescent
Forest and the same Forest Ridge where halflings live. They gather in small
prides, and are clever and cautious hunters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of simply charging in, a kirre who isn’t desperately hungry will stalk
its prey for hours to evaluate its capabilities and behavior, and will adapt its
tactics to ensure their success. With some, they might be extra-sneaky and
attack when the prey’s guard is down. With others, they might harass and make
noises to scare the prey into making a foolish mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book entry mentions that kirres are only one of several species descended
from ancient great cats. Other names mentioned are tigones and “the reptilian
lirr”, though these two aren’t present in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only have one stat block here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kirre&quot;&gt;Kirre&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kirre is a Large Natural Magical Beast, and a Level 13 Skirmisher with 131
HP. It has a Speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has two basic attacks: a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and a slightly weaker &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; that slows
for a turn on a hit. The &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; at-will ability lets it make two claw
attacks in one action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Springing Pounce&lt;/strong&gt; lets the kirre bite, shift 4 squares, and bite again. This
becomes a nice fight opener when combined with the &lt;strong&gt;Scattering Leap&lt;/strong&gt;
move-action encounter power, which lets the beast jump 6 squares, push adjacent
enemies at the destination 2 squares, and then shift 2 squares to follow one of
those enemies. The Pounce recharges when the creature is bloodied, which also
makes it useful for escaping a dicey situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter it can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Forceful Roar&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks the
Fortitude of enemies in a Close Blast 3. On a hit it deals force damage, pushes
2 squares, and knocks prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy moves to a square where it flanks the kirre, it can use its
&lt;strong&gt;Barbed Tail&lt;/strong&gt; to fend then off, making a Reach 2 melee attack that knocks
prone and inflicts 10 ongoing damage (save ends) on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirres are smart enough to ally with creatures of other species, though they
demand that their allies be at least as smart as themselves. Those who aren’t
will be treated as prey instead. This is a low bar for other sapient creatures
to clear, which means they will sometimes even accept humanoids as pack
mates. They can be most often found in the company of halflings, though goliaths
and giths that live in greener areas are also known to ally with kirres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re regular monsters, but their spread of abilities means they fight like
elites! An encounter featuring a pair of kirres and a handful of humanoid allies
will give PCs quite a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/28/wir-dscc-kirre.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/28/wir-dscc-kirre.html</guid>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>dnd4e</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
