<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 12:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 12:52:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Jhakar</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-jhakar.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A jhakar, a stocky dog-lizard hybrid with a pug-like face.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Described as “small, squat, and pugnacious”, these round boys are reptilian dog
equivalents with keen senses and a vicious streak. On the wild they follow your
standard pack hunter structure, but they’re also frequently “tamed” by people
for use as combat, guard, and tracker animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tamed” is in quotes here because jhakars don’t form bonds of loyalty with their
handlers. They respect strength and pain, but they also nurse grudges. So the
process of training a jhakar is quite cruel and results in a creature that’s
likely to turn on their handler as soon as it sees a chance. Ironically, because
of this owning a trained jhakar is seen as a sign of strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jhakars are Small Natural Beasts with the Reptile tag. They have a ground speed
of 6 and Low-Light Vision. Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Uncanny Senses&lt;/strong&gt;, which
makes their attacks ignore concealment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jhakars don’t have supernatural tracking abilities like some of the monsters we
saw before, but you can probably consider them as good at it as a trained
mundane hound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jhakar-tracker&quot;&gt;Jhakar Tracker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This specimen is a Level 1 Skirmisher with 28 HP and all standard jhakar
traits. As mentioned above, it’s probably as good at tracking as a mundane dog,
but its stat block focuses more on what it does once it finds its prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tracker’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; does standard damage with a sizable bonus against targets
granting combat advantage to it. The attack also lets the tracker shift 1 square
as an effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter the tracker can use an &lt;strong&gt;Opportunistic Chomp&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction
when an enemy ends its turn within 2 squares. It lets make a free bite attack
with the damage bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trackers are unlikely to stay in one place for very long. Their free shift with
a bite lets them move in, bite, and then dart away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jhakar-trapjaw&quot;&gt;Jhakar Trapjaw&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This beefier specimen is a Level 3 Soldier with 47 HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;Bite&lt;/strong&gt; is a bit
stronger, grabs on a hit, and lets the trapjaw make a secondary attack against
Fortitude. If that one hits, the grabbed victim takes 5 ongoing damage until
the grab ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trapjaw can also &lt;strong&gt;Drag Down&lt;/strong&gt; a grabbed victim, attacking their
Fortitude. If they hit, they deal heavy damage and knock the target prone. It
can’t get up until the grab ends either! This recharges when the creature is
first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike trackers, jhakar trapjaws are set up to choose a PC and make their day
extremely bad. They’ll do exactly that, positioning themselves as the center of
attention to let their quicker buddies attack the party while they’re
distracted. This works no matter who those allies are, so it’s appropriate for
both wild and domesticated jhakar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry is short and to the point, just like the creatures it
describes. You’ll never ever need to include normal dogs or wolves in our Dark
Sun Campaigns if this book has anything to say about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An encounter group of wild Jhakars will probably include one or two trapjaws
with trackers making up the rest of the numbers. And of course any of the other
doglike creatures in this or other books could be reskinned as a jhakar. They
also work in any mixed encounter as trained beasts, as they are fairly common in
that role.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/17/wir-dscc-jhakar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/17/wir-dscc-jhakar.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Inix</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-inix.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An inix, a yellowish giant lizard with a brown beak and carapace.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most of the Athasian fauna we saw so far, these giant lizards are fairly
docile omnivores. They mostly eat plants and roots, though they’ll also feed on
carrion and small animals. They only attack people if directly
threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inixes are widely domesticated for use as mounts, draft animals, and
livestock. Some people like to keep juveniles as pets. In the wild, they roam in
small bands. Inix females lay eggs once a year, and are capable of producing
viable eggs even without a male.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inixes are Natural Beasts, with the Reptile tag. When forced to fight they
attack with bites and with swipes of their large and powerful tails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inix-juvenile&quot;&gt;Inix Juvenile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inix juveniles are only about half the size of adults, which means they’re
Medium. This slighter build makes them faster than adults. Juveniles also have
venom in their bites, which they lose as they grow up. They’re Level 4
Skirmishers with 57 HP and a speed of 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, their &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; is venomous, dealing a mix of physical and
poison damage. As a minor action they can attempt a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Trip&lt;/strong&gt;, which attacks
Fortitude. On a hit, the inix knocks the target prone and can shift 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inix-adult&quot;&gt;Inix Adult&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adults are size Large, and Level 9 Brutes with 120 HP and a Speed of 6. They’ll
probably open the fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Tail Slap&lt;/strong&gt; that attacks the Fortitude of
enemies in a Close Blast 2. On a hit it deals standard physical damage and
knocks the targets prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, it’s time for the &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals standard physical damage. When it
hits a prone target, the bite deals extra damage and grabs that target. The
victim can only try to stand up after the grab ends, and the inix can keep
making bite attacks against it (but not against others while the victim remains
grabbed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the inix is serving as a mount, it can use the &lt;strong&gt;Warding Tail&lt;/strong&gt; ability. This
triggers when the rider is hit by an opportunity attack provoked by making a
ranged or area attack, and lets the inix use Tail Slap against the triggering
creature as a free action. This makes them a fine mount for artillery monsters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short and sweet entry. It’s always good to see another member of the club of
Athasian creatures that are not suicidally aggressive predators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encounters with domesticated inixes tend to be much more interesting than those
with wild ones, as they can feature more varied encounter groups. As mentioned
above, adults are awesome mounts for artillery and controller riders. They’re
also fun to have as the draft animal for a “runaway wagon” scenario, as they
tend to be much harder to physically stop than horses.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/15/wir-dscc-inix.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/15/wir-dscc-inix.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Id Fiend</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-id-fiend.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An id fiend, a big toothy lizard, hanging out on a rock outcropping.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Id fiends are big toothy lizards with psionic powers of fear manipulation,
which they use to hunt their preferred prey. Which is, of course, people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As reasonably smart magical beasts, they are capable of making alliances with
other creatures, though these tend to be strained at best. More often, an id
fiend might craft fearful illusions to manipulate those creatures into helping
it attack others. When that happens, the best tactic is to focus on the id
fiend - when it dies, its control ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Id fiends are a major threat to civilians, but a favorite target of seasoned
monster hunters. The House of the Mind in Draj pays generously for live
specimens, whose fresh organs and fluids go into making alchemical potions meant
to awaken someone’s psychic potential. Many of those are dubious at best, but at
least some of them have real effects. The book mentions “terror ichor” by name -
this is a consumable reagent that can be used to enhance fear-based powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Fiends are Large Aberrant Magical Beasts with the Reptile tag. This probably
makes them the most mundane-looking aberrants we saw so far. Just a big lizard,
not a tentacle in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, they end up filling the empty niche left by absence of low-level
dragons in Athas. They’re Level 1 Solo Controllers with 120 HP, Darkvision, a
Speed of 6, an immunity to Fear and Resist 5 Psychic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fiend can attack with a &lt;strong&gt;quick slash&lt;/strong&gt; of its claws, which deals light
physical damage and lets it shift 1 square; with a bite of its &lt;strong&gt;Snapping Jaws&lt;/strong&gt;
that deals more damage and slides the target 1 square; or with a &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt; that uses both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of a breath weapon, it has the &lt;strong&gt;Manifest Fear&lt;/strong&gt; power (recharge 4+),
which affects enemies in a Close Burst 5. Those hit by it are dazed for a turn
as they see a vision of their worst fears becoming reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the fiend dazes a few enemies, it will use the &lt;strong&gt;Fearful Torment&lt;/strong&gt; power, a
minor-action ranged attack that targets one or two tazed creatures. A hit deals
psychic damage, immobilizes, and inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks for a turn. I
guess this means it makes the vision of fear worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the fiend is first bloodied, Manifest Fear recharges and it can use the
power immediately as a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like id fiends prefer to use their fear powers to kill their victims if
possible, though they’re also perfectly capable of physical fighting as seen
above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single id fiend makes a fine boss battle for beginner PCs. Once they gain a
level or two, you can begin to add thralls enraptured by visions of fear, and
fooled into thinking the PCs are monsters to be slain. As the book says, killing
the fiend will likely free the thralls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an interesting monster, I think. Effectively a low-level dragon that
breathes fear. You can level it up a bit to make it more challenging for
mid-Heroic PCs, but I’d probably set that as the upper bound of their power.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/13/wir-dscc-id-fiend.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/13/wir-dscc-id-fiend.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Human</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I keep mentioning Mixed Groups of People as possible encounter
groups? How they can be anything, allied or hostile, made up of free or enslaved
individuals, working for any one of the setting’s factions or none at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s exactly the kind of description you get for humans in this entry. They
are the most numerous humanoid species on Athas, they are infinitely varied and
adaptable, and all the other stuff you have read about them a thousand times in
other places. What this tells me is that those Mixed Groups of People will be
mostly made up of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans in Athas are mechanically identical to humans elsewhere. Medium Natural
Humanoids with Speed 6, and with absolutely everything else determined by
training in each specific stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any of these stat blocks can easily be adjusted to represent a member of another
species by adding that species’ signature traits o it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-slave&quot;&gt;Human Slave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If humans make up the bulk of those Mixed Groups of People, then it’s logical to
assume they also make up the bulk of Athas’ enslaved population. You’ll see them
in large numbers while walking down the street of any of the sorcerer-kings’
city states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Human Slave is a Level 1 Minion Brute, armed with a &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt; that’s likely
improvised. They gain +1 bonus damage for each ally adjacent to their target,
and &lt;strong&gt;Laborer’s Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; make them stay up for an additional turn after
being reduced to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, they’re quite bad at fighting, and will likely only do so if
they have no other choice. Only their large numbers make them a threat to
PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-wasteland-raider&quot;&gt;Human Wasteland Raider&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a typical member of those hostile Mixed Groups of People who attack you
while you’re traveling the wastes, intent on either killing you, taking your
stuff, or both. They’re Level 2 Soldiers with 40 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most striking thing about this stat block is the big editing error right in
the middle, a &lt;strong&gt;barbed spear&lt;/strong&gt; attack that has no listed damage and should be
ignored. The raider’s actual weapon is a &lt;strong&gt;Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; that does standard physical
damage and can be used in a stronger &lt;strong&gt;Gutting Dagger&lt;/strong&gt; attack against someone
grabbed by the raider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the spear was supposed to be the attack that grabbed the target? As it is,
the raider has to use the default rules and perform a Grab action to do
it. My suggestion here would be to replace the &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack with a
&lt;strong&gt;Barbed Spear&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage, grabs on a hit, and cannot be used
against other targets while the raider has a target grabbed. Gutting Dagger
would then turn into Gutting Spear, with the same effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-dune-trader&quot;&gt;Human Dune Trader&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember disliking the emphasis the book put on elven traders being unreliable
and dishonest, but it looks like it doesn’t have much better to say about the
human ones. This one is described as being flanked by burly bodyguards as he
cheerfully lies about the price and quality of his goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dune Traders are Level 4 Controllers with the Leader tag and 55 HP. They’re
armed with &lt;strong&gt;hatchets&lt;/strong&gt; that do physical damage and cause the target to grant
Combat Advantage for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While unbloodied, they can spend minor actions on &lt;strong&gt;Goading Commands&lt;/strong&gt; that let
one ally within 6 squares move their speed as a free action. While bloodied,
this changes to a &lt;strong&gt;Furious Glare&lt;/strong&gt;, a standard action that attacks the Will of
enemies in a Close Blast 3. It does no damage, but immobilizes and makes the
targets grant combat advantage on a hit (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-gladiator-novice&quot;&gt;Human Gladiator Novice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those gladiators who managed to survive their first few fights can go on to
achieve fame and greatness… but this one is still figuring out the surviving
part. There are many like him on every arena. He’s a level 4 Soldier with 55 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gladiator novice fights with a &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and marks on a
hit, and can perform a &lt;strong&gt;hamstring cut&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage, knocks
prone, and slows (save ends). If an adjacent enemy stands up, the novice can
use &lt;strong&gt;Stay Down!&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction to attack their Reflex and knock them back down
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book remarks that gladiators are one of the opponent types that have
in-character reasons for picking less than optimal combat options during a
fight, as long as they make for a better show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-overseer&quot;&gt;Human Overseer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first explicitly Evil stat block in this entry. The things they oversee are
the sale, transport, and daily (mis)treatment of slaves. Whether they display
malicious glee or banal apathy towards the cruelty that surrounds them, it
remains true that their job is to perpetuate it. They’re Level 9 Controllers
with the Leader tag and 96 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overseers are armed with &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian Swords&lt;/strong&gt;, and they have extensive training
in psychic powers that assault and dominate the mind because of course they
do. They project a &lt;strong&gt;Mental Mire&lt;/strong&gt; around themselves (aura 2) that slows enemies
who starts their turns inside. &lt;strong&gt;Not So Fast!&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack that deals
psychic damage and pulls 3 squares. And &lt;strong&gt;Do My Bidding&lt;/strong&gt; targets one slowed
creature within 2 squares and dominates it for a turn on a hit. This one is
thankfully not at-will - it recharges when the overseer is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-slavehunter&quot;&gt;Human Slavehunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another Evil entry. Slavehunters do what it says on the tin, roaming both the
wilds and the streets looking for new people to enslave. Anyone who looks like
they’d fetch a good price and won’t put up much of a fight is fair game. They’re
Level 10 Skirmishers with 103 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This villain is armed with a &lt;strong&gt;Mace&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;Obsidian-toothed Whip&lt;/strong&gt;. A hit
with the mace lets them shift 1 square. A hit with the whip pulls the target 1
square and knocks it prone. As minor actions, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Swift Pursuit&lt;/strong&gt; to
shift 3 squares (recharges when bloodied) or &lt;strong&gt;Cutting Lash&lt;/strong&gt; to inflict ongoing
10 damage (save ends) on a prone creature as an encounter power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book mentions a power named “Face Smash”, but this isn’t present on the stat
block. I guess there were some editing hiccups, and it was replaced by Cutting
Lash without any changes to the surrounding text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-templar-of-tyr&quot;&gt;Human Templar of Tyr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth Edition Dark Sun is set right after the sorcerer-king of Tyr was deposed
and killed in a violent revolution, and this book describes the city’s templars
as being “cast adrift” and only relying on “themselves and each other” to impose
their will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to me like a fancy way to say they immediately pivoted to being a
crime syndicate after losing their official authority, though I remember
something in the older 2e books about Tyr still having some templars in its
government. This stat block is Evil, so I’m guessing it represents a “loyalist”
templar who is now a mobster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This templar is a Level 10 Controller with 106 HP. It fights exclusively with
Force magic. Its basic melee attack is an &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Spear&lt;/strong&gt; that does force
damage and slides targets 1 square on a hit. The basic ranged attack is an
&lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same amount of force damage and pushes 2
squares. &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Cage&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is an Area Burst 2 spell that attacks
all creatures in the area. On a hit it restrains and deals 10 ongoing force
damage (save ends). The book says the templar is not shy about including some of
its own allies in the area if it will help them get more PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the templar’s powers explicitly mention defiling, but you could give
them a version of the next stat block’s passive trait if you wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-defiler&quot;&gt;Human Defiler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Athas, despoiling an already ravaged ecosystem is a big taboo that’s sure to
draw the ire of those who see you do it… unless you’re a sorcerer-king or a
templar, I guess. The defilers represented by this stat block are neither, but
they really want to be and think the scorn of the ignorant masses is a light
price to pay for Ultimate Cosmic Power. You could also uses these stats for a
higher-ranking templar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Human Defiler is Level 14 Artillery with 108 HP (and also Evil). It has the
&lt;strong&gt;Defiling&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait, which deals 5 necrotic damage to all enemies within
3 squares whenever the defiler uses an implement power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its only non-implement power is a &lt;strong&gt;staff&lt;/strong&gt; bonk that causes a mix of physical
and necrotic damage. The templar prefers to fight from a distance with lightning
spells. &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Lance&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic ranged attack that does lightning damage,
and &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Serpent&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that does a bit less lightning
damage but also inflicts ongoing 10 poison damage (save ends). Once per
encounter, the Defiler can use &lt;strong&gt;Dimension Door&lt;/strong&gt; to teleport 10 squares,
something it will probably use as an emergency escape measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy within 10 squares of the defiler spends a healing surge, it can
use &lt;strong&gt;Defiling Serpent&lt;/strong&gt; as a free action to regain HP equal to half the value
of the triggering surge and recharge Lightning Serpent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-mind-adept&quot;&gt;Human Mind Adept&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re out of the Evil Zone again. This is a powerful human telepath that can be
cast in any role, friendly or not: a Level 15 Controller with 145 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind adepts rely solely on their powers (and on their teammates, of course) for
defense. We start with an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Overwhelming Thoughts&lt;/strong&gt; that makes it so
any enemy that ends their turn inside cannot target the adept with an attack
until the end of their next turn. This means melee-based PCs will only be
attacking them every other turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty much all of the adept’s attacks are psychic powers that target Will. For
melee, we have the &lt;strong&gt;Mind-Wracking Touch&lt;/strong&gt; dealing psychic damage and making the
target grant combat advantage for a turn. For greater ranges we have the at-will
&lt;strong&gt;Paralyzing Blast&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5) which targets enemies, deals light psychic
damage, and immobilizes for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adept’s ultimate technique is &lt;strong&gt;Will of the Master&lt;/strong&gt;, a ranged attack that
deals no damage and dominates (save ends). While the target is dominated, it
emits harmful psychic waves: any enemy that starts their turn within 2 squares
of the target takes 5 psychic damage and is immobilized for a turn. This is an
encounter power that recharges whenever it misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the adept is reduced to 0 HP, it causes &lt;strong&gt;Mental Overload&lt;/strong&gt; in a Close
Burst 1. This targets enemies and on a hit deals psychic damage and stuns for a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;human-blade-noble&quot;&gt;Human Blade Noble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-human-blade-noble.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A red-haired woman human wearing leather armor and holding a sheathed sword.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most powerful human in this entry is not a wizard or a psychic, but someone
who is Just That Good with a sword. Or in other words: Hello, Ms. Malenia! Fancy
meeting you here. This is a Level 17 Controller with 163 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blade noble has a trait named &lt;strong&gt;Unpredictable Flank&lt;/strong&gt; that gives them combat
advantage against any enemy adjacent to one of their allies. No need to setup a
by-the-book flanking position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;Duelist’s Blade&lt;/strong&gt;, which given the context is probably one
of the few magical steel swords that still survive in Athas. Its basic attacks
do physical damage and slide the target 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dance of Blades&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rlnv_DCBEa8&quot;&gt;technique&lt;/a&gt; that reminded me of
Malenia: it attacks enemies in a Close Burst 2, deals the same damage as a basic
attack, immobilizes, and inflicts ongoing 5 damage (save ends). On a miss it
still does half damage, which is a rarity on a rechargeable attack. The noble
can shift 2 squares as an effect as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For triggered actions we have &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Parry&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power that
triggers when an ally of the noble’s within 2 squares is hit by a melee or
ranged attack. As an interrupt, the noble shifts 2 squares to be adjacent to the
ally and rolls an attack using its standard bonus vs. AC. If that’s higher than
the triggering attack roll, the triggering attack misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The individual stat blocks are pretty cool, but the lore is your standard Humans
Are The Most Generic thing. In the end this ends up being a very ecletic set of
People that you can reskin as any species and any narrative role that best fits
your specific campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some more recent games have explicitly gone this route for pretty much
every humanoid NPC, giving us stat blocks based on narrative or mechanical role
(“Bandit”, “Guard”, “Brute”, “Wizard”) and then letting us assign any species as
necessary. D&amp;amp;D 4e wasn’t quite there yet, but ended up doing it by accident on
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/11/wir-dscc-human.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/11/wir-dscc-human.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Guns of Wolfenstein, Part 02: The Old Blood</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html&quot;&gt;our previous article&lt;/a&gt;, we took a look at the guns that appear on Return
to Castle Wolfenstein (2001), whose timeline I named “Wolfenstein-1” for ease of
reference. In this one, we’ll take a look at the timeline I called
“Wolfenstein-2”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wolfenstein-2 setting is the chronology used by the trilogy of games made up
of Wolfenstein: The New Order (2014), Wolfenstein: The Old Blood (2015) and
Wolfenstein II: The New Colossus (2017). The Old Blood is a prequel to The New
Order, so it happens first even though it’s the second game. We’ll talk about it
in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot-overview-contains-spoilers&quot;&gt;Plot Overview (Contains Spoilers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Old Blood is a retelling of the “escape from Castle Wolfenstein” story that
made up the first two chapters of the 2001 game. Where the Wolfenstein-1 version
was just a pulpier version of WW2, this one goes all in on the alternate history
approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like World War 2 in the Wolfenstein-2 timeline starts off more or less
like it did in our world, but things go off the rails somewhere along the
way. Deathshead, the same mad scientist from the 2001 game, is wildly more
successful at coming up with absurd weapons and getting them mass-produced. As a
result the war streches for longer than it did in our world. The game happens in
&lt;em&gt;1946&lt;/em&gt;, with the war still raging on and the Allies on the losing side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like in the 2001 game, B.J. Blazkowicz and Agent One infiltrate Castle
Wolfenstein. Their goal here is more well-defined - among the documents stored
in the castle, there’s a folder that details the location of Deathshead’s secret
fortress, where he’s been developing all these superweapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Castle here is much larger than it was in the first game, and has been
upgraded from its medieval roots into a giant concrete fortress full of
superscience security measures, including prototype supersoldiers tethered to
power lines. Its owner is still an occult-obsessed Nazi officer named Helga, who
now works under Deathshead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broad outline of events is the same - the two get captured, Agent One dies
under torture, Blazko escapes the castle. He heads to the nearby village of
Wolfburg, where Helga leads an archaeological dig in search of buried occult
secrets. Whatever she does triggers a sort of zombie apocalypse. Helga releases
a giant zombie and dies failing to control it. B. J. escapes with the secret
document folder after killing said zombie, completing his mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guns&quot;&gt;The Guns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the usable guns in this game are captured Nazi hardware, since you start
the game proper unarmed save for a (surprisingly effective) sharpened metal
pipe. This “early” in the timeline, a lot of the weapons presented here still
have real-world equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pistols&quot;&gt;Pistols&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pistol-model-1946&quot;&gt;Pistol Model 1946&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still mostly a &lt;strong&gt;Luger P08&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT98), with the only difference being
that it has a 10-round magazine instead of an 8-round one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It accepts a suppressor, which is available to you from the start. It weights
0.25kg, adds -1 to Bulk and makes the gun &lt;em&gt;cinematically silent&lt;/em&gt;. This means
enemies won’t notice the gun firing unless a bullet impacts the environment near
them, or if they survive being shot by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Pistol 1946&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d+2 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;160/1800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1.2kg/0.3kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rifles&quot;&gt;Rifles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assault-rifle-model-46-t&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle Model 46-T&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still pretty much a &lt;strong&gt;StG-44&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT115). It has a folding foregrip not
present in the real weapon, but that doesn’t affect its stats in any way either
in the computer game or in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marksman-rifle-bombenschluss&quot;&gt;Marksman Rifle (Bombenschluss)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is likely a version of the &lt;strong&gt;Mauser Kar98K&lt;/strong&gt; (p. HT111). Unlike the real
weapon, this one’s magazine is inserted from the side, which means the gun can
still be fired from a prone position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two obtainable upgrades. The first is a 10-round extended magazine
that adds -1 to Bulk and weights 0.44kg loaded. The other is a scope on a
tacticool folding mount. It adds 0.5kg to weight and changes Acc to 5+2. It can
be folded in or out of position with a Ready maneuver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;weapon-table&quot;&gt;Weapon Table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Assault Rifle 46-T&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;500/1300&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.6kg/1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;30(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bombenschluss&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1000/4300&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.5kg/0.25kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shotguns&quot;&gt;Shotguns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;double-barreled-shotgun&quot;&gt;Double Barreled Shotgun&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 10-gauge classic makes two appearances: at the start of the game with a
full length barrel, and at the end with the barrel sawn off to “whippet”
length. The full-length gun uses the same stats as the &lt;strong&gt;Lefevre Automatic
Hammerless&lt;/strong&gt; from High Tech. The sawn-off one uses the stats below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shockhammer&quot;&gt;Shockhammer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a semi-automatic 12-gauge shotgun with a Rube Goldberg action. The gun
takes shells from a revolving cylinder that alternates between its twin barrels
with every cycle, which is supposed to allow for a higher rate of fire. The
stats below are somewhat inspired by the &lt;strong&gt;Daewoo USAS-12&lt;/strong&gt; from High Tech, but
there are enough differences to warrant its own stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible upgrade here is a 20-round cylinder that changes Shots to 20(5) and
Weight to 8.2/2.1kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Double-Barreled Shotgun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2d-1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.15/0.15kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2x13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2(3i)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;12†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7+1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shockhammer&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1d+1 pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/800&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.1/1.05kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3x9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10(5)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11†&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1/3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grenades-and-launchers&quot;&gt;Grenades and Launchers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hand-grenade&quot;&gt;Hand Grenade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enemy soldiers use a version of the historical &lt;strong&gt;“stick hand grenade 24”&lt;/strong&gt;
filled with TNT, as mentioned in p. HT190: Damage 7d cr ex, weight 0.7kg, Fuse
4-5. They’re not shy about throwing them at you if you stay for more than a few
seconds behind cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kampfpistole-war-pistol&quot;&gt;Kampfpistole (“war pistol”)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a version of a historical flare gun used in WW2 that could also fire
grenades. Its extremely limited ammo is the best choice for taking out the
tankiest enemies in the game, so I think it fires the HEAT round described in
High Tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Kampfpistole&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d(10) cr ex&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10/330&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1kg/0.1kg&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;+ 3d cr ex linked&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heavy-weapons&quot;&gt;Heavy Weapons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see another familiar face here: the &lt;strong&gt;Venom Heavy Machine Gun&lt;/strong&gt;, which loses
its edgy name but is basically the same weapon I already covered in my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/11/04/guns-of-wolfenstein.html&quot;&gt;previous
post on Wolfenstein guns&lt;/a&gt;. It’s found in the hands of early-model
supersoldiers, and has 250 round belts weighting 10kg. Even a beefy guy like
B. J. has trouble carrying it around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incarnation of the Venom is excellent to mow down human soldiers and
zombies, but doesn’t actually do much to the supersoldiers that carry
it. Therefore we can assume it fires regular ammo instead of armor-piercing: Dam
6d+2 pi.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/04/guns-of-wolfenstein-02.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/04/guns-of-wolfenstein-02.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Hejkin</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-hejkin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A hejkin.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hejkin are abominations created by the “rampant use of arcane magic” according
to the book, though it doesn’t specify whether they the product of accident or
deliberate experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These small and twisted humanoids can see beyond the world and into a “heaving,
squirming space filled with nightmares”. Their powers are tied to this place,
and to the nastier primal spirits of Athas. The easy answer here would be that
they have a direct mental connection to the Far Realm, but maybe this is another
nightmare dimension more appropriate to your game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, hejkin venerate the spirits of earth and stone as cold and callous
masters that nevertheless provide life. Their culture forbids shaping or carving
into the earth. This means that people who do strike the earth are seen as
horrible heretics to be eliminated. They also reserve the same hatred for those
who “misuse” arcane magic, which probably means those who use it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hejkin live in natural caves that contain natural water sources. They don’t
shape these in any way, but they do use magic to lay various sigil-based traps
on the walls. They venture out to find food, or they might be driven to a frenzy
by some astrological event or another that holds special meaning in that Other
Place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hejkin tend to target spellcasters, miners, and anyone working on other similar
occupations that they can reach by traveling from their homes. They gleefully
steal food and supplies from their victims and then finally murder them, turning
them into yet more food. No one is safe from their cookpots, not even other
hejkins. This makes them our fifth humanoid cannibals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hejkins are Small Aberrant Humanoids with ground and burrow speeds of 6, plus
Darkvision, Earth Walk and Resist Lightning 5. They often have access to some
sort of lightning magic, though the specifics vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hejkin-sparker&quot;&gt;Hejkin Sparker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one’s particularly infused with lightning. It’s a Level 1 Soldier with 31
HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;Arcing Defense&lt;/strong&gt; gives it +2 to AC and Will while adjacent to another
hejkin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sparker’s &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; do physical damage and mark for a turn. If the target is
bloodied, they mark even on a miss. Their &lt;strong&gt;Grounded Current&lt;/strong&gt; power (recharge
5+) attacks enemies in a Close Burst 2, deals lightning damage, and pulls 2
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a marked enemy decides to move away or ignore the mark, the hejkin can use
a &lt;strong&gt;Telluric Arc&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt. This attacks the triggering enemy’s Reflex
and deals 10 lightning damage on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hejkin-chanter&quot;&gt;Hejkin Chanter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chanter’s song is mostly unintelligible, but sometimes you can discern a
horrible phrase or two. The song gives it power over earth and lightning, and I
guess shaping the earth doesn’t count as heresy if a chanter does it. They’re
Level 2 Controllers with 37 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; to physical damage and slow for a turn. If the target is
bloodied or already slowed, it’s immobilized for a turn instead. &lt;strong&gt;Earth’s
Voice&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge when first bloodied) is a close blast 5 that targets enemies,
deals thunder damage, pushes 3 squares and knocks prone. &lt;strong&gt;Static Song&lt;/strong&gt;
(encounter) is a close burst 3 that deals lightning damage and dazes (save
ends). On a miss it deals half damage and dazes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally we get a little trick: &lt;strong&gt;Twisted Earth&lt;/strong&gt; is a minor action melee attack
against Fortitude that teleports the target on a hit, making it swap places
either with the chanter or with one of the chanter’s allies that’s within 5
squares. Say, why does Team Monster have a brute in the back line?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hejkin-raver&quot;&gt;Hejkin Raver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one’s even more feral than usual, and has no thoughts in their head other
than a craving for blood. It’s a Level 2 Brute with 45 HP. Its &lt;strong&gt;Claws&lt;/strong&gt; do
physical damage and heal it for 3 HP if the target is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blood Marker&lt;/strong&gt; lets the raver use Claw against an adjacent enemy as a reaction
when it is first bloodied. &lt;strong&gt;Blood Shakes&lt;/strong&gt; is a minor action that targets an
adjacent bloodied enemy and knocks it prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like the brute that would be stationed at the back row waiting for a
sparker to teleport it into the PCs’ backline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hejkin being right next to halflings and sharing some common traits (like their
size and ground speed) makes me think that they might be corrupted
halflings. Mechanically, they appear to be what you use instead of goblins and
kobolds to challenge beginning adventurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hejkin don’t collaborate with other humanoids, but they do train and keep all
sorts of insectoid beasts, with a preference for those who can burrow. Kruthiks
and Ankhegs are favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/01/hejkin.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/08/01/hejkin.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Halfling</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-halfling.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A halfling wielding a spear and wearing bone armor, sneaking through a
    forest.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athasian halflings are physically identical to their standard 4e counterparts,
but their culture is very different. If you have ever heard of Dark Sun in any
detail, you’ll likely also have heard that it has cannibal halflings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is true, but I feel it’s lost a bit of its impact here, halfway down the
critter list for the book. Halflings are the fourth cannibal humanoids we met so
far, after belgois, braxats, and gith. I’m not even counting all the magical
beasts that eat sapients, or we’d be here all day reciting names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They still have the disctinction of being our first &lt;em&gt;playable&lt;/em&gt; cannibals. Most
Dark Sun halflings belong to the tribal cultures that inhabit the Forest Ridge,
one of the last remaining green regions of Athas. They’re very territorial and
distrustful of other species, violently defending their homes from any
invasion. Their cannibalism is mostly ritualistic, though the book also says
they eat captured intruders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individuals or small groups often leave the Forest Ridge to explore the Seven
Cities and the deserts between them. Some stick around and find employment as
guides, scouts and trackers. The worst among them might become slavers or
raiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfling tribes will deal honorably with those that are honorable to them in
turn, but anyone who breaks an oath to a halfling tribe will be declared their
eternal enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other distinction halflings have is that they’re some of the oldest sapient
peoples of Athas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athasian halflings have the exact same stats as standard ones. They’re Small
Natural Humanoids with a ground speed of 6 and the &lt;strong&gt;Nimble Reaction&lt;/strong&gt; trait
that gives them +2 to AC against opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the stat blocks here are enthusiastic users of poison, which is a good
survival strategy in a world where everyone is larger than you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;halfling-forest-runner&quot;&gt;Halfling Forest Runner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your typical sneaky halfling scout-type, this is a Level 2 Skirmisher with 37
HP. They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;poisoned spear&lt;/strong&gt; that does a mix of physical and poison
damage, and have a special technique named &lt;strong&gt;Strike and Slip Away&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
4+) that lets them make a stronger spear attack that deals ongoing poison damage
(save ends). As an effect they can then shift 5 squares and make a Stealth test
to hide if they have any cover or concealment at the end of this shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;halfling-wilder&quot;&gt;Halfling Wilder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A halfling psion trained in their ancient traditions. This one is Level 3
Artillery with 38 HP. Their main ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Mind Thrust&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10)
that deals psychic damage and makes the target grant combat advantage for a
turn. They have a simple &lt;strong&gt;club&lt;/strong&gt; for melee emergencies. All of their attacks
dels extra damage when the target grants combat advantage, making them good at
focused fire tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;halfling-forest-keeper&quot;&gt;Halfling Forest Keeper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty traditional druid of the sort that loves summoning and
controlling vines and plants… which makes it a very exotic and mysterious
spellcaster by Athasian standards, where everyone else has sand and sun
powers. Forest Keepers are respected leaders of their people, responsible for
preserving their oral traditions and lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our stat block here is for a Level 6 Controller with the Leader tag and 72
HP. Its melee basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Distracting Staff&lt;/strong&gt; that does standard damage
on a hit and lets an ally of the keeper within 5 squares shift 1 square. At
range if fires &lt;strong&gt;Thorn Darts&lt;/strong&gt; that deal poison damage and make the target
vulnerable 5 to poison for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit Creepers&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is our “vines” spell, an Area Burst 2 within
10 that affects only enemies, targets Reflex, deals physical damage, and
restrains on a hit (save ends). Allies caught in the burst recover 5 HP instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Constricting Creepers&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a stronger version that deals physical
damage in a Close Burst 3 around the keeper, and knocks prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;halfling-headhunter&quot;&gt;Halfling Headhunter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An elite champion whose mission is to stalk and eliminate the tribe’s worst
enemies… and to bring their heads as proof. It’s a Level 11 Skirmisher with
114 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The headhunter’s attacks all do extra damage when it has &lt;strong&gt;combat
advantage&lt;/strong&gt;. Its main weapon is a &lt;strong&gt;kukri&lt;/strong&gt; that does a blend of physical and
poison damage, and it can also throw equally poisoned &lt;strong&gt;Javelins&lt;/strong&gt; that also
slow on a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Harrying Attack&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) lets the headhunter make a
dagger attack, shift 3 squares, and then make another dagger attack all as part
of the same action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use these tools to stay at the edges of a fight and harry the
squishies. Add some leveled-up wilders to make them even stronger by making the
PCs vulnerable to poison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their Forest Ridge homes, halflings are very unlikely to be accompanied by
humanoids of other species, but they do domesticate a lot of the local wildlife
for use in battle. In another twist that seems extremely exotic to Athasians and
very familiar to us, most of this wildlife consists of mammals and birds,
instead of reptiles and insects. Panthers, kirres (which we’ll see soon),
griffons, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When met in the general Seven Cities area, they join the pool of species you can
draw from to assemble Mixed Parties of People.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halflings are very skirmisher-y here, and it looks like all stat blocks are
simple enough that you can adjust their level directly without having to make
big changes to their abilities. Monster Manual halfling stats work well in
conjunction with these, though I’d replace any slings with poison darts or the
equivalent to keep the flavor.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/22/wir-dscc-halfling.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/22/wir-dscc-halfling.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Goliath</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dark Sun always had “half-giants” ever since its 2e days. They were very large,
very strong, and had this funky random alignment rule. Here in Fourth Edition,
they’ve been syncretized with goliaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Athasian goliaths are also known as half-giants. They’re not a natural species,
but a product of sorcerer-king experimentation blending human and giant
DNA. Nowadays, most goliaths live in the city-states, but there are communities
of them out in the mountains of the Tyr Region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s official: The Dark Sun Creature Catalog has nothing nice to say
about &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;. Here, it says city-dwelling goliaths are brutal enforcers for
the templars and the Sorcerer-Kings, and that mountain-dwelling ones are
“barbaric raiders” who have little use for companions who are not “pets or
slaves”. Some of them dwell among the giants of the Sea of Silt, where they are
treated as menial servants but also permitted to take part in raiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2e lore about half-giants said they were so lolrandom that you actually rolled
on a table every day to see what half your alignment would be. This is gone from
their 4e incarnation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-number&quot;&gt;The Number&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, goliaths are Natural Humanoids and occupy the very high end of Medium
size. Their speed is 6, and their signature power is &lt;strong&gt;Stone’s Endurance&lt;/strong&gt;, a
minor action encounter power that gives them some amount of damage resistance
for a turn. Here, the specifics vary per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-enforcer&quot;&gt;Goliath Enforcer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representing your typical goliath thug, raider, or mercenary, this is a Level 8
Brute with 105 HP. It’s armed with a &lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt;, and if surrounded by PCs it
can &lt;strong&gt;Push Through&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action. This is an attack vs. Fortitude that
deals no damage, pushes 1 square, knocks prone, and lets the goliath shift into
the vacated square. It recharges once it’s first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone’s Endurance here gives Resist All 5 for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the enforcer is reduced to 0 HP, &lt;strong&gt;Vengeful Clout&lt;/strong&gt; lets it make one last
attack with &lt;strong&gt;Vengeful Clout&lt;/strong&gt;, targetting Fortitude, dealing greatclub damage,
and knocking prone on a hit. Despite the name, the enforcer doesn’t have to
target the person who defeated it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-enforcer-legbreaker&quot;&gt;Goliath Enforcer Legbreaker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the same Goliath Enforcer from before as seen by PCs in the mid-Paragon
tier, who have far surpassed it in skill. It’s a Level 16 Minion Brute. It has
the same Greatclub and Vengeful Clout attacks as the regular level 8 version,
but dealing appropriate damage for its level and minion-ness. Its Stone’s
Endurance makes it take no damage from the next attack that hits it before the
end of its next turn, which sounds powerful but is the only version of the
ability that would make any difference on a minion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to note that both the Enforcer and the Legbreaker are worth 350
XP, so XP total ends up being an interesting guideline for when to upgrade or
downgrade a monster’s quality as it goes down or up in level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-gladiator&quot;&gt;Goliath Gladiator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better-trained goliath fighter usually met in the arena, with a big bone
greataxe and an arsenal of fancy tricks. It’s a Level 11 Soldier with 114 HP and
the Leader tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attacks of the &lt;strong&gt;Bone Greataxe&lt;/strong&gt; deal standard damage and immediately end
the target’s marks on the gladiator. It can also use the weapon in a &lt;strong&gt;Leg
Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that targets Fortitude, deals the same amount of damage, slows and
prevents the target from shifting for a turn. And finally, it can be used in a
&lt;strong&gt;Skull Cleaver&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that also targets Fortitude, deals heavy damage,
daze, and impose a -2 penalty to saves (save ends both). This recharges when the
goliath misses with the power, so it will keep trying until it hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks to me like the gladiator really wants to get past the party’s defenders
with the help of its basic attacks, and then use the special maneuvers on the
party’s squishies that are likely to have a worse Fortitide defense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goliath’s leaderly abilities are all Minor Actions: &lt;strong&gt;Get Up!&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
5+) lets an adjacent ally either stand up as a free action, or make a save
against a dazing, immobilizing or restraining effect. &lt;strong&gt;Offensive Form&lt;/strong&gt; lets it
mark every adjacent enemy for a turn. Its Stone’s Endurance gives Resist 10 All
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-kings-guard&quot;&gt;Goliath King’s Guard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you finally go meet that crime boss or petty warlord who has an army of
goliath legbreakers at his service, these are the dudes who will be standing
next to him as his elite bodyguards. They’re Level 16 Soldiers with 154 HP,
wielding halberds and wearing scale armor. Their weapons give them &lt;strong&gt;Threatening
Reach&lt;/strong&gt; 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They might also have metal blades, because their basic attack is described as a
&lt;strong&gt;Halberd&lt;/strong&gt; without any material qualifiers as “bone” or “obsidian”. They do
standard damage, slide the target one square and mark it for a turn. The
&lt;strong&gt;Mighty Clout&lt;/strong&gt; technique (recharge 5+) deals heavy damage, slides 1 square,
and knocks prone. Their Stone’s Endurance gives them Resist 10 All for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A relatively simple stat block, but it’s good at its job of preventing PCs from
getting close to the boss. As mentioned above, it goes well with a small
army of legbreaker minions in addition to the boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the vitriol heaped upon them by the book, ultimately Goliaths also fit
the category of People, so you might find them in the usual Mixed People
Encounters as well. They can be allies or enemies, free or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks are pretty simple. Big fighters with big weapons. I thought the
gladiator was the standout here, lots of interesting martial tricks on that one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/20/wir-dscc-goliath.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/20/wir-dscc-goliath.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Golem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;That’s the title of the entry, but I’ll try to not to use it outside of the
monster names since it’s a bit appropriative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As as far as D&amp;amp;D goes, these are our “top-tier” constructs, usually placed in
guardian roles but sometimes found following their creator around and responding
to direct commands from them. They’re made by binding an elemental into a
physical shell made out of some material, as we saw in the Monster Manual/Vault
reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bone, clay, flesh and stone constructs are as common here as they are in other
settings, but not even the wealthiest and most wasteful of Sorcerer Kings would
make a construct out of iron, let alone other metals. Instead, Athasian wizards
have developed other models made of more commonly available materials. This
doesn’t mean the constructs themselves are common, as most of the rituals to
make them are jealously guarded secrets, and even those who still know them
don’t necessarily know the theory behind the recipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind you, metal constructs might still be found in the depths of some Green Age
or Red Age ruins, and they remain exceedingly dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of our specimens here are Large Natural Animates with the Construct
tag. They’re immune to disease, poison, and sleep. Everything else varies per
stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;salt-golem&quot;&gt;Salt Golem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a construct made out of rock salt, which has some different properties
from common stone. The most relevant here is that it’s surrounded by a haze of
salt particles shed from its main body, which it can control. Salt is highly
toxic at these concentrations and the creature can send it right into your
bloodstream if you have any open wounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salt constructs are Level 11 Elite Brutes with 278 HP, a ground speed of 5
(cannot shift), and Darkvision. They’re surrounded by a haze of &lt;strong&gt;Toxic Salt&lt;/strong&gt;
that acts as an aura (2), which inflicts -2 to the defenses of any enemy
inside. If the enemy is bloodied, it also takes 5 poison damage when it starts
its turn in the aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creature attacks with the now-traditional &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals heavy damage
and on a hit inflicts 5 ongoing poison damage and -2 to attacks (save ends
both). &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; lets it slam twice in one action. Its special attack
controls that salt cloud to cause &lt;strong&gt;Horrid Dehydration&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 3, enemies
only, recharge 4+), which damages then weakens and slows for a turn. If the
target is bloodied it the conditions become (save ends both) instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dune-golem&quot;&gt;Dune Golem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a construct made out of loose sand bound together by air magic. It can
hold a humanoid shape, but it’s diffuse instead of solid, making it particularly
resistant to conventional attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dune construct is a Level 13 Elite Soldier with 184 HP. It has a ground speed
of 5, and a burrow speed of 5 on loose earth. In addition to the standard
immunities to disease, sleep, and poison, it also takes half damage from melee
and ranged attacks. Unlike its solid cousins from this entry, it can shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creature is surrounded by an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Gusting Sands&lt;/strong&gt;, which counts as
difficult terrain for enemies inside. Whenever such an enemy tries to stand up
from prone inside the aura, they must roll a save. If they fail, they stay prone
and waste the action they spent trying to get up. We also see the &lt;strong&gt;Unhindered&lt;/strong&gt;
trait here, which lets the construct pull grabbed victims along when it moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The construct’s &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; deal the usual damage, and grab on a hit. It can have
up to two grabbed victims, and can sustain the grabs for free. It has &lt;strong&gt;Double
Attack&lt;/strong&gt;, so it could grab two victims in the same action if it hits with both
slams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grabbed victims are susceptible to &lt;strong&gt;Engulf&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action attack that deals
light damage but starts inflicting ongoing 15 damage until the grab ends!  And
then you have &lt;strong&gt;Shifting Sands&lt;/strong&gt; a move action power that lets the construct
either shift its speed, or to shift half its speed and gain phasing during this
movement. While shifting, it ignores difficult terrain and can move through
enemy spaces, so this is a good escape hatch in addition to being a way to play
keep-away with the suffocating grabbed victims and their allies. One special
condition with the phasing here is that it only works if the surface in question
has a hole wide enough to let a grain of sand through, which shouldn’t be a
problem in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;obsidian-golem&quot;&gt;Obsidian Golem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another construct made from a type of stone with specific properties. In this
case, obsidian is more or less natural volcanic glass. Like the stone they’re
made from, these constructs are very very sharp. They’re also deceptively fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are Level 19 Elite Soldiers with 358 HP. Their speed is merely 4 and they
cannot shift, but they’re &lt;strong&gt;Razor Sharp&lt;/strong&gt;. This property is modeled as an aura
(1). Any enemy inside the aura that moves to another square inside the aura
takes 10 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of Double Attack, obsidian constructs have &lt;strong&gt;Inexorable Action&lt;/strong&gt;, which
lets them roll initiative twice and take two whole turns per round at those
counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The construct’s &lt;strong&gt;Slams&lt;/strong&gt; deal the usual brute-tier damage, push 1 square, knock
prone, and inflict ongoing 5 damage (save ends) from the bits of obsidian that
break off and get stuck in the wound. It can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Stunning Handclap&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 6+) which attacks all enemies in a Close Burst 5. On a hit it deals
thunder damage and stuns for a turn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rechargeable multi-target stun is a terrifying prospect. A lucky recharge roll
might let the creature use this twice in a round, which is a very bad thing for
the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re gonna run into some of these things eventually in any D&amp;amp;D campaign that
goes on for long enough, and these ones are reasonably interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If guarding a site, they’ll either be accompanied by more constructs or by other
long-lasting guardians such as undead, devils, or demons. If found as
bodyguards, they’ll be accompanied by their masters and any other goons you care
to add to the group.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/15/wir-dscc-golem.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/15/wir-dscc-golem.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Gith</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-dscc-gith.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A gith warrior with a spear.
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dscc/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things we learned about the cosmology of Athas early in the Campaign
Setting reading is that its Shadowfell is locally known as the Gray, and it’s
suspected to block access to the Astral Sea and any other worlds beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This becomes relevant here, because the people known as the Gith are said to
have arrived on Athas long ago, sailing from beyond the Gray in silvery
ships. Once here, however, they found out they couldn’t go back. To make matters
worse, these alien visitors found out that they were particularly susceptible to
the corruptive influences of Athasian arcane magic, which turned them Darker and
Sunnier over the generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present-day gith are more monstrous in appearance than the ones you’re used
to. Their mindset is also more monstrous, which is saying something considering
these were probably githyanki invaders to start with. Despite the mutations
they’ve undergone, they retain their psychic abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gith organize in nomadic hunter communities, wandering through the moutains and
the Tablelands region. They make no particular distinction between standard
animals and sapient outsiders when it comes to chosing their prey, and think
both make fine eating. Some Gith groups are dedicated to gathering the scattered
parts of their original ships, hoping to reassemble them so they can get off
this rock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gith are Medium Natural Humanoids with Speed 6. Their signature power is the
same as that of standard githyanki: &lt;strong&gt;Telekinetic Leap&lt;/strong&gt;, an encounter power
that lets them fly 5 squares as a move action. Other attacks and abilities vary
with training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gith-savage&quot;&gt;Gith Savage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rank-and-file of any large gith raiding force, the book describes their
lives as nasty, brutish, and short. These Level 4 Minion Skirmishers fight with
obsidian-tipped spears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gith’s basic &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt; attack damages and lets it shift 1 square. Once per
encounter they can enhance one attack into a &lt;strong&gt;Telekinetic Pierce&lt;/strong&gt;, which
targets Fortitude, deals the same damage and pushes the target 1 square. I think
this above might be the first psychic power I’ve seen that &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; target
Will. There are a few others in this entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gith-hobbler&quot;&gt;Gith Hobbler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hunters are level 4 Artillery with 46 HP. They prefer to stay far away
throwing Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;Javelins&lt;/strong&gt;. Once per encounter they can throw a particularly
well-aimed &lt;strong&gt;Pinning Javelin&lt;/strong&gt;, that does a bit more damage and immobilizes
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone gets too close, they’re subject to the hobbler’s aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Brain
Fog&lt;/strong&gt;, which inflicts a -2 penalty to attacks and damage to enemies inside. I
wonder if there’s one of these near me these days. Someone who insists on
attacking them in melee might force the hobbler to use its &lt;strong&gt;bone dagger&lt;/strong&gt;,
which does light damage and lets them shift 1 square on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gith-spearhead&quot;&gt;Gith Spearhead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A front-line fighter wielding a barbed obsidian-headed spear. It’s a Level 5
Brute with 76 HP. The &lt;strong&gt;Vicious Spear&lt;/strong&gt; is pretty strong, as expected of a
brute, and can be used in a &lt;strong&gt;Focused Stab&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) that deals more
damage and knocks prone. If the target is bloodied, the attack deals &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt;
damage and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the spearhead is reduced to 0 HP, it lets out an &lt;strong&gt;Ancestor’s Appeal&lt;/strong&gt;, a
Close Burst 1 that targets Fortitude and deals psychic damage. In addition to
the damage, a hit also inflicts ongoing 5 psychic damage, and a further 5
psychic damage whenever the target uses a daily or encounter power (save ends
both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;git-drone&quot;&gt;Git Drone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drones are gith that show increased psychic aptitude as children, and are
subject to a torturous training regimen to further develop their powers. They’re
Level 5 Controllers with 62 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drones emit a &lt;strong&gt;Brain Fog&lt;/strong&gt; aura that works like the hobbler’s, but is much
wider in radius (3). They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Bone Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and with
&lt;strong&gt;Telekinetic Thrusts&lt;/strong&gt; at up to range 5. These deal force damage, and slide 2
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every so often they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Psychic Nova&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+). This is an Area
Burst 1 Within 5 that targets Reflex, deals untyped damage, and makes the target
suffer 5 psychic damage whenever they use a daily or encounter power (save
ends). If the target is bloodied, it instead deals ongoing 5 damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one time I briefly played a Dark Sun game, one of the PCs was a “standard”
gith fighter, so I had thought the gith of Athas were both unchanged from their
astral relatives and playable. Turns out I was wrong! Mechanically they’re still
similar to githyanki, but their look and feel is pretty different than what I
expected, and there are no rules for gith PCs in the Campaign Setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gith are commonly found in all-gith hunting parties, perhaps accompanied by
domesticated baazrags or other trained beasties. They can also be found in mixed
parties of People, whether as willing members or as slaves commanded to fight.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/07/wir-dscc-gith.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2025/07/07/wir-dscc-gith.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
