<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 20:04:10 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 20:04:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Hag</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-hag.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned way back in the MM/MV post about &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/05/16/hag.html&quot;&gt;Hags&lt;/a&gt;, they’re a species of
fey that resemble fairytale witches in appearance and behavior. They tend to
have great knowledge of magic, but also tend use it to further selfish and
greedy schemes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic lore remains the same in the MM3, which also adds that hags are
keepers of secrets. They’re always after new treasure and new secrets, generally
of the type that increases their power. They use divination magic, pacts with
mortals, and a network of portals that weaves through the Feywild and the middle
world, which they also use to keep connected to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hags are of course loathe to part with any of their secrets for
free. Adventurers seeking information from a hag must usually agree to do them a
favor, which commonly means doing something nasty to one of the hag’s many
enemies. These enemies might include archfey, demons, devils, other hags…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hags are Medium Fey Humanoids and have Low-Light Vision. Everything else varies
with stat blocks, which are usually split along the lines of which type of magic
a hag uses in combat. I don’t think they’re supposed to be different sub-species
or anything of the sort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pact-hag&quot;&gt;Pact Hag&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is your typical “sinister village witch”, living in a hut out of sight of
the village itself. This location is far enough away to deter curious casuals,
but still close enough that someone who really wants to make a deal with the hag
can easily reach it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pact hag is much more willing to negotiate with these visitors than most of
her relatives, though she’s still just as prone to seeking deals that benefit
her more than they do the petitioner. She usually keep ogres, trolls, and
dangerous fey fauna as bodyguards. They’re initially out of sight, but can
arrive quickly if a fight breaks out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pact hags are Level 11 Controllers with the Leader tag and 115 HP. In a fight,
they use all sorts of fun mind control magic, starting with a &lt;strong&gt;Pact of
Obedience&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that allows allies inside to spend 5 HP to reroll a missed
attack roll with a +2 bonus to the reroll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Compelling Staff&lt;/strong&gt; that deals light damage but
forces the target to make a melee basic attack against a target of the hag’s
choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her basic ranged attack is named &lt;strong&gt;Pact of Compelled Obedience&lt;/strong&gt; and does no
damage at all, but it dominates the target for a turn instead. Fun (TM) for the
whole party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her special attacks follow along the same lines. &lt;strong&gt;Pact of Choked Aggression&lt;/strong&gt;
also doesn’t do immediate damage and inflicts a nasty curse on the target:
they take 10 psychic damage the first time they hit a creature during one of
their turns. This lasts until the end of the encounter, or until one of the
target’s allies attacks the target. And it recharges when no enemy is affected
by the curse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Pact of Shared Agony&lt;/strong&gt;, which the hag can only
use while bloodied. It’s another curse: until the end of the encounter, if the
target is within 10 squares of the hag, they take 10 psychic damage whenever the
hag takes any amount of damage. This power recharges whenever the hag misses
with it, so she can keep using it until she hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This big emphasis on indirect damage means pact hags work best when surrounded
by those beefy bodyguards, and will probably try to flee the fight once they
become bloodied. Pact of Shared Agony is good for discouraging pursuit by melee
strikers. Their “Pact” theme makes them a good patron for a heroic-tier fey
warlock! This patron hag might either level up as the PC does, or you can have a
story where the PC “trades up” to a better teacher Sith-style once the hag’s
demands become untenable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dream-hag&quot;&gt;Dream Hag&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hags, as you might imagine, focus on dream magic. They can send dream
visions to people, a power they use to lure their (or their paying customer’s)
enemies to traps. However, the constraints of dream magic mean the hag doesn’t
have full control over the content of the visions, so genuinely useful
information tends to slip through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dream Hags are Level 19 Controllers with 179 HP. They project a &lt;strong&gt;Nightmare
Weaver&lt;/strong&gt; aura (3) that causes unconscious enemies inside to become dominated for
a turn. They stand up and perform one action of the hag’s choice while still
remaining unconscious. The wording here makes it clear that this puppetry
continues while the enemies remain inside the aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Staff of Mindless Reverie&lt;/strong&gt;, which damages and dazes
for a turn on a hit. Their at-will ranged attack are weaponized &lt;strong&gt;Nightmare
Visions&lt;/strong&gt; that deal psychic damage and slide the target 5 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then we have the powers that make people unconscious so the hag can exploit
her aura. Both affect a Close Blast 5! &lt;strong&gt;Dust of Dreams&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) dazes on
a hit (save ends), and this worsens to unconsciousness after the first failed
save. &lt;strong&gt;Sleep’s Undeniable Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; (Encounter) makes its targets unconscious
right away. It’s a (save ends) effect and it also ends if the target is
attacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it’s possible for the hag to put the whole party to sleep at once if she’s
really lucky. This &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; be an automatic total party kill if you run the
abilities as written, though - sleeping PCs can still roll saves to end the
effect, and in the case of the encounter power they also wake up if attacked. Of
course, this attack will probably be an auto-crit if it comes from an enemy, so
it’s still a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think it’s acceptable to fudge things a little if Team Monster’s goal is
something other than killing the PCs. If the goal is capturing them, or taking
them somewhere else, then you can fade to black if the whole party falls asleep
and have them wake up at that place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mist-hag&quot;&gt;Mist Hag&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are among the most powerful of hags. They’ve been accumulating secrets,
artifacts and power for ages, and they dwell in the deepest forests of the
Feywild. Their dwellings are surrounded by a thick mist that they have full
control over. If the Death Hag from the MM1 was a “Baba Yaga wannabe”, this one
is closest to the real deal. She’s pretty much an arch-fey herself. The Mist Hag
does not deal with devils - devils deal with &lt;em&gt;her&lt;/em&gt;. A few of them probably have
been pressed into service as her bodyguards. Other possible allies include epic
undead, fomorians, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Mist Hag is a Level 27 Controller with the Leader tag and 247 HP. She has a
zippy ground speed of 8, instead of the standard 6 for a medium humanoid. Her
aura is a &lt;strong&gt;Mist Shroud&lt;/strong&gt; that makes allies within 1 square insubstantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hag’s &lt;strong&gt;Mist Staff&lt;/strong&gt; damages and pushes targets 5 squares. During the push,
targets act as if they had the Phasing trait, which means the hag can push them
through walls and other creatures. The final destination square must still be
empty, but the hag doesn’t need to have a line of effect to it or the other
squares of the push. If you want to get cute with this ability, include a piece
of hazardous terrain surrounded by walls in your battle map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her basic attack is &lt;strong&gt;Mist on the Wind&lt;/strong&gt;, which damages and removes the
target from play for a turn! The target returns to play in a square of the hag’s
choice within 4 squares of its original position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Choking Mist&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a ranged attack serves as a reminder
that the PCs are breathing the same mist the hag can control. It deals heavy
physical damage and ongoing 20 damage (save ends). Every time the target fails a
save, the hag can slide them 3 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an enemy gets to within 2 squares of the hag, the hag can use &lt;strong&gt;Maze of
Mist&lt;/strong&gt; to mess with them. This is a triggered effect that doesn’t require an
action, so it can happen every time the trigger happens. When it does, the hag
can roll a d20. On a 10 or higher, she slides the triggering enemy 1
square. This makes closing to melee reach a lot harder than usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said back in the original article, I like hags when they are portrayed as
their own species of fey being that don’t necessarily need to obey natural
laws. They’re fairytale witches, with a penchant for doing the things fairytale
witches do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I think treating each hag stat block as an entirely different species
is going a bit too far. I prefer to treat those as differences of skill and
training.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/20/hag.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/20/hag.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Gremlin</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-gremlin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just look at this pointy boy. They’re not even trying to hide the inspiration
for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, D&amp;amp;D has had monsters named “gremlin” since almost its beginning, but the
lore for them its new to this edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, the fomorians under King Thrumbolg took a large group of goblin
captives, transformed them into bioweapons, and released them into the cities of
their eladrin enemies. The new creatures had a great aptitude for deception and
sabotage, and an engineered predilection for it. These were the first gremlins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They did their job wonderfully, disrupting the alliance of eladrin city states
arrayed against Thrumbolg by altering the correspondence between them, murdering
key officials, and other such deeds. However, they also ended up doing the same
sort of thing to Thumbolg’s own court, causing great damage to it. Gremlins
gotta gremlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The little rascals were cast out, and over the ages spread through the Feywild
and the middle world. Though they sometimes live openly in the communities of
other sapients, many gremlins follow their engineered calling and hide out among
their chosen victims, taming vermin to do their bidding and engaging in the same
ghastly shenanigans their ancestors did back in the day, basically for the
lulz. The worst among them find natural allies in demons, who have the same
appetite for chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of things gremlins do, taken from the stat block descriptions: stealing
documents and heirlooms from a royal court and stashing them to be found in the
quarters of visiting nobles; intercepting and altering important correspondence
so that a call for peace becomes a declaration of war; and plain old serial
murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gremlins are Small Fey Humanoids with low-light vision and a speed of 6. They
have two signature abilities present in almost all stat blocks. The first is
&lt;strong&gt;Sabotaging Presence&lt;/strong&gt;, an large aura (size 5) that gives enemies inside a -5
penalty to skill checks. The second is &lt;strong&gt;Gremlin Tactics&lt;/strong&gt;, a reaction that
allows them to swap spaces with an enemy that misses them with a melee attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skill-wise, training in Stealth and Thievery is nearly universal, and they
occasionally know other “thiefy” skills like Bluff as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gremlin-deceiver&quot;&gt;Gremlin Deceiver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deceivers are Level 5 Controllers with 63 HP, which makes them the earliest
gremlin the PCs are likely to find. Like other gremlins, their presence is going
to be hidden at first, and they only fight when found out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deceivers fight with their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt;, but their magic is a lot more
interesting. They can cast a fireball-sized &lt;strong&gt;Befuddling Burst&lt;/strong&gt; that targets
Will and, on a hit, deals psychic damage and prevents targets from shifting or
standing up (save ends). The burst itself doesn’t knock them prone - that’s what
the &lt;strong&gt;Slip Up&lt;/strong&gt; minor-action attack does. This is a ranged attack that targets
Will and does no damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For added lulz, pair them with other monsters that can knock people prone, such
as other gremlins, or wolves reskinned as dire rats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gremlin-skulker&quot;&gt;Gremlin Skulker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skulkers are Level 7 Lurkers with 64 HP, and they’re surprisingly sticky. Aside
from the standard gremlin traits, they have a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Sneak&lt;/strong&gt; passive that
makes them invisible while adjacent to an enemy, and &lt;strong&gt;Opportunistic Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;
that gives them extra damage in opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks do okay damage and “curse” the target: if the target
moves away from the gremlin, they fall prone at the end of their movement. And
when an enemy adjacent to the skulker moves, the &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Skulk&lt;/strong&gt; encounter
power allows them to shift up to 6 squares &lt;em&gt;simultaneously&lt;/em&gt;, following the enemy
as it moves so it stays adjacent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want this one right in the middle of the PCs, preferrably starting the fight
already there with some of those strong opportunity attcks after sneaking in
undetected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gremlin-conniver&quot;&gt;Gremlin Conniver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connivers are Level 17 Controllers with 162 HP. That’s quite a jump in power!
They’re probably similar to the OG gremlins that destroyed the eladrin alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack also teleports the target 5 squares on a hit. Their
&lt;strong&gt;Connive&lt;/strong&gt; spell is a non-damaging, at-will ranged attack that dominates on a
hit (&lt;em&gt;save ends&lt;/em&gt;!). Fortunately only one creature can be dominated at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action it can also create a &lt;strong&gt;Beguiling Fog&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+), a
fireball-sized area attack against Will that does no damage. It always dazes the
enemy - a hit means it’s a (save ends) effect, a miss means it only lasts a
turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While connivers have little direct damage potential, they can dole out some of
the game’s most annoying status effects at-will. The teleport effect on their
basic claw attack is also particularly wonderful in battlefields with dangerous
terrain or other hazards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gremlin-prankster&quot;&gt;Gremlin Prankster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pranksters are Level 17 Minion Controllers, perfect for when you want to
re-enact a certain 80s movie. They’re not particularly hardy, but they like to
run around in huge crowds and try to cause as much chaos as possible before
vanishing. They have a basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack and a &lt;strong&gt;Slip Up&lt;/strong&gt; ranged attack
that’s similar to the Deceiver’s, but also slides the target 3 squares before
knocking them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teme for the Gremlins 2 movie was playing through my head the entire time I
was writing this. I love these critters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re also very interesting mechanically and can end up making your PCs pull
their own hair out in frustration. That can lead to memorable sessions if you do
it properly, but can also be frustrating for the &lt;em&gt;players&lt;/em&gt;, so consider the
examples below cautiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you really want the PCs to have a bad time, make sure your gremlin encounter
takes place in a site full of traps and other hazards that require skill checks
to disable. Or even have the PCs deal with a gremlin battle and a skill
challenge at the same time. The skill penalty from Sabotaging Presence is
&lt;em&gt;untyped&lt;/em&gt;, meaning it technically stacks, but if you’re feeling merciful you can
say it caps out at the -5 a single gremlin would provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That skill penalty also aids grappling-centered monsters! The roll to escape a
grapple is a skill check, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since a lot of gremlins can knock PCs prone, they also go really well with
monsters that can do ugly things to prone PCs. Especially evil GMs might want to
keep in mind that 2 Gremlin Deceivers and 2 Needlefang Drake Swarms make up a
valid Level 3 encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/19/gremlin.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/19/gremlin.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Gnoll</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-gnoll.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh boy, more gnolls. They’ve been in every Monster Manual for this edition. I
skipped the MM2 entry because it turned out to fully overlap the Monster Vault,
but the one in this book is specifically meant to complement the MV instead of
overlapping with it. We don’t get much in the way of new lore, but we get a few
new stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, gnolls are Medium Natural Humanoids. They have low-light vision and
their ground speed is 7. Their signature ability remains &lt;strong&gt;Pack Attack&lt;/strong&gt;,
giving them a +5 damage bonus on melee and ranged attacks against an enemy that
has two or more gnoll allies adjacent to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gnoll-skulker&quot;&gt;Gnoll Skulker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first gnoll, however, is a bit of an exception. These runty buggers are too
cowardly to employ the usual brutish gnoll tactics, so they usually keep to the
edges of the fight and wait for opportunities to strike isolated enemies from
surprise. They’re good at this, but it’s not a fighting style that’s valued in
“mainstream” demon-worshipping gnoll society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skulkers are Level 5 Lurkers with 51 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;Peerless Camouflage&lt;/strong&gt; allows
them to make Stealth checks to hide even when they only have partial cover or
concealment, and to stay hidden for an additional turn after leaving
cover. They lack Pack Attack but have &lt;strong&gt;Something to Prove&lt;/strong&gt;, gaining a +5
damage bonus against enemies that have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; allies adjacent to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with a &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;shortbow&lt;/strong&gt;, and have a &lt;strong&gt;Hit and Run&lt;/strong&gt;
maneuver that allows them to shift 2 squares after hitting with the bow if they
attack from hiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A band of gnolls with some skulkers in it is a lot harder to fight. If you
spread out a bit to make it harder for the standard gnolls to use Pack Attack,
the skulkers get you with Something to Prove, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gnoll-war-fang&quot;&gt;Gnoll War Fang&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War Fangs are heavily armored commander-types that also make use of demonic
powers. They’re anti-paladins of Yeenoghu, basically. War Fangs are Level 6
Soldiers with 72 HP and the Leader tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;War Fang Defense&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) grants allies a +2 bonus to AC, and they
fight with a Longsword that deals extra damage when they’re bloodied (this
stacks with Pack Attack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per round as a minor action, they can issue a &lt;strong&gt;Demonic Challenge&lt;/strong&gt; that
works a lot like the paladin version - it marks an enemy within 3 squares, and
whenever the marked enemy makes an attack that doesn’t target the war fang they
suffer 10 fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any enemy misses the war fang with a melee attack, the &lt;strong&gt;No Mercy&lt;/strong&gt; ability
allows an ally adjacent to that enemy to make a melee basic attack against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;War Fangs work very well when positioned in the second row of the enemy front
line, because they’ll improve the front-liners’ defenses and mark the PCs from a
place where they can’t be easily attacked. They also do very well on the front
line when surrounded by their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chosen-of-yeenoghu&quot;&gt;Chosen of Yeenoghu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a gnoll necromancer, a Level 7 Elite Controller with 156 HP. It fights
with a &lt;strong&gt;staff&lt;/strong&gt; in melee and fires &lt;strong&gt;bolts of ruination&lt;/strong&gt; that deal necrotic
damage at range, but its main schtick is filling the battlefield with ghostly
hyenas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chosen can summon a single &lt;strong&gt;Hyena Spirit&lt;/strong&gt; as a minor action, or four of
them at once with the &lt;strong&gt;Call Beyond the Grave&lt;/strong&gt; encounter power. &lt;strong&gt;Spirit
Strike&lt;/strong&gt; is a 1/round minor action that allows a spirit to make a free basic
attack with a +2 bonus. Finally, &lt;strong&gt;To the Front&lt;/strong&gt; is a power that teleports
every adjacent ally 10 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a monster, not a PC, so it doesn’t use PC summoning rules. Hyena Spirits
are Level 7 Minion Soldiers and each one has their own full set of actions in
the initiative order. They have a &lt;strong&gt;Spectral Jaws&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) that slows enemies
caught inside, and a standard basic bite attack. When one of them dies, the
Chosen takes 5 damage. Depending on how the Chosen is positioned, killing the
hyenas might be the only way the PCs can damage it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirits are worth 0 XP if they’re summoned by a Chosen, but you can include
them in a fight by themselves and have them work as normal minions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continue to mourn the fact that they never expanded playable non-evil gnolls
beyond that single Dragon article, while remarking that the mechanics for these
gnolls are pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/16/gnolls.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/16/gnolls.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Girallon</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-girallon.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how, way back in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/05/04/ape.html&quot;&gt;“Ape”&lt;/a&gt; entry, I commented that I wasn’t fond
of the “pulp fiction carnivorous gorilla” cliches some of them were leaning on?
Then you might imagine how I feel about this particular monster. I first saw
them in the 3e Monster Manual, but they might have appeared in a supplement for
an earlier edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A girallon is what happens when you take every single one of those cliches, lump
them together, and double the result. It’s an evil carnivorous gorilla that has
twice the size, twice the appetite for human flesh, and twice the number of arms
as the standard version of the trope. To complete the cliche bingo card,
girallons have white fur and are frequently worshipped as gods by “savage
jungle-dwelling tribes”. So yeah, not a great look so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girallons are voracious carnivores and messy eaters that have the habit of
leaving viscera and entrails lying around their territories. They can climb and
move through the treetops with practiced ease, but their large size means they
need to sleep on the ground. Their lairs are usually in caves or ruins. Though
not sapient, some of them learn to make trails in their territory’s vegetation
that lead to prime ambush spots, which can act as an effective lure for sapient
prey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Girallons are usually the most badass predators in their region. They’re either
solitary or organized in small bands, and do not willingly seek out allies of
other species. Still, they’re sometimes “tamed” by giants, trolls, fomorians and
other such sapients. Prospective girallon keepers must be either big and strong
enough to physically beat the creatures into submission, or have the knowledge
of magic necessary to keep them dominated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;girallon&quot;&gt;Girallon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic model and the template used for the others. This is a Large Natural
Beast and a Level 12 Brute with 145 HP. It has a ground speed of 8 and a climb
speed of 6. Its four arms act as a &lt;strong&gt;Threatening Claws&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) that makes all
enemies inside grant combat advantage, and a &lt;strong&gt;Combat Climber&lt;/strong&gt; trait that make
it not provoke opportunity attacks when climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack is Reach 2 and does the heavy damage expected of a
brute, and the &lt;strong&gt;Claw Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; special (recharge 5+) allows it to make four
half-damage claw attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;girallon-alpha&quot;&gt;Girallon Alpha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This specimen is much bigger and stronger than a typical girallon. It has all
the same traits as the basic model but is level 17 with 195 HP. It has two new
abilities as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a positioning thing: &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Claws&lt;/strong&gt; is a free action triggered
when an enemy starts its turn within 2 squares of the alpha. The alpha slides
that enemy 1 square, which is perfect for breaking flanking maneuvers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is a special attack: &lt;strong&gt;Rend and Tear&lt;/strong&gt; targets enemies in a Close
Blast 3, does heavy damage, and slides the targets 3 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;infernal-girallon&quot;&gt;Infernal Girallon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago some devils decided infusing packs of girallons with the power
of Hell for use as bioweapons in the Blood War would be a swell idea. Now there
are packs of Infernal Girallons roaming and hunting through both the Elemental
Chaos and the Nine Hells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These have all the same traits as a basic girallon but are Immortal instead of
Natural. They have the Devil keyword and Darkvision. They’re Level 22 Brutes
with 249 HP and all the same abilities as a basic girallon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their first new power is a trait named &lt;strong&gt;Burning Soul&lt;/strong&gt;. This aura (2) causes 10
fire damage to enemies caught inside, or 20 if the girallon is bloodied. Better
give your defenders some protection from fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their other new power is an attack named &lt;strong&gt;Burning Ichor&lt;/strong&gt;, a Close Blast 3 that
does immediate and ongoing fire damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, an even bigger girallon that is on fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You already know my opinion of their lore. I’m tempted to reskin these things
into demons or some other type of monster. I guess the exception is the lore for
Infernal Girallons. “Devils tried to do science, it did not go as planned” is a
good hook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, the Girallon is a basic paragon-tier brute, serviceable but not
spectacular. The enhanced versions add more interesting special attacks, so
depending on your needs you might want to down-level an alpha instead of using
the basic version.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/14/girallon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/14/girallon.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Giant, Hill</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-giant-hill.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another entry that that adds extra stat blocks to complement the existing MM1
and upcoming Monster Vault monsters. This one is for hill giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new lore here is minimal or restates things we saw elsewhere. Hill Giant
bands are usually small and consist of a single family group - they’re too
anti-social to form more complex organizations. Every once in a while a larger
group will manage to hold together for an extented period of time. Their leaders
style themselves kings, and the log fortresses they build are known as
steadings. You might have heard about a famous adventure with the words
“Steading”, “Hill Giant” and “King” in its title, wink wink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, Hill Giants are Large Natural Humanoids (Giants), with a basic speed
of 8. All of the ones here look like the iconic club-swinging D&amp;amp;D giant, with
the big difference being in how they fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hill-giant-smashers&quot;&gt;Hill Giant Smashers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Smasher is pretty much a “Hill Giant Lite”. It’s slightly weaker than a
standard MV giant, and doesn’t throw rocks. To compensate, it’s more mobile and
has a few more tricks in melee. This is the stat block you use for those lone
mercenary giants that get hired as living tanks by smaller evil humanoids like
hobgoblins, bugbears, or gnolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smashers are Level 11 Brutes with 137 HP. They have a passive &lt;strong&gt;Mobility&lt;/strong&gt; trait
which allows them to roll saves against being slowed, immobilized, or restrained
at the start of their turns instead of at the end. This also works for any
save-ends effect that includes these conditions, like “ongoing 5 damage and
slowed (save ends both)”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all giants in this entry they wield Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt;, and their basic
attack deals a bit of automatic splash damage to a secondary target on a
hit. Once per encounter they can perform a &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Crush&lt;/strong&gt; to attack everyone
in a close burst 2, and they can also perform a &lt;strong&gt;Brutal Smash&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
double damage and recharges on a miss. So they’ll keep trying that one until
they hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hill-giant-rockthrower&quot;&gt;Hill Giant Rockthrower&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM1 and MV give us an artillery giant that uses big javelins. But if you
want your giants to throw rocks and nothing but rocks, the Rockthrower is for
you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rockthrowers are Level 12 Artillery with 97 HP. As artillery monsters, their
&lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; attacks are kinda weak, but their basic ranged attack is a
&lt;strong&gt;Knockdown Throw&lt;/strong&gt; that does a bit more damage, pushes the target 2 squares,
and knocks them prone. They can also throw with a bit more force for a
&lt;strong&gt;Shattering Rockburst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which deals damage in an area and dazes
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use the same tactics as a catapult: seek high ground, rain death from
above. I imagine hiring a bunch of rockthrowers is quite a bit cheaper than
maintaining your own siege engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hill-giant-avalancher&quot;&gt;Hill Giant Avalancher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avalanchers are the heroic prodigies of their people. They’re much smarter than
your typical hill giant, and often end up as leaders or kings. They get their
name from their clever rock-throwing tricks and from their brutal charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Avalancher is a Level 14 Skirmisher with 139 HP. They can make basic
&lt;strong&gt;Greatclub&lt;/strong&gt; attacks and perform &lt;strong&gt;Crushing Charges&lt;/strong&gt; that do the same amount
of damage and knock targets prone. From a distance they can throw &lt;strong&gt;Rolling
Rocks&lt;/strong&gt;, which in addition to doing damage on a hit slide the target 4 squares,
knock them prone, and gather no moss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After they knocked a bunch of PCs prone, Avalanchers will move using &lt;strong&gt;Stomping
Shifts&lt;/strong&gt;, which allow them to shift 4 squares and pass through prone enemies’
spaces. They deal an automatic 8 damage to a prone enemy when they pass through
their spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avalanchers will always try to use their Crushing Charge if possible, and will
make use of Stomping Shift to position themselves for a new charge and to deal
additional damage to prone enemies. They use Rolling Rocks to break up tricky PC
formations and to return fire against ranged attackers they can’t charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s more hill giants, which it’s okay because I like hill giants. I like that
the Smasher is explicitly meant to be included as the “surprise bruiser” in a
lower-leveled humanoid group. A smasher and its humanoid employers work well as
a boss battle for a group of level 8-10 PCs, depending on how many other
monsters you add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Avalancher gives you an interesting option for a leader type who is not a
titan.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/12/giant-hill.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/12/giant-hill.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Giant, Frost</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-giant-frost.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know the drill by now - Frost Giants appeared in the MM1 and were about to
get rewritten with new math on the Monster Vault. The MM3 brings in an
assortment of them that can complement the “basic” entries in the MV. You can
look at those basic entries &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/04/frost-giants.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frost giant lore remains the same. They’re plus-sized asshole vikings who like
to live in cold regions, fight with a variety of axes, and use lots of ice
magic. Some think this behavior is in service of a greater plan laid down by
their primordial masters, but that might be reaching a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frost Giants are Large Elemental Humanoids with the Cold and Giant
keywords. Their signature trait remains &lt;strong&gt;Icebound Footing&lt;/strong&gt;, which reduces any
forced movement imposed on them by 2 squares and can reduce it to 0. They can
also roll a save to avoid being knocked prone. They have Resist 15 Cold, and
their ground speed is 8 with Ice Walk, which allows them to ignore ice or
snow-based difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frost-giant-berserker&quot;&gt;Frost Giant Berserker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d expect someone with “Berserker” in its name to be a Brute, but these are
Level 16 Skirmishers with 157 HP. The book describes them as those hot-headed
youngsters who are too undisciplined to fight like proper brutes and instead
keep running around the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;Freezing Greataxes&lt;/strong&gt;, which do a mix of physical and cold
damage. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Storm Charge&lt;/strong&gt; that doesn’t provoke opportunity
attacks from its movement and deals heavy physical damage. Once per encounter,
the berserker can use its &lt;strong&gt;Primordial Rage&lt;/strong&gt; to shift its speed and make three
basic attacks along the way, each against a different target. A bit more often
(recharge 4+) they can take a &lt;strong&gt;Giant Stride&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 6 squares and move
through enemy spaces while doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These giants are perfect for running right past the party’s defenders and
harassing their squishies. For extra annoyance, stage the fight in a map full of
ice-based difficult terrain, which doesn’t affect frost giants but makes it
harder for those defenders to reposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frost-giant-shield-bearer&quot;&gt;Frost Giant Shield Bearer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shield bearers are the opposite of berserkers. They’re the hardened veterans who
get the best gear and the best training. This makes them suitable to form the
core of a raiding party, or a lord’s honor guard. They’re huscarls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shield bearers are Level 18 Soldiers with 174 HP. They’re heavily armored and,
as the name implies, are just about the only frost giants who carry
shields. They still wield axes, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Coordinated Attack&lt;/strong&gt; ability gives them combat advantage against any
enemy that has another shield bearer adjacent to them, no flanking
required. Their &lt;strong&gt;Icy Battleaxes&lt;/strong&gt; do cold damage and mark for a turn. Once per
encounter they can enhance an attack and turn it into a &lt;strong&gt;Protective Strike&lt;/strong&gt;,
which deals 10 extra cold damage and grants 25 temporary HP to an ally within 10
squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Defensive Stand&lt;/strong&gt; allows them spend a minor action to choose an enemy
within 10 squares. If that enemy moves within reach before the end of the shield
bearer’s next turn, the shield bearer gets a free attack against that
enemy. It’s not an opportunity attack, so it should work with shifts or other
forms of movement too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re all set up to fight in tight formations and hold ground, which means
they go well with artillery and ranged controllers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;frost-giant-chieftain&quot;&gt;Frost Giant Chieftain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any frost giant community not led by a titan will likely be led by one of
these. This chieftain is a Level 20 Controller with 190 HP. He has an
&lt;strong&gt;Emanating Cold&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that makes enemies inside grant combat advantage to
cold creatures (i.e, frost giants and any monsters that are likely to tag along
with them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chieftain fights with an &lt;strong&gt;Icy Greataxe&lt;/strong&gt; that does cold damage, and can
attack at range with a &lt;strong&gt;Eye of the Storm&lt;/strong&gt; spell that does immediate and
ongoing cold damage in addition to slowing the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the chieftan can create a Medium or Large &lt;strong&gt;Pillar of Ice&lt;/strong&gt;
within ten squares. The pillar lasts for a turn and “occupies” its space,
meaning no one can move through. It blocks line of sight and slows anyone who
starts their turn next to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chieftain can also cast a spell named &lt;strong&gt;Grip of Winter&lt;/strong&gt; that creates a zone
that slows and deals cold damage to those inside. The zone lasts for the whole
encounter and the power recharges once the chieftain is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s your ranged controller to go with the shield bearers. Chieftains should
stay behind a line of their bodyguards, making the already difficult terrain of
the icy battlefield even worse with ice pillars and slowing attacks. Then you
release the berserkers to step over all that and hit the PC’s back ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like giants in general, so I like these MM3 giant entries even though they
don’t include much new lore. The trio presented here has nice mechanical synergy
and should also be fun to use with the frost giants from the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/10/giant-frost.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/10/giant-frost.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Giant, Fire</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-giant-fire.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the ghouls we just covered, fire giants are classic monsters that appeared
both in the original Monster Manual, and who would appear again in the upcoming
Monster Vault. The MM3 gives a selection of fire giant stat blocks that
complements that of the MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore for fire giants remains pretty much the same as it was &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/06/fire-giants.html&quot;&gt;in the
MM/MV&lt;/a&gt;. The new bits here add that the ancient fire giant empire had close
contact with the efreets of the Elemental chaos, and that their many volcano
fortresses were linked to each other and to the City of Brass via teleportation
circles and portals. Most of these portals are deactivated in the present day,
though the giants labor to reignite them wherever they find one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, fire giants love to team up with other fire creatures, preferrably
ones they can dominate and command. Some of them end up in the service of more
powerful masters like efreets or the older red dragons, but since fire giants
always think they should be the ones in charge they make for untrustworthy
subordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Giants are Large Elemental Humanoids with the Giant keyword. They have a
ground speed of 8 and Resist 15 Fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-giant-lavamaster&quot;&gt;Fire Giant Lavamaster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a name that looks like it came from the writer’s 8-year-old
child. Lavamasters are… masters of lava! Their magic allows them to control
magma and use it both as a weapon, and to heal their allies. Lavamasters are
Level 17 Controllers with 164 HP and the Leader tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They project an aura (2) of &lt;strong&gt;Hearthflames&lt;/strong&gt; that hurts enemies and bolsters
allies. Enemies caught inside take 10 fire damage; bloodied allies recover 10 HP
when they start their turns inside the aura. This is not any kind of “drain”
effect. Allies recover HP regardless of whether there are enemies to damage or
not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lavamaster attacks with a &lt;strong&gt;Molten Sword&lt;/strong&gt; that deals fire damage, and can
also use several spells. &lt;strong&gt;Magma Lash&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack that deals a bit more
fire damage than the sword, and pulls the target 4 squares. If the target ends
up adjacent to the lavamaster, the giant grabs them. The spell recharges when
the giant has no target grabbed. &lt;strong&gt;Magma Burst&lt;/strong&gt; is like an at-will
mini-fireball that leaves a fiery zone in its affected area. The zone lasts for
a turn, counts as difficult terrain, and deals fire damage to enemies inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the lavamaster has an enemy grabbed, &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Vendetta&lt;/strong&gt; allows the lavamaster
itself or one of its allies to make a free attack against that enemy whenever
the enemy attacks the lavamaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good tactic here is to keep away and repeatedly fireball the enemy, grabbing
anyone who gets too close. Keep a Brute or two nearby as bodyguards so they can
make free attacks against the grabbed victim and benefit from that healing aura.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-giant-flamedancer&quot;&gt;Fire Giant Flamedancer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This martial artist is trained in an ancient style developed by the efreets. It
combines mobile spear fighting with fire-based teleportation magic. Flamedancers
are Level 18 Skirmishers with 174 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Nimble Reaction&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them +4 to AC vs. Opportunity Attacks, and
their &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Spear&lt;/strong&gt; basic attack deals fire damage and allows them to shift
2 squares on a hit. They can also make at-will &lt;strong&gt;double attacks&lt;/strong&gt;, which must be
against different targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can make a &lt;strong&gt;Flameburst Leap&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action,
teleporting 8 squares and dealing automatic fire damage to any enemies adjacent
to them at the starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t expect a giant to be this agile! The same stat block can be used
for a slightly lower-level efreet without much issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-giant-smokecaller&quot;&gt;Fire Giant Smokecaller&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smokecallers are what passes for a “subtle” fire giant spellcaster. They
surround themselves in clouds of volcanic smoke, and attack by turning that
smoke into a pyroclastic cloud aimed at their enemies. It’s “subtle” without
necessarily being “stealthy”, unless you’re already in an environment naturally
choked with sulphurous smoke. Which is… actually a common situation when
you’re fighting fire giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smokecallers are Level 19 Lurkers with 140 HP and a nice speed of 10. They fight
with a &lt;strong&gt;Smoldering Whip&lt;/strong&gt; that has a fantastic reach of 5. It targets Reflex,
does fire damage, and pulls up to 3 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its main tactic consists of two abilities: &lt;strong&gt;Smokecloud&lt;/strong&gt; creates a zone of
smoke in a Close Burst 3 that lasts for a turn. It blocks line of sight for all
creatures except the smokecaller. While inside this zone, the smokecaller can
use &lt;strong&gt;Cindersmoke&lt;/strong&gt; to attack all enemies in a Close Blast 5. This deals fire
damage on a hit, and it ends the smokecloud immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both are standard actions, which means the lurkery routine here is Smokecloud
followed by Cindersmoke on the next turn. Cindersmoke does the same damage as a
whip attack to each target. This means the whip is only worth it if its forced
movement component would synergize with something. An example is when you have
multiple smokecallers and one of them wants to pull a PC into its buddy’s
upcoming Cindersmoke area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the ghoul entry, this one feels like it was designed to fit together with
the (upcoming, at the time) Monster Vault. The giants here all use the same
improved math as the ones that would appear on the MV, and they fill roles which
the more “classic” MV lineup does not. Combining the two gives you enough
ready-made stat blocks to make a dungeon inhabited solely by fire giants, though
you might also want to sprinkle in some hell hounds, elementals, and enslaved
azer that just need that final push to revolt.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/giant-fire.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/giant-fire.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Magic Item: The Coffee Machine From Hell</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I dreamed about this thing today, and what use is a blog if I can’t use it to
write about the weird things I dream up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This looks like a chunky, tabletop coffee machine of the sort that can be made
at TL8, and which might be found in an office. It’s self-contained, with
internal reservoirs for beans and plastic cups. An authorized technician
supposedly refills those after working hours, but employees who stay late never
see this technician, no matter how late they stay. And yet, the machine never
seems to run out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The device bears the name of a company that does indeed make this type of
appliance, though instead of their usual logo it has an upside-down star with a
smiley face. It has no model name or other contact information printed anywhere
on its body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coffee Machine From Hell has a counter-intuitive control panel. Several
button presses are required to tell it what you want, but that’s just bad
interface design. The Machine’s true curse is more insidious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As its name implies, the Coffee Machine From Hell is literally a torment device
built by demons. It will do its nominal job of producing cups of shitty office
coffee, but only if the user is making one for themselves (i.e, being
self-serving) or is thinking hostile or hateful thoughts about the intended
recipient of the drink. Someone who’s genuinely trying to help, or even just
being neutral about it, will find the machine seizes up or behaves
unpredictably. Even if all buttons are pressed correctly, it will spit mangled
cups, spill hot liquid on the countertop, make the wrong drink, and generally go
out of its way to make user experience a nightmare and to never ever produce
whatever it is the third party ordered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placed in an office where “making a coffee for someone else” is an accepted part
of the culture, the Machine will soon turn it into a nest of hate and
resentment. This is accelerated if the “someone else” is always the
boss. Unlucky interns and employees will cause mess after mess until they start
to truly hate the boss. The boss, in turn, will be frustrated that no one else
seems to be able to operate this “simple” machine that always works for them and
will come to hate their underlings in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanics&quot;&gt;Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its shitty interface, no roll is required to operate the Machine. It
does however read the operator’s mind to see if it should trigger the curse, in
which case it behaves as if a critical failure had been rolled. This will either
result in a humiliating mess, or in a normal-looking but undrinkable cup of
coffee that’s sure to cause inflict a nasty surprise on its intended recipient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who is wise to the curse can try to trick the device into operating
normally with a successful &lt;strong&gt;Mind Block&lt;/strong&gt; roll, or through any powers they have
that can shield their thoughts from telepathy. This roll can me made at the
usual &lt;strong&gt;Will-5&lt;/strong&gt; default if the character lacks the skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The machine’s infernal nature can be detected by any power or spell that detects
evil or infernal powers. It can be “cleansed” through &lt;strong&gt;Exorcism&lt;/strong&gt; or equivalent
powers, like a more typical cursed artifact. Its greatest defense against
detection and exorcism is that neither of these abilities are common in the
settings in which it appears. Its true nature can’t be detected by purely
scientific means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-use-it-in-a-game&quot;&gt;How to use it in a game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coffee Machine From Hell is a perfect addition to any oppressive office your
PCs must infiltrate for a while, particularly if they’re undercover as
interns. It’s something of a trap in that case: If everyone else already hates
each others’ guts, the PCs will be the only ones who trigger the curse, and this
will draw undue attention to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, every office &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; Hell has one of these, but it can also be present
on Earthly companies under demonic influence, or just wind up in an otherwise
normal company without any explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs on an infiltration mission will most likely need to trick the
machine. Exorcism attempts are too obvious and will likely blow their cover,
especially if they are actually infiltrating Hell. In an infiltration scenario
where the office is weird or evil in other ways, the machine is unlikely to be
the only obstacle they face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a campaign centered on paranormal investigation or monster hunting, the PCs
might be hired to find the problem behind a supernaturally toxic work
environment. If they have supernatural means of detecting evil, they’ll be able
to easily find the Machine, but in those cases it might be only one of the
sources of trouble. If they must rely only scientific instruments, then finding
the Machine is considerably harder even if they can easily use Exorcism to
cleanse it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/coffee-machine-from-hell.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/08/coffee-machine-from-hell.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>items</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Ghoul</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-ghoul.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As classic monsters, Ghouls had their 4e debut on the first Monster Manual, and
would end up making it into the Monster Vault as well. Here, the Monster Manual
3 gives us a few specialized ghoul variants that can compliment the ones on the
MV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic lore for ghouls remains the same. You can check out a description of
it on my post about &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/20/ghoul.html&quot;&gt;ghouls in the MM/MV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MM3 emphasizes that ghouls are creatures of pure evil, since they used to be
individuals who practiced cannibalism or did other equally horrible things in
life. It adds that they are not only driven by a hunger for flesh, but are also
drawn to places where evil is powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghouls will spontaneously show up at the home bases of evil cults, especially
those who worship Orcus or one of his exarchs. These villains often secure the
ghouls’ services by paying in live captives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghouls will also seek out ruins and dungeons where great evil is entombed,
sometimes digging for miles to reach these places if they happen to be deep
underground. This attraction handily explains why the ghouls that live in these
places prefer to hang out there rather than terrorizing the countryside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some adventurers like to use these ghoul tunnels and warrens as a way to reach
their dungeons or the Underdark, but this is a risky proposition as any ghouls
living in the tunnels will have a terrain advantage against the interlopers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three different varieties of Ghoul here, none of which seem to be
reprinted in the MV. They’re all Medium Natural Humanoids with the Undead
tag. They have Darkvision, Immunity to disease and poison, Resist 10 Necrotic,
and Vulnerable 5 Radiant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghoul-flesh-seeker&quot;&gt;Ghoul Flesh Seeker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cultist of Orcus who has undergone a voluntary transformation into a
ghoul. I guess the origin could be applied to any stat block, but this specific
entry describes a stealthy bastitch. They sometimes hunt in civilized
settlements, disguising themselves with heavy robes. When accompanying other
monsters, they like to strike from ambush while the PCs are busy with their less
stealthy buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flesh Seekers are Level 4 Lurkers with 45 HP. Their ground speed is an excellent
8, and their &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Skulk&lt;/strong&gt; trait allows them to roll Stealth to hide in
combat when they have partial cover or concealment (normally you need full cover
or concealment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and immobilizes (save ends) on a
hit. They don’t have abilities to exploit this directly, but “standard” ghouls
do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have two “lurker”-y special attacks. The first is &lt;strong&gt;Prepare For
Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt;, which they can use against a creature from which they were hidden
at the start of their turn. It does more damage than the claw attack, and on a
hit the flesh seeker knocks the target prone and grabs it. The target can escape
using the normal rules (Athletics DC 14 or Acrobatics DC 16) but takes a -2
penalty on the escape test and can’t stand up until the grab ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Render Unto Orcus&lt;/strong&gt;, and it can only be used on a
target grabbed by the flesh seeker. No special riders here, just a massive chunk
of damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tactics write themselves: Ambush -&amp;gt; Prepare For Sacrifice -&amp;gt; Render Unto
Orcus. If someone pries you off your victim, hide and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adept-of-orcus&quot;&gt;Adept of Orcus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cannibal priest of Orcus who died and returned as a ghoul. This one retains
its memories, but since it already behaved like a ghoul in life the only way you
can tell it’s because it can use magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adepts are Level 6 Controllers with the Leader tag and 71 HP. Their speed
is 8. They project an &lt;strong&gt;Uneasy Grave&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5). Any non-minion ghoul ally that
dies inside this aura comes back as a zombie rotter (a minion) at the start of
its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adept’s &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; damages and immobilizes, as typical for ghouls. It also has
three spells, all ranged attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Grave Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will) does no damage and
restrains (save ends). &lt;strong&gt;Call to Feast&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) immobilizes (save ends)
and allows a ghoul ally adjacent to the target to make a free basic attack
against them. And &lt;strong&gt;Grave Dust Cloud&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is an area spell that does
necrotic damage and creates a zone that does 5 necrotic damage to any enemy who
enters it or ends their turn inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These things are extremely dangerous when paired with traditional ghouls, since
they can paralyze from a distance and allow their buddies to do huge damage
right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ghast&quot;&gt;Ghast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghasts are a monster as traditional as the ghoul. Basically, they’re stronger
and stinkier ghouls. The MM and MV had Abyssal Ghouls to fill this role, but
they were level 16. This official Ghast entry is appropriate for mixing in with
standard ghouls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghasts are what happens when a ghoul goes for too long without eating the flesh
of the living. Instead of starving, they rot from the inside and become even
more desperate and voracious. This rot is what gives them their horrible stench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghasts are Level 6 Brutes with 85 HP. They’re a bit slower at speed 6, and their
&lt;strong&gt;Stench of Death&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) slows any living creatures that start their turns
inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and immobilizes for a turn. They
can use a &lt;strong&gt;Devouring Bite&lt;/strong&gt; against an immobilized creature, which does huge
damage and keeps recharging until they hit with it. After the bite hits and is
spent, they can use their &lt;strong&gt;Rabid Claws&lt;/strong&gt;, to make two melee attacks against
immobilized creatures. Each one does slightly less damage than the basic bite,
but if the two hit they hurt more overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new ghoul types can fit into the same types of encounter group as the ones
from the MM/MV, which means they pair well with Orcus cultists and other
undead. And now you have enough ghoul stat blocks to make a large variety of
all-ghoul encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for my impressions… I like ghouls as opponents, and I would like to repeat
my warning from the original article to prefer the MV ghouls over the MM1
ones. The ones from this book pair well with the MV versions.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/05/ghoul.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/05/ghoul.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merging GURPS Weapon Skills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Peter V. Dell’Orto made a post in his blog Dungeon Fantastic about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/07/possible-weapon-skill-mergers-for-gurps.html&quot;&gt;merging GURPS weapon skills&lt;/a&gt;. I really, really like the idea, so I thought
about writing about how I’d do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dell’Orto’s post is specific to Dungeon Fantasy and to his own Felltower
campaign. Mine is a bit more generic since I don’t have an active campaign
going, and I tend to kind of mix up Dungeon Fantasy and default GURPS rules in
my head. Consider it an addition to my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/12/18/df-house-style.html&quot;&gt;House Style&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for doing this is also pretty well-covered by this &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/08/why-all-merging.html&quot;&gt;follow-up Dungeon
Fantastic Post&lt;/a&gt;: having too many fine distinctions between spells and skills
in a cinematic campaign can serve as a bit of a damper on the pacing and
excitement of the campaign. My usual players tend to have a certain resistance
to trying stuff that’s not on their character sheets, especially in a complex
system like GURPS, so having broader traits would allow them to experiment a bit
more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-skills&quot;&gt;The Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns where this post is in effect, I’m going to use the following list
of weapon skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Axe/Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This skill is a combination of the original &lt;strong&gt;Axe/Mace&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt;. When
using a flail, the character suffers a -1 skill penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games that use Techniques, &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt; is a new Hard technique that defaults to
Skill-1 and has a maximum level equal to Skill. This means you can buy the -1
penalty off for 2 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fencing-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Fencing (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new skill merges &lt;strong&gt;Rapier&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Saber&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Smallsword&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows you to
use not only these three “titular” weapons, but also any other weapon that would
fall under those skills, such as the jian (Rapier) or the light stick
(Smallsword).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the normal rules for fencing weapons apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;force-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Force Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-3, One-Handed Sword-3, Two-handed Sword-3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should I ever play a science fiction game with force swords, this gets merged
with &lt;strong&gt;Force Saber&lt;/strong&gt;. Whether you get fencing parries or not depends on the stat
line of the weapon you’re using. The “Fencing parries for everyone!” option is
also valid in a more explicitly Star Warsy game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;knife-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Knife (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges the original &lt;strong&gt;Knife&lt;/strong&gt; skill with &lt;strong&gt;Jitte/Sai&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Main-Gauche&lt;/strong&gt;. Any weapon that could be used with either of these can be used
with the new skill. Weapons use their Main-Gauche profiles for this, meaning
there’s no penalty for using the off hand and the user gets fencing parries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, “knife expert” PCs always went for Main-Gauche anyway. People
who dropped a point in Knife as a back-up skill almost never ended up using it,
so they can just drop a point in this one instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jutte and the Sai get both a +2 for disarm attempts and fencing parries
without any special stance switches required. They are rare enough in my games
that I don’t believe it will be a problem. And by “rare” I mean no one has taken
these weapons and no one has tried a disarm yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;One-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4, Two-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the skill used for all one-handed swords, merging both &lt;strong&gt;Broadsword&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Shortsword&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blade length is an important consideration in real life, but it’s below the
level of granularity I prefer. This also broadens the range of really cool magic
swords your sword-wielding players can find and immediately use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pole-weapons-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Pole Weapons (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Sword-5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges &lt;strong&gt;Polearm&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Staff&lt;/strong&gt;. The Form Mastery perk is
redundant for these weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about that sweet Staff parry bonus? If it’s in your weapon’s stat line
under Staff, you get it. If it’s not, you don’t. The only exception to this are
balanced two-handed spears, which I feel should have the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Axe-Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Axe/Mace, but for two-handed weapons. The same rules apply for two-handed
flails, including the existence of a Hard technique to buy the -1 penalty off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much the same skill as the original, with a suitably altered list
of defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-all-the-other-skills&quot;&gt;What about all the other skills?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the more exotic weapon skills, like Whip, Kusari, and Tonfa, remain the
same. I might change my mind in the future and come back to this, but I haven’t
actually used any of them in my games, so it makes no difference for them to
stay as-is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-rule-weapon-familiarity&quot;&gt;Optional Rule: Weapon Familiarity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like how these skills are merged, but still feel a staff user shouldn’t
be able to pick up a halberd and wield it just as proficiently right away, then
you can use a version of the Familiarity rules from the GURPS core book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs are considered familiar with any weapons they acquire during character
creation. If they pick up a weapon that would be used with a different skill
under the standard rules, they have a -2 penalty to use that weapon until they
can spend a few hours practicing with it. This takes time but costs no money or
points. In effect, it can only happen when the PCs have a significant amount of
downtime (such as when returning to town from a dungeon in DF). After this, the
PC is considered familiar with that weapon type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this up as an option, but it’s not one I’ll use myself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
