<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 01:33:24 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 01:33:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Merging GURPS Weapon Skills</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Peter V. Dell’Orto made a post in his blog Dungeon Fantastic about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/07/possible-weapon-skill-mergers-for-gurps.html&quot;&gt;merging GURPS weapon skills&lt;/a&gt;. I really, really like the idea, so I thought
about writing about how I’d do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dell’Orto’s post is specific to Dungeon Fantasy and to his own Felltower
campaign. Mine is a bit more generic since I don’t have an active campaign
going, and I tend to kind of mix up Dungeon Fantasy and default GURPS rules in
my head. Consider it an addition to my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2018/12/18/df-house-style.html&quot;&gt;House Style&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for doing this is also pretty well-covered by this &lt;a href=&quot;https://dungeonfantastic.blogspot.com/2022/08/why-all-merging.html&quot;&gt;follow-up Dungeon
Fantastic Post&lt;/a&gt;: having too many fine distinctions between spells and skills
in a cinematic campaign can serve as a bit of a damper on the pacing and
excitement of the campaign. My usual players tend to have a certain resistance
to trying stuff that’s not on their character sheets, especially in a complex
system like GURPS, so having broader traits would allow them to experiment a bit
more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-skills&quot;&gt;The Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In campaigns where this post is in effect, I’m going to use the following list
of weapon skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Axe/Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This skill is a combination of the original &lt;strong&gt;Axe/Mace&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt;. When
using a flail, the character suffers a -1 skill penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In games that use Techniques, &lt;strong&gt;Flail&lt;/strong&gt; is a new Hard technique that defaults to
Skill-1 and has a maximum level equal to Skill. This means you can buy the -1
penalty off for 2 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fencing-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Fencing (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new skill merges &lt;strong&gt;Rapier&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Saber&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Smallsword&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows you to
use not only these three “titular” weapons, but also any other weapon that would
fall under those skills, such as the jian (Rapier) or the light stick
(Smallsword).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the normal rules for fencing weapons apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;force-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Force Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-3, One-Handed Sword-3, Two-handed Sword-3&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should I ever play a science fiction game with force swords, this gets merged
with &lt;strong&gt;Force Saber&lt;/strong&gt;. Whether you get fencing parries or not depends on the stat
line of the weapon you’re using. The “Fencing parries for everyone!” option is
also valid in a more explicitly Star Warsy game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;knife-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Knife (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges the original &lt;strong&gt;Knife&lt;/strong&gt; skill with &lt;strong&gt;Jitte/Sai&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;Main-Gauche&lt;/strong&gt;. Any weapon that could be used with either of these can be used
with the new skill. Weapons use their Main-Gauche profiles for this, meaning
there’s no penalty for using the off hand and the user gets fencing parries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, “knife expert” PCs always went for Main-Gauche anyway. People
who dropped a point in Knife as a back-up skill almost never ende up using it,
so they can just drop a point in this one instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jutte and the Sai get both a +2 for disarm attempts and fencing parries
without any special stance switches required. They are rare enough in my games
that I don’t believe it will be a problem. And by “rare” I mean no one has taken
these weapons and no one has tried a disarm yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;One-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Fencing-4, Two-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the skill used for all one-handed swords, merging both &lt;strong&gt;Broadsword&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;Shortsword&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blade length is an important consideration in real life, but it’s below the
level of granularity I prefer. This also broadens the range of really cool magic
swords your sword-wielding players can find and immediately use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pole-weapons-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Pole Weapons (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Two-Handed Sword-5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This merges &lt;strong&gt;Polearm&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Spear&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Staff&lt;/strong&gt;. The Form Mastery perk is
redundant for these weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about that sweet Staff parry bonus? If it’s in your weapon’s stat line
under Staff, you get it. If it’s not, you don’t. The only exception to this are
balanced two-handed spears, which I feel should have the bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-axemace-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Axe/Mace (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, Axe-Mace-3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Axe/Mace, but for two-handed weapons. The same rules apply for two-handed
flails, including the existence of a Hard technique to buy the -1 penalty off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;two-handed-sword-dxaverage&quot;&gt;Two-Handed Sword (DX/Average)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defaults: DX-5, One-Handed Sword-4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much the same skill as the original, with a suitably altered list
of defaults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-all-the-other-skills&quot;&gt;What about all the other skills?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the more exotic weapon skills, like Whip, Kusari, and Tonfa, remain the
same. I might change my mind in the future and come back to this, but I haven’t
actually used any of them in my games, so it makes no difference for them to
stay as-is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-rule-weapon-familiarity&quot;&gt;Optional Rule: Weapon Familiarity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like how these skills are merged, but still feel a staff user shouldn’t
be able to pick up a halberd and wield it just as proficiently right away, then
you can use a version of the Familiarity rules from the GURPS core book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs are considered familiar with any weapons they acquire during character
creation. If they pick up a weapon that would be used with a different skill
under the standard rules, they have a -2 penalty to use that weapon until they
can spend a few hours practicing with it. This takes time but costs no money or
points. In effect, it can only happen when the PCs have a significant amount of
downtime (such as when returning to town from a dungeon in DF). After this, the
PC is considered familiar with that weapon type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this up as an option, but it’s not one I’ll use myself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/03/merging-weapon-skills.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Gargoyle</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-gargoyle.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gargoyles made their 4e debut in the first Monster Manual. I wrote about them
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/12/gargoyle.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Though that article includes a whole bunch of gargoyles, most of them
are from the Monster Vault. When the MM3 was published, we still only had the
two originals from the MM1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entry adds a lot more variety, and it doesn’t actually overlap with the
later MV gargoyles, so we’re going to be looking at all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gargoyle lore remains basically the same, and you can read it &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/12/gargoyle.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. We get
two new bits in this entry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that efreets love to train packs of gargoyles to hunt sapients for
sport. The elemental lords are endlessly amused by their pets’ penchant for
sadism when hunting. In the world, cultists of the Elder Elemental Eye
frequently recruit and train gargoyles to guard their temples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is that while gargoyles have a fearsome reputation in the world, they
tend to be viewed as weak in their native Elemental Chaos. There, they are more
often the prey than the hunter. Gargoyle packs skulk in caves and other secluded
locations, and only attack when they greatly outnumber their target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All gargoyles in this entry are Medium Elemental Humanoids with the Earth
keyword. They have Darkvision, a ground speed of 6, and a flight speed
of 8. They’re immune to petrification, and all but one of them have a passive
trait called &lt;strong&gt;Lurking Presence&lt;/strong&gt;, which gives them a +10 bonus to Stealth
against enemies’ passive Perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also interesting to note that none of the gargoyles in this entry have the
Lurker role - with these and the ones from the MV, you can build varied
all-gargoyle encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ironstone-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Ironstone Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identified by the rust-red streaks covering their bodies, Ironstone Gargoyles
behave like their “default” cousins, hanging out in mountain passes and ruins
waiting to raid unsuspecting passers-by. They wait in ambush but fight in a more
aggressive and mobile way than usual once combat starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironstone Gargoyles are Level 7 Skirmishers with 80 HP and the traits outlined
above. They use &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; to fight, and have a special attack named &lt;strong&gt;Crashing
Stride&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+). This allows them to shift 4 squares and make claw
attacks against two targets at any point along the shift. If they hit, they also
slide the target 1 square and knock it prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When surrounded, a &lt;strong&gt;Leaping Glide&lt;/strong&gt; (at-will move action) allows them to fly 4
squares without provoking opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hornstone-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Hornstone Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This robust specimen is distinguished by its large horns, which it uses to gore,
impale and drag victims in combat. It’s a Level 8 Brute with 107 HP and all
standard traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those horns can be used in an &lt;strong&gt;Impaling Charge&lt;/strong&gt;, an attack which must be used
as part of a charge. It does heavy damage and grabs the target by impaling them
in the gargoyle’s horns. The target takes 5 ongoing damage while the grab
lasts. Escaping uses the standard rules (Athletics DC 22 or Acrobatics DC 19).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gargoyle can use &lt;strong&gt;Skewering Drag&lt;/strong&gt; as a move action to move half its speed
and automatically pull the grabbed victim along with it. Neither provokes
opportunity attacks from the other during this movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the basic &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack for last because it interacts with the above
abilities: aside from doing the usual heavy damage of a Brute, it allows the
monster to use Skewering Drag as a free action. Attacking the grabbed victim is
a perfectly valid choice, mind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In combat they’ll do their best to impale and drag an enemy away. If the charge
fails they prefer to fly away and try again rather than stand and fight with
basic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;obsidian-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Obsidian Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obsidian gargoyles are kinda brittle, but also covered in sharp edges. Massive
flocks of these things darken the skies of the Elemental Chaos, and they’re the
preferred variant of Elemental Eye cultists. They’re Level 8 Minion Soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attacks are nothing special, but they also have a &lt;strong&gt;Cruel Claws&lt;/strong&gt;
passive that deals 4 damage to an enemy who leaves a square adjacent to the
gargoyle. That’s not a lot, but it triggers on a shift and &lt;em&gt;stacks&lt;/em&gt;. Surround a
PC with these beasts. Leave only one way out. Dare them to take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;runic-gargoyle&quot;&gt;Runic Gargoyle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an &lt;em&gt;artificial&lt;/em&gt; gargoyle variant, originally created to serve the Elder
Elemental Eye. Their skin looks like white marble covered in arcane runes, and
they are a lot smarter than your average gargoyle. Some of them have since
broken out of their servitude and found jobs with different groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Runic Gargoyles are Level 8 Soldiers with 87 HP and all standard traits &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt;
for Lurking Presence, since they don’t really have natural camouflage. They were
made to be bodyguards, and their runes can be configured to bind them to a
designated “master”. I guess “client” might be a better word for free runic
gargoyles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack marks the target for a turn. They can also use an
&lt;strong&gt;Avenging Claws&lt;/strong&gt; maneuver that dazes instead of marking. This recharges when
they’re first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a move action, they can teleport &lt;strong&gt;To the Master&lt;/strong&gt;, appearing in a space
within 2 squares of the client. There is &lt;em&gt;no range limit&lt;/em&gt; on this, and it allows
you to have a cool scene where the boss snaps his fingers and a gang of gargoyle
guards teleports in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the gargoyle is adjacent to its client and the client takes damage, it can
use &lt;strong&gt;Shielding Wings&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt to take the damage instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters&quot;&gt;Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same encounter building tips for MM1/MV gargoyles also apply here. The
efreet and Elder Eye angles are new and just as valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inter-gargoyle synergy is highest between the gargoyles from this entry. You
have a couple of variants who are excellent at inflicting forced movement, and a
minion who deals damage to enemies who move away from it. And since all of them
fly, they also pair well with pits and other floor-based hazards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat blocks in this entry don’t really change my general opinion of
gargoyles. They might be &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; iconic, as the exceptional case in a D&amp;amp;D
adventure is meeting an inanimate gargoyle statue who &lt;em&gt;won’t&lt;/em&gt; come to life and
try to kill you. For this reason, you don’t want to use them too much in your
actual game. Still, by combining the MM3 and the MV you have enough variants to
make that one gargoyle encounter truly memorable.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/02/gargoyle.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/02/gargoyle.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Frog</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-frog.jpg&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Not a D&amp;D illustration.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every individual roleplayer has a set of D&amp;amp;D monsters they consider “iconic”,
regardless of what the publisher has to say about it. Years ago, I remember one
such player saying that to him “giant fucking frogs” were the most iconic D&amp;amp;D
monster. It’s not D&amp;amp;D if you don’t fight a huge-ass frog at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that criterion we can shut the grognards up for good now. Here is the moment
when 4e finally becomes D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real-world frogs are usually quite useful creatures. Most species are harmless
to humans and eat disease-spreading insects. Some consider them cute and, if
nothing else, they can be tasty when properly prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In typical D&amp;amp;D fashion, this book calls such creatures “pests” because they’re
not fuzzy wabbits. And then it moves on to focus on monstrous frogs, who are big
and aggressive enough to eat people. They live in surface swamps and on
underground lakes in “natural” caves or in the shallow Underdark. There are
several different species, and the book implies they’re atavistic survivors from
the world’s prehistory, like sharks and crocodiles in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A monstrous frog won’t usually leave its home territory to hunt people, but it
will eat anyone foolish enough to wander through that territory. “Beware of
Frog” signs are a common sight in villages close to the borders of their
habitat. Frog attacks are a potential hazard for PCs traveling through marshy
terrain, and the book suggests they could be hired by a wealthy family to
retrieve some heirloom from the belly of a frog who ate its former bearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All frogs shown here are Medium Natural Beasts, though you could probably
home-brew larger specimens if you want. They’re Aquatic, which lets them breathe
underwater and gives them bonuses against non-aquatic enemies in underwater
combat. They also have good Swim speeds and low-light vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thornskin-frog&quot;&gt;Thornskin Frog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These frogs have brown skin covered in thick spines. The spines are not
effective in combat but give them a distinctive look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thornskins are Level 1 Brutes with 35 HP. They have a ground speed of 4 and a
swim speed of 6. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and they can also &lt;strong&gt;pounce&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+). This lets them shift their speed, deald more damage than a bite
and knocks the target prone. As a minor action they can use a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue
Grab&lt;/strong&gt; that pulls a target 2 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, these critters do everything you could expect from a classic giant
frog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sporeback-frog&quot;&gt;Sporeback Frog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-sporeback.png&quot; width=800/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sporebacks are the laziest hunters imaginable. They pick a spot and wait there
for prey to wander into the reach of their barbed tongues. They move so little
that mushrooms often grow on their backs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most creatures smart enough to pose a threat to these monsters have long since
learned to avoid them. As a result, sporebacks never expect their chosen prey to
put up a fight, and don’t usually run away unless they’re very close to death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sporebacks are Level 2 Controllers with 42 HP. Their ground speed is a pitiful
3, and their swim speed is 5. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and
slows, and their Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Barbed Tongues&lt;/strong&gt; damage, pull the target 2 squares,
and knock it prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they die, the mushrooms on their back burst and perform a &lt;strong&gt;Spore
Release&lt;/strong&gt;, a close burst 2 attack that deals poison damage and inflicts a -2
attack penalty (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For extra nastiness, have the sporebacks in your encounter group stay
&lt;em&gt;underwater&lt;/em&gt; and use their tongues to drag PCs there. This works even better if
all of Team Monster has the Aquatic keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;murklord-frog&quot;&gt;Murklord Frog&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murklords are entirely black, and have two parallel bio-luminescent stripes
running down their backs. These flare up when the frog is startled or feels
threatened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These beautiful creatures are the opposite of sporebacks when it comes to
attacking prey. They perform darting strikes from the muddy margins of their
watery homes, and grow even more frantic and ferocious when wounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murklords are Level 2 Skirmishers with 39 HP. They have ground and swim speeds
of 6. Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and they can also perform a
&lt;strong&gt;Leapfrog&lt;/strong&gt; attack (recharge 4+) that deals more damage and allows them to
shift 3 squares both before and after making the attack. Perfect for leaping out
of the water, taking a bite, and returning before the PCs can react.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, it can also perform a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Tongue Lash&lt;/strong&gt; that does no
damage but slides the target 1 square on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The murklord’s attacks use d6s as their damage dice: 1d6+4 for the bite, 2d6+4
for the limited-use Leapfrog. After the frog is first bloodied, though, those
d6s become d12s, significantly increasing its damage potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;encounters&quot;&gt;Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goblins, kobolds and bullywugs commonly employ trained monstrous frogs as mounts
and war beasts. Only the bullywugs have succeeded in &lt;em&gt;domesticating&lt;/em&gt; them,
though - the others must capture wild frogs and train those. When bullywugs make
alliances or trade agreements, they commonly make a gift of trained war frogs to
their new partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with no access to trained frogs can still use them by keeping them
captive and releasing a bunch of angry half-starved frogs in the general
direction of the enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I’d go as far as calling huge-ass frogs “iconic D&amp;amp;D monsters”,
but they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; cool. These ones are properly froggy in their mechanics, and you
can probably extend their usefulness by giving them additional levels,
increasing their size, and giving them a Swallow attack.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/01/frog.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/08/01/frog.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Foulspawn</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-foulspawn.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foulspawn had their 4e debut in the first Monster Manual. If you read the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/09/foulspawn.html&quot;&gt;post I wrote&lt;/a&gt; about them, you’ll see that MM1 Foulspawn were plagued by some
design flaws, but you could speculate from their lore that they were the end
state of mortal Far Realm cultists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore in this entry is mostly a re-statement of the original foulspawn
lore. They’re more actively inimical to the natural world than most other Far
Realm denizens, and cross over where the barrier between dimensions is thin to
attack mortal settlements. They drag some of their victims back with them, and
those unfortunates eventually become foulspawn themselves after having their
bodies and minds warped by the Far Realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still plenty of room for you to portray foulspawn as the “end state” for
a lot of mortal cultists who worship cthulhoid entities - they’re the ones who
step into the portal willingly. If all you had to go with were the MM1 entries,
this was kind of an ironic fate, as the foulspawn there were kinda weak. Let’s
see if this is still true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foulspawn are Aberrant Humanoids with a ground speed of 6 and a teleport speed
of 3. They mix physical attacks with powers that warp space and damage enemy
minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;foulspawn-wretch&quot;&gt;Foulspawn Wretch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most unwilling victims probably turn into these. Wretches are Small Level 7
Minion Skirmishers with low-light vision and the standard traits listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have a &lt;strong&gt;Ceaseless Murmurs&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait that inflicts a -2 penalty to
the Will of any PC adjacent to two or more wretches. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; attack
deals a bit of damage and allows another wretch within 6 squares to teleport
adjacent to the target. And when they die, their &lt;strong&gt;Screaming Echo&lt;/strong&gt; ability
teleports a non-minion ally within 6 squares to the position previously
occupied by the dead wretch!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wretches are made to use standard “monster wave” tactics - use a lot of them and
have them crowd around the PCs. Try to get them adjacent to the PC’s squishies
on the back line, so that when they die they teleport your front-line bruisers
there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;foulspawn-mockery&quot;&gt;Foulspawn Mockery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spellcaster with a raven skull for a head. Mockeries use mind-bending magic to
force the PCs close together and then hit them with area attacks. They’re Medium
Level 10 Controllers with 104 HP, low-light vision, and the standard traits
outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; which is actually stronger than almost any
attack from a MM1 fouslpawn simply because it uses the correct math. They attack
at range with a &lt;strong&gt;Mind Harrier&lt;/strong&gt; spell that deals psychic damage and imposes one
of those interesting custom effects. If a target hit by Mind Harrier is not
adjacent to any of its allies by the end of its next turn, it takes an extra 10
psychic damage and 10 ongoing psychic damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the mockery has used Mind Harrier to push the PCs together, it can hit them
all with a &lt;strong&gt;Maddening Burst&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which deals psychic damage and
dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;foulspawn-warpcaller&quot;&gt;Foulspawn Warpcaller&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are like aberrant bards, or those things that keep dancing around Azatoth
playing flutes and pipes. They’re Medium Level 12 Controllers (Leaders) with 126
HP, Darkvision, and the standard traits outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Droning Pipes&lt;/strong&gt; act as an aura (3) that makes enemies inside Vulnerable
5 to Psychic damage. This is important because Psychic is pretty much the
signature damage type for foulspawn and other aberrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warpcallers can &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; in melee for good damage, but their magic is the star
of the show here. &lt;strong&gt;Warped Sending&lt;/strong&gt; is an at-will ranged attack that deals
psychic damage and teleports a foulspawn ally within 5 squares of the target to
a space adjacent to the target. &lt;strong&gt;Twisted Dismissal&lt;/strong&gt; does the same damage,
immobilizes the target (save ends) and teleports it 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Warpmind Field&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a fireball-sized area attack that
deals psychic damage and creates a zone that lasts for a turn and can be
sustained with a minor action. Enemies who enter the zone or end their turns
there take 10 psychic damage. An enemy inside the zone can’t target anyone
further than 5 squares away. And the warpcaller can spend its move action to
move the zone up to 4 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warpmind Field is an excellent fight opener if you drop it on the party’s
archers. If they move outside the zone to fire on their turn, Twisted Dismissal
can push them back inside and keep them there, possibly combined with a move
action spent moving the zone closer. And Warped Sending is another handy way to
teleport your brutes past the PC’s defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;friends-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Friends and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foulspawn usually only work with other foulspawn, though if you’re using the
ones from the MM1 you really, really need to fix their math. Other appropriate
company includes gibbering mouthers and other aberrant creatures that deal
psychic damage. And according to the book they also sometimes work with cultists
of Tharizdun and Demogorgon - the kind of person who wants to wreck the world
but doesn’t care how it happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore remains the same, but the mechanics on these foulspawn are quite a bit
better. I’m not just talking raw numbers either - the MM1 foulspawn rarely did
more than spam basic melee attacks. These have a lot more variety.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/28/foulspawn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/28/foulspawn.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Forsaken</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later monster books in a D&amp;amp;D edition are usually where you find those monsters
from previous editions who weren’t “iconic” enough to appear earlier, but
sometimes they’re also where you can find some truly ambitious entries. After
all, the authors have pages to fill and most of the classics have already been
done. The Forsaken are one of the most ambitious new monsters presented by the
MM3. Or at least they &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; new. If a monster by this name existed earlier it
was likely completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dawn War saw the death of many gods. In most such occasions, the dead god’s
essence dispersed across the Astral Sea. However, a few gods were slain while
physically present in the world, and their essence could not escape. Instead, it
deposited itself in some of the mortal sapients that inhabited the world even
back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the gods in question were dead and gone, these new vessels of their power
acquired a memory of what it felt like to be immortal. This memory became a
source of torment, for their owners were themselves mortal. They remembered and
missed something they never had, and could never have. Overwhelmed by these
feelings, these people ritually removed their own eyes so they would never have
to gaze upon the mortal world again, and vowed to destroy and absorb the
essences of the remaining gods so that they could steal their divinity for
themselves. They called themselves the Forsaken, and they are still known by
that name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our narrative present there are several different Forsaken tribes, each with
their own approach to their grand design. They travel through all the universe
in search of mystical secrets that will increase their power and allow them to
become gods. They tangle and skirmish with Vecna worshippers, inflitrate astral
dominions, and even journey the Hells. Some set up elaborate networks of
followers and co-conspirators in the mortal realms. Some make plans to trap and
devour a god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forsaken are epic-level threats. They’re Medium Natural Humanoids with the Blind
keyword and Blindsight 20. This means they can’t be affected by the “blinded”
status and they’re immune to gaze attacks and most vision-based impairments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Fragment of Immortality&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when they
hit 0 HP. It clears all effects from them, removes them from play and returns
them a turn later with about 25% of their HP restored, in a space within 5
squares of their last location. The fragment allows them to cling to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of their other abilities come from training and vary per stat block. They
tend to have some vague similarities to PC divine classes, but any divine power
would come from the Forsaken themselves rather than from a deity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-fearwrack&quot;&gt;Forsaken Fearwrack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-forsaken-fearwrack.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearwracks are spellcasters who delve deep into the mysteries of fear and death,
confronting that which most scares the forsaken and inflicting it on
others. There’s an enclave of them in the outer shores of Celestia, and though
the inhabitants of that dominion very much want to see them gone, they fear
meeting their final death at the hands of the Forsaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearwracks are Level 26 Artillery with 150 HP. They &lt;strong&gt;Inspire Fear&lt;/strong&gt;, which acts
as an aura (1) that inflicts a -2 penalty to all enemy defenses against fear
attacks. Almost all of their attacks have the Fear keyword, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wield rods as implements, which I guess makes them a bit similar to PC
invokers in look and feel. Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Fear Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that
targets Will, deals psychic damage, and forces the target to move its speed away
from the invoker. The invoker chooses the path, but each square must be further
away than the previous one. Why is this different from a push? Because the
victim can provoke opportunity attacks during this movement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range they fire &lt;strong&gt;Terror Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; which do the same amount of psychic damage
and allow an ally adjacent to the target to make a melee basic attack against
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often they can also employ a &lt;strong&gt;Curse of Mortality&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), which
targets Fortitude and inflicts 20 ongoing damage (save ends). The target has a
-2 penalty to save against this, and each failed save increases the ongoing
damage by 5 to a maximum of 30. I guess the damage looks like rapid aging, and
since there’s no exception in the text it works even on beings who do not
normally age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from Fragment of Immortality, fearwracks have another reaction power in
the form of &lt;strong&gt;Cleansing Wounds&lt;/strong&gt;, which clears all enemy effects from them when
they first become bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An all-fearwrack group has a surprising amount of synergy. If the PCs close to
melee with one of them, others can target the PC with Terror Bolt to open them
up to a free Fear Strike. This causes the PC to run away and potentially get hit
with &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; Fear Strikes. The fearwrack choses the victim’s path and there’s
nothing forbidding them from walking them into traps or pits either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are occasions where the fearwrack &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; the PC to stay close, though -
their aura makes the Curse of Mortality even harder to resist with a total -4
save penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forkaken-infiltrators&quot;&gt;Forkaken Infiltrators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infiltrators have an amazing talent for long-term impersonation. Some believe
they inherited it from the deity whose essence initially infused them. They join
up with churches and cults of all types of deity, from Pelor to Vecna, with the
goal of reaching a high post in their hierarchy. From that lofty perch they gain
access to all sorts of restricted divine secrets, and can abuse their authority
to sabotage the cult from within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infiltrators are Level 27 Skirmishers with 200 HP. They wield a kophesh in one
hand and a hand crossbow in the other, and they use the classic strategy of
moving around to gain combat advantage while discouraging the PCs from making
opportunity attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they have &lt;strong&gt;Combat Advantage&lt;/strong&gt; against a target, any attack they hit also
immobilized the target and allows the infiltrator to shift 2
squares. &lt;strong&gt;Punishing Response&lt;/strong&gt; is a mighty discouragement indeed: when an enemy
hits the infiltrator with an opportunity attack, the enemy takes the same damage
dealt to the infiltrator plus 5!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Khopesh&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Hand Crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; are accurate and do solid damage, but have
no built-in riders. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Careful Attack&lt;/strong&gt; with the sword that
deals about 25% less damage but gives the infiltrator a +2 bonus to defenses for
a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No combat-time shapeshifting powers here, so I guess any transformations either
take more time, or are just the fruit of epic-level tradecraft rather than
shape-shifting magic. Infiltrators do get training in all the social skills plus
Stealth, and their high level means they’re better at those than most mortals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-loreseeker&quot;&gt;Forsaken Loreseeker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loreseekers are the rank and file of the Forsaken spying operation, tasked with
actively breaking into libraries, vaults, and minds to steal the knowledge
contained within. I guess a big part of the big-I Infiltrator’s mission is to
open the way for loreseekers. Some believe they can steal all the memories of a
creature they kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loreseekers are Level 27 Minion Soldiers, which tells me they’re not really
meant to engage in combat most of the time and/or that they work in large
teams. When forced to fight, they use weapons similar to those of the
Infiltrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Hand Crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; attack marks for a turn, and their melee attack also
performs a &lt;strong&gt;Theft of Memory&lt;/strong&gt;. During the target next turn, all enemies except
the attacking Loreseeker are invisible to the victim. Memory erasure in real
time! The loreseeker loses this ability after it uses Fragment of
Immortality. Yes, despite being a minion they also have this ability, so you
need to hit them twice to defeat them for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-slaughterer&quot;&gt;Forsaken Slaughterer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-forsaken-slaughterer.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some Forsaken find the memory of immortality a weight too great to bear. It eats
at their sanity until their mind snaps, and they’re consumed by rage and
grief. The other forsaken keep these unfortunate individuals in reserve for use
as living weapons. They’re more sensitive to divine power, you see, and tend to
fly into a murderous frenzy when they sense some. It wouldn’t do to waste that
kind of god-killing potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaugheterers are Level 28 Brutes, which means they can indeed challenge
demigods and other things of that nature when backed up by a team of similar
level. They have 253 HP, and the other standard Forsaken traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaughterers have a couple of interesting passive traits: &lt;strong&gt;Relentless
Slaughter&lt;/strong&gt; is an aura (1) that halves the benefits of healing for any enemy
inside; and &lt;strong&gt;Proximal Resistance&lt;/strong&gt; gives them Resist 10 against all ranged and
area attacks if no enemies are adjacent to them. This makes them very capable of
charging through an open field to engage PCs in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with paired khopesh swords, and their basic &lt;strong&gt;Khopesh&lt;/strong&gt; attack does a
nice chunk of damage - almost as much as a Balor’s sword, with the main
difference being the lack of the High-Crit property. They can also use an
&lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable Cut&lt;/strong&gt; that splits that damage between two adjacent targets. This
isn’t a multi-attack - if the first target gets hit, the second takes damage
automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all Forsaken, slaughterers have Fragment of Immortality as a triggered
action. They also have another very interesting one called &lt;strong&gt;Blood for
Blood&lt;/strong&gt;. It triggers when they’re first bloodied, and consists of a Close Burst
1 attack against all enemies that does damage equal to each target’s healing
surge value. That’s 25% of their HP, and it’s likely to bloody them since it
will go off a ways into the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slaughterers are offensive brutes - you want them to charge past the defenders
and attack your squishies. They’ll be particularly eager to target divine
characters like clerics and invokers, so having a paladin with you is probably
the best way to make them stop and fight your defenders. Otherwise they’ll
definitely risk opportunity attacks and mark punishments to break through, with
Blood for Blood working as a nasty surprise for those PCs who prove adept at
hurting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;forsaken-mastermind&quot;&gt;Forsaken Mastermind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forsaken Masterminds are strategists. They run operations whose scope
encompasses an entire region, sitting at the center of a web of different cells
and agents that include several other Forsaken as well as their mortal
pawns. Their goals tend to involve heavy stuff like interfering with the designs
of the gods themselves, or those of their direct servants. A mastermind should
only enter combat directly if all of their other plans have been thwarted by
meddlesome adventurers, but they’re far from defenseless if it comes to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masterminds are Level 29 Controllers with 213 HP and the Leader keyword. They’re
masterful warriors, and also employ some magic focused on disrupting divine
powers. They’re surrounded by an &lt;strong&gt;Inspire Resilience&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5), which grants
an extra 40 temporary HP to any forsaken ally who uses Fragment of Immortality
within it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;khopesh&lt;/strong&gt; attack makes the target marked by one of the
mastermind’s allies within 5 squares! So it forces the PC to target that ally
instead of the mastermind itself, and allows the ally to use any mark-related
abilities it may have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also use a &lt;strong&gt;hand crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; that can make a solid ranged basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their main spell is &lt;strong&gt;Tainted Wave&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will Close Blast 3 attack that
targets enemies, deals untyped damage, and makes those it hits lose &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
temporary HP and become unable to regain HP for a turn. It targets Fortitude, so
most defenders might have a good shot at resisting it, but if it hits they’re in
trouble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often (recharge 5+), they can use &lt;strong&gt;Delayed Retribution&lt;/strong&gt;, an area spell
that targets enemies’ Reflex. Those it hits take some damage and, more
importantly, will become stunned for a turn if they attack the mastermind during
their next action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone uses a divine power within 10 squares of the mastermind, it can use
&lt;strong&gt;Wrath of the Forsaken&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This ends all negative effects on an
ally within 10 squares, and allows them to make an immediate recharge roll to
recover an expended power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quite like these guys. Their lore feels epic and horrific at the same time,
and their mechanics are cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do wonder how the Forsaken perpetuate themselves, as they’ve been around since
the Dawn War and are very explicitly not immortal. Perhaps they’re still
&lt;em&gt;unaging&lt;/em&gt;, or maybe there is a procedure for exposing a mortal victim to the
fragment of immortality that belonged to a deceased Forsaken, bringing them back
in a new form Go’auld style.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/25/forsaken.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/25/forsaken.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Elemental</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-elemental.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementals are a pretty iconic part of D&amp;amp;D, since they’ve shown up on every book
we’ve covered so far. The MM1 and MM2 elementals were built to showcase the
mixed nature of the Elemental Chaos, so they were always a different combination
of two or more elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was pretty cool, but it also caused some edition warriors complain that
they missed the traditional single-element quartet from editions past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 3 brings the “singlementals” back, with heroic, paragon and
epic variants of all four classic types. The Lesser (heroic) variants would be
reprinted in the Monster Vault, and we already covered them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/16/elemental.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll
look at the standards and greaters now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;air-elemental&quot;&gt;Air Elemental&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air Elementals are Lurkers. They have a ground speed of 0, but very high air
speeds with Hover. They also have some degree of vulnerability to Fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lesser Air Elemental is Level 1 and covered &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/16/elemental.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;air-elemental-1&quot;&gt;Air Elemental&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Level 10 Lurker has 81 HP and a flight speed of 8. It has the same
&lt;strong&gt;Phantom on the Wind&lt;/strong&gt; trait as the lesser version, which makes it become
invisible when it starts the turn not adjacent to any enemies. This lasts until
the end of its next turn or until it attacks, so it will remain invisible until
it does close in to attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;slam&lt;/strong&gt; with no riders, and it can use a &lt;strong&gt;Rampant
Storm&lt;/strong&gt; that does more damage over a Close Burst 3 area and dazes targets that
couldn’t see the elemental before it attacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classic lurker tactics: start invisible, Rampant Storm, move away to become
invisible again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;greater-air-elemental&quot;&gt;Greater Air Elemental&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is Large and Level 20 with 143 HP and a speed of 10. It has most of the
same traits of the standard air elemental with bigger numbers, and it replaces
Rampant Storm with &lt;strong&gt;Engulfing Winds&lt;/strong&gt;. This melee attack pulls and grabs the
target. The elemental can move freely with a grabbed victim, which takes 20
ongoing damage until they escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one wants to grab someone and play keep-away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;earth-elementals&quot;&gt;Earth Elementals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth Elementals are Soldiers. They have a burrow speed equal to their walking
speed. &lt;strong&gt;Earth Glide&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to pass through earth and stone as if it had
phasing, and their &lt;strong&gt;Brittle Skin&lt;/strong&gt; means they take a -2 penalty to all defenses
for a turn when hit with thunder damage. They attack with &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, the Lesser Air Elemental is covered in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/16/elemental.html&quot;&gt;MM/MV article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard &lt;strong&gt;Earth Elemental&lt;/strong&gt; is level 11 with 119 HP and Speed 7. It gains a
&lt;strong&gt;Quake Stomp&lt;/strong&gt; attack that covers a selective Close Burst 2 and targets
Fortitude, damaging those it hits, sliding them 2 squares, and knocking them
prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Greater Earth Elemental&lt;/strong&gt; is Large, Level 22 with 212 HP, and replaces
Quake Stomp with &lt;strong&gt;Flattening Stomp&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets a single creature for heavy
physical damage and automatically knocks all enemies within 2 squares of the
target prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fire-elementals&quot;&gt;Fire Elementals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fire Elementals are skirmishers. They run very fast and can fly, though not as
well as an air elemental. Their &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; deal only ongoing fire damage, and
&lt;strong&gt;Flickering Flame&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to shift a number of squares as a minor
action. If they’re hit with cold damage, though, they’re &lt;strong&gt;Frozen in Place&lt;/strong&gt; and
can’t shift for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All elementals have a reaction ability that deals some sort of fire damage
around them when they’re hit by an attack. This gets more powerful as the
elemental gets bigger. Lessers are level 1, standards Level 11, and Greaters
level 21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;water-elementals&quot;&gt;Water Elementals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water elementals are controllers. They have a swim speed equal to their ground
speed, and are &lt;strong&gt;Aquatic&lt;/strong&gt;. This gives them attack bonuses against non-aquatic
enemies when fighting underwater. They’re &lt;strong&gt;Sensitive to Cold&lt;/strong&gt;, and after
taking cold damage they gain Vulnerable 5 against the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; attack to hit them
before the end of their next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; do some physical damage and inflict ongoing physical damage from
the water that gets into people’s lungs.  &lt;strong&gt;Drowning Essence&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to
slide victims taking this ongoing damage as a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack seems to be surging like a wave, dealing damage and pushing
or sliding people around. It gets more damaging, more frequent, and pushier the
bigger the elemental gets. It has different names for each elemental: &lt;strong&gt;Whelm&lt;/strong&gt;
for Lessers, &lt;strong&gt;Whirlpool&lt;/strong&gt; for standards, and &lt;strong&gt;Surging Waves&lt;/strong&gt; for Greaters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess you can notice me getting gradually more bored with classic elementals
as I wrote the above post. These ones are better than they used to be in earlier
editions, but I can understand why the Monster Vault only reprinted the
lessers. The more powerful versions are pretty much the kind of thing you can
write yourself using the standard monster leveling rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all other elementals, they fit easily into any adventure or encounter that
also features someone who could conceivably summon and bind them. They also work
well as “widlife” in the Elemental Chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/23/elemental.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/23/elemental.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Drow</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first looked at Drow during our &lt;a href=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2020/02/02/drow.html&quot;&gt;Let’s Read of the Monster Manual and
Vault&lt;/a&gt;, and you can read that post by clicking the link. The basic lore of
the drow remains the same, and this entry adds a bit more alongside some
epic-tier drow enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainstream Lolth-worshipping drow society is a nightmare of intrigue and
backstabbing, as we have already seen. Every drow is plotting to backstab their
superiors while keeping an eye out for similar plots coming from their
subordinates and peers. The higher they rise, the more favor they have in the
eyes of Lolth. Where does it end, though? What reward awaits those followers who
become such tracherous vermin they become one of Lolth’s favorite children?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why, they get to go live in the Demonweb and do it all over again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abyssal drow make up the bulk of the non-demon population of the Demonweb. The
broad outlines of their society are largely the same as those in the world -
they organize themselves into a number of factions that struggle for dominance
and Lolth’s personal favor. There are three important differences, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that these abyssal factions are centered around powerful and
charismatic individuals rather than around a city-state or noble house. The
second is that they’re made up of a mix of abyssal drows and demons of various
kinds. The third and most surprising difference is that there is almost no
&lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; intrigue within these factions. The stakes in the Abyss are too
high - Abyssal drow form stable alliances because they can’t afford to backstab
their allies down here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaders of these factions are usually Lolth’s Exarchs, and they occupy the
highest position any mortal worshiper of Lolth can aspire to. When in the Abyss,
they spend their time managing their faction and its intrigues against the
others. When outside the Demonweb, they tend to infiltrate other sapient
cultures or even act as overt ambassadors of Lolth within them. Examples of such
culture includes the giants and efreets of the Elemental Chaos or the devils of
Hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abyssal drow are still drow: Medium Fey Humanoids with a Speed of 7 and
Darkvision. Everything else about them is a function of training and varies per
stat block. Not even the classic Darkfire power is a constant, though it still
shows up in some individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drow-zealot&quot;&gt;Drow Zealot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zealots are terrifying epic level warriors, but among the drow of the Abyss
they’re considered the rank and file, the lowest of the low. Most arrived from
the world not too long ago, their minds filled with dreams of glorious
purpose. Some are instead long-term residents of the Abyss who have been busted
down to zealot from some loftier rank due to some mistake or act of
disobedience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In either case, the first thing Lolth does to a drow who attains this rank is to
curse them with a demonic spider infestation. The constant pain and suffering
this causes serves as a powerful incentive for zealots to strive for
promotion. The spiders that crawl out of their orifices and wounds also provide
some occasional help in combat, as they attack the drow’s enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zealots are Level 23 Brutes with 265 HP. They have Resist 10 poison and the
usual drow traits. They fight with a Fullblade, a huge two-handed sword that
appeared in one of the Adventurer’s Vault supplements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While bloodied they project a &lt;strong&gt;Spider Host&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1), which causes any enemy
in the aura that becomes bloodied to take 20 ongoing poison damage (save ends)
as the demon spiders crawl from the zealot’s bloodstream to the enemy’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;fullblades&lt;/strong&gt; do the heavy damage you’d expect from an epic brute, and if
the zealot misses with the attack it gains a +2 to attacks and a +5 to damage
against the same target until the end of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zealots have the traditional &lt;strong&gt;Darkfire&lt;/strong&gt; ability, a minor-action encounter
power that targets Reflex. It makes the target grant combat advantage and
nullifies any invisibility or concealment for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the zealot reaches 0 HP, it explodes in a &lt;strong&gt;Spider Burst&lt;/strong&gt;, creating a
Close Burst 1 zone that lasts until the end of the encounter and causes 10
poison damage to anyone that starts their turn inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other zealots are immune to the zone’s damage due to their poison resistance, so
they have no trouble stepping over the ruptured corpses of their allies. They’ll
charge the PCs and hack away without much care for their own wounds, since their
auras kick in when they’re bloodied. They pair well with Leader enemies that
grant extra attacks, since those could allow them to benefit from the damage
bonus given by a missed attack more than once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;draegloth-abomination&quot;&gt;Draegloth Abomination&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-drow.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abyssal drow often summon, bind, and otherwise ally with demons, but some
priestesses go further and make their own. Draegloths are created by abyssal
magic from a mix of demon and drider DNA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draegloths are pretty much impossible to control, which isn’t usually a very
desired trait in lab-bred monsters. Because of this their creation is usually
done as an act of devotion to Lolth, and they’re gifted directly to the goddess,
to whom they are quite loyal. They can be found patrolling the Demonweb
alongside other Lolth-favored demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draegloth Abominations are Huge Elemental Magical Beasts with the Demon
tag. They look like elephant-sized driders, or like the dapper fellow here in
the illustration. They’re Level 24 Lurkers with 174 HP, ground and climb speeds
of 8, Darkvision, and Tremorsense 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does double damage against a dazed
creature. The &lt;strong&gt;Slashing Claws&lt;/strong&gt; ability allows them to make two claw attacks
with the same action. Their other attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Tethering Web&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5
vs. Reflex). A hit does a small bit of poison damage and tethers the target
(save ends). Tethered targets are dazed, and the demon can pull them adjacent to
itself with a free action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can use a power named &lt;strong&gt;Maddening Darkness&lt;/strong&gt;. This
attacks the Will of all enemies in a Close Burst 2. On a hit, it slows and dazes
for a turn. This power also creates a zone of darkness that blocks line of sight
and blinds those within (with the exception of the demon in both cases). The
zone also lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When damaged, the draegloth can use a &lt;strong&gt;Dark Leap&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction. This is
another encounter power, and it recharges when it’s first bloodied. It allows
the creature to immediately recharge and use Maddening Darkness, and then
teleport 8 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it has top-tier Variable Resistance (Resistance 20 switchable
3/encounter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draegloths want to strike from ambush and open up with Maddening
Darkness. They’ll claw as many dazed PCs as they can, and use Dark Leap with the
PCs begin counter-attacking. From what point on they’ll try to stay away and
tether the squishies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drow-shadowblade&quot;&gt;Drow Shadowblade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lolth delights in treachery, even between her own followers. So when a drow
assassin is skilled and resourceful enough to murder one of the priestesses that
rule the drow city-states, that assassin gets invited to the Abyss and becomes a
Shadowblade. These epic assassins have access to the best gear, the deadliest
poisons, and to a special technique that lets them animate and control their own
shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadowblades are Level 24 Lurkers with 171 HP and the usual drow
Darkvision. Their ground speed is 7 and they have phasing, which means they can
walk through walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Short Sword&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead of attacking, they can spend
their action to cast &lt;strong&gt;Animated Shadow&lt;/strong&gt;, creating an allied animated shadow
within 10 squares. The shadow lasts until the end of the shadowblade’s next
turn and counts as an ally for flanking purposes, but is immune to attacks. When
the shadowblade moves on its turn, the shadow slides an equal number of squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a target is flanked by both the shadowblade and its shadow, the assassin
can use a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that deals the same damage as a basic attack plus 10
necrotic damage. This causes the shadow to burst into a zone of blinding
darkness to which the drow itself is immune. It lasts for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the shadowblade can poison its weapon with &lt;strong&gt;Soulrot Venom&lt;/strong&gt;,
which adds a complicated rider to the next attack it hits before the end of the
encounter. That hit will weaken the target (save ends). The first failed save
also makes the target take 15 ongoing necrotic damage; the second strips it of
all resistances and immunities! A successful save ends all those effects. The
venom recharges once the shadowblade is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, its mastery of the sword manifests as the &lt;strong&gt;Persistent Blade&lt;/strong&gt; power
(recharge 4+). This is a free action that triggers when the shadowblade misses
with its sword, and it allows it to make a basic attack against a different
enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shadowblade alpha strike is kinda scary. It summons the shadow and envenoms
its weapon “off-screen”, and then flanks and stabs a PC through a wall. If this
hits, the PC will take damage from the sword, bonus necrotic damage from the
shadow, and will be subject to soulrot venom. If this misses, the shadowblade
can still stab someone else and poison them as a consolation prize. As soon as
it can move again, it will fade into the wall and get ready for another shadow
strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drow-archmage&quot;&gt;Drow Archmage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A drow wizard powerful enough to be invited to live in the Demonweb, where they
give themselves over to the Abyss and become rather warlock-like. Despite their
demonic power, these spellcasters fear for their souls, which become fair game
to their demon buddies if they die. They are quick to run away from a fight if
it seems like they’re losing, abandoning their thralls and allies to their fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archmages are Level 25 Artillery with 178 HP and the standard drow traits. They
fight in melee with &lt;strong&gt;Daggers&lt;/strong&gt; that do physical damage and inflict a -4 attack
penalty for a turn; and at range with &lt;strong&gt;Abyssal Bolts&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 20 vs. Reflex)
that do acid and poison damage. They can also use two encounter spells that
target Fortitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cruel Banishing&lt;/strong&gt; (melee 1) does no damage, but teleports the target 7 squares
and dazes them (save ends). This is a lot deadlier if there are draegloths on
Team Monster!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demonic Grasp&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10) immobilizes the target and suspends them 1 square
up. Immobilized targets can still fight, they just can’t move. However, while
the target is affected by this spell, they take 10 poison damage every time they
&lt;em&gt;or their allies&lt;/em&gt; damage a demon, drow, or spider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the archmage can perform an &lt;strong&gt;Unwholesome Sacrifice&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+), dealing 20 damage to an adjacent ally in order to either recharge
an encounter power or get a +10 damage bonus to a ranged attack made before the
end of its next turn. Finally, it also has the same &lt;strong&gt;Darkfire&lt;/strong&gt; power as the
zealot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drow-exalted-consort&quot;&gt;Drow Exalted Consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drow society is matriarchal, and though plenty of career paths are open to drow
men the loftiest heights of power are usually denied to them. The only way for a
male drow to be part of the real elite is to become consort to a powerful
priestess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a consort is about more than looking pretty - they’re also expected to
serve their ladies as bodyguards and knights. This practice continues in the
Abyss, where Exalted Consorts are hand-picked by Lolth herself for their beauty
and martial skill. She imbues them with divine power, and places them under the
service of her priestesses in the Demonweb. This means Exalted Consorts are
kinda like epic paladins or avengers of Lolth. I guess a gift of new consorts is
a sign that Lolth particularly favors that priestess today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exalted Consorts are Level 25 Skirmishers with 224 HP. They wield paired
&lt;strong&gt;longswords&lt;/strong&gt; in combat with a graceful, mobile fighting style. Aside from
basic attacks, they can use an at-will technique named &lt;strong&gt;Warding Blades&lt;/strong&gt; that
does nearly double the damage of a basic attack and gives them a +6 AC bonus
against opportunity attacks for a turn. This allows them to move around the
battlefield much more freely than most enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have another technique named &lt;strong&gt;Blurred Steel&lt;/strong&gt; that allows them to make
three basic attacks in the same action. Up to two of which can target the same
creature, and the power recharges when the consort moves more than 3 squares in
its turn. This is a good move to alternate with Warding Blades in order to
spread damage around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lolth’s power turns the standard drow Darkfire into an attack named &lt;strong&gt;Darkfire
Revelation&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action which targets Reflex and deals fire damage. A hit
nullifies invisibility and concealment for a (save ends) duration, longer than
the single turn of basic Darkfire. This is an encounter power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their last encounter power is &lt;strong&gt;Lolth’s Favor&lt;/strong&gt;, which triggers when the consort
becomes bloodied. As a reaction, they teleport 7 squares, and cause all enemies
adjacent to them at the destination to grant combat advantage for a turn. This
is not an escape power, but something used to press the attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warding Blades should be the consort’s attack of choice even when it doesn’t
plan on moving much, the extra damage is too good to pass up. Blurring Steel is
a good alternative for when the consort manages to run or teleport past the PC
front line and close in on the poorly-armored squishies at the back, followed by
more Warding Blades in subsequent turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;drow-lady-of-spiders&quot;&gt;Drow Lady of Spiders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lady of Spiders” is the second-highest rank in Lolth’s priesthood. There are
only sixty-six of these in all of existence, and the only way to ascend to their
ranks is to kill one of the incumbents. The only drow who outranks them is
Eclavdra, Lolth’s main exarch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Lady of Spiders will always be found commanding a sizable force of drow,
demons and spiders of similar level. Her commands and her magic act as a big
force multiplier for her lackeys. Her powers include a lot of poison- and
mind-based magic, as well as the ability to heal allies and to summon demonic
spiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a Lady is a Level 27 Elite Controller with 494 HP. She projects &lt;strong&gt;Lolth’s
Blessing&lt;/strong&gt; as an aura (2) that heals bloodied allies inside for 10 HP at the
start of their turns. However, she’s &lt;strong&gt;Sensitive to Light&lt;/strong&gt;, which causes the
aura to shut down for a turn if the Lady takes radiant damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;scourge&lt;/strong&gt; that damages and slides enemies 2
squares on a hit, and her basic ranged attack &lt;strong&gt;Conjures Venom&lt;/strong&gt; straight into a
victim’s bloodstream to deal poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She can also cast an at-will spell to summon &lt;strong&gt;Coccooning Webs&lt;/strong&gt; around a
target, restraining them and dealing ongoing 25 poison damage (save ends
both). I think we just broke the record for most ongoing poison damage in an MM
so far, unless someone else reached 30 and I forgot. A target who makes the save
is still slowed until they pass a second one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lady’s mind magic is represented by &lt;strong&gt;Irrefutable Command&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a
Close Burst 3 that targets up to 2 creatures in the burst. Targets must choose
between charging another creature of the Lady’s choice or taking 50 psychic
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d say her signature ability is &lt;strong&gt;Bring Forth the Widows&lt;/strong&gt;, though. It takes a
standard action and summons a Medium demonic shadow spider to a space within 10
squares of the priestess. The Widow has 100 HP and the Lady’s defenses. It also
has speed 8 (spider climb 8), and moves whenever the Lady takes a move
action. It stays in the field for the rest of the fight or until destroyed, and
if it’s destroyed this power recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lady can order the Widow to attack with a minor action, and this deals
physical and ongoing poison damage. The spider can also make opportunity attacks
using the Lady’s opportunity action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the lady is hit in melee, her &lt;strong&gt;Fearsome Wrath&lt;/strong&gt; attacks the Will of all
enemies in a close burst 5. On a hit they’re pushed 5 squares and stunned for a
turn. This fear effect recharges once the Lady is first bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impression&quot;&gt;Final Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this and the Lolth entry that we’ll find a further into the book
(spoilers!), you have everything you need to run a 4e rendition of the GDQ
module series. Abyssal drow are the sort of enemy you’ll find in the Demonweb
itself, and their unique abilities give you a spicier result than what you’d get
if you just used leveled-up MV drow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to change much of their lore even if non-evil drow are common in
your setting. These are the people who chose to dedicate themselves to Lolth,
goddess of betrayal, mistress of the cycle of abuse, etc. etc.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/21/drow.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/21/drow.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dread Warrior</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-dread-warrior.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common zombies are mindless beasts who fight in a clumsy, instinctual way. Dread
warriors are… still mindless, but the ritual that creates them also imbues
them with more refined combat skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of a dread warrior is to act as a guard and protector. Their
creation binds them to their master, whom they are compelled to protect and
obey. When a dread warrior’s master dies, their reaction is a bit
unpredictable. Some lose their animating force and drop lifelessly to the
ground, others go berserk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of being bound to a person, they can be bound to an item instead,
protecting it from theft and damage even after their creator passes away. Liches
might use this to bind a troop of dread warriors to their soul receptacle, for
example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dread Warriors are Medium Natural Animates with the Undead keyword. They have
low-light vision and a natural speed of 6, modified by armor. They have a
signature traits: &lt;strong&gt;Eyes of Undeath&lt;/strong&gt; allows the warrior’s master to see and
hear anything the creature sees and hears. It also allows the master to speak
through it. There’s no range limit! This makes them excellent emissaries,
decoys, or security “cameras”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individual warriors have additional traits related to their training and
intended function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dread-protector&quot;&gt;Dread Protector&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your basic security model. Some necromancers like to fill their lairs with these
things so that they always have the reassuring presence of a bodyguard no matter
which room they are in. One does get used to the smell eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dread Protectors are Level 3 Soldiers with 47 HP. They wear heavy armor and
wield greataxes. Their speed is 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from Eyes Undeath, they also have a &lt;strong&gt;Shield of Undeath&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1). If
their master is inside this aura, they only take half damage from melee and
ranged attacks. The protector &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; take the other half of this damage,
making this a very good power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greataxe marks on a hit, and though the protector doesn’t have any other
abilities that make use of the mark it does make it harder to attack the
master. Instead of moving normally they can use &lt;strong&gt;Protector’s Call&lt;/strong&gt; to teleport
their speed to square adjacent to the master. This makes it very hard for PCs to
isolate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dread Protectors will seek to always stay adjacent to their master and keep the
most dangerous melee opponent marked. The best tactic for dealing with them is
to hit them with close or area attacks. These will target both them and their
master, ignoring both the mark penalty and Shield of Undeath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dread-marauder&quot;&gt;Dread Marauder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lightly armored warrior wields a short sword and a bow. It’s not any
smarter than the other dread warriors, but Eyes of Undeath still makes it a
superb scout since the master can see what it sees and order it from afar. If
they die out there, it’s no great loss - the master knows what they need to know
by that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dread Marauders are Level 5 Skirmishers with 53 HP and speed 6. They deal extra
damage when they have &lt;strong&gt;Combat Advantage&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;In the Master’s Defense&lt;/strong&gt;
gives them combat advantage against anyone adjacent to their master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;bow&lt;/strong&gt; give them both melee and ranged basic attacks, and
&lt;strong&gt;Skirmish Strike&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to shift 3 squares before making either one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So aside from being good scouts, dread marauders also serve as good deterrents
against melee PCs, since those PCs will be exposed to stronger attacks from the
marauder as long as they remain adjacent to the master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dread-archers&quot;&gt;Dread Archers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These warriors are meant to act as sniper platforms and fire support for the
master, and to man the ramparts of the master’s fortress. They’re Level 6
Artillery with 57 HP and speed 6. Their gear is similar to the marauder’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As artillery monsters, their &lt;strong&gt;bow&lt;/strong&gt; attack is more accurate than the
&lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt;. Once per encounter they can make an &lt;strong&gt;arcing volley&lt;/strong&gt; area attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their greatest powers are their custom passive trait and reaction, however!
&lt;strong&gt;Channel of Undeath&lt;/strong&gt; allows the master to make implement attacks as if they
occupied the archer’s square, as long as they can see the archer. And when the
master hits with an attack, the archer can use the &lt;strong&gt;Sustained Attack&lt;/strong&gt; reaction
to make an immediate bow attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am unsure whether I’d allow the master to “see” the archer through Eyes of
Undeath, but I’d definitely allow them so see the archer through a telescope!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dread-guardian&quot;&gt;Dread Guardian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a more powerful version of the dread protector, a Level 7 Soldier with
79 HP. It’s equipped with heavy armor, a shield, a sword, and a bow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the &lt;strong&gt;bow&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; attacks mark on a hit, and this time the
protector &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make a sword attack as an opportunity action when a marked enemy
attacks the master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Zombie warriors” are almost as classic as “skeleton warriors” in the dungeon
fantasy genre, so I think these are pretty nifty. They’re also awesome
mechanically, because Eyes of Undeath and the other passives allow for a lot if
interesting underhanded tricks.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/20/dread-warrior.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/20/dread-warrior.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dragon, Volcanic</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-dragon-volcanic.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volcanic dragons were created by Vezzuvu, the Living Mountain. The petitioners
who approached this primordial were &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt;. You see, dragons were made in Io’s
image, but Io’s demise proved he was weak. Therefore, these dragons thought,
&lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; were weak, and this realization felt like an insult to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vezzuvu promised that if the dragons bathed in the boiling magma of his domain,
their weak flesh would be burned away and replaced with a truly strong body. His
petitioners obeyed and dove in. The survivors became volcanic dragons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All was well with the volcanics for a time, but then their old pride and sense
of entitlement began to gnaw at them again. Where their new bodies truly
stronger? Had they been given all the power they were promised, all the power
they surely deserved? When they concluded they hadn’t, they turned on their
former master and went their own way. Their history from this point on is filled
with instances of volcanic dragons allying with servants of either the gods or
the primordials for a time, only to betray them a short time later. In our
narrative present, everyone knows an alliance with these beasts is likely to end
in sudden but inevitable betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical volcanic dragon’s temperament is like that of a red, but worse. They
make a show of craving treasure and rulership over a territory, but what they
truly crave is destruction. In other words, volcanic dragons love burning stuff,
especially flesh. It makes them feel good. They like the company of other
fire-elemental beings with similar dispositions, but any alliance they make is
temporary at best. They live inside volcanoes and on other similar burning
landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Volcanic Dragons follow the same general format of the other catastrophics
you could argue they are right about getting a bad deal from Vezzuvus. They’re
Elemental Magical Beasts with the Dragon and Fire keywords, Darkvision, and a
Clumsy Flight speed equal to their ground speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;volcanic-dragon-wyrmling&quot;&gt;Volcanic Dragon Wyrmling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wyrmlings are Medium Level 5 Brutes with 77 HP and Speed 6. They’re surrounded
by an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Noxious Fumes&lt;/strong&gt; that deals 3 poison damage to enemies who
end their turns inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon’s basic &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; are weaker than those of most brutes,
but the bite inflicts ongoing fire damage and the claws strip the target of all
fire resistance until the start of the dragon’s next turn. As usual &lt;strong&gt;wyrmling
fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to use both attacks in the same action while bloodied. Use the
claw first!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When hit by a fire attack, the wyrmling uses a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Flare&lt;/strong&gt; as a reaction,
causing each enemy inside the dragon’s aura to take 5 fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;young-volcanic-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Volcanic Dragon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young’uns are Large Level 10 Elite Brutes with 264 HP and speed 8. They have all
the same attacks as the wyrmling, but their Wyrmling Fury upgrades to a full
&lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt;. Their numbers are also bigger, of course, and they gain two
new attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Growing Heat&lt;/strong&gt; is their “disaster” ability. When activated with a minor
action, it makes their Noxious Fumes aura grow to size 3, then to size 5 on the
next turn, and then explode in the turn after that. This explosion targets
Reflex and deals both immediate and ongoing fire damage. After it resolves the
dragon’s aura shrinks to its original size and the power recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dragon can also create a &lt;strong&gt;Lava Vent&lt;/strong&gt;, an Area Burst 1 zone that lasts
until the end of the encounter and deals 5 fire damage to anyone who enters or
starts their turn there. This recharges once the dragon is first bloodied, so
each dragon in the fight can create 2 vents total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-age-categories&quot;&gt;Other Age Categories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adults&lt;/strong&gt; are Level 15 Elite Brutes with 363 HP, and have all the same
abilities of a young dragon with bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elders&lt;/strong&gt; are Huge Level 20 Elite Brutes with 468 HP, and likewise have all the
same abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancients&lt;/strong&gt; are Huge Level 25 Elite Brutes with 574 HP. They have all the same
abilities as elders and are also able to create a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Fissure&lt;/strong&gt; in addition
to the lava vents. This works like a temporary wall of fire (and it’s a wall 6
pattern) that deals 20 fire damage to anyone who tries to touch or cross it. It
only lasts for a turn but it’s a minor action and a recharge 5+ attack instead
of an encounter power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volcanic dragons might be weaker than traditional ones, but they’re much better
at subverting expectations. Typical PCs might see that it’s a fire monster and
load up on fire resistance effects, only to realize the dragon’s aura deals
&lt;em&gt;poison&lt;/em&gt; damage and it can remove fire resistance with its claws. Also, the bulk
of the damage from its basic attacks is untyped, further limiting the usefulness
of fire resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lore-wise, paranoia and entitlement seem to be their strongest personality
traits. They’re hard to deal with because they always feel they’re not getting
their due. Even when a deal is fair and happens as promised, they’ll probably
feel the other party got one over on them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/17/dragon-volcanic.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/17/dragon-volcanic.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dragon, Earthquake</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-dragon-earthquake.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earthquake dragons were created by Balcoth, the Groaning King. The petitioners
who approached this Earth primordial were terrified by the death of Io, and were
willing to swear loyalty to anyone who could protect them. Balcoth agreed, and
fulfilled his promise by swallowing the dragons up and keeping them inside his
furnace-like belly, where they “cooked” and were changed by his essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balcoth would vomit up a few earthquake dragons when he needed their
service. When the primordial was beheaded and slain during the Dawn War, the
rest of his dragons escaped through the wound and into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, Earthquake dragons are extremely into the whole “living
disaster” thing. When they settle down somewhere, the surrounding region is soon
wracked by tremors of increasing intensity and duration. The dragon feeds on the
people killed by these tremors, and will sometimes destroy a city on purpose
just because they can. They lair in the ruins for months, digesting their prey
and enjoying the view of the ruins until they grow tired of them and fly away to
look for another place to devastate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike their blizzard cousins, earthquakes are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; team players. They’ll form
temporary alliances with inedible creatures (mostly earth-themed), and can
sometimes be bribed into service by mortals, but these arrangements never last
long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dragons aren’t great fliers, but they can swim through earth and rock as
if it was water. They hunt by suppressing their earthquake aura and stalking
their prey from underground. When they attack, they make a spectacular entry and
fight with all of their powers, though they usually retreat back underground
rather than fighting to the death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earthquake Dragons follow the same general plan as Blizzards. They’re Elemental
Magical Beasts with the Dragon and Earth keywords. They have Darkvision,
Tremorsense, and both burrow and clumsy flight speeds that are about half of
their ground speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;earthquake-dragon-wyrmling&quot;&gt;Earthquake Dragon Wyrmling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Medium Level 4 Soldier with 58 HP, representing the youngest dragon
that can be a threat in combat. Their speed is 6 (burrow 2, clumsy flight
2). They project a Quaking Earth aura (1) with a very “soldierly” effect: if an
enemy inside the aura makes an attack that doesn’t include the dragon as a
target, the enemy falls prone and takes 5 damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wyrmling’s &lt;strong&gt;bite&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;claw&lt;/strong&gt; basic attacks do physical damage without
riders, and &lt;strong&gt;Wyrmling Fury&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make both attacks in the same action
while it’s bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they have a &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Quake&lt;/strong&gt; ability that triggers when they’re knocked
prone or subjected to forced movement. It knocks all enemies inside the dragon’s
aura prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-earthquake-dragon&quot;&gt;Young Earthquake Dragon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young dragons are Large Level 9 Elite Soldiers with 206 HP. Their ground speed
increases to 8, their burrow and flight speeds to 4. They have all the same
abilities as a wyrmling, with bigger numbers. They replace Wyrmling Fury with a
proper &lt;strong&gt;Double Attack&lt;/strong&gt; and add two new powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earthen Maw&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) is a melee attack that does more damage than a
basic bite and restains the target (save ends). After the first save the target
is instead petrified! A save still ends this, but the target is entirely unable
to act until they make that save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their “disaster” power is &lt;strong&gt;Rising Tremors&lt;/strong&gt;, which follows the same pattern
seen for blizzard dragons. When it’s activated with a minor action, it increases
the dragon’s aura size to 3. At the end of the next turn, the aura increases
again to 5. And at the end of the turn after that, the dragon makes a Close
Burst 5 attack vs. Reflex. This one deals physical damage, knocks targets prone,
and prevents them from standing back up (save ends). After the attack, the aura
resets and this power recharges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-age-categories&quot;&gt;Other Age Categories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adults&lt;/strong&gt; are Level 14 Elite Soldiers with 288 HP, and have all the same
abilities with bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elders&lt;/strong&gt; are Huge Level 19 Elite Soldiers with 374 HP, and again have all the
same abilities with bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancients&lt;/strong&gt; are Level 24 Elite Soldiers with 456 HP, and gain Threatening
Reach 3. They once again have all the same abilities as younger dragons with
bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m surprised the dragons in this entry are still marked as Unaligned despite
being a lot more actively destructive and cruel than blizzard dragons. I’d have
thought “I exist to satisfy my twin urges to destroy and devour” would rate a
Chaotic Evil alignment. Of course, you can go the other way and give them more
flexible personalities and more varied motivations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, earthquake dragons are very good at knocking people down and
&lt;em&gt;keeping&lt;/em&gt; them down, so they pair really well with melee lurkers and skirmishers
whose attacks are more powerful when they have combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/16/dragon-earthquake.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/07/16/dragon-earthquake.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
