<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 15:48:06 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 15:48:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.10.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jade Irinka, the Sixth Raven</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the player characters for my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/lets-play-hells-rebels/&quot;&gt;solo Hell’s Rebels campaign&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jade Irinka was an orphan of uncertain but numinous parentage who was adopted as
a sort of mascot by the original Silver Ravens during their early exploits. She
was too young to go out with the Ravens on their missions, but she witnessed
their results and listened to their stories with rapt attention. Jackdaw,
knowing victory would be uncertain in the final Thrune invasion, sent her away
from the city with other non-combatant friends, hoping they would be able to
come back once the fighting was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things didn’t turn out well, and Jade never got the chance to return. She aged
slowly but eventually reached maturity and set out to follow on the footsteps of
her heroes. Her natural charisma and skill with the sword let her achieve some
small measure of renown around the Inner Sea as an heroic adventurer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent news from Cheliax convinced Jade it’s finally time to return home and
take up the Ravens’ fight. She doesn’t remember many details about those days,
but she’s confident she will find a way. Everything she’s done so far has been
to prepare herself for this. As the campaign starts, she has just caught up on
the events and rumors of the last few days and decides to attend the Aria Park
protest to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have guessed from her name, Jade is inspired by Jasper Irinka, the
Child of the Sun, one of the iconic characters from Chuubo’s Marvelous Wish
Granting Engine. I’m using Jade instead of Jasper as the name because I like it
more - it’s the name of Jasper’s Mother, the Angel of the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Jade looks almost exactly like Jasper. Dark brown skin, voluminous and fiery
red hair, green or blue eyes depending on the light. She has an athlethic build
from all her adventuring, though her equipment is somewhat less than elegant
at the moment. Unlike Jasper, she has only two arms at present and is unlikely
to grow more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This name might also give you a hint about who her ancestors are in the
Pathfinder setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-notes&quot;&gt;Build notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jade’s stats below are based on the Aristocrat archetype from GURPS Dungeon
Fantasy Denizens: Swashbucklers. This gives her amazing sword and leadership
skills, though I removed some of the template’s more classist traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her being a long-lived half-spirit is mostly a story thing for now, as I didn’t
take an official template. You can use these stats for a charismatic human
swashbuckler in some other campaign without changing any numbers. If you do want
to emphasize her supernatural side, you can let her gradually take on
Half-Spirit traits with earned character points. That’s what I intend to do
eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jade already has a +5 reaction bonus from almost everyone and an extra +3 from
professional fighters. I’m hoping to use earned points to increase that even
further, maxing out her Charisma, Born War-Leader talent, and perhaps even
Appearance. She’s going to be the public face of the rebellion, after
all. Holiness and its attendant powers are also not out of the question in the
future, as they’d make her even better at fighting demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;character-sheet&quot;&gt;Character Sheet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ST&lt;/strong&gt; 11 {10}; &lt;strong&gt;DX&lt;/strong&gt; 15 {100}; &lt;strong&gt;IQ&lt;/strong&gt; 12 {40}; &lt;strong&gt;HT&lt;/strong&gt; 12 {20};&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damage 1d-1/1d+1; Basic Lift 12.1kg; HP 11; Will 12; Per 12; FP 12; Basic Speed 7;
Basic Move 7;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ambidexterity {5}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appearance (Impressive) {12}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Born War Leader 3 {15}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charisma 2 {10}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combat Reflexes {15}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Luck {15}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weapon Master (Backsword) {-20}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weapon Adaptation (Broadsword to Saber) {1}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code of Honor (Soldier’s) {-10}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2024/08/30/lphr-player-characters.html&quot;&gt;Enemies (Monster of the Week)&lt;/a&gt; (9-) {-15}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pacifism: Cannot Harm Innocents {-10}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sense of Duty (Adventuring Companions) {-5}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vow (Never refuse a challenge to combat) {-10}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quirks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick your own! {-5}&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skills&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acrobatics (H) DX-1 {2} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diplomacy (H) IQ-2 {1} - 10&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fast-Draw (Sword) (E) DX+1 {1}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 16&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gesture (E) IQ {1} - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guns (Pistol) (E) DX+1 {2} - 16&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jumping (E) DX {1} - 15&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leadership (A) IQ+4 {1}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 16&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public Speaking (A) IQ+1 {1}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 13&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saber (A) DX+5 {20} - 20&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Savoir-Faire (High Society) (E) IQ {1} - 12&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stealth (A) DX-1 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategy (H) IQ+2 {2}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 14&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tactics (H) IQ+2 {2}&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - 14&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrestling (A) DX-1 {1} - 14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loadout&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$1000, 11.41kg. No encumbrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ordinary Clothing: Free; 1kg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Backsword: Basket hilt gives DR 4 to the hand and allows a Hilt Punch. $550,
1.5kg.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pouch: Fits 1.5kg of small items. $10, 0.1kg.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Coins: 8 silvers, 23 coppers. $183, 0.31kg.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Minor Healing Potion: Heals 1d HP. $120, 0.25kg.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light Cloth Armor Suit: DR 1 to all locations except the head. $137, 8.25kg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Combat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assumes no encumbrance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defenses&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dodge: 11&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Parry: 14F (sword), 11 (Unarmed, DX)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;DR: 2 on skull, 0 on eyes, 5 in sword hand, 1 everywhere else.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attacks&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Backsword (20): 1d+4 cut or 1d+2 imp, Reach 1.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hilt Punch (15): 1d-1 cr, Reach C.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;+1 from Combat Reflexes &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;+3 from Born War Leader &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;+2 from Charisma &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/24/lphr-jade-irinka.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/24/lphr-jade-irinka.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        <category>character</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Review: GURPS Gun Stats</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine the following situation: you want to feature a certain gun in your
campaign, but you want to do it “properly”. You’re not the kind of GM who would
feel good about just tossing some random numbers in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weapon in question is not in any of your books, and it’s different enough
from the ones that are that you can’t just reskin an existing gun. That’d be the
same as using random numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the story above resonated with you, then you’ll love GURPS Gun Stats. It
gives you an official system to write up GURPS 4th Edition stats for guns
starting from their real world data. If the lack of these rules stopped you
before, you’ll love this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, players who were really into statting up guns might already have been
doing this for years by either building them using the rules from GURPS Vehicles
for 3rd edition, or by using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://gamingballistic.com/2022/04/11/old-ballistics-spreadsheet-a-repost/&quot;&gt;very scary unofficial spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; cooked up
by Douglas Cole for his own use. Gun Stats is still useful for them, as it’s
much simpler than the spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-looks&quot;&gt;How It Looks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a typical Warehouse 23 PDF. All black and white, with the by now
classical GURPS two-column layout combined with the usual excellent table of
contents and index. Its written by David Pulver with additional material by
S.A. Fisher Hans-Christian Vortisch, which is kind of a seal of quality in
itself when it comes to gun-nut material in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interior art is mostly a mix of illustrations clearly based on photos or 3D
models with a weird “acid etching” surface filter applied to them to unify the
look. You also have a few hand-drawn illustrations. The art credits are fairly
long, listing several photo repositories and 3D studios in addition to a couple
of individual artists. I admit the “acid etching” filter made me take a closer
look, but I believe all the art in this book is either drawn or edited by human
hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Totally-Not-From-Assassin’s Creed lady on page 9 has a bit of an awkward
pose, but it’s organic awkwardness. The rest of the pieces are fine, and look
good without getting in the way of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How It Works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I found nifty about the book is that it’s more than a collection of
formulas. It has some instruction on how to actually do the research to get that
real-life gun data, and a little checklist. You’ll need things like the empty
weight, barrel length and overall length of the gun itself; the weight and
dimensions of its projectile and of the whole cartridge; and how much propellant
it uses per shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of those stats (like the weights and costs) can be written straight into
the stat sheet, while others are used in relatively simple equations to derive
stuff like damage, Accuracy, and range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it. While those simple calculations can still be a little intense
they’ll get you the results you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the book you have a printable checklist for your own research, and
three example weapons: a French anti-material rifle, a 19th-century 6-pounder
cannon, and the gun on the M1A2 Abrams tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caveats-and-annoyances&quot;&gt;Caveats and Annoyances&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book works best when dealing with historical or modern guns that have ample
information available to the public, whether in Wikipedia, more specialized
sites, or even sales brochures. The less information is available for a specific
weapon, the more you’ll have to guesstimate when filling your checklist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can already see this with the Abrams tank gun here. Recent data about it and
its ammunition is classified, so they either use Gulf War-era information or
just make educated guesses about some of its measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fictional guns will often be harder, because they very often lack a lot of
measurements entirely, as those weren’t necessary to tell the story. You’ll have
to come up with those yourself, or maybe go looking for the work of other fans
who have already spent a ton of time doing exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all perfectly doable, but presumably you wanted this book because you
didn’t want to guess all the numbers. On the other hand, doing this will give
you a pretty good ideas of the ways in which this or that fictional weapon is
unrealistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final annoyance for me specifically: like all other GURPS books, this one uses
Imperial measurements exclusively for its calculations. Yes, even though modern
gun data is often presented in metric. You gotta convert all of that to feet,
pounds, and inches before doing the work, which is doubly annoying to me because
I’m going to convert a lot of that right back for the final writeups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS Gun Stats gives me the same impression as a classical UNIX or Linux
command line tool. It’s designed to do one job, it does that job pretty well
despite some usability issues, and it has a lot of options that can be difficult
to remember without looking at the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need to do that job, this is the tool for you, and the learning curve is
worth it. If you’re happy to just toss some eyeballed stats onto a table and
call it a day, then you can skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/20/review-gurps-gun-stats.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/20/review-gurps-gun-stats.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>review</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels has a project page!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/lets-play-hells-rebels/&quot;&gt;right here&lt;/a&gt;, and you can also access it via the Projects link on the
site’s header. Turns out I’ve already published a lot of stuff about this
project over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/18/lphr-project-page.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/18/lphr-project-page.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Wilderness Hazards</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing our read of the Hazards section, we’ll now see a few Wilderness
hazards. These are all naturally occurring, and most are extra-dangerous
versions of the terrain we saw earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wilderness-hazards&quot;&gt;Wilderness Hazards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chokedust-cloud-level-2-lurker&quot;&gt;Chokedust Cloud (Level 2 Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more dangerous version of the stuff you might find in ash wastes, silt pools,
and deserts with particularly fine sand. This is a 3-by-3 area of particularly
fine and powdery stuff, and the slightest disturbance will cause it to form a
cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can roll Perception to notice the area is different, and if they pass
that first test they can roll an easier Nature one to learn exactly why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hazard triggers when someone steps into the area, or when a portion of it is
included in a blast or burst attack. The entire area erupts into a choking cloud
that attacks the Fortitude of those standing on it. On a hit it blinds and
inflicts ongoing 5 damage (save ends). The cloud stays around after this -
victims cannot save against its effects while they remain inside. I imagine it
also attacks anyone who steps into it after this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can roll Acrobatics when moving into the area to avoid disturbing it,
and they can roll Endurance to steel themselves and gain a +2 to Fortitude
against the cloud’s next attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;badlands-tremor-level-5-lurker&quot;&gt;Badlands Tremor (Level 5 Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small localized earthquake. It has four epicenter squares scattered through
the encounter area. The GM can either roll randomly or place them for maximum
inconvenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can roll Perception to listen for the groaning noise that precedes
the tremor, and then Nature to identify it as an incoming earthquake and (with a
good enough roll) where the epicenters are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tremor starts when the encounter does - roll initiative for it. On its
initiative count, a random epicenter makes a Close Burst 5 attack vs. Reflex
that damages and knocks prone on a hit, half on a miss, and makes its area
difficult terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only countermeasure is an Acrobatics check on your turn to brace yourself
for the next tremor. Staying away from the tremor areas also works, but it might
not be feasible depending on the map’s layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;silt-sink-level-8-lurker&quot;&gt;Silt Sink (Level 8 Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A much more dangerous version of the Silt Pool terrain from before. This is a
4-by-4 squares wide, 30-foot deep hole filled with silt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a Perception roll to notice the ground is different, and then a Nature
check to realize this is a deep pit that could bury someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone steps onto the pit’s area, they suffer an attack against their
Reflex. On a hit they take fall damage (3d10, as if the pit was empty), and then
get immobilized and begin to take ongoing 5 damage until they escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An escape attempt requires a series of Athletics or Acrobatics check against the
pit’s escape DC. Each success causes the victm to rise 10 feet towards the
surface. If they’re still in the pit at the end of their turn, they remain
immobilized however. So it takes 3 successes for someone to fully escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another character can try to help the victim if they can find a way to reach
them (such as with a long branch or pole), using a move action to automatically
pull them up by 10 feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;devil-dune-level-9-obstacle&quot;&gt;Devil Dune (Level 9 Obstacle)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge pile of loose sand that is currently being pushed by the winds and moving
at a surprisingly high speed. This could be a natural phenomenon, or it could be
the work of an angry spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be automatically noticed, and there’s a Nature check to realize it’s
dangerous. The dune rolls Initiative, and on its turn it shifts 4 square towards
the nearest creature. When it enters a creature’s space, it can attack their
Reflex to try to engulf them. This damages, slows, inflicts ongoing 5 damage,
and obscures vision beyond 2 squares (save ends all). On a miss, it just slows
for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who starts their turn entirely inside the dune takes an attack against
their Fortitude, which deals heavy damage and restrains. It takes an escape
roll, not a save, to get out of the sand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only countermeasure, other than staying the heck away, is the option to roll
Acrobatics as an interrupt before the dune attacks your Reflex. The result of
the roll becomes your new defense against that attack, even if it was lower than
your Reflex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;false-oasis-level-13-elite-lurker&quot;&gt;False Oasis (Level 13 Elite Lurker)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This 6-by-6 square area looks like an oasis, but it’s actually an
illusion. Behind it is a 2-by-2 area filled with blood-sucking creeper plants,
which counts as blocking terrain. Sounds like just the kind of thing a group of
sand brides would set up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Insight check might let someone recognize the oasis as an illusion, but not
identify what it hides. A harder Arcana test can do both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone gets to within 3 squares of the illusion’s borders, the hazard rolls
initiative. On its turn, the creepers reach out and try to pull the victim, an
attack against AC that deals no damage and pulls the target 2 squares. This can
target up to three creatures, so it not being an opportunity attack is actually
an advantage. There’s enough time for multiple victims to approach the sweet,
sweet illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a character starts their turn adjacent to the actual creeper squares, they’re
targetted by an opportunity action that attacks their Fortitude and, on a hit,
weakens and inflicts ongoing 10 necrotic damage (save ends). On a miss, it deals
5 necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t pierce the illusion or staying away is not an option, you can
destroy the false oasis with violence (105 HP, vulnerable 15 radiant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dust-funnel-level-15-blaster&quot;&gt;Dust Funnel (Level 15 Blaster)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tornado, more or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roll Initiative for the hazard when combat starts, and choose a square on the
battle map. On its first turn, the dust funnel manifests in a Close Burst 2
around that square, and takes up that much space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Perception or an easier Nature test can identify this spot as the forces build
up, before the funnel manifests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its turns, the funnel moves 1d10 squares and makes an attack against anyone
who happens to be in its area. On a hit, it damages, knocks prone, and
immobilizes its targets (save ends). Until the target passes a save, they get
dragged along with the funnel whenever it moves. Of course, targets who get
dragged along will suffer the attack again next turn, since they will be in
reach of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine if this thing manages to grab &lt;em&gt;every other combatant&lt;/em&gt;, monsters and PCs
alike. That’d be hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters can make a hard Nature check to figure out where the funnel will move
in its next turn, and if they can’t escape its path they can spend a standard
action to grab onto something and get +4 to all defenses against its next
attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;desert-glass-level-17-obstacle&quot;&gt;Desert Glass (Level 17 Obstacle)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already saw what an even mix of sand and powdered glass can do. This is a
stretch of ground that’s mostly pure glass, in much bigger chunks. It’s super
slippery and cuts you to ribbons if you fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hazard covers 20 contiguous squares, in any configuration the GM wants. All
of them are difficult terrain. If they’re not obvious, such as if there’s a
thin layer of sand over them, they can be identified with a Perception test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who enters, starts their turn, or stands up from prone on one of these
squares takes an attack against Reflex that damages, knocks prone, and inflicts
ongoing 10 damage (save ends). It the target was already prone, they are dazed
for a turn instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one or more squares of the glass are included in an area attack that has the
cold, thunder, or force keywords, the affected squares make a Close Burst 1
attack that deals the same amount of immediate and ongoing damage as the other
one, and then disappear. They got shattered and blew up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venomous-spines-level-21-blaster&quot;&gt;Venomous Spines (Level 21 Blaster)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are from a species of tree that grows on some of the rare jungle biomes of
Athas. When someone gets near, the tree forcibly ejects an omni-directional
cloud of venomous spines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Perception check can notice there’s something funny about that tree. A Nature
check can identify it before the PCs enter its range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack hits a Close Burst 5 around the tree, dealing heavy poison damage and
making a secondary attack that on a hit blinds and inflicts ongoing 5 poison
damage (save ends). On a miss, it deals half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who knows the tree is dangerous can close in without triggering it with
an Acrobatics or Stealth check. They can then use hard Nature checks to reduce
the size of the burst by 2 per successful check, entirely “disarming” the tree
with the third success. I’m guessing they’re plucking the spines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defiled-plain-level-24-obstacle&quot;&gt;Defiled Plain (Level 24 Obstacle)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A patch of ground so thoroughly defiled it’s not just dead, it’s
“undead”. Anyone stepping on it will have their life force drained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Perception check can tell the ground is unnatural, and an Arcana check can
identify its danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The attack deals heavy necrotic damage and inflicts vulnerable 10 to all damage
(save ends). The first failed save causes the target to lose a healing surge,
and the second one makes the vulnerability &lt;em&gt;permanent&lt;/em&gt; until cured by a ritual
like Remove Affliction. A miss deals half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A character near or on the affected area can make a hard Arcana check to
neutralize it for a turn. Characters without Arcane Defiling powers or abilities
have a +2 on this test. Those who have these take a -2 instead. A preserver
(which I assume means someone without those abilities) can choose to spend 2
healing surges to destroy the hazard, which I guess means they can restore some
of the place’s lost life. The book says those healing surges can only be
regained through an extended rest, which feels redundant but I guess means no
other trick that would normally allow an early recovery can do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hazards are generally scarier versions of the terrain we saw earlier, so
they’re certainly appropriate for inclusion in battles taking place in that
terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it for the book! I hope you enjoyed the reading. I’m trying to think
of what to do next, so any suggestions are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/12/wir-dscc-wilderness-hazards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/12/wir-dscc-wilderness-hazards.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Play Hell&apos;s Rebels: A Decision</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in a &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2025/12/22/lphr-background-change.html&quot;&gt;post back in December&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve been actually playing this
solo game in a sporadic fashion for years. And as I said back when I started, I
planned to post it here. So why didn’t I?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it was anxiety over art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I was going to do was to post the stats for my player
characters, and since these were going to be “proper blog posts”, I decided I
wanted to have illustrations for them just like I have for all the other
characters I posted before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My method of procuring them was going to be the same. I’d use search indexes and
trawl some specific art sites for published images I could add to the post, with
proper credit and a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For certain characters, that’s dead easy. But for a couple of others I ended up
never finding an image that &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; matched what I wanted. Or when I did find
one that had the right vibe, it turned out the artist explicitly forbade this
kind of usage, even with proper credit. Also one of my sources was Pinterest and
I had just learned that one site had a serious “proper credit” issue. Whoops!
What to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know exactly what suggestion is already forming in a lot of your brains right
now, and I’m gonna stop y’all right there and say “no”. I’m not using AI for
this, or anything else. Not now, not ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after way too long you’ll get those posts without illustrations at all. I
can’t draw, but I can write, so you’re getting verbal descriptions. And maybe
then I can finally proceed with publishing this.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/11/lets-play-hells-rebels-announcement.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/11/lets-play-hells-rebels-announcement.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lets-play</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>dungeon-fantasy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Hazards</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if the stuff we saw on our previous post was pretty hazardous, none of it
counts as a “hazard” in mechanical terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference is that Terrain is entirely passive. It might do something
when you step on it, or it might allow a character to perform some special
action when next to it, but it never &lt;em&gt;initiates&lt;/em&gt; any interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hazards, on the other hand, have enough “agency” to count as a monster for
encounter building purposes. They can make attacks, and can also be disabled by
the methods outlined in its description. Traps are the most popular example of
hazards, but these rules can also model dangerous terrain features that weren’t
built to do harm on purpose. Obviously, unlike real monsters, traps and hazards
don’t use tactics. They just follow their “programming”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traps and hazards have their own set of roles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blasters&lt;/strong&gt; make ranged or area attacks. A crossbow trap is the most popular
example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lurkers&lt;/strong&gt; can disappear for a while after making their attacks, so dealing
with them is harder. A blade trap that retracts into the wall is a good
example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obstacles&lt;/strong&gt; impede movement, both by their presence and with attacks that
slow the target down. They might block passage entirely or require characters
to make tricky movement or puzzle-solving skill checks to pass.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warders&lt;/strong&gt; are alarm systems. They can have damaging attacks too, and will
make them as soon as they detect intruders, but their main function is to warn
others about the presence of those intruders. The alarm might only sound once,
or keep sounding while the hazard persists. In truth, this seems to be kind of
a catch-all category. If the hazard can’t conceal itself after attacking and
doesn’t really impede movement, it’s a warder. A shrieker mushroom is a
non-damaging example.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summarized descriptions below, I always start with a description of the
hazard’s nature and appearance, what it does when triggered, and how to avoid or
disable it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arena-hazards&quot;&gt;Arena Hazards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This subsection details hazards that might be found in the many gladiatorial
arenas of Athas. They’re placed on purpose to make things more “interesting”,
but they’re not really &lt;em&gt;traps&lt;/em&gt; per se.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worthy-sacrifices-of-draj&quot;&gt;Worthy Sacrifices of Draj&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a 3-by-6 square pile or corpses with their hearts torn out. &lt;em&gt;Animated&lt;/em&gt;
corpses, that will try to grab, pull, and gnaw on anyone they sense nearby. It’s
a Level 8 Obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs can notice the corpses are animated with Perception or Religion. The pile
makes opportunity attacks that damage and grab against any character who steps
adjacent to it. Roll Initiative for it after the first such attack. On its
turn, it will try to pull any grabbed victims into itself, dealing the same
damage as the initial attack and inflicting ongoing 10 necrotic damage while the
victims remain inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PC can choose to make an Acrobatics test when they step adjacent to the pile
to avoid the opportunity attack. They can disable it either by good old
fashioned violence (70 HP, resist necrotic, vulnerable radiant), or by
improvising an exorcism with Nature and Religion. This is a complexiy 1 skill
challenge where each failure deals 5 necrotic damage to the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blood-trees-of-gulg&quot;&gt;Blood Trees of Gulg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are large trees with red leaves. The main arena in Gulg has about a dozen
of these planted in a semi-random arrangement. Their trunks completely fill a
square and count as blocking terrain. Their branches stretch 3 squares in every
direction from the trunk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rumor that these trees have red leaves because they feed on blood is
false. The leaves are naturally red, and the trees are mostly harmless. They
only turn carnivorous when they’re about to bloom, you see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no fixed blooming season - the timing for that is rather random. For
this specific arena, at most 3 trees might be dangerous at a time. The rest are
still blocking terrain, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood Trees are level 9 Warders. Their presence is obvious, and a Nature or
Perception check can allow a PC to notice that a given tree is “primed” and what
its reach is (it’s 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone steps into that reach, the tree makes an opportunity attack that
damages and knocks prone on a hit. On its turn, it apparently uses another set
of branches to make attacks against Fortitude to damage, poison and fling away
anyone it hits with those. That’s ongoing 5 poison (save ends), plus a secondary
attack that makes a 5-square push on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood trees can be destroyed by violence (100 HP, resist 10 poison); and a PC
can succeed at a Nature check when stepping into their reach to avoid the
opportunity attack and be ignored by the tree for the rest of the encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;obsidian-façades-of-urik&quot;&gt;Obsidian Façades of Urik&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arena in Urik is a former pit from an obsidian mine. Its walls are wickedly
sharp and good enough at absorbing heat that by noon the arena resembles a huge
natural air fryer. Guess when fights take place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters inside the arena are exposed to Sun Sickness, a disease detailed in
the Dark Sun Campaign Setting that probably represents heat stroke and
dehydration. The walls are a variable level Obstacle, and moving adjacent to
them subjects the character to an attack that deals mixed physical and fire
damage that rises with tier. Characters doing so on purpose can attempt an
Acrobatics check to avoid this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-up&quot;&gt;Next up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wilderness hazards! Because the world itself is also out to get you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/10/wir-dscc-hazards.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/10/wir-dscc-hazards.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Athasian Terrain</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re done with monsters for now, and we’re getting into a section about
terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrain is as important a building block for a fun encounters as the monsters
that make it up, and this section has some uniquely Dark and Sunny examples for
you to add to your battlemaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;barbed-cacti&quot;&gt;Barbed Cacti&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when they don’t uproot themselves to hunt you down, Athasian cacti can
still be dangerous. These specimens have sharp spines that break off and stay
stuck to you. Lines of barbed cactus squares can be used to cordon off some
areas of the battlefield, and provide an excellent barrier for artillery
monsters to hide behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering a square of barbed cacti deals 3 damage and inflices -2 to attack rolls
(save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brambleweed&quot;&gt;Brambleweed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like barbed cacti, but worse. Brambleweed grows in sprawling thickets that can
thrive even in defiled areas, because they can use the blood or corpses of
captured creatures as nourishment. Some defilers plant them intentionally as
defensive measures in their lairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creature that ends their turn in a brambleweed square is restrained until the
end of their next turn. A creature that &lt;em&gt;starts&lt;/em&gt; their turn there (which they
will if they were restrained) takes 5/tier damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;defiled-terrain&quot;&gt;Defiled Terrain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a more varied category describing several possibilities for what might
remain behind after a major act of defiling. It can be used as pre-existing
terrain in an area what was subject to defiling in the past, or you can place it
in the middle of the fight after someone uses Arcane Defiling or an equivalent
power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ash-field&quot;&gt;Ash Field&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the remains of plant life caught in a defiling field. Sometimes the
wind causes them to pool in terrain depressions to form areas of Settled Ash,
which can act as a terrain feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone who’s adjacent to a square of settled ash can make an Athletics test to
raise a cloud of it, which functions as a blast attack vs. Fortitude that blinds
for a turn on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;black-sand&quot;&gt;Black Sand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The residue of defiling mixed in with the local soil. People standing on black
sand only regain half the normal amount of HP from healing effects. Wasn’t there
an entire geographical region covered in the stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dead-magic&quot;&gt;Dead Magic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Areas that have lost so much to defiling that they have nothing left to
give. Anyone standing on dead magic squares takes a -5 penalty to attack with
arcane or primal powers, and is barred from using Arcane Defiling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book recommends being careful with dead magic areas, particularly if there
are a lot of arcane and primal PCs in the party. Usually only very powerful
defilers are capable of creating them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sickening-heat&quot;&gt;Sickening Heat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is either a mystical side effect of defiling, or it could just be a natural
consequence of killing all that plant cover. Creatures ending their turn on
these squares are weakened for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This terrain can do a number on your party’s strikers, and monsters who have the
ability to inflict forced movement simply love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;glimmering-mirage&quot;&gt;Glimmering Mirage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mundane mirages are the effect of heat haze in the distance. These ones are more
than that: they’re illusions crafted by malicious primal spirits. In addition to
luring travelers, they persist once they get closer, and can conceal all kinds
of danger behinds their alluring façades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glimmering mirages form walls 4 or more squares long. They block line of sight,
and give concealment against ranged attacks to anyone standing adjacent to
them. At the end of every turn, you roll a d6 for each mirage. A 1 means it’s
gone, a 6 means it moves 5 squares, and other results mean it stays put.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lightning-pillar&quot;&gt;Lightning Pillar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally a pillar of congealed lightning, probably created due to the area’s
proximity to an “electric” region of the Elemental Chaos. PCs and enemies might
be able to use their Arcana, Nature, or Religion skills to “hack” such a pillar
and make it deliver a lightning strike to a chosen target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mudflats&quot;&gt;Mudflats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are natural areas where underground water surfaces a bit and mixes with
the soil, creating an area that is both dusty and sludgy at the same
time. Inland mudflats are the next best thing to oases, and draw many animals
and people who learn to extract water from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly thick mud flats are difficult terrain, and can contain &lt;strong&gt;mud sink&lt;/strong&gt;
squares representing deeper areas. Creatures standing adjacent to those can be
pushed into them, which will immobilize them (save ends), with a slow
after-effect due to the clinging mud (also save ends). Voluntarily or
accidentally stepping into one would have the same effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;psychic-reservoirs&quot;&gt;Psychic Reservoirs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fragile purple crystals that grow in psychically charged areas sheltered from
the winds, these can be tapped by psionic characters to boost their attacks. It
takes a minor action to tap into an adjacent crystal, which makes it crumble to
dust. If the character uses power points, they gain 1 bonus point that lasts
until the end of the encounter. Otherwise they gain +5 to their next damage roll
from a psionic power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rocky-badlands&quot;&gt;Rocky Badlands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These regions are too rough to support permanent settlements, so they’ll mostly
feature as ambush sites. They’re filled with &lt;strong&gt;teetering stone pillars&lt;/strong&gt; that
can be pushed onto enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;salt-flats&quot;&gt;Salt Flats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bone-dry regions are a hassle to fight in, as salt will inevitably get in
the wounds and make them sting like hell. They’re also filled with loose &lt;strong&gt;salt
piles&lt;/strong&gt; that work a lot like the Settled Ash hazard above, except that they also
slow the target if it was bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sandy-wastes&quot;&gt;Sandy Wastes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What most people think of when they hear “desert”. They can contain 3x3-square
&lt;strong&gt;Small Dunes&lt;/strong&gt; that anyone might use as a hiding or ambush spot, even if they
can’t normally burrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;silt-pools&quot;&gt;Silt Pools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They work a lot like mud flats, except there’s no water, just very fine
dust. Usually filled with difficult terrain, and with &lt;strong&gt;deep silt spots&lt;/strong&gt; that
restrain (save ends) anyone who falls or gets pushed into them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slipsand&quot;&gt;Slipsand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandy areas where some magical or psionic effect caused a significant amount of
tiny glass crystals to be mixed in with the sand. They’re slippery &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; sharp,
requiring an Athletics check from any who enters them to avoid falling prone and
taking damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tree-of-life&quot;&gt;Tree of Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These extremely rare plants are imbued with a much greater than usual amount of
vital energy, which enables them to resist and even recover from defiling
attempts given enough time. Ironically, this makes them extremely valued by
sorcerer-kings and other powerful and rich defilers, which cultivate them for
use as batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think earlier editions kept a more or less precise list of the remaining trees
of life in Athas - they were &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; rare. In this edition, I believe their
number is less restricted, but the most likely place you’re going to find one is
still in the “boss room” for these defilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees of life emit a 5-square aura. Creatures within always regain the maximum
possible HP from variable healing effects, and have a +5 to perform divination
rituals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever someone performs Arcane Defiling inside the aura, or use some other
necrotic power that damages one of their allies, the tree takes the damage
instead. Trees have 500 HP and Vulnerable 10 Necrotic, and die when they
hit 0. They regenerate 5 HP per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ztal-horde&quot;&gt;Z’Tal Horde&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A much funnier and more mundane piece of terrain! Z’tals are tiny, slimy, stinky
lizard-bug-things that gather in very large swarms. They’re relatively harmless,
but still a bother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A z’tall horde fills one or more squares, which are difficult terrain. Someone
who ends their movement in such a square takes 5/tier poison damage from the
stink. Someone who starts their turn in a horde square must roll a save before
taking any other actions. A failure means they fall prone because of the
slippery slime. A close or area attack that deals at least 1 point of damage
will automatically disperse a horde square with no roll required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re sometimes bred as living security measures, but a horde of these
annoying scavengers might naturally form around the corpse of any large
creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-up&quot;&gt;Next Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hazards! What, you thought these were the hazards?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/09/wir-dscc-athasian-terrain.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/02/09/wir-dscc-athasian-terrain.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Sunwarped Monster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is your one stop shop for generating horribly mutated varieties of standard
monsters. The name “Sunwarped” comes from the belief that these mutations are
caused by Athas’ scorching sun, but there are many different causes. These
creatures might have been exposed to concentrated psionic energy, lived for too
long in defiled areas, or been victims of terrible experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pristine Tower is also a prime source of mutated monstrosities, altering any
who linger near it for too long. To hear people talk about it, it was the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt;
such source in previous editions, but now it’s just one more among many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunwarped creatures are obviously misshapen when compared to typical
specimens. They might be exceedingly assymetrical, have extra limbs or eyes, and
so on. These descriptors give me a kind of “science fantasy” vibe, because they
match what you would expect radiation to do in 50s-style atomic horror tales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, sunwarped creatures get a +2 to Endurance, and might also get one or two
&lt;strong&gt;Sunwarped Traits&lt;/strong&gt; in addition to their extra theme powers. These traits
usually give it an extra bonus in one area and a small penalty in another. There
is a table here with some examples, but the GM is free to come up with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a creature might get digging claws that give it climb and burrow speeds equal
to its base speed, but also reduce that base speed by 1. Or uneven eyes that
give it all-around vision but inflict a -3 penalty to ranged and area
attacks. Or something that gives +1 to one defense and -1 to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these changes are situational, and their effectiveness depends entirely
on the monster they get applied to. A Brute with no ranged attacks will find
those uneven eyes to be a pure bonus, while an extra limb that aids in grappling
would be wasted on an artillery monster. While you can min-max and only give
monsters traits that increase their power, you can also do the opposite to show
how random these mutations can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The split is pretty clear in this theme - attack powers either deal damage or
apply debuffs to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breath of the Blazing Sun&lt;/strong&gt; probably has this name because almost no one in
Athas would know what radiation is. It’s a Close Blast 4 vs. Fortitude that
blinds its targets and makes them vulnerable to radiant and fire damage (save
ends both).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burning Blood&lt;/strong&gt; will make xenomorph fans happy, as it represents a
high-pressure jet of hazardous blood spraying out when the creature is
hit. This is a reaction that makes a Close Blast 3 attack vs. Reflex, and
inflicts ongoing acid + fire damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ravaging Fury&lt;/strong&gt; is a free action encounter power, meaning it can be used in
the creature’s own turn without spending actions. Once this is used, if the
creature hits with its next attack it will immediately gain an action point
that it can use before the end of its next turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sticky Hide&lt;/strong&gt; makes the monster be constantly covered in goo. Any enemy that
hits the creature with a melee attack is subject to an attack vs. their
Reflex, and if that hits the weapon used on the attack gets yanked out of
their hands and and sticks to the monster’s slimy coating. Recovery is
automatic but requires staying adjacent to the monster and spending a standard
action.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These heal of buff the creature itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enraged Growth&lt;/strong&gt; makes the monster grow one size category when first
bloodied! It pushes anyone adjacent to make room, and gains 10 temporary
HP/tier. This gets more awesome when you apply it to a monster that is already
big.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feast on Flesh&lt;/strong&gt; causes the creature’s melee basic attack to give it 5/tier
temporary HP on a hit as it consumes some of the target’s flesh. The book
itself says that while you’d expect to see this only for bite attacks, you can
add it to any attack and come up with a suitably freaky explanation for why it
works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misshapen Body&lt;/strong&gt; means the creature’s important anatomical bits are not
where you’d expect them to be, so it can roll a d20 when it takes a critical
hit, downgrading it to a normal hit on a result of 10+. These are the same
mechanics of a normal save, but since they’re written out in full I guess it
means it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;count&lt;/em&gt; as a save, so wouldn’t get general save bonuses such
as those of an elite or solo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can also make such misshapen creatures &lt;strong&gt;Steady-Footed&lt;/strong&gt;, letting them
also roll actual saves against falling prone because their weird shape ends up
being more stable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get a very strong “atomic horror” vibe from this theme, except it’s happening
in a setting where people don’t know about radiation, and so the mutations get
blamed on other causes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/28/wir-dscc-sunwarped-monster.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/28/wir-dscc-sunwarped-monster.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Psionic Adept</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As we all know by now, psychic powers are very common in Athas. Anyone might
have some, even if that’s not their main specialty. For PCs, this is implemented
as a couple of character themes (Noble Adept and Wilder).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For NPCs and monsters, we have the Psionic Adept theme presented here. You can
add this to a non-psionic monster to make it more controller-ish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psionic Adepts gain a +2 to either either Diplomacy and Intimidate (force of
personality!) or to Insight and Perception (sixth sense!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the usual design strategy of adding new abilities that work “around”
established attacks, we get a collection of powers that hinder and debuff
enemies. All of the ones that require attack rolls target Will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blind the Mind’s Eye&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a ranged attack that makes the
creature invisible to the target (save ends). This ends when the creature
attacks the target. Lurkers can use this to enable their big attacks, while
others can use it as a way to ease pressure on themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empathic Wall&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) creates a 12-square wall that lasts a turn. It
blocks line of sight. People can cross it, but its squares are difficult
terrain, and anyone inside them is lightly obscured.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mantle of the Mind&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a close burst 4 that attacks will and
prevents affected targets from targeting the creature with their attacks (save
ends).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Marionette&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) is a sustainable domination power. It
dominates for a turn on a hit, but can be sustained with standard actions to
let the creature repeat the attack against the same target, potentially
prolonging the domination. On a miss, it dazes for a turn. It’s a little
weaker than a fire-and-forget (save ends) power, because it eats up standard
actions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Three variants of &lt;strong&gt;Psionic Augmentation&lt;/strong&gt; that add a little extra something
when the creature hits with a melee basic attack. One deals extra psychic
damage, the other dazes for a turn, and the third one inflicts ongoing psychic
damage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a lot more clearly “utilities” than the ones for elemental
creatures. They’re all encounter powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mental Bastion&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt that gives a +4 to Will, potentially
turning a hit into a miss.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open the Mind’s Eye&lt;/strong&gt; gives blindsight 5 and all-around vision for a
turn. The latter means the creature cannot be flanked.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oracular Empathy&lt;/strong&gt; is a weird one. When an nearby ally of the creature is
hit by an attack, the creature can use a reaction to switch its initiative
order to be just after the attacker’s.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psionic Flight&lt;/strong&gt; automatically pushes each adjacent enemy 1 square and lets
the creature fly its speed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty cool! It seems more thematically tight to me than Elementally
Infused. Adding these powers to someone like an ogre would be a nice/nasty
surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/22/wir-dscc-theme-psionic-adept.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/22/wir-dscc-theme-psionic-adept.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let&apos;s Read the 4e Dark Sun Creature Catalog: Elementally-Infused Monster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Athas is a world particularly close to the Elemental Chaos, and so there are
lots of places in it that are soaked in elemental energies of some kind. The
creatures that inhabit these areas often end up elementally-infused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book suggests changing the creature’s origin to elemental if its mutations
end up being inheritable, though that just affects the lore and so it’s just
necessary if it will affect the game’s stories in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main mechanical thing you must decided about an elementally-infused creature
is its element. All of its powers that deal damage have it written as “[damage
type]” in the book, and you’re meant to replace that lacuna with a type
corresponding to the creature’s associated elements: one of fire, acid, cold,
thunder, or lightning (very very frightening!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of its attacks need to do the same type of damage. Multi-element
elementals are a thing now, after all. And you might decide to make one or more
of these attacks untyped, which would be common for an earth elemental whose
rock-based attacks deal physical damage for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementally-infused creatures get +2 to Intimidate and Athletics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-powers&quot;&gt;Attack Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these powers deal damage of the type you chose above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Auras&lt;/strong&gt;, one that triggers when the monster is
bloodied and damages enemies inside, and one that is always active and makes
enemies vulnerable to your chosen element.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Eruption&lt;/strong&gt; causes an explosion when the monster is first bloodied,
a close burst 2 that targets Reflex and deals elemental damage equal to the
monster’s best basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Manifestation&lt;/strong&gt; converts the damage of all of the monster’s
attacks to your chosen element.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Persistence&lt;/strong&gt; is recharge 5+ and inflicts 5/tier ongoing damage of
the chosen type when the monster hits with a melee attack. It’s said to
increase “damage output and entertainment value”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious here is &lt;strong&gt;Elemental Damage Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;, which should be high
enough for the monster to resist its own attacks (or I guess 5/tier if you don’t
want to do math). If a monster’s attacks are untyped, you could give it
variable resistance instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all of the others deal damage, proving that the “attack”/”utility” split
is more of a guideline here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Dissipation&lt;/strong&gt; lets the monster vanish from play for a turn and
reform next to an enemy, dealing a bit of damage and making them grant combat
advantage for another turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Ground&lt;/strong&gt; is a third aura variant, this time meant to keep enemies
close. The aura’s radius becomes difficult terrain and enemies take damage
when they leave it, instead of when they enter it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Step&lt;/strong&gt; deals elemental damage to anyone who hits the monster with
an opportunity attack while it moves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elemental Transport&lt;/strong&gt; lets the monster teleport between patches of hazardous
terrain that deal damage of the chosen type. Clever!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mutable Body&lt;/strong&gt; is appropriate for water-based or otherwise gooey monsters,
and lets the creature count as one size smaller when squeezing through narrow
openings.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want elemental damage? We got elemental damage! I like the design strategy
of additional attack powers that modify and work around the monster’s usual
attacks, and it works particularly well here.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/20/wir-dscc-themes-elemental.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2026/01/20/wir-dscc-themes-elemental.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>dark-sun</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
