<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 19:48:47 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 19:48:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: A Note on Fiends</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post doesn’t correspond to an entry in the book, but I figured I’d write it
to explain a few important differences in organization between the MM3 and its
predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two Monster Manuals had huge multi-monster entries for the “Three
Dees”: Demons, Devils, and Dragons. These entries included some general lore
that applied to all of them, and a huge number of individual stat blocks with
their own bits of lore. They were a real chore to cover!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dragons are still like that, because we’re going to be looking at a whole new
dragon sub-category here. But the fiends (demons and devils) are organized
differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the third main monster book in the edition. Pretty much everything that
needed to be said about general demon and devil lore has already been said in
the previous books, and likely on a few extra supplements that came out
alongside them. So the demons and devils in this book are all in their own
individual entries labeled as “Demon, X” and “Devil, Y”. That’s going to make
them much easier to cover!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one demon we already covered in the past, the Babau, and for that one
I’m just going to refer you to the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/11/07/babau.html&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt; I made a while back. I
believe every other demon and devil here is new to the Let’s Read project, so
I’ll cover one entry per post on them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/06/demons-intro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/06/demons-intro.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Demon, Klurichir</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-demon-klurichir.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Abyss is home to several powerful demon lords, each of whom has their own
ruinous designs on the rest of the universe and is building an army to enact
those designs. Yet these armies rarely seem to leave the Abyss to start their
invasions. One of the reasons for this is that the demon lords hate each other
as much as they hate everything else, and spend much of their time locked in
eternal bloody warfare. Another one is that you have huge hordes of “unclaimed
demons” who prefer to pursue their own personal goals instead of organizing into
a large force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it looks like the seed of cosmic evil at the bottom of the Abyss has had
enough of this lack of focus, so it started producing a special brand of demon
from pure elemental evil energy and sending them to the upper layers to clean
house. These are the klurichirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every klurichir is a contender for the rank of demon lord, and has a real shot
at it given enough time. They differ from the existing demon lords in that they
were never primordials, but were instead born as demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These demons are quick to take control of those unclaimed hordes, and use them
to shake things up in the Abyss. They do this by throwing them against the
forces of the incumbent demon lords as they fight each other. They surround
themselves with other epic-tier officers like balors and nafelshnees, and spend
the lives of their lesser underlings freely because there are always more where
those came from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only get a single stat block for klurichirs. They’re Huge Elemental Humanoids
with the Demon tag, and Level 28 Soldiers with 258 HP. They have Blindsight 5,
and are immune to fear. Their ground speed is 8, and they fly at speed 12 with
clumsy maneuverability, meaning they fight on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Klurichirs project a &lt;strong&gt;Malign Influence&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that prevents enemies inside
from regaining HP by any means. They fight with gigantic Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;axes&lt;/strong&gt; that
do more damage when the demon is bloodied and mark for a turn. They can make
occasional &lt;strong&gt;Savage Hew&lt;/strong&gt; attacks (recharge 5+) that hit everyone in a Close
Burst 3 for the same damage and effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a marked enemy moves, the klurichir can try to grab then with its Reach 2
&lt;strong&gt;pincers&lt;/strong&gt; a reaction. This does some initial damage on a hit, and from that
point on the demon can spend minor actions to sustain the grab and deal the same
amount of damage automatically. Only one victim can be grabbed at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the klurichir is first bloodied, it speaks a &lt;strong&gt;Blasphemous Utterance&lt;/strong&gt; that
deals necrotic damage and dazes (save ends) in a Close Blast 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huh, it turns out klurichirs are actually a bit weaker than Balors, who are
Level 27 Elite Brutes. So I have a bit of a hard time believing the text that
says they’re “on the cusp of becoming demon lords”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe that also applies to balors, and you can reskin klurichirs into “baby
balors” wielding axes instead of the classic sword and whip combo. It’s also
relatively easy to make klurichirs into elites via the usual rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, I like the “no healz” aura and the pincers, which combine to put
grabbed PCs in a very unfortunate situation. Damaging a grabbed PC is a minor
action and the demon can still attack them with that high-damage axe.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/06/demon-klurichir.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/06/demon-klurichir.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Dark One</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark Ones appeared in the first 4e Monster Manual, and you can read my take on
that book’s entry &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/09/16/dark-one.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This entry adds a few more stat blocks and tries to
fill in the lore gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-dark-one.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read the post linked above, you’ll see that the MM1 contained little in
the way of Dark One Lore. I speculated that most of them would be peaceful
civilians like halflings are, but it seems that the Monster Manual 3 is moving
in the opposite direction by saying they’re &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; thieving murderers. I guess
this is a prelude for some of the even more egregious stuff you could find on
the Monster Vault and on some early 5e supplements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book says Dark Ones are “incapable” of crafting beautiful or useful
objects. This is described more like a divine curse than some sort of
neurological limitation. Everything they make is destined to be ugly, fragile,
and useless. Their armor crumples, their weapons shatter. So instead of making
their own stuff, they steal other people’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the MM1 said, most Dark Ones live in the Shadowfell. This one says that they
tend to see the middle world as a, well, “loot pinãta”, full of stuff just
waiting to be taken. They tend to go for “loot caches” that are relatively
hidden from the larger societies of the middle world, and target groups that are
isolated from those same societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other worlds, your typical team of Dark One acquisition experts is in direct
competition with adventuring parties for the XP and treasure contained in
dungeons, bandit lairs, and cultist strongholds. The PCs could arrive at one of
these places only to discover a group of Dark Ones got there first and took all
the stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them prefer to work as mercenaries instead of thieves, and they’ll join
forces with anyone who pays them. Often their clients end up being cults of
Vecna and other appreciators of the sneaky-stabby arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, if you want to tone down the speciesism here, you can just remove
the divine curse bit. If you still want a Dark One community to be dependent on
goods from outside, you can say they rely on &lt;em&gt;trade&lt;/em&gt; more than on theft and
mercenary work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the basic Dark One information remains identical to what it was on the
MM1. They’re Small Shadow Humanoids with Darkvision, a Speed of 6, and two
signature abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is &lt;strong&gt;Dark Step&lt;/strong&gt;, an at-will move action that lets them move 4 squares
with a +4 AC bonus against opportunity attacks, and gain combat advantage
against any enemies it ends up adjacent to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is &lt;strong&gt;Killing Dark&lt;/strong&gt;, which causes them to explode in a cloud of inky
darkness when reduced to 0 HP, blinding any enemies adjacent to them for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hex-knight&quot;&gt;Hex Knight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hex Knights are the closest thing Dark Ones have to noble warriors, though their
codes of conduct apply only to members of their own society. Their gear is very
similar to that of a common sneaky-stabby Dark One: leather or hide armor, short
sword, hand crossbow. Their fighting style, however is much more direct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hex Knights are Level 4 Soldiers with 54 HP. They mark enemies using the
&lt;strong&gt;Shadow Hex&lt;/strong&gt; minor action, which lasts until the fight ends or the knight uses
it on someone else. Enemies who ignore the mark grant combat advantage to all
enemies for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;hand crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic ranged attack and it’s merely okay. Knights are
better in melee, where their basic &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; can attack twice with one
action, and each hit slows the target. Knights can also use their swords in a
&lt;strong&gt;Vicious Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which targets 1 or 2 enemies with a sword
attack that also does ongoing damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shadow-bolters&quot;&gt;Shadow Bolters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These spellcasters are usually on some secret mission to acquire a treasure or a
valuable bit of information, and will prioritize that mission over whatever else
might be going on. They might pose as mercenaries or allies to some other
faction as a cover. Once they have what they seek, they’ll abscond, leaving
enemies and allies alike behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bolters are Level 5 Artillery with 50 HP. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; in melee
and with &lt;strong&gt;black bolt&lt;/strong&gt; spells at range, and they’re all about gaining combat
advantage. The &lt;strong&gt;Deadly Precision&lt;/strong&gt; trait gives them combat advantage against
any enemy flanked by two allies, even if the bolter themselves are far
away. When they hit someone with combat advantage, they deal 5 extra necrotic
damage to the target and to any of the target’s allies adjacent to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The black bolts also make a hit target take 5 necrotic damage whenever they
provoke an opportunity attack (save ends), which is very situational but might
be useful to punish mobile PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shadow-speakers&quot;&gt;Shadow Speakers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadow Speakers are the Dark Ones that know the necessary rituals for crossing
between the middle world and the Shadowfell. They lead “acquisition” expeditions
into the middle world, and are responsible for bringing them back home. They
carry little clay jugs filled with soil from the Shadowfell as a focus for their
powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shadow speakers are Level 6 Controllers with 70 HP. They fight with &lt;strong&gt;short
swords&lt;/strong&gt; and shadow magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Curse&lt;/strong&gt; that deals necrotic damage,
makes the target grant combat advantage, and inflicts 5 necrotic damage when the
target provokes an opportunity attack (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often, they can cast a &lt;strong&gt;Choking Shadow&lt;/strong&gt; spell (recharge 5+), which deals
heavy necrotic damage and immobilizes for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even one of these is an excellent force multiplier for a Dark One party, or
really for any encounter group whose members deal extra damage with combat
advantage. Just have then stay at the range limit for Shadow Curse and spam it
on the PCs to make them all grant combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Shadow Speakers tend to be “load-bearing monsters” for Dark
One encounter groups, since they’re the group’s only way home. If the Shadow
Speaker is in too much danger, the entire group might try to make a run for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the greater encounter variety, but I dislike the extra emphasis on a
species-wide negative stereotype (“they’re all thieves, every last one of
them”). I’ll stick to my initial assumptions that these stat blocks represent
the Dark One equivalent of adventurers and other combatants rather than typical
members of the culture.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/01/dark-one.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/06/01/dark-one.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Craud</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-craud.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think crauds are a new monster. At the very least they’re one I haven’t met
before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crauds are giant crawdads! These crustaceans are about the same height as a
halfling, but bulkier. They tend to show up in large numbers in maritime and
coastal areas that have suffered extensive environmental damage such as from
pollution or overfishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these circumstances they’re very aggressive and voracious man-eaters, raiding
ships and villages with terrifying frequency. If a craud “army” shows up at your
village or town, they’ll keep showing up every few days until either all of them
or all of you are dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This causes some scholars to speculate that crauds are the vengeance of Melora
made manifest and sent against those who despoil her coasts. Others defend the
more mundane explanation that crauds attack sapients because their usual food
sources have been driven to extiction by the environmental damage. In a world
where the goddess of nature is real, though, is there any difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess non-distressed crauds normally stay mostly underwater and feed on fish
and such. They’re non-sapient but have good teamwork instincts and a somewhat
“hive-like” social organization where certain individuals known as Kings can
direct other crauds via patterns of flashing colors and lights in their
carapaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes an unscrupulous sea-borne villain like a pirate captain will manage to
catch a craud king, torturing it in specific ways to direct its “subjects” to
attack interesting targets. Coastal druids and clerics of Melora know gentler
ways to secure the cooperation of these crustaceans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crauds are Medium Natural Beasts with the Aquatic keyword. They have darkvision,
and move at speed 6 on land or in water. The effects of the Aquatic keyword
haven’t changed, but in this book they’re written down on all the stat blocks as
a trait: aquatic creatures can breathe underwater, and when fighting underwater
gain a +2 attack bonus against non-aquatic opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;craud-impaler&quot;&gt;Craud Impaler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impalers are lithe and quick on their feet, usually arriving at the head of a
craud “army”. Their job is to tie up the opposition until their stronger cousins
can arrive. They’re cautious, and become more so after being bloodied,
preferring to focus on already weakened opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impalers are Level 3 Skirmishers with 51 HP. They fight using &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; and some
sort of pointy appendage that allows them to make an &lt;strong&gt;Impale&lt;/strong&gt; attack. It has
Reach 2, deals light physical damage, and inflicts ongoing 5 damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impale is an encounter power, and the claws are a bit underpowered too. But the
&lt;strong&gt;Scissor Claws&lt;/strong&gt; at-will ability allows the impaler to make two claw attacks,
and if both hit the creature immediately recharges Impale and uses it as a free
action. That’s a lot of damage if everything hits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when the impaler misses with an attack, &lt;strong&gt;Scuttle&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to shift 2
squares as a free action. So if that any component of that claw/claw/impale
combo fails to hit, the beast can try to get away safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;craud-crusher&quot;&gt;Craud Crusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the “stronger cousins” the impalers are waiting for. Their claws are
so huge they can crush a human torso, or bludgeon that human with enough force
to send them flying. When they arrive, they engage the impalers’ opponents and
free the impalers up to scuttle around and be skirmishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crushers are Level 4 Brutes with 70 HP. Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; do surprisingly little
basic damage, but a hit with them also grabs the target. Crushers can grab one
victim at a time, and can inflict automatic damage to them with a minor
action. Once per encounter they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Hammerclaw&lt;/strong&gt; to backhand a fool,
dealing heavy damage, pushing 1 square, and knocking them prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the crusher reduces anyone to 0 HP by any means, &lt;strong&gt;Red Tide&lt;/strong&gt; gives them a +5
bonus to their next damage roll. This is an incentive for them to target enemies
previously softened by impalers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;craud-king&quot;&gt;Craud King&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craud Kings are imposing specimens whose shells are covered in bio-luminescent
organs. Signals from these organs direct other crauds and boost their morale in
a fight. There might be some magic involved here, as some of their light
patterns have an effect on humanoids too. The creature is also a pretty good
fighter itself, so its ideal location is at the forefront of the melee
surrounded by loyal subjects. The best way to influence a craud force is to
influence its king, as discussed in the Lore section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kings are Level 5 Soldiers with the Leader tag and 67 HP. Their lights project
an aura (3) named &lt;strong&gt;Blood in the Water&lt;/strong&gt;, giving allies a +2 bonus to attack
bloodied targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;claws&lt;/strong&gt; do good damage and slide the target 1 square. &lt;strong&gt;Claw Flurry&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) allows them to attack twice, and if a slid enemy ends up adjacent
to one of the king’s allies, the ally gets to make a free attack too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By changing the pattern of its lights, the King can use the &lt;strong&gt;Angler’s Lure&lt;/strong&gt;
ability as a minor action. This is a charm attack that does no damage, pulls
the victim 3 squares, and marks it for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, when the king is bloodied it prompts all of its allies to act &lt;strong&gt;For The
King&lt;/strong&gt;. All allies within 5 squares of the wounded sovereign immediately shifts
4 squares closer to the king and make free attacks against any enemy they end up
next to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this had been a 3e-style entry, I’d probably have glossed over it
entirely. Giant crawdads, yawn. The varied stat blocks to make them more
interesting, as does the “nature’s vengeance” aspect of their lore. That’s a
handy adventure hook built right into the monster entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you could complete the lineup seen here with custom-made artillery
crauds that fire high-pressure water jets. Or maybe you could use the
“controlled by pirates” angle to pair them up with pirate musketeers.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/30/craud.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/30/craud.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Cloaker</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-cloaker.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloakers are an old D&amp;amp;D standby, originating back in the days of AD&amp;amp;D 1st
Edition where they belonged to a category of monsters that looked like
furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lore introduction for cloakers in this book actually references their
“gygaxian gotcha” origins! It tells the story of a thief who had the bad habit
of looting the room while his buddies were still fighting the monsters, and who
died when the “fine leather cloak” he found in Tsojcanth turned out to be a
cloaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from that easter egg, though, the “disguised cloak” thing is
gone. Cloakers are still sneaky, but they prever to fly silently and swoop on
from above. They’re sapient but profoundly anti-social, and their preferred
“team-up” method is to follow group of other monsters unnoticed, from a safe
distance. When those other monsters find tasty prey, the cloaker swoops in to
grab some of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloakers tend to avoid each other except in rare “conclaves”, where a whole
bunch of them huddle up in a big sphere and exchange news and gossip. Outside of
that you’ll only find cloakers cooperating if their lives are in imminent risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether hunting or defending themselves, cloakers fight by slapping with their
barbed tails and by enveloping victims with their flexible wings that can choke
and crush someone to death. They also emit a strange moaning sound that causes
unnatural fear in those who hear it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloakers are Large Aberrant Magical Beasts with Darkvision. Their ground speed
is a pitiful 2 (clumsy), but their flight speed is 8. Despite being aberrant
there’s nothing in their lore linking them to the Far Realm. If you wanted, you
could make them Natural or give them another any other origin without changing
anything about their stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cloaker-ambusher&quot;&gt;Cloaker Ambusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are your common specimens. They’re Level 12 Lurkers with 95 HP. Those
&lt;strong&gt;Unnerving Moans&lt;/strong&gt; count as an aura (2) with the Fear keyword, inflicting a -2
attack penalty on non-deafened enemies caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The afore-mentioned &lt;strong&gt;Tail Slap&lt;/strong&gt; is a basic attack doing standard physical
damage, but the &lt;strong&gt;Envelop&lt;/strong&gt; ability gets lots of text. It’s an attack that
targets Reflex and does no immediate damage. On a hit the target is grabbed,
pulled to the cloaker’s space, and becomes blinded, dazed, restrained and takes
10 ongoing damage. While enveloping a victim, any attacks that hit the cloaker
do half damage to the monster and half to the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is a grab, escaping requires an Athletic test against the cloaker’s
Fortitude (24) or Acrobatics against its Reflex (23). I guess explicit escape
DCs are a Monster Vault innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, the cloaker ambusher can use &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Shift&lt;/strong&gt; to gain
concealment for a turn. If it was already concealed by the environment, it gains
total concealment instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cloaker-lord&quot;&gt;Cloaker Lord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cloaker that managed to live to a more advanced age than most of its
peers, and has mastered the natural magic that powers its moan. It’s a Level 18
Controller with 172 HP and all the same abilities as a basic cloaker plus a few
more moaning-related ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is &lt;strong&gt;Terrifying Moan&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+), a Close Burst 2 targetting
Will. It does psychic damage and forces the target to move its speed away from
the monster. This isn’t a push, it’s a move, so the victim could trigger
opportunity attacks from other monsters during it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second one is &lt;strong&gt;Hypnotic Moan&lt;/strong&gt;. It affects the same area but instead of
doing damage it stuns for a turn on a hit and dazes for a turn on a
miss. Thankfully it’s an encounter power, so this will only happen once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the cloaker’s Unnerving Moan aura and the area covered by its attacks
increase from 2 to 5 when the creature is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Envelop ability is kinda frightening, but I guess my impression of cloakers
remains the same it’s always been: meh.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/30/cloaker.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/30/cloaker.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Chitine</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-chitine.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitines feel like a late-3e addition to the game, and likely had slightly
different lore back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitines are an artificially engineered people. The first of their kind were
produced in drow laboratories in an attempt to create the perfect slaves. The
techniques and materials used were a mixture of arcane magic, prayers to Lolth
and both souls and genetic material from elves, spiders, and demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did not work out. Soon after the first batch of chitines was created, &lt;em&gt;Lolth
herself&lt;/em&gt; intervened to grant them freedom and allow them to strike back at their
would-be enslavers. This makes a lot more sense once you remember Lolth doesn’t
really like or trust her worshippers, as we discussed in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2021/06/24/demons-04.html&quot;&gt;Yochlol&lt;/a&gt; entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lolth’s intervention caused a special priestly caste of chitines, known as
Choldriths, to emerge from the vats and lead their people to freedom. In our
narrative present, chitines inhabit the upper Underdark and believe themselves
to be the true chosen of Lolth. The relationship between their two peoples can
be summed up as “kill on sight”, though chitines are more willing to negotiate
with non-drow peoples and trade their service as mercenaries in exchange for
money, weapons and magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most chitines are devout Lolth worshippers to the same extent drow are, though
each people considers the other’s faith heretical. Chitines believe they, and
not the drow, are Lolth’s favorites, and that her true form is that of a spider
rather than that of a drow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creation of the chitines is a relatively recent event, so they lack much
experience with surface. They know it exists, but haven’t really explored it and
tend to see it as a source of baffling mysteries. The book mentions a story
about a shifter illusionist that managed to convince a chitine settlement that
she was an aspect of Lolth, and used them to attack a nearby drow settlement and
assassinate a rival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an interesting side box here about how chitines build their lairs. The
basic structure here is a &lt;strong&gt;suspended fortress&lt;/strong&gt;, a tear-shaped web sack hanging
from the ceiling that’s large enough to contain two or three floors of
chambers. Larger settlements have several of these linked by walkways. You can
use this style to build chitine-themed dungeons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitines are Medium Natural Humanoids with the Spider keyword. They have
Darkvision, and a Spider Climb speed equal to their ground speed (usually
6). Most of them prefer daggers for combat, with specialists using other
weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their signature power is a &lt;strong&gt;Web Line&lt;/strong&gt; (move action, encounter), which can be
used when they’re climbing and allows them to fly 5 squares. Everything else
comes from training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chitine-grunt&quot;&gt;Chitine Grunt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitines don’t really have the concept of a “non-combatant”. When their lairs
are attacked, every individual inside grabs a knife or four and rushes to its
defense. The vast majority of them are going to use this stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grunts are Level 5 Minion Brutes. They wield four &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; which can be used
for melee or ranged basic attacks. When killed they emit a &lt;strong&gt;Dying Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; that
inflicts a -2 penalty to the defenses of all adjacent enemies for a turn. This
is an untyped penalty, so I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; it might stack. I’m not sure, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chitine-warrior&quot;&gt;Chitine Warrior&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These chitines have a combination of extra training and experience that makes
them a much greater threat in combat. They’re Level 5 Brutes with 72 HP. They
carry eight daggers, four in hand and four ready to replace any thrown
blades. Like their minion counterparts, they can use &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; for melee and
ranged basic attacks, and they can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Four Blade Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that
consists of four slightly weaker dagger attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re pretty much a non-minion version of the Grunt, and they never step on
the actual floor of the map unless they can’t help it, attacking instead from
the ceiling and walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chitine-scounts&quot;&gt;Chitine Scounts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scouts patrol and defend the approaches to a chitine cave, using rapid-firing
hand crossbows to attack from unexpected angles. They’re Level 5 Artillery with
48 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their melee basic attack is still a &lt;strong&gt;dagger&lt;/strong&gt;, but those &lt;strong&gt;hand crossbows&lt;/strong&gt;
have a lot more range than a thrown knife. Using the &lt;strong&gt;Furious Volley&lt;/strong&gt; ability,
they can make up to two dagger and two crossbow attacks with a single
action. Once per encounter they can fire a &lt;strong&gt;Poisoned Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; that targets
Fortitude, does the same damage as a regular attack and inflicts 10 ongoing
poison damage. That’s a lot for level 5!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chitine-marauders&quot;&gt;Chitine Marauders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chitine custom says that any offspring beyond the first eight in a clutch must
be cast out to fend for themselves in the Underdark. If these outcasts manage to
survive a year out there, they’re welcomed back. Most who survive don’t bother
trying to return, and instead form their own outcast communities. They set up
ambush spots by building camouflaged web doors over niches in narrow tunnels,
from which they emerge to surround victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marauders are Level 6 Skirmishers with 72 HP. They’re armed with paired &lt;strong&gt;short
swords&lt;/strong&gt;, and the &lt;strong&gt;Quick Jabs&lt;/strong&gt; ability allows them to make two attacks per
action with them, shifting 2 squares after each one. They deal extra damage if
they have combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same stat block can of course be used for non-marauder chitine skirmishers
if you need some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chitine-web-crafter&quot;&gt;Chitine Web Crafter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web crafters are those chitines specialized in producing webs and building stuff
with them. They’re responsible for architecting and building those suspended
fortresses, as well as the traps and mechanisms that go into them. The web
crafter’s guild is usually the second most influential organization in a chitine
society - if you anger them, your home might come crashing down with you
inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choldrith priests are the only group above them, and one way they keep the
web crafters in check is to demand they participate in combat. Chitine patrols
or raiding parties probably include a web crafter or two, who might act as the
officer in charge. If the crafters had time to prepare before the fight, the
battle map certain to include web-based hazards and traps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web crafters are Level 6 Controllers with 72 HP. They fight in melee with
lightly-poisoned &lt;strong&gt;speads&lt;/strong&gt; that do physical damage and slow for a turn. They
can throw &lt;strong&gt;poisoned web orbs&lt;/strong&gt; that do poison damage and also slow for a turn,
or &lt;strong&gt;web balls&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) that do physical damage and restrain (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can also create a &lt;strong&gt;Web Wall&lt;/strong&gt; once per encounter. The wall is 6 squares
long and counts as destructible blocking terrain. Each square as the same
defenses as the crafter and 10 HP. They’re vulnerable to fire, but attacking
them in melee causes immobilization (save ends) as the webs stick to the PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clever crafters might use walls to separate defenders from squishies, and then
bombard the squishies with poison and the defenders with web balls while their
melee buddies move freely between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choldrith&quot;&gt;Choldrith&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choldriths are the special priestly caste created by Lolth’s intervention in the
original chitine production process. They’re visibly different from common
chitines, resembling pale driders. They’re invariably at the top of chitine
social hierarchies, and their flocks are so devoted to them that there are
stories of chitines who collapsed their whole colonies while resisting a
troglodyte raid, killing themselves so their choldrith leaders might survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choldriths are Large Natural Humanoids with the Spider keyword, and Level 8
Controllers (Leaders) with 90 HP. In combat they use a mix of natural weapons
and Lolth-themed magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that does poison damage and immobilizes
for a turn. Their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Web&lt;/strong&gt; that does physical damage and
restrains for a turn. They can also use a &lt;strong&gt;Shadow Spider Curse&lt;/strong&gt; that deals
poison damage and makes the target grant combat advantage to spiders (save
ends). “Spiders” here means anything with the Spider keyword: actual spiders,
chitines, driders, ettercaps…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter choldriths can summon a cloud of &lt;strong&gt;Choking Vapors&lt;/strong&gt;, which
deal immediate and ongoing poison damage over an area. They remain as a zone
that deals 5 poison damage to anyone who enters or ends their turn there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choldriths “leaderly” skills are both triggered actions. &lt;strong&gt;Spider Queen’s
Enforcer&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt that triggers when an ally within 5 squares misses an
attack. It deals 5 damage to the ally and makes them reroll the attack. &lt;strong&gt;For
the Spider Queen&lt;/strong&gt; is an interrupt that triggers when the choldrith is hit with
a melee or ranged attack, and redirects the damage to an adjacent ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I actually remember seeing that chitine illustration in a book for a
previous edition, and pretty much glancing right past the entry. The 4e strategy
of including several variant stat blocks for each monster certainly paid off
here. With this entry plus a few spiders from the other books you have enough
monsters for a whole themed dungeon, covering all roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I can understand why they waited until the MM3 to do a chitine
writeup. They have a lot of thematic overlap with drow, and there would be
little reason to include both in a campaign that wasn’t entirely about Lolth. In
such a campaign they would make good heroic tier opponents for GMs who dislike
manually adjusting monster levels, since drow are by default paragon tier.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/26/chitine.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/26/chitine.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Cave Fisher</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-cave-fisher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe Cave Fishers originated in AD&amp;amp;D, one of the many examples of “cave
ceiling fauna” in that edition. Your group might be on the lookout for
darkmantles, spiders and piercers, but they’ll never see the cave fisher
coming. This is their 4e debut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cave fishers are nonsapient predatory arthropods about the size of an adult
human. They’re entirely natural and mundane, by the standards of D&amp;amp;D. They hunt
by hiding in cave ceilings, and pulling prey from the ground using either sticky
strands or spear-like appendages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, cave fishers hang out underground. They prefer caves with
high ceilings and plenty of ledges, where they make their nests. They organize
themselves in loose collectives, and newly-mated pairs fly out to look for an
empty ledge to nest in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two varieties of cave fisher presented here aren’t different species,
they’re different sexes: anglers are female, and spikers are male. Anglers lay
eggs and watch the nest, hunting only when prey wanders nearby. Spikers range
farther out to look for food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cave fishers can’t usually be tamed, but people tend to use meat-based bait to
lure them to caves they want protected and to distract them when passing through
those caves. Hobgoblins sometimes capture fisher eggs and train them from
hatching to serve as living artillery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adult cave fishers are Medium Natural Beasts. Spawn old enough to be a threat
are Small. They have darkvision, a ground speed of 6 and a climb speed of 5 with
Spider Climb (5 and 4 for the spawn).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cave-fisher-spawn&quot;&gt;Cave Fisher Spawn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fisher spawn lead a stressful existence from very early on. A weak individual is
likely to be devoured by its siblings if they get hungry enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Small spawn are Level 2 Minion Brutes. They attack with their &lt;strong&gt;pincers&lt;/strong&gt;
and do extra damage against immobilized, restrained, or helpless targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cave-fisher-angler&quot;&gt;Cave Fisher Angler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This adult female tends to stick close to the nest, and rely on its ledge for
concealment. To hunt, she lowers a sticky filament to just above head height of
the passing prey, and snaps it around the prey’s neck when they pass
underneath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anglers are Level 3 Lurkers with 37 HP. They have the &lt;strong&gt;Sniper&lt;/strong&gt; trait, which
ensures they stay hidden if they make a ranged attack from concealment and miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is useful because their &lt;strong&gt;Filament Strangle&lt;/strong&gt; counts as a ranged attack! It
has range 5, targets Reflex, and though its initial damage is weak it pulls the
target 3 squares and restrains them (save ends). The pull can be vertical, and
the target can end that movement suspended in midair. This effect can be
sustained with standard actions in subsequent rounds, dealing automatic damage
to the target and pulling them again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from passing the save, there are few options from escaping the
filament. The victim can teleport or be teleported, which frees them
automatically; or one of their allies can target the filament with an
attack. The filament has the same defenses as the angler, and hitting it frees
the victim but deals no damage to the beast itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an angler does get into melee range of a PC, it can also use its basic
&lt;strong&gt;pincer&lt;/strong&gt; attack, which does average damage and has no special effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s likely that the PCs will only realize an angler is hunting them when the
first victim gets grabbed by a filament. And once that happens it can stay in
full cover atop that ceiling ledge until it has to peek out to try and grab
someone else!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cave-fisher-spiker&quot;&gt;Cave Fisher Spiker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spikers are the males of the species. Instead of producing a single strand of
filament, they can spit small tangles of it at greater ranges. These either
harden into spikes, or envelop a victim and begin contracting. The creature uses
these techniques to kill its prey and drag the carcass back to its nest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spikers are Level 3 Artillery with 37 HP. They have the same Sniper trait as the
angler, and a &lt;strong&gt;Camouflage&lt;/strong&gt; trait that gives them +2 to defenses against ranged
and area attacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attacks are a &lt;strong&gt;pincer&lt;/strong&gt; in melee, and a &lt;strong&gt;filament spike&lt;/strong&gt; at
range. Those contracting filaments are represented by the &lt;strong&gt;Filament Wrap&lt;/strong&gt;
attack (recharge 5+), which does no immediate damage but immobilizes the target
and inflicts 5 ongoing damage (save ends both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spikers tend to focus their fire on a single victim, since their instinct is to
kill it quickly and make off with the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cave-fisher-line-spiker&quot;&gt;Cave Fisher Line Spiker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hobgoblins that manage to capture a batch of cave fisher eggs like to use a
combination of magic and their ancient beast-taming techniques to turn them into
weapons of war. This results in a specimen that’s less robust than a wild
spiker, but which can follow commands and fire in formation to support the
troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Spikers are Level 4 Minion Artillery. They have the usual &lt;strong&gt;pincer&lt;/strong&gt; melee
attack, and their basic ranged attack is a &lt;strong&gt;slowing spike&lt;/strong&gt; that does a bit of
damage and slows for a turn. Once per encounter they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Toppling
Spike&lt;/strong&gt; that deals a bit more damage and knocks prone. Since they’re minions,
this should be their first attack. Line spikers want to stay far away from the
front lines and will likely run away rather than engage the PCs in melee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cave fishers have enough unique mechanics to distinguish themselves from
other “ceiling fauna”. Their low level makes it likely they’ll be the first such
fauna the PCs meet. They can also inhabit the Underdark, but you might want to
boost their levels if you want to place them there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since they’re regulars, your PCs shouldn’t run into lone fishers, at least not
as a full combat encounter. You can make an “all-wildlife” encounter with 2-3
mated pairs at once, or with 1 mated pair and other opportunistic underground
predators. Line spikers, of course, will always be accompanied by squads of
goblinoids including at least one beast tamer.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/24/cave-fisher.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/24/cave-fisher.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Post Cyberpunk!</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/800517c403ee40194b3e22356dfe823a.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=https://www.deviantart.com/hidrico/art/Style-Over-Substance-Cyberpunk-2077-802599843&gt;
      By Hidrico on DeviantArt
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned back in my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2022/05/19/cp-red-review.html&quot;&gt;Cyberpunk RED review&lt;/a&gt;, I felt the game didn’t
quite clear my “Threshold of GURPS”. This particular term is new but the idea
itself is almost exactly 5 years old now. I first mentioned it in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/21/to-gurps-or-not-to-gurps.html&quot;&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;, where I discussed what makes me want to reach for GURPS in an
adaptation and what makes me look for other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CP RED’s native system is fine! The reason I say it didn’t “clear the threshold”
is that it’s exactly the sort of system and setting described in the “When to
GURPS” section of that 2017 post. It worries about modeling specific concrete
actions, and it worries about the details of how they’re executed. In addition
to this, the system itself doesn’t have any mechanical novelties that aren’t
reproducible in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, while I’d happily play the native system in a one-shot or something
like that, given enough time to prepare I’d prefer to adapt its setting to
GURPS. Talking about how I’d do it is an excellent excuse for an Octopus
Carnival post. It helps that “Cyberpunk” has been one of the genres GURPS set
out to support since its beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-1-high-concept&quot;&gt;Part 1: High Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberpunk-the-setting is actually a fairly broad place that supports a large
variety of campaigns… but most people seem to be fans of that fairly narrow
slice of stylish street mercs pulling heists for money and/or personal
reasons. I’m not gonna lie, I’m like most people in that regard and so I’m going
to focus on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the setting has three distinct “eras” now, they all look and feel mostly
the same. The main changes are to the map of Night City and the specific reason
why Johnny Silverhand is raiding Arasaka Tower this time. I think we might be
able to condense that long timeline down a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to mix in my personal preferences: I believe cyberpunk doesn’t
&lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be a dystopia. This is something you might have gathered from my
previous posts on the subject. I find a lot of cyberpunk settings tend to
confuse “things are bad” with “things can never get better”, and I don’t want to
do that here. For Cyberpunk Red specifically, this ends up resulting into a game
that tells players simple survival is the most they can expect in the same book
where it touts the epic exploits of Bartmoss and Silverhand. I want to treat
them as “iconic” characters in the modern sense, which means that if those
clowns can do all this, so can the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we are: a game about stylish street mercs in the neon-lit future, living
in the fictional Night City. They get into noir-ish situations for money, and
see them through for personal reasons. Hostile factions are mostly corporations,
crime syndicates, or violent themed gangs with corporate ties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though PCs often fight for personal stakes they can still end up having a big
impact in the setting&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. PCs who are smart about it and make use of collective
action can make big, lasting, positive change, but even more traditional “band
of badasses” actions will still do something. Not every campaign has to be about
this, but the play style should be possible and supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-2-time-and-place&quot;&gt;Part 2: Time and Place&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, it’s Night City in the neon-lit cyber future. Feel free to
use the present date that suits you best. Set it in one of the official dates of
the original game. Set it in 2100 just to spite Transhuman Space. Make it 20XX,
21XX, 22XX, whatever. Or be like William Gibson and never even mention calendar
years. The backstory follows the same general lines of the original, using
relative dates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifty-something years ago the US government descended further into fascist
stupidity than ever before&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Over the next few decades its economy and
environment crashed big time, the entire West Coast seceded, and the government
was either powerless to stop the rise of the megacorps or was actively helping
them along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-something years ago Johhny Silverhand performed his one and only raid on
Arasaka Tower, which is more or less a combination of the events from the 2013
and 2023 raids in the original chronology. Arasaka’s nuke blows up, and the
political and literal fallout from this causes heavy backlash against megacorps
in general all over the world. Though many are still around, they can no longer
do whatever the fuck they want without fear of consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our narrative present is a blend of CP RED and 2077. Night city rebuilt enough
to leave “survival mode”, but it’s still something of a crime capital where the
corps have lots of influence and habitually pay those themed gangs to do their
dirty work. It also has a relatively large “edgerunner” culture with its own
honor codes and a surprisingly large propensity to take jobs from people who are
neither corp- nor gang- affiliated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of past wars to be a veteran of. The most recent one was
the Corp War that finally died down let’s say 5 years ago. It featured lots of
big corps going at each other, and lots of governments cracking down on them for
it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberware is common enough that most people sport at least a bit of
“fashionware” from their late teens onwards. Most people won’t cut off healthy
limbs in order to replace them, but there are plenty of maimed veterans and
victims of disease for whom cybernetic replacements are an appealing
prospect. Implanted augmentations are somewhat more common, with the most
popular by far being a GitS-style “cyberbrain” implanted computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guns and armored clothing are common and relatively easy to get in Night
City. This is not generally a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; thing, and contributes to the city’s still
dismal violence statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertisements are nowhere near as aggressive and explicit as they are in
CP 2077. The real world is bad enough on that front that you don’t need to
further “enhance” it to make a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rache Bartmoss did not “destroy” the NET, because we don’t need to justify rules
changes with an in-setting event. Feral AI gods running on mutated data centers
is too good an image to pass up, though, so those are still there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-3-characters-and-their-stuff&quot;&gt;Part 3: Characters and Their Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of our rules is going to be GURPS Action, because this is a game about
action heroes. The default is that players get to build their PCs using the
250-point archetypes from GURPS Action 1. This makes them experienced
edgerunners. Greenhorns would use the lower-point templates from Specialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our default ruleset is the one from GURPS Action 2, with the main changes to
that being due to the science fiction elements we’re introducing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gear-and-cyberware&quot;&gt;Gear and Cyberware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base tech level is 9, though TL8 gear is still widely available. We’re
either not that far into the future or it’s simply easier to print at home than
the more advanced stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers and biotech are at TL10. You can run a mind emulation from a
portable system, and miraculous speed-healing drugs are available. Implants are
drawn from Ultra-Tech and Bio-Tech and are mostly TL9, though some TL10 things
that appear in the CP books would also be available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyberware &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; inherently erode your humanity. Not even if you replace
your healthy bits with chrome that’s better than human standard. We use the
usual GURPS mechanics of making implants cost character points at character
creation and both points and money afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any template can spend its discretionary points on cyberware from Ultra-Tech or
implants from Bio-Tech. This means most PCs might have one or two implants to
start with, though having none is also a valid choice. Campaigns where the PCs
are meant to start out chromed to the gills might give them 25 or 50 extra
points to spend on starting cyberware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;netrunning&quot;&gt;Netrunning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hacking, I want a streamlined system. The one from Pyramid #3/21 is a good
start, since one of its goals is to prevent the isolation from the classic
“dungeon crawl” system of CP 2020. However, I want to rely even less on virtual
reality and be more like Ghost in the Shell or CP 2077.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prospective hacker needs a Neural Interface Implant of some sort (UT,
p. 216). A &lt;em&gt;cyberdeck&lt;/em&gt; is either a Computer Implant (Complexity 5, UT p. 215) or
a small computer (Complexity 6, UT p. 22) with a cable jack and a tiny radio
communicator, but without any built-in terminal. The “default” interface tier is
“Augmented Reality”, where the hacker sees the necessary interfaces alongside
the physical world. It’s possible to go “Full Immersion”, which is faster but
leaves the character effectively unconscious in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters running AR have a -2 penalty in opposed tests against characters
running Full Immersion. This is the only game effect, so it’s only worth giving
up your physical senses when you run into an immersed enemy hacker or an enemy
AI (which always counts as immersed). Programs and skills are the same as in the
Pyramid article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest change from the Pyramid article is in level design. Generally
speaking, “interesting” hackable servers and networks are not directly connected
to the public Internet, and the hacker PC must be on-site to access them. The
smallest and most common target is a single device with a basic firewall,
usually something like a security camera or an automatic door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sites with better security link their devices into a slightly larger
network. This is a bit more similar to the design examples of the Pyramid
article, but remember not to make them too large. Such a network might encompass
all security devices in a given floor. No connecting through a megacorp’s
top-secret research server through the vending machines in the lobby!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;People&lt;/em&gt; might also be a valid target for hacking, if they have those
nearly-ubiquitous computer implants. The implant can have any defenses that
could be installed in a computer of the same Complexity and usually contains at
least a basic firewall. Overcoming those defenses might allow netrunners to
“jam” the target’s senses with spurious sensory data or even run the Damage
program. Savvier opposition might link their internal computers into a more
secure network overseen by a friendly hacker, or just turn the their wi-fi off
entirely if it doesn’t confer any combat benefit to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it. That’s enough to play your classic edgerunners in the
Cyberpunk 2020/RED/2077 setting. Any of the Screamsheets from 2020 or RED should
be readily adaptable, since they have little in the way of stats to begin
with. The gigs and side jobs from 2077 also provide plentiful inspiration and
material for tabletop adventures, and that game’s main plot gives you an idea of
what the sort of “high impact” adventure that leaves a crater looks like. You
might need a bit more thought to devise adventures about organizing collective
action, but they’re also quite possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Possibly leaving a big crater. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you’re using a 2077 date, that’s Trump’s thankfully fictional second
mandate starting in 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/23/one-post-cyberpunk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/23/one-post-cyberpunk.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>cyberpunk-red</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Catoblepas</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-catoblepas.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first saw the Catoblepas in the AD&amp;amp;D 2nd Edition Monster Manual, and I was
very surprised to learn it’s not a “lolrandom” original monster. It’s a
legendary creature from Ethiopia, described by Roman historians Pliny the Elder
and Claudius Aelianus. I can’t tell whether that makes it part of Ethiopian or
Roman folklore - I’m sure someone more qualified than me can make that
distinction. Their name is derived from a Greek word meaning “to look
downwards”. The plural of catoblepas is &lt;em&gt;catoblepones&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia speculates that the original descriptions of the catoblepas might be
referring to a wildebeest or gnu, and you need only look at Wayne England’s
illustration above to know he’s really done his homework. A D&amp;amp;D catoblepas looks
like a wildebeest with a horrible nightmare where its neck and head should
be. Their long necks are always bent down due to the great weight of their
heads, which is where their name comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D catoblepones are creatures of shadow and death. They are native to the
Shadowfell but have a natural ability to wander between worlds. People believe
they appear in places that are about to be stuck by tragedy, which is kinda true
since the beast’s breath and gaze are deadly. They’re associated with the Raven
Queen and sometimes show up as part of her entourage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite their reputation as beasts of ill omen, catoblepones are often the
targets of hunting expeditions. Knights hunt them because defeating such a
dangerous beast brings great glory; others perform ritual hunts in honor of the
Raven Queen. Success in these ritual hunts might please the goddess enough that
she grants a blessing to the hunters. A catoblepas can be tracked by the trail
of destruction it leaves, and the Raven Queen is particularly pleased by hunters
who make an effort to mend this damage as they pursue their quarry. To them, she
might grand a mighty boon such as returning someone to life or giving a living
person the ability to foresse their own death and avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slain catoblepas reforms in the Shadowfell after a while, and begins wandering
again. Their arrival in a region is often preceded by supernatural phenomena
such as hauntings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get two varieties of catoblepas here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;catoblepas-harbinger&quot;&gt;Catoblepas Harbinger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A classic beast of ill omen, the catoblepas harbinger appears in places full of
hubris to announce they’re about to be hit by famine, war, or other
tragedies. It feeds on pride, anger, despair and other negative emotions,
growing ever larger over time. The poisonous gases it exhales are a byproduct of
this vitriolic diet. I wonder if one of these showed up in the throne room of
the Nerathi emperor before the empire fell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Harbinger is a Large Shadow Beast, and a Level 10 Elite Controller with 220
HP. It lumbers along at speed 6 and has Resist Necrotic 5 and Blindsight 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all catoblepones, the Harbinger emanates the &lt;strong&gt;Raven Queen’s presence&lt;/strong&gt;, an
aura (5) that causes anyone inside who fails a death saving throw to lose HP
equal to half their bloodied value. By the standard rules, any creature who hits
their bloodied value in negative HP dies automatically, so this aura makes PCs
die after &lt;em&gt;at most&lt;/em&gt; two failed saves instead of the usual three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When drawn into a fight the harbinger &lt;strong&gt;gores&lt;/strong&gt; with its horns and uses its
&lt;strong&gt;poison breath&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5, recharge 5+), which obviously does poison
damage and inflicts ongoing poison damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone within 5 squares of the harbinger willingly tries to move away from
it, they’re subject to the beast’s &lt;strong&gt;Final Glance&lt;/strong&gt;, an opportunity action that
targets Will. A victim hit by the glance takes 5 necrotic damage and becomes
Vulnerable 5 to all damage (save ends). When they pass that save, they take
another 10 necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;catoblepas-tragedian&quot;&gt;Catoblepas Tragedian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an older specimen that usually hangs out in places where dead souls
cross over into the Shadowfell, absorbing all the negative emotions that
accompany them. This steady diet has made it grow much larger, and reshaped its
face so it looks like a tragedy mask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tragedians are Huge Shadow Beasts, and Level 18 Elite Controllers with 360
HP. They’re mostly identical to harbingers, with larger numbers. They also have
a couple of new abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is a &lt;strong&gt;Withering Gaze&lt;/strong&gt; used as an active attack against a bloodied
enemy. It targets Will, does a tiny bit of necrotic damage, and weakens (save
ends). After the first failed save, the target is also blinded. After the
second, the target’s hit points drop to -1. And yeah, this does mean they need
to make death saves and it does subject them to the Raven Queen’s Presence
aura. This power recharges whenever no enemy is affected by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second new ability is &lt;strong&gt;Inevitable Call&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor action that automatically
hits an enemy within 20 squares and pulls them 3 squares closer to the
Tragedian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catoblepones are sticky melee controllers. The basic Harbinger has good powers
to prevent PCs from getting away from them, opening them up from attack from the
other monsters in the fight. It pairs really well with monsters that can do
heavy damage, like brutes and some artillery, because you want to force the PCs
to roll death saves as soon as possible. The Tragedian is all that and more. It
has powers to draw PCs closer to itself and perhaps even force them into
negative HP early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to dismiss these monsters outright because I found the name “catoblepas”
ridiculous, but their 4e incarnation has really evocative lore! I’m a fan now.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/22/catoblepas.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/22/catoblepas.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 3: Cambion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series! Click &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/mm3-4e&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambions made their 4e debut in the Monster Manual and were covered
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2019/07/25/cambion.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This MM3 entry brings us a few more cambion stat blocks, and an extra
helping of lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic lore hasn’t changed: cambions are the direct offspring of a mortal and
a devil. The first Monster Manual just described the mortal parent as “depraved
or foolish”, but MM3 gets into a little bit more detail on how that
happens. It’s about as horrific as you’d imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “foolish” mortals are the ones who sign infernal contracts. Many of them
include “make a baby” as part of the price. The “depraved” ones are cultists,
but that doesn’t mean the process is enjoyable for them either. The highly
hierarchical nature of Hell means mortal cultists and lesser devils must
conceive cambions as commanded by their superiors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever their origin story, cambions mature quickly and are soon put to work
furthering the schemes of their masters. Most of them swear loyalty to Asmodeus
directly and are set loose upon the world to enact various schemes. Fierna and
Belial also walk around with a cambion honor guard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambions associate with lesser devils and mortal diabolists. Those who style
themselves as leaders might have a retinue of guards and advisors. The advisors
are sometimes oni or rakshasa, and in that case they’ll be the true power behind
the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-monsters&quot;&gt;The Monsters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambions are Medium Immortal Humanoids with the Devil keyword. They have
darkvision and fire resistance (which is 10 in all stat blocks in this
entry). Their wings give them a flight speed of 8 (clumsy), which means they
fight with their feet on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cambion-wrathborn&quot;&gt;Cambion Wrathborn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the name, wrathborn are fairly subtle. They can use magic to appear as a
mortal version of their natural appearance, and they use this ability to
infiltrate mortal societies and attain positions of power through intrigue and
violence. They &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have a short temper, though, and tend to interpret even the
smallest slight as a grave insult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrathborn are Level 9 Skirmishers with 100 HP. Their disguise ability is named
&lt;strong&gt;Wicked Guise&lt;/strong&gt;, and it remains on while the wrathborn is unbloodied. When that
happens, they assume their true form and project an aura (1) of &lt;strong&gt;Burning
Anger&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals 5 fire damage to those caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight a bit like extra-mobile infernal warlocks, using a shortsword and a
wand. The basic sword attack is &lt;strong&gt;Pain Blade&lt;/strong&gt;, which damages and makes the
target grant combat advantage for a turn on a hit. They can use a maneuver named
&lt;strong&gt;Path of Pain&lt;/strong&gt; to shift 4 squares and make a Pain Blade attack at any point
during the shift. The wand shoots &lt;strong&gt;fire bolts&lt;/strong&gt; that target Reflex and do fire
damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter, while bloodied, the wrathborn can also use &lt;strong&gt;Burst Skyward&lt;/strong&gt;
to deal fire damage around themselves (Close burst 2 vs. Reflex) and fly 8
squares without provoking opportunity attacks. This is good to avoid getting
surrounded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chained-cambion&quot;&gt;Chained Cambion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm3-4e-cambion-chained.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2010 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chained cambions are exactly what it says on the tin: cambions bound up in
chains, with iron masks affixed to their faces. I’m guessing this is what
happens when someone tries to imprison a cambion and it kinda-sorta breaks
free. Their bodies are completely bound, but they can move and fight by
controllng the chains that bind them. Their chief emotion is hate. The only
sound from behind the mask is a hoarse scream of rage. Zero subtlety. Zero
chill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chained cambions are Level 10 Controllers with 110 HP. Since they walk around by
moving their chains like spider legs, they lack a flight speed. They’re
surrounded by a &lt;strong&gt;Blinding Field&lt;/strong&gt; (aura 3) that makes its covered squares count
as difficult terrain for enemies. Their &lt;strong&gt;Child of Chains&lt;/strong&gt; trait makes them get
a +2 attack bonus when immobilized or restrained, as well as a +2 bonus on saves
to end those conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These monsters attack by hitting people with their enchanted chains and
screaming into their minds. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;Chain Lash&lt;/strong&gt; attack has a reach of 3,
and if it hits a dazed enemy it also immobilizes them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psychic screaming is expressed as two different attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Vile Fetters&lt;/strong&gt; is
a reach 5 melee attack that targets Will and does psychic damage. If the target
ends it next turn closer to the cambion than it started, it becomes dazed (save
ends). &lt;strong&gt;Unfettered Scream&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) is a close blast 3 that targets
Fortitude, does psychic damage, pushes 2 squares, and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action the chained cambion can use a &lt;strong&gt;Mind Shackles&lt;/strong&gt; spell. It
automatically hits 2 enemies within 5 squares of the cambion. Shackled enemies
take 10 psychic damage at the start &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; at the end of their turns if they’re
not adjacent to the other shackled enemy at that moment. Each enemy saves
independently from the other, so it’s possible for one of them to be free and
the other still shackled. The first successful save reduces the damage to 5, the
second eliminates it. This power recharges when the cambion is bloodied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like a chained cambion will want to shackle a pair of enemies and then
keep them apart by interposing himself between then and using Unfettered Scream
to push them away, or Vile Fetters to prevent them from going around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cambion-infernal-scion&quot;&gt;Cambion Infernal Scion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the unfortunate mortal forced to be a cambion parent is a noble or
even a monarch. Infernal scions are an object lesson on why hereditary
government is a bad idea. This one covets Asmodeus’ positition as the ruler of
Hell and is working to supplant him. I guess he’s still a ways away from doing
that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s a Level 12 Elite Soldier with 250 HP, wearing mail and wielding a magic
sword. This &lt;strong&gt;Burning Longsword&lt;/strong&gt; does fire damage and marks for a turn. If a
marked enemy tries to ignore the mark, the scion can use &lt;strong&gt;Majestic Stride&lt;/strong&gt; to
teleport adjacent to them and hit them with the sword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to using the sword to mark people, the scion can use &lt;strong&gt;Oath of the
Nine&lt;/strong&gt; (minor action, 1/round) to do so. This automatically marks an enemy
within 3 squares and gives them Vulnerable 10 Fire for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When not bloodied, the scion can use &lt;strong&gt;Dread Command&lt;/strong&gt; (Ranged 5 vs. Will, minor
action, 1/round) to dominate an enemy for a turn. Once bloodied he flips out,
losing this ability and replacing it with &lt;strong&gt;Fiend Razor&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows it to
make 2 sword attacks with an action. This is an interesting way to implement an
elite’s multi-attack ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambions are… okay I guess? The mechanics in this entry are interesting, but
the lore doesn’t quite get me going. I feel I can make some use of the infernal
scion, but the others don’t make stories jump to my mind just from reading them.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/22/cambion.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2022/05/22/cambion.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
