<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 18:24:26 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 18:24:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Gray Render</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-gray-render.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see something of a rarity in this series: a monster whose 4e incarnation
I find &lt;em&gt;strictly worse&lt;/em&gt; than its previous ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray Renders first appeared in 3e, where they were these big, clawed,
carnivorous brutes with an oddly endearing trait: they would sometimes imprint
on another creature and basically dedicate their lives to protect it and take
care of it. This creature could be a sapient, or even a PC if the GM was feeling
cute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth Edition gray renders lose the imprinting, and replace it with a constant
urge to destroy and feed. Some sages theorize they’re somehow tied to the
metaphysical concept of entropy despite being natural beasts, since they seem
particularly fond of targetting sapient settlements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t like this change because, as you might have surmised by now, I’m not
fond of always-hostile, attacks-on-sight-and-fights-to-the-death monsters. I
literally never saw anyone mention grey renders online without also mentioning
and praising the imprinting. Remove that and you’re left with something that’s
virtually indistinguishable from, say, a goristro demon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray Renders are Large Natural Humanoids with a Chaotic Evil alignment and
Int 2. They’re Level 19 Elite Brutes with 452 HP and blindsight, who fight using
claws, bites, and sheer brutality. In other words, almost like slightly smaller,
slightly dumber goristros with blindsight. They have Speed 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Claw&lt;/strong&gt; that also grabs on a hit. They can make
two claw attacks per action, and if both hit the same target they also inflict
ongoing damage on account of the rending. They can use a grabbed victim as a
club, inflicting more damage than the claw, pushing the target of the attack 4
squares from the impact, and dealing half the rolled damage to the “weapon”. Or
they can bite the grabbed victim for massive damage, with a Daze rider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While bloodied, their claw attack also knocks a target prone on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray renders are said to be too destructive to cooperate with anyone, but some
predators and scavengers have taken to following them from safe distance to
exploit their rampages. So we get these encounter groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 18: 1 gray render, 1 bodak skulk, 2 guulvorgs. Opportunistic followers
can be sapient too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 20: 1 dire bullette, 1 gray render, 3 nabassu gargoyles. The gargoyles
are watching the kaiju battle and waiting to feast on the loser’s remains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stat block is cool, but the lore is “meh” at best. Reskin this into a demon
and/or add the imprinting back to make it more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/01/gray-render.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/10/01/gray-render.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Goliath</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think Goliaths first appeared in the Races of Stone supplement for 3.5. In
Fourth Edition, their first appearance was as a playable option in the
PHB 2. They get their corresponding “monster” entry here, with a couple of stat
blocks suitable for use as opposition or NPC allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re one of the many playable peoples designed to give players a “taste” of
being a cool fantasy monster without being unbalanced. Eladrin arguably do it
for Sidhe; dragonborn do it for dragons; tieflings for fiends; deva for
angels. Goliaths do it for giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-goliath.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical goliath is stated to be between 7 and 8 feet tall, so whether
they’re on the large side of Medium or the small side of Large is a matter of
opinion. The book’s opinion is that they’re Medium, since that allows them to be
playable. Their skin is gray or brown, and speckled with coin-sized bony growths
that look like rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goliaths have existed since shortly after the Primordials created the world,
which might mean they’re a kind of byproduct of the creation of the Giants in
the same way the origin of the Dragonborn is tied to that of dragons. Goliaths
don’t care enough about that to make myths about it, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All throughout their history they’ve preferred to keep to a nomadic existence in
the more mountainous areas of the world, so there isn’t much about them in other
people’s records either. While it’s fairly common for individual goliaths to
travel the “lowlands” as adventurers or explorers, they haven’t engaged in any
grand diplomacy or empire-building as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culturally, goliaths place a lot of value in individual skill and prowess, and
this makes them very competitive. Their communities probably have all sorts of
tournaments and contests in their calendars. Individual goliaths tend to turn
everything into a contest, even if only in the privacy of their own minds - they
keep score and constantly compare themselves both to their companions and to
their own past performance. That battle where Legolas and Gimli compare their
kill counts? That’s every fight where a goliath is involved. This does have the
downside of making them get a bit depressive when they fail to measure up to
their own standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect Kord is a very popular deity among goliaths, and they also often
worship the primal spirits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as the rules are concerned, Goliaths are Medium Natural Humanoids. They
have a natural speed of 6, and human-equivalent senses. Their signature ability
is &lt;strong&gt;Stone’s Endurance&lt;/strong&gt;, a minor-action encounter power which gives them
some resistance to all damage for a turn. The value of this resistance is 5/tier
(5 at heroic, 10 at paragon, 15 at epic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-sunspeaker&quot;&gt;Goliath Sunspeaker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is more of a primal priest of the sun spirits than a cleric of Pelor,
focused on burning people with sun-powered lasers. Sunspeakers are Level 7
Artillery with 64 HP, wearing light armor and using an orb as an implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their melee basic attack is the &lt;strong&gt;Sunspeaker’s Hand&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex and
deals light radiant damage. &lt;strong&gt;Solar Sphere&lt;/strong&gt; does the same at Range 20 with
better damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less often, the sunspeaker can use &lt;strong&gt;Solar Rays&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) against up to 2
targets within Range 10. This deals light radiant &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; fire damage, as well as
ongoing damage of the type chosen (save ends). This allows them to potentially
stack two sources of ongoing damage on someone with the same power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If cornered, the sunspeaker can use &lt;strong&gt;Flaring Leap&lt;/strong&gt; (move action; encounter) to
jump 3 squares and then move its remaining speed. This jet-powered jump causes a
fire in the sunspeaker’s starting space, which deals damage to adjacent enemies
or to those foolish enough to enter the flaming square. The fire lasts for a
turn and can be sustained with minor actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it can use a big area attack named &lt;strong&gt;Call Down The Sun&lt;/strong&gt; once per
encounter, which is a bit weaker than Solar Sphere but targets a lot of people
and does half damage on a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goliath-guardian&quot;&gt;Goliath Guardian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more straightforward but no less powerful martial type. The guardian is a
Level 9 Soldier with 96 HP. It’s heavily armored by still has speed 6, wielding
a bastard sword and a light shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its basic &lt;strong&gt;sword&lt;/strong&gt; attack marks for a turn, and if the target is prone it’s
also prevented from getting up for the same amount of time. The guardian knocks
people prone with &lt;strong&gt;Ram’s Charge&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), a maneuver that deals light
physical damage and has a long list of riders: it pushes the target 2 squares,
knocks it prone, and allows the goliath to make a free sword attack against the
target. As the name says, it can be used as part of a charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Warrior’s Leap&lt;/strong&gt; is a passive that allows the guardian to jump
without provoking opportunity attacks. It still uses the standard jump rules
(and it’s high Athletics score) for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guardians are awesome in moutainous terrain that’s full of cliffs. Even if their
targets aren’t thrown overboard, they’ll still stay on the ground for quite a
while, granting advantage to the guardian and any sneak-attacking skirmisher
buddies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goliaths often team up with similarly-inclined mountain-dwellers, which can
include dwarves, galeb duhrs, or goblins. I suppose that might include stone
giants as well, if you level your goliaths up a bit. The sample encounter is
level 9, and includes a galeb duhr rock-caller, 3 goliath guardians, and 1
sunspeaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like goliaths, they fill a very specific “huge person” niche. These two stat
blocks are interesting from a mechanics standpoint as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/28/goliath.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/28/goliath.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Golem</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Golems showed up in the first MM and were iconic enough to later make it to the
Monster Vault. I covered those &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/30/golem.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and you can check that same post to
see their basic lore. The Monster Manual 2 brings us yet more golems, which
share the same basic lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, golems are Natural Animates with the Construct keyword. They’re
immune to disease, poison, and sleep. They have darkvision, and though their
ground speed tends to be high they cannot shift. Most are Large, but one of the
examples here is Huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bone-golem&quot;&gt;Bone Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-golem-bone.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bone golems are made from the skeletons of several creatures, whose bones are
sharpened and fitted together to form the construct’s body. Despite being made
of bones and beloved of necromancers, it’s a construct animated through
elemental magic and not an undead monster. Throw this one into an encounter that
does have undead skeletons in it, and it should be good to surprise your PCs a
bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bone Golems are Level 12 Elite Brutes with 302 HP. It’s so spiky the pointy bits
count as a &lt;strong&gt;Bone Spikes&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) that deals 5 damage to any enemy that enters
it. The pointy bits also justify the &lt;strong&gt;Osseous Retaliation&lt;/strong&gt; trait, which deals
a bit of automatic damage to anyone who hits the golem with an opportunity
attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This construct fights with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Bone Spurs&lt;/strong&gt;, and can attack twice per
action with them. It can also fire a &lt;strong&gt;Bone Volley&lt;/strong&gt; (burst 3 vs. Reflex,
recharge 6+) that deals heavy physical damage and dazes (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the golem is destroyed &lt;strong&gt;Bone Death&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to make one last
attack. If Bone Spurs is charged then it uses that, otherwise it makes a basic
bone spur attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chain-golem&quot;&gt;Chain Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-golem-chain.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Huge golems are modeled after chain devils, and are often tasked to guard
prisons and Actual Dungeons instead of the usual tombs or treasure vaults. As
you might have guessed, their fighting style is very grapple-intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chain Golems are Level 22 Elite Soldiers with 418 HP, a speed of 8, and all
standard golem traits. Their &lt;strong&gt;Entangling Chains&lt;/strong&gt; act as an aura (3) that slows
everyone caught inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic attack is a Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Chain&lt;/strong&gt; that does physical damage and pulls
the target 2 squares. &lt;strong&gt;Chain Smash&lt;/strong&gt; is their double attack power, allowing it
to attack two different targets in one action. While they’re bloodied, &lt;strong&gt;Berserk
Attack&lt;/strong&gt; allows them to make a chain strike against anyone who damages them as a
reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that and we didn’t even use the grappling rules yet! We have to do that for
&lt;strong&gt;Chain Grab&lt;/strong&gt;, though. This at-will attack is a Close Burst 2 that does the
same damage as the basic strike, pulls targets 1 square, and grabs them. The
escape DC is 32 or 35 depending on the skill you use. The golem can move away
from the grabbed victims without ending the grab because chains. Once it
finishes moving it can either slide the victims next to itself or let them go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So your typical chain golem will try to keep the whole party grabbed while it
smacks them around with its chains. PCs who aren’t grabbed will still be slowed,
and the golem’s strikes will pull them back if they try to run away. Staying far
away and using ranged attacks is a good tactic against them, but that speed of 8
will make keeping away a real chore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;clay-golem&quot;&gt;Clay Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-golem-clay.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clay Golems were one of the original golem types described in the first entries
back in AD&amp;amp;D or in the nebulous times before it. They were originally inspired
by the legend of the golem of Prague, and so were the only golem that required
divine magic to make (all the others were arcane).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fourth Edition, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/02/12/eidolon.html&quot;&gt;eidolons&lt;/a&gt; are used to represent divine constructs, so
clay golems have the same arcane/elemental origin as the other types. They have
a somewhat “runny” appearance, but are surprisingly fast and retain a slightly
less harsh version of the ability to inflict unhealing wounds that they had in
previous incarnations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stat-wise, they’re Level 15 Elite Brutes with 368 HP, Large size, a speed of 6,
and all common golem traits. Their basic attack is a Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Slam&lt;/strong&gt; that does
heavy physical damage and curses the target, making it unable to regain HP. This
is a (save ends) condition, but it’s still quite dangerous, since it makes
wounds inflicted by &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; enemies unhealing, not just the golem’s. &lt;strong&gt;Clay
Smash&lt;/strong&gt; allows it to slam two different targets in one action, and they have the
same Berserk Attack reaction as the chain golem above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Hasty Reaction&lt;/strong&gt; passive trait allows them to roll initiative twice and
take the highest result, and &lt;strong&gt;Unstoppable&lt;/strong&gt; is a move-action encounter power
that allows them to move 8 squares and pass through enemy spaces. They draw
opportunity attacks when doing this, but reduce their damage by 10. This isn’t
worded like a resistance, so I guess powers that bypass or reduce resistances
don’t work against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iron-golem&quot;&gt;Iron Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These made it into the MV, so we already covered them. The MM2 has two versions,
the Level 20 one that we saw, and a Level 26 “Iron Golem Juggernaut” that’s
basically the same aside from being size Huge and having bigger numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each kind of golem presented here gets a sample encounter. I guess there was
something of an editing snafu here, because most golems have their encounter
listed right after their stats, but the one for chain golems is all by its
lonesome in an “Encounter Groups” section at the end of the overall entry. I
guess it must be there because it has two golem types in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: 1 bone golem, 4 horde ghouls (minions), 1 human wizard lich. So
that’s the kind of caster who makes bone golems.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 15: 1 clay golem, 1 shadar-kai gloom lord, 2 shadow snakes. A Zehiri
operation, if you still want to associate clay golems with clerics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 21: 1 chain golem, 1 dark naga, 1 iron golem. Someone &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; wanted
this place guarded.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 24: 1 iron golem juggernaut, 1 storm gorgon, 1 djinn skylord. A noble,
his pet, and his mechanical manservant.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a point past which adding more golem types feels a bit redundant. There
are also so many non-golem constructs out there that I almost think “golem”
should be a singular monster type with very specific characteristics, rather
than a whole family of them. Otherwise it would be best to do away with the term
entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/golem.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/golem.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Goblin</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-goblin.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D Fourth Edition uses “Goblins” to describe a set of closely related species
of humanoids: actual goblins, hobgoblins, and bugbears. They’re a very
traditional component of the game and we looked at lots of them in the
MM1/Monster Vault Let’s Read. The post covering their basic lore is &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/22/goblinoids.md&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the first Manual covered them so well, the second brings us a small number
of more specialized stat blocks for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bugbear-wardancer&quot;&gt;Bugbear Wardancer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wardancers are specialized martial artists. Their weapon of choice is a
two-handed heavy flail, which they swing in wide arcs while moving through enemy
forces in the battlefield. The end result looks something like a dance, thus the
name. There’s a religious element to the art: there are different schools
organized around the worship of different exarchs of Bane, who compete among
each other to see whose war dance is the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wardancer presented here is a Level 6 Skirmisher with 70 HP, low-light
vision, and Speed 7. Its basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Flail Dance&lt;/strong&gt; that does physical
damage and has a lot of stacked riders: it pushes the target 2 square and knocks
it prone, and also allows the bugbear to shift 1 square. Yes, this is an at-will
basic attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wardancer also has a couple of special attacks. &lt;strong&gt;Flail Barrier&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge
5+) does a bit of automatic damage in a burst 2 around the bugbear, and makes it
take half damage from weapon attacks until the end of its next turn. &lt;strong&gt;Flail
Assault&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2 vs Reflex; encounter) does a bit more damage and knocks
those it hits prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the wardancer’s attacks deal extra damage if it has combat advantage against
the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goblin-acolyte-of-maglubyet&quot;&gt;Goblin Acolyte of Maglubyet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another martial artist, this one a goblin from a sect devoted to Maglubyet. In
previous editions (and again on 5th), Maglubyet is the main goblinoid deity, but
here he’s one of Bane’s Exarchs. His acolytes seek to make themselves in his
image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Acolyte is a Level 1 Controller with 29 HP, Speed 6, and low-light
vision. They wield a battleaxe in combat, and back it up with a bit of divine
magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acolytes are surrounded by a &lt;strong&gt;Life Scourge&lt;/strong&gt; aura (2) that prevents enemies
inside from recovering hit points. Their basic attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Slashing Shroud&lt;/strong&gt;
that consists of an axe strike that also makes the acolyte invisible to the
target until the end if the acolyte’s next turn. A good option against PC
defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can attack at range with the &lt;strong&gt;Hand of Maglubyet&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 10
vs. Fortitude), a telekinetic attack that deals force damage and either slides
the target 3 squares or immobilizes it for a turn. &lt;strong&gt;Maglubyet’s Fists&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+) allows them to use this attack twice in a single action. So as far
as martial artists go, this is one of those annoying hadouken spammers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acolyte also has the standard &lt;strong&gt;Goblin Tactics&lt;/strong&gt; power that allows it to
shift 1 square as a reaction when missed by a melee attack. This is what you
would change if you were making acolytes of other species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lolthbound-goblin&quot;&gt;Lolthbound Goblin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goblins are generally big on Bane worship, but that’s not universal among
them. This is a goblin whose people have been slaves to the drow for
generations. Their training, and even their physiology, have some important
differences from your usual goblins. They’re clearly meant to be encountered
alongside drow, though for that to work out you’ll need to make those drow lower
level or the goblin higher level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As written, the Lolthbound Goblin is a Level 3 Soldier with 45 HP. They have
speed 6, and replace the usual low-light vision with full darkvision. They wear
light armor and fight with a war pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Lolthbound Goblins are within 5 squares of a drow, they gain a +2 bonus to
all their attacks and defenses. That &lt;strong&gt;pick&lt;/strong&gt; is a high-crit weapon and marks
targets for a turn on a hit. Once per encounter they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Stinging Blow&lt;/strong&gt;
that deals poison damage and instead of marking increases any ongoing poison
damage the target is taking by 5. This synergizes with the poisoned weapons drow
so often carry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also once per encounter they can use a &lt;strong&gt;Lolthbound Shriek&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5
vs. Fortitude), which deals light thunder damage to anyone in the area who is
not a drow or spider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the usual Goblin Tactics reaction, they also have &lt;strong&gt;Drow Protector&lt;/strong&gt;,
an interrupt where the goblin throws himself in front of a drow that’s just been
targetted by an attack, becoming the target instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lolthbound-goblin-slave&quot;&gt;Lolthbound Goblin Slave&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a Level 12 Minion Skirmisher version of the lolthbound goblin above,
which makes it appropriate for use with drow without the need for level
adjustments. They’re also armed with war picks, and add a hand crossbow to their
loadout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic melee attack is a &lt;strong&gt;Stinging Pick&lt;/strong&gt;, which works just like the
Stinging Blow from the regular version. Their basic &lt;strong&gt;crossbow&lt;/strong&gt; attack deals a
bit more damage if they’ve moved 3 or more squares before making it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also gain the attack and defense bonus from being near drow, and have
Goblin Tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hobgoblin-fleshcarver&quot;&gt;Hobgoblin Fleshcarver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the hobgoblin specialized martial artist. Unlike the bugbear and goblin
examples, fleshcarvers don’t seem to have a religious component to their
training. It’s all about hard work and crafting your own custom-fitted
weapons. Their weapons of choice are a polearm and a set of poisoned throwing
darts, whose poison is harvested from serpents they hunt as part of their
training. Fleshcarvers never refuse a challenge to combat, though they’re smart
enough to not let such a challenge distract them in the middle of an ongoing
battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleshcarvers are Level 6 Elite Controllers with 146 HP. They have Speed 6 and
low-light vision, wear heavy armor, and are armed with the afore-mentioned
specialized weapons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their stance and movements act as an aura (2) named &lt;strong&gt;Fleshcarver’s Trap&lt;/strong&gt;,
dealing 5 damage to any enemy inside the first time they move during their
turn. Their &lt;strong&gt;glaive&lt;/strong&gt; is reach 2 and is used both for basic attacks and for an
at-will &lt;strong&gt;Glaive Flurry&lt;/strong&gt; that targets all enemies in a close burst 2, does more
damage than the basic attack, and slides targets 2 squares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At range they can throw those &lt;strong&gt;Toxic Darts&lt;/strong&gt; to do a bit of poison damage and
slow the target (save ends). If the target was already slowed, it’s immobilized
instead. When they’re hit by a melee attack, they can use their reaction to
shift 2 squares and make a dart attack. And finally, fleshcarvers have the same
Hobgoblin Resilience and Phalanx Soldier powers from MM1 hobgoblins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These hobgoblins are more effective when lots of enemies are in reach, but the
selective targetting on their area attack means they engage all those enemies
while fighting in formation for that sweet defense bonus from Phanlanx Soldier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new goblinoid specialists can be inserted into any goblin encounter, and
being goblins themselves also work well with any of their typically allied
creatures. These are the encounters we get on the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 1: 1 goblin acolyte, 3 goblin warriors, 1 Lolthbound Goblin. It’s likely
the whole group are drow slaves, with the LBG being their leader. The level
math works out, but the LBG’s drow-related skills are wasted here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: 2 bugbear wardancers, 2 bugbear warriors, 1 barghest battle lord. A
warlord and their bodyguards.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 6: 1 fleshcarver, 3 hobgoblin soldiers, 2 dire wolves. A patrol with a
little extra kick to it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 13: 4 lolthbound goblin slaves, 1 drow priest, 2 blade spiders, 2 drow
warriors. Lots of poison being thrown around on this one, which makes the
minions more dangerous than their level would indicate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these new additions, because their stat blocks are interesting and their
associated lore fleshes goblin culture out a bit more. I like that they’re
complex enough to have multiple martial styles.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/goblin.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/16/goblin.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Gnome</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gnomes were introduced in the first Monster Manual, and you can see the post I
did on them &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/21/gnome.html.&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. By the time the MM2 came out, they were already available
as a playable option in the Player’s Handbook 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We get three new gnome stat blocks in this entry, but one of them (the Gnome
Entropist) also appeared in the Monster Vault and so was covered in the original
post. We’ll cover the other two here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gnome-mistwalker&quot;&gt;Gnome Mistwalker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gnome Mistwalkers are like the triple-classed fighter/illusionist/thieves of
yore. They’re skilled at illusion magic and melee combat, using those to ambush
their targets. This sort of training is common among gnome brigands, who build
elaborately disguised hideouts and strike at merchants passing along nearby
trade routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistwalkers are Level 5 Lurkers with 51 HP and all standard gnome traits
(including the Fade Away and Reactive Stealth powers described in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/21/gnome.html.&quot;&gt;original
post&lt;/a&gt;). They wear light armor and wield picks in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;picks&lt;/strong&gt; have the High-Crit property, and they deal extra damage to targets
granting them combat advantage. &lt;strong&gt;Mistwalker’s Strike&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) allows
them to become invisible until the end of their next turn, shift 2 squares, and
make a pick attack in that order. This means the attack will always benefit from
the extra damage, and won’t disrupt the invisibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the two standard powers, they have a third defensive ability in
the form of &lt;strong&gt;Blur of Movement&lt;/strong&gt;, a reaction that allows them to teleport 1
square when hit by an enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gnome-entropist&quot;&gt;Gnome Entropist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their mechanics were covered in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/21/gnome.html.&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;, but here we get a bit of
extra lore on them. Entropists are magicians whose power flows from the
Elemental Chaos. This tends to interfere with their natural link to the Feywild,
so they’re not usually the most stable of gnomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gnome-wolverine&quot;&gt;Gnome Wolverine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gnome is the best at what it does, and what it does ain’t pretty, bub. And
that’s pretty much all you need to know to understand this short berserker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolverine is a Level 9 Skirmisher with 95 HP, lightly armored and wielding an
axe. His natural speed of 5 becomes 7 on a charge, and he has a +3 to AC against
opportunity attacks plus the standard gnome powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That &lt;strong&gt;axe&lt;/strong&gt; can be used for basic strikes and for an &lt;strong&gt;Unbalancing Swipe&lt;/strong&gt; that
does the same damage, slides the target 2 squares on a hit and knocks then prone
on a critical. When the Wolverine drops an enemy to 0 HP, &lt;strong&gt;Vicious Fury&lt;/strong&gt;
allows him to shift 5 squares and gain a +3 bonus to damage rolls until the end
of his next turn. Once per encounter, and once again after being bloodied,
Wolverine can use a &lt;strong&gt;Shrieking Strike&lt;/strong&gt; that’s much stronger than the basic
attack and does a bit of splash damage to an enemy adjacent to the target. Hit
or miss, it grants Wolverine a +3 bonus to all defenses until the end of his
next turn. This can be used as part of a charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite my joking, this Wolverine doesn’t regenerate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two sample encounters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: 1 entropist, 2 wolverines, 2 spriggan giantsouls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: 3 entropists, 2 phase spiders, 1 satyr piper, and 1 will-o’-wisp.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All seem to be the sort of gnome who’s up to no good, since they include the
dodgier sort of fey (spriggans/redcaps and the wisp).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like 4e gnomes, so I liked seeing more of them. The wolverine is particularly
fun, because it goes so hard against type.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/01/gnome.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/01/gnome.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Gnolls</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The absolutely best thing about the Monster Manual 2 gnolls is that I don’t have
to talk about them! It turns out I’ve already covered them all in the
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/20/gnoll.html&quot;&gt;MM1/Monster Vault gnoll post&lt;/a&gt;. The Deathpledged Gnoll, Fang of Yeenoghu, and
Gnoll Gorger that appeared in the Monster Vault all had their first appearances
here in the MM2. Just read the original article for everything you need to know
about 4e gnolls.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/01/gnolls.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/09/01/gnolls.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Giants</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual and the Monster Vault contained plenty of giants, whose
lore in 4e is pretty awesome. I covered their basic lore &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/30/giants.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and also had
individual posts for &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/01/earth-giants.html&quot;&gt;hill&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/04/frost-giants.html&quot;&gt;frost&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/06/fire-giants.html&quot;&gt;fire&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/07/death-giants.html&quot;&gt;death&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/04/10/storm-giants.html&quot;&gt;storm&lt;/a&gt;
giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monster Manual 2 added more giants, and it’s actually where Frost Giants
made their first appearance in this edition. We already covered them in the
corresponding post linked above. In this one, we’ll cover the two other
varieties introduced in the same entry: Eldritch and Stone giants. The latter
are old standbys, and I had never heard of the former until now. If they existed
in a previous edition, it was in one of the more out-of-the-way supplements or
Dragon articles for 3e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eldritch-giants&quot;&gt;Eldritch Giants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-giant-eldritch.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the basic lore post, the primordials made the first Giants from
the same elements they used in the world, to help them shape and understand
it. Well, it turns out &lt;em&gt;raw magic&lt;/em&gt; is as much a basic building block of the
world as the more classical elements of earth, fire, air, and water. Therefore,
it got its own Giant type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eldritch giants were among the most powerful creations of the Primordials, and
they helped a lot with shaping the flow of magical energies in the still-cooling
world. Today their power is much diminished from what it was at the dawn of
time, and most of them dedicate their lives to accumulating magical power and
knowledge in hopes of returning to those lofty heights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both eldritch giants and titans are still well-versed in magic. They know how to
form weapons out of pure force, and they tattoo their bodies with symbols that
allow them to absorb the magic of others and teleport at will. They live near
sources of arcane power, and jealously hoard knowledge and artifacts. Eldritch
giant social hierarchy is based on how much power individuals managed to
accumulate - Eldritch Titans tend to be at the top. An individual eldritch giant
or titan might have more abilities than what is depicted in the “typical” stat
blocks of this entry, and they’ll certainly have access to lots and lots of
magic rituals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most interactions between mortals and eldritch giants as written here are likely
to be hostile, since the giants don’t have much reason to be friendly. They love
binding and enslaving other creatures with magic, though, so they might be
encountered alongside powerful elementals, slaads, and other such creatures. A
more reasonable group of them would make valuable allies against powerful
incorporeal enemies, though, since they specialize in force magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eldritch-giant&quot;&gt;Eldritch Giant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Standard” eldritch giants are Large Fey Humanoids with the “giant”
keyword, and Level 18 Skirmishers with 171 HP. They have low-light vision, 10
force resistance, and a +5 bonus to saves vs. charm effects. Their ground speed
is 8 and they also have a teleport speed of 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These giants fight in melee with Reach 2 &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Blades&lt;/strong&gt; that target Reflex
and deal force damage, and at range with Range 20 &lt;strong&gt;Force Missiles&lt;/strong&gt; that do the
same. Being so large, they can also use &lt;strong&gt;Sweeping Sword&lt;/strong&gt; attacks to target
everyone in a Close Blast 2 instead of a single victim, and they can do that
even when charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a minor action, they can deploy an &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Field&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 5; recharge
5+) that counts as difficult terrain and makes enemies inside take extra damage
from the their attacks. Also as a minor action, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Consume Magic&lt;/strong&gt;
to absorb a magic zone created by a PC. This requires them to hit the caster’s
Will with an attack, and if they succeed their own attacks get a big damage
boost until the end of their next turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eldritch-titan&quot;&gt;Eldritch Titan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eldritch Titans are Huge, and Level 21 Elite Skirmishers with 394 HP. They have
the same passive traits as their smaller cousins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their Reach 3 &lt;strong&gt;Eldritch Hammers&lt;/strong&gt; deal more damage, and they can make two
attacks per action, even on a charge. Their ranged force attack is also stronger
and pushes the target 5 squares on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once per encounter they can cast a &lt;strong&gt;Force Hammer&lt;/strong&gt; that damages everyone on a
close blast 3, pushes then 3 squares and knocks them prone. On a miss the
targets still take half damage and are pushed. They have the same Consume Magic
and Eldritch Field abilities as eldritch giants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stone-giants&quot;&gt;Stone Giants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other type of classic earth giant, Stone Giants are among the most
reasonable people among all giantkind. They usually don’t care about raiding or
conquest, and just want to be left alone in their mountain homes. Discrete and
contemplative sorts, they can stay immobile for years while lost in thought, and
are surprisingly adept at hiding themselves in their home terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone passing throug stone giant territory might never spot them at all, and
ill-intentioned travelers might find themselves ambushed before they can do any
harm. The exception to all of this is when the giants are feeling rowdy and want
to have some fun: their favorite game is basically dodgeball with enormous
boulders, and when they’re in the middle of it they don’t usually pay attention
to any smaller creatures who might be in the path of those boulders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone giants are one of the few Giants who are actually on friendly terms with
communities of galeb duhrs and azers. They have a long and proud tradition of
stone carving, and their magic is based on carved runes. It’s possible the
dwarves originally learned their own rune-magic from stone giants, though modern
dwarf scholars dispute this notion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friendly giants of other types, unable to stand their generally unpleasant
societies, often move in with stone giants. Conversely, evil stone giants tend
to move out of their ancestral homes and throw their lot with their more
villainous relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stone-giant&quot;&gt;Stone Giant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-giant-stone.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Giants are Large Elemental Humanoids with the Earth and Giant
keywords. They’re Level 14 Soldiers with 140 HP, immune to petrification, and
have a ground speed of 8 with Earth Walk. This lets them ignore difficult
terrain with a “geological” origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use giant-sized &lt;strong&gt;stone greatclubs&lt;/strong&gt;. As usual for soldiers, their basic
attacks mark on a hit and they can make opportunity attacks marked creatures in
reach that move or shift. They can also make a &lt;strong&gt;Staggering Sweep&lt;/strong&gt; that works
like an area attack, pushes targets 2 squares, and marks them. At range, they
can &lt;strong&gt;hurl rocks&lt;/strong&gt; like you’d expect out of an old-school giant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While they’re unbloodied, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Stone Bones&lt;/strong&gt; as an interrupt when hit
by an attack, gaining 5 resistance do its damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stone-giant-runecarver&quot;&gt;Stone Giant Runecarver&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spellcaster is a Level 16 Controller with 155 HP and the Leader
keyword. Their magic is partly about slowing and immobilizing enemies, and
partly about doing unpleasant things to enemies suffering from those conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight in melee with &lt;strong&gt;Enruned Picks&lt;/strong&gt;, which are High-Crit weapons and have
a slow (save ends) rider. &lt;strong&gt;Grasping Stone&lt;/strong&gt; ensures that any enemy slowed by
the giant is also immobilized for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magic-wise, their &lt;strong&gt;Rune of Thundering Echo&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) deals thunder damage
over an area and inflicts ongoing thunder damage (save ends) on targets who are
slowed or immobilized. The &lt;strong&gt;Rune of Stony Sleep&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 6+) affects a
similar area, deals physical damage and slows (save ends). After the first
failed save, slowed enemies become petrified instead (save still ends). That
rune also creates a zone within its affected area that inflicts a -2 penalty
against saves vs. slowness or immobilization effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Save ends” petrification might not sound so bad, but runecarvers also have a
&lt;strong&gt;Hardened Focus&lt;/strong&gt; aura (5) that makes all petrified enemies inside lose any
damage resistance they have &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; gain Vulnerable 5 to all damage. An evil
runecarver is a good counter to a group of PCs who thought a fight against frost
or fire giants was going to be easy just because they packed the right elemental
resistances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stone-titan&quot;&gt;Stone Titan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone Titans are basically Stone Giants Plus, being Huge in size and Level 18
Elite Soldiers with 348 HP. They fight unarmed and throw rocks, but there are
some important differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, their marking ability is a &lt;strong&gt;Slipstone Distortion&lt;/strong&gt; aura (1) that marks
any enemy who starts their turn inside. Their &lt;strong&gt;slams&lt;/strong&gt; deal extra damage to
marked enemies, and they can make opportunity attacks against marked enemies
like stone giants can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, they can use an &lt;strong&gt;Avalanche Stomp&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) to attack everyone in a
Close Burst 3, with a hit doing heavy damage and causing the very earth to grab
the targets. The escape DC is 28, and the giant doesn’t need to spend actions to
sustain the grab. A miss still does half damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And third, they can “charge” a thrown rock and turn it into a &lt;strong&gt;Quakestone&lt;/strong&gt;
(recharge 5+), making it into an area attack that does light damage, knocks
prone, and dazes (save ends) on a hit. A miss does half damage and knocks prone
without the daze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-impressions&quot;&gt;Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eldritch giants have a somewhat unusual name and appearance when compared to the
traditional types, but they’re a lot closer to them than it seems at first. I
guess calling them “Force Giants” would have been a little too on the nose, but
this is basically what they are. They use Force attacks in the same way a frost
giant would use Cold, or a fire giant would use Fire. Their fighting style is
similar, aside from the “I eat magic!” thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stone giants on the other hand are one of the traditional types that have been
there since the beginning. I’m happy to see them here because your average stone
giant fits the “Earth Giant” mold a lot more readily than a hill giant, who’s
just a big human-looking person. I also like that the book doesn’t consider all
of them evil, and even mentioned that they partner up with non-evil individuals
of the other giant types. I often ponder how to make sapient monsters less evil
and hostile when I discuss them, so it’s nice to see an entry that does that as
written.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/31/giants.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/31/giants.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Ghost Legionnaire</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-ghost-legionnaire.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Monster Manual already includes a bunch of &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/18/ghost.html&quot;&gt;ghosts&lt;/a&gt;, and it even
has a basic Phantom Warrior. Here we have a more specific implementation of that
concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These creatures are the ghosts of soldiers who died in battle more or less at
the same time as the entire rest of their units. The emotional bonds between
them and the trauma of their violent massed deaths causes their spirits to fuse
and to rise as undead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legionnaires always appear as a unit, and they look like individuals acting in
concert, but they’re all part of the same collective ghost. So it might have
been more accurate to title this entry “Ghost &lt;em&gt;Legion&lt;/em&gt;”. Members of the legion
can possess the living and make them experience the soldiers’ last moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a ghost legionnaire is damaged, it always displays the wounds it suffered
in its final battle rather than the ones that were actually inflicted on it. So
a squad killed by some wizard’s acid-infused fireball would grow progressively
more burned and melted as the PC paladin stabs them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ghost legion might be endlessly reliving its last battle when found, seeing
any living intruders as their enemies. It might also be following the orders of
a more powerful undead being, particularly if that being was one of its
commanders in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual legionnaire is a Medium Natural Humanoid with the Undead keyword,
and a Level 13 Soldier with 100 HP. Despite being a ghost, it’s not considered
insubstantial, but it has 10 necrotic resistance and isn’t especially vulnerable
to radiant damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legionnaires fight with the same weapons they had in life, making &lt;strong&gt;devastating
cuts&lt;/strong&gt; with their melee weapons or shooting &lt;strong&gt;ghost arrows&lt;/strong&gt; that do necrotic
damage. They can also use their &lt;strong&gt;Battle Visions&lt;/strong&gt; power to possess a
target. This has range 20, targets Will and deals psychic damage with a Dominate
(save ends) rider. While the target is dominated, the ghost is removed from the
map. When the target finally makes their save, the ghost reappears in an
adjacent space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ghost’s main weakness takes the form of a trait named &lt;strong&gt;Call to
History&lt;/strong&gt;. It allows a PC to make a DC 25 History check as a minor action to
recall details about the legionnaire’s original unit. A success here makes the
PC’s next attack against that ghost deal 10 extra damage. I don’t think you can
stack multiple checks in a single attack, but you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make a check every turn
before you attack. Someone who was possessed and made their save has a +5 bonus
to these tests for the rest of the fight, as those horrifying battle visions act
as extra reference material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collective nature of a ghost legion is expressed by the &lt;strong&gt;Soul Link&lt;/strong&gt;
trait. Basically, you combine the HP totals of all legionnaires present in the
fight into a single pool. Damage to any individual legionnaire is subtracted
from this combined pool. The whole unit is destroyed when this pool is reduced
to 0, but until that happens all legionnaires remain in the fight! This makes
the usual “focus fire” strategy considerably less effective against them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sample encounter is Level 15, and quite straightforward: a 5-ghost unit and
a human lich wizard from the MM. A Nerathi squad plus their former commanding
officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the “collective HP” gimmick! It shouldn’t be too hard to add or
subtract levels from the stat block given here, either, meaning you can bring
the Fun (TM) of ghost legions to the party no matter what their
level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t much of a story difference between a ghost legionnaire and a phantom
warrior, as you can see by their names. This suggests that one way to get a
level 4 legionnaire would be to remove Insubstantial from the warrior and add
Soul Link in its place. You can likely do the same with any other thesaurus
buddies that might come along (banshee battlers, figment fighters, spectral
soldiers, wraith warriors…).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/29/ghost-legionnaire.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/29/ghost-legionnaire.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Genasi</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-genasi.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of “people touched by the elements” is a 3e thing, but genasi as
presented in Fourth Edition are slightly different than what came before
them. They debuted in the Forgotten Realm Player’s Guide as a playable option,
and would later appear in the MM2 in “monster” format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lore&quot;&gt;The Lore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In previous editions genasi were humans with “genie blood”, but in Fourth
they’re simply humanoid sapients from the Elemental Chaos. They’re given no
cosmically significant origin story like tieflings or daeva, so I must assume
they simply evolved naturally in that plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi look more or less human and have human proportions, but each of them also
has an &lt;em&gt;elemental manifestation&lt;/em&gt;. The five known manifestations are “firesoul”,
“watersoul”, “windsoul”, “stormsoul”, and “earthsoul”. Each genasi is born with
one of these and an individual’s manifestation has more to do with their
environment than with genetics. A genasi community built inside a volcano is
going to have a lot of firesouls, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A genasi’s manifestation accents their physical appearance and defines some of
their inborn powers and resistances. It’s an always active part of their being,
not something they can turn off. Some of them train to acquire additional
manifestations. PCs can have two at most, but some NPCs can have more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi live primarily in the Elemental Chaos. They have an easier time of it
than most other mortals but still must step lightly around efreeti and the
like. They can also be found in the world or in the Feywild, since they don’t
have any more difficulty living there than a human would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers&quot;&gt;The Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi are Medium Elemental Humanoids, with a ground speed of 6. They tend to
have keywords corresponding to their elemental manifestations: a fire genasi
will have the Fire keyword, and so on. Their manifestation also determines what
elements they are resistant to, if any, and the themes of their powers. What
those powers are is mostly a function of training, so varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-elemental-dervish&quot;&gt;Genasi Elemental Dervish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m the Avatar, and you’re gonna have to deal with it!” This is a genasi
warrior who has learned to manifest multiple elements, and trained extensively
with the double sword. They can move equally well on the ground, in the water,
or in the air. Their sword attacks can cause several different types of
elemental damage, as can their magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elemental dervishes are Level 18 Elite Controllers with 344 HP and keywords for
the four “classic” elements (air, earth, fire, water). They have ground, swim,
and fly speeds of 6, and 10 resistance to cold, fire, and lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of its turn, the Dervish chooses an between fire, lightning and
thunder. Their &lt;strong&gt;double sword&lt;/strong&gt; attacks will deal both immediate and ongoing
damage of that type. They can make two of those per action, being elites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a dervish is hit by an adjacent enemy, it can use its reaction to respond
with a &lt;strong&gt;Fiery Riposte&lt;/strong&gt;, which targets Reflex and inflicts 10 ongoing fire
damage (save ends). If the enemy was already on fire, their existing ongoing
fire damage increases by 10 instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their special attack is &lt;strong&gt;Primordial Storm&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+), which allows them to
shift 6 squares and perform three attacks in order against different targets at
any point along the movement. The first is &lt;strong&gt;Promise of Storm&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals
thunder damage and makes the target Vulnerable 5 to thunder (save ends). The
second is &lt;strong&gt;Earth Shock&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals physical damage and stuns for a turn. The
third and last one is &lt;strong&gt;Lightning Cut&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals lightning damage and
inflicts 10 ongoing lightning damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elemental dervish is flashy and awesome, and given enough time or
well-selected comrades they can set up some interesting elemental damage combos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-fireblade&quot;&gt;Genasi Fireblade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very straightfoward hot-headed warrior who charges into combat with a flaming
falchion. It’s a Level 11 Brute with 139 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;falchion&lt;/strong&gt; it wields is a High-Crit weapon and inflicts ongoing fire
damage. It has the same Fiery Riposte as the dervish, dealing 5 ongoing damage
instead of 10. Its other power is &lt;strong&gt;Fan The Flames&lt;/strong&gt; (Close Burst 1 vs. Reflex;
recharge 5+), which sets people on fire and gives them a -2 penalty to saves
against ongoing fire damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fireblades are going to charge into combat, Fan the Flames, and then get to work
on cutting people up and setting them on fire at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasy-hydromancer&quot;&gt;Genasy Hydromancer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AKA, a waterbender that’s also partially made of water. This Level 8 Controller
has 91 HP, a swim speed of 8, and fights with a high-crit &lt;strong&gt;Scimitar&lt;/strong&gt; and lots
of water powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic &lt;strong&gt;Wave Bolt&lt;/strong&gt; (ranged 5) deals physical damage and slides targets 3
squares; &lt;strong&gt;Whirling Vortex&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 5+) does the same in a burst around the
hydromancer that affects only enemies; &lt;strong&gt;Drowning Touch&lt;/strong&gt; inflicts ongoing
damage on a single target (save ends), but only recharges once the target saves
or drops to 0 HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “partially made of water” bit is expressed by two other abilities: &lt;strong&gt;Liquid
Body&lt;/strong&gt; is a reaction that allows them to take half damage from the triggering
attack, and &lt;strong&gt;Swift Current&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter) allows them to shift their speed with
the ability to move through enemy spaces and basically ignore all terrain
effects while doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-skyspy&quot;&gt;Genasi Skyspy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A windsoul genasi that fights with paired shortswords and uses their mobility
powers to enhance their hit and run tactics. They’re a Level 7 Skirmisher with
78 HP and 5 cold resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their basic &lt;strong&gt;short sword&lt;/strong&gt; attack allows them to shift 1 square on a hit, and
they can make two of those against an opponent granting them combat
advantage. &lt;strong&gt;Feather-Footed&lt;/strong&gt; gives them an AC bonus against opportunity
attacks, and &lt;strong&gt;Sky Jaunt&lt;/strong&gt; (recharge 4+) allows them to fly until the end of
their current turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should the PCs manage to surround the skyspy, the genasi can use &lt;strong&gt;Manifest
Whirlwind&lt;/strong&gt; (close burst 2; encounter) to do some damage, push them 1 square,
and knock them prone. This should help clear some space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genasi-stoneshield&quot;&gt;Genasi Stoneshield&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A heavily armored earthsoul warrior wielding a heavy pick in battle. It’s a
Level 10 Soldier with 106 HP. Stoneshields are difficult to push around - any
forced movement applied to them is reduced by 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;war pick&lt;/strong&gt; is a High Crit weapon, and it also marks on a hit. This mark is
remarkable for being (save ends) instead of only lasting a turn. Marked targets
take a -5 penalty to damage against the stoneshield’s allies. They can also
attack with a &lt;strong&gt;Mighty Bull Rush&lt;/strong&gt; that does the same damage as the pick and
pushes the target 1 square. It also allows the stoneshield to move into the
target’s previous position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they can stomp really hard and cause a non-damaging &lt;strong&gt;Earth Shock&lt;/strong&gt;
(minor action; encounter) that covers a Close Burst 2 and knocks enemies prone
on a hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genasi can be found alongside a large variety of other creatures, particularly
elementals. They’re as morally varied as humans, so a villain could certainly
employ genasi henchpeople. We have three example encounters here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 8: 3 genasi skyspies riding hipogriff dreadmounts, accompanied by their
pet shardstorm vortex elemental.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 10: 2 fireblades, 2 stoneshields, and a trained magma strider.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Level 19: Two storm archons (a squallshield and a tempest weaver) and two
elemental dervish mercs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about genasi doesn’t give me the sort of instant adventure inspiration
that some of the other monsters do, but I like that they exist. Their presence
in the Elemental Chaos gives you an excuse to place “normal everyday
communities” in that plane for your PCs to interact with. Not every EC
settlement is a githzerai monastery or the City of Brass.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/26/genasi.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/26/genasi.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the 4e Monster Manual 2: Fomorian</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Fomorians first appeared in the first Monster Manual, and we covered them
&lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/07/fomorian.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This entry gives us more fomorian stat blocks, and a few more bits of
lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we have a bit of general lore, which is really a logical extension of the
fact that Fomorians believe themselves the most important creatures in the
universe. They hate all other fey, but that hate manifests as a desire to
subjugate rather than exterminate them. Their perfect world is one where
fomorians rule absolute over the Feywild and have all its other inhabitants
forever toiling to please their masters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this obsession, fomorians are eternally at war with the other fey
civilizations. It’s likely they’ll never succeed in conquering all of the
Feywild, but they’ll never stop trying either. I suppose there must also be some
level of internecine strife among them, because it seems to be they’re very
likely to fight over who gets to be supreme ruler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining bits of lore concern the individual stat blocks here, and so will
be covered in those stat blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numbers-wise, fomorians still retain their common traits from the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2020/03/07/fomorian.html&quot;&gt;first
article&lt;/a&gt;: they’re Huge Fey Humanoids with the Giant keyword; they’re
extremely perceptive (trained Perception, Truesight 6); and they have some sort
of “evil eye” ability that varies per stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-ghost-shaman&quot;&gt;Fomorian Ghost Shaman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-ghost-shaman.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost shamans are necromancers who enslave the spirits of those they kill. They
command these spirits as if they were puppets, enacting sadistic plays for their
own amusement. They also use enslaved spirits as weapons in combat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ghost shamans are Level 16 Elite Controllers with 312 HP. They have darkvision
in addition to the other fomorian traits. All of their attacks are magical in
nature and, except for the Evil Eye, target Fortitude. Their basic melee attack
is &lt;strong&gt;Death’s Touch&lt;/strong&gt;, which deals necrotic damage and slows (save ends). Their
&lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; is a minor-action ranged attack that inflicts ongoing necrotic
damage (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At will, they can use &lt;strong&gt;Spirits of Possession&lt;/strong&gt; (close blast 3), which targets
people taking ongoing necrotic damage and dominates them on a hit (save ends). A
bit less often they can use &lt;strong&gt;Darksoul Mist&lt;/strong&gt;, which is like a necrotic fireball
that leaves a zone of darkness in the affected area. This blocks line of sight
for anyone without darkvision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-cackler&quot;&gt;Fomorian Cackler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-cackler.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cacklers are sly but unhinged assassins who get their name because they
constantly laugh a disturbing laugh. They can be silent when they want to be,
though, and are amazingly stealthy for someone the size of a house. They can
also use magic to shrink down to Medium size, which helps a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cacklers are also excellent at disguising themselves, since their minds can
easily construct entire fake personalities to aid in that. It’s possible for
previously discarded personalities to momentarily come to the fore again,
though, which is part of why they’re so unstable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They fight with &lt;strong&gt;daggers&lt;/strong&gt; bigger than the average human greatsword, which they
can use in melee or throw out to range 10. The thrown dagger attack can target
one or two enemies, and they return after it resolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; makes them invisible to the affected enemy, and they get a
big bonus to damage against targets that can’t see them. &lt;strong&gt;Size Alteration&lt;/strong&gt;
lets them switch between Huge and Medium as a minor action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-totemist&quot;&gt;Fomorian Totemist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-totemist.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totemists are fomorian spellcasters that collect the heads of those they kill
and build chains out of them. Each head in the chain is imbued with necromantic
power, and can channel a different curse. Most totemists have a preference for a
particular type of head - one might favor eladrin heads, another dwarves, and so
on. Some of them select prospective additions to their chains year in advance,
following the lives of their future victims until the time is right for the
“harvest”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totemists are Level 18 Elite Skirmishers with 352 HP. They fight with the
afore-mentioned &lt;strong&gt;Chain of Heads&lt;/strong&gt;, which is Reach 4, does physical damage and
inflicts ongoing necrotic damage. They can also channel curses through the chain
as a minor action, with an ability with the very unfortunate name of
&lt;strong&gt;Voodoo&lt;/strong&gt;. There are three possible effects: the &lt;strong&gt;Glorious Head&lt;/strong&gt; blinds, the
&lt;strong&gt;Wasting Head&lt;/strong&gt; weakens, and the &lt;strong&gt;Bewildering Head&lt;/strong&gt; forces the target to make
a melee basic attack against an ally in reach. After attacking, the totemist can
shift 1 square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; does light necrotic damage and inflicts a -2 penalty to
saves, which helps that blindness or weakness last longer. And finally we have
&lt;strong&gt;Fresh Rage&lt;/strong&gt;, a passive trait that makes their first succesfful attack in
their turn deal extra damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-blinder&quot;&gt;Fomorian Blinder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-blinder.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blinders have more specialized and discerning tastes than totemists. They
collect &lt;em&gt;eyes&lt;/em&gt; instead of lugging whole heads around. Blinders are the scholars
and sages of fomorian-kind, acting as repositories of their civilization’s
lore. They’re also very good at eye-based magic - if anyone knows how to make a
defense against the Evil Eye, it’s them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blinders are Level 20 Elite Artillery with 296 HP. They use &lt;strong&gt;quarterstaffs&lt;/strong&gt;
for melee combat but their forte is eye magic. &lt;strong&gt;Acid Eye&lt;/strong&gt; is a ranged attack
that deals acid and necrotic damage, and whose enervating properties prevent the
use of encounter or daily powers for a turn. &lt;strong&gt;Shower of Ichor&lt;/strong&gt; (encounter)
deals the same damage over a wider area, and also inflicts ongoing acid and
necrotic damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blinder’s actual &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; is quite powerful: it does no damage by
itself, but someone cursed by it will take the same damage the fomorian inflicts
on other enemies with their other attacks. It ends when the victim saves
successfully, or when the fomorian uses this on someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, blinders have no abilities that actually blind people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fomorian-butcher&quot;&gt;Fomorian Butcher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-mm2-4e-fomorian-butcher.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2009 Wizards of the Coast
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Butchers are big fomorians with big blades who like to cut people up for
fun. Such simplicity is a bit disappointing after we saw all those esoterically
evil fomorian casters and assassins, but they’re still very dangerous and just
as ambitious. In fact, they go to absurd lengths to fulfill their serial-killer
urges, and will often trade their souls to devils and make other dangerous deals
in exchange for more power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Butchers are Level 22 Elite Brutes with 514 HP. They use titan-sized
&lt;strong&gt;falchions&lt;/strong&gt;, which are High-Crit weapons. They’re all about focusing on a
single victim and hacking them apart with repeated strikes: when they score a
critical, they can make another free attack with the falchion against the same
victim, and their attacks deal a bunch of extra damage against a victim they
already hit earlier in the same turn. Their &lt;strong&gt;Evil Eye&lt;/strong&gt; restrains (save ends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways they can get that extra damage from a “subsequent” hit:
the bonus attack from a critical, spending an action point to attack again, and
I’d say hitting with the Evil Eye also counts for this. So they’ll always try
that before swinging their blades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-encounters-and-final-impressions&quot;&gt;Sample Encounters and Final Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the sample encounters here are “Assorted Fomorians” from this book and
the MM. One of them also involves drow and Lolthbound Goblins. Generally
speaking you can also frequently find fomorians accompanied by cyclops slaves,
or by other evil fey they’ve enslaved or allied with. Devils could also make an
appearance, since it seems Fomorian diabolists are somewhat common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lot is quite a bit more flavorful than the fomorians in the MM, and the
extra lore does justice to the basics laid down by the first book. “Voodoo” is a
very unfortunate name for an ability, but it’s easy enough to change.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/25/fomorian.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2021/08/25/fomorian.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
