<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 14:40:09 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 14:40:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Iliyanbruen Guardian</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-neverwinter-dead-eladrin-guardian.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, so back in Olden Times there was an elven empire named Illefarn that
reached as far as the North. Over the course of history this empire broke up
into three successor states. The one that covered our current region of interest
was named Iliyanbruen. This is important because if you get the two confused the
surviving eladrin of Iliyanbruen will tut-tut at you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, when Netheril’s magic winked out, one of their floating islands fell on
the Neverwinter Wood. This was a disaster for both the humans living on the
island and the nation of Iliyanbruen that happened to be beneath it. Many of its
inhabitants decided to call it quits and move to Evermeet, which means more or
less leaving the world behind for good. Others decided to try and preserve their
culture, and enacted a ritual to move their capital city of Shandarar to the
Feywild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their new home was anything but safe, though, as a lot of the same beings who
had driven the original elves away from the Feywild at the dawn of time were
still there and they didn’t like the arrival of these invaders one bit. After a
period of strife, though, the elves managed to re-establish their nation there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iliyanbruen still exists in the modern day, its borders a ways away from the
place where Shandarar used to be. With the coming of the Spellplague, the world
and the Feywild began to enter in conjunction, which made the crossing once
again possible. After a lengthy battle to drive a covey of hags away from
Shandarar, the eladrin managed to send scouts and explorers though to the
world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side note, I don’t know if the people of Iliyanbruen became eladrin after
millennia of living in the Feywild or if they were already a type of elf that
got recast as eladrin when the editions changed. We’ll be looking into some of
those later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, upon arriving at the world, the eladrin of Iliyanbruen were horrified to
learn the old ruins of their empire were not only in a state of disrepair but
had also been looted and plundered. They were quite mad about it. You leave your
stuff lying around for a mere three thousand years and these uppity mortals
think they can come and take it. What an outrage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eladrin of New Shandarar began debating what to do and soon fell into two
distinct camps. One faction wants to invade the world in force and rain
vengeance upon anyone who lingers near the ruins of Iliyanbruen (i.e, everyone
in our regional map). The other also wants to restore the old cities to their
glory, but only wants to take revenge on the people directly responsible for the
thefts. This does require learning who these people are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC is one of the investigators responsible for finding this out. They helped
retake Sharandar from the hags, were among the first to arrive on the world, and
decided to make it their home as they try to reconstruct the history of the
ruins and find the thieves. They belong to the moderate faction, and as the
campaign starts they’re getting desperate for results because the firebrands
back home are about to win the debate. They need concrete results, and fast, if
the world is to avoid an eladrin invasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even worse, the main obstacle to their investigation isn’t the ludicrously large
time scale. No, it seems there’s someone out there actively trying to prevent
eladrin investigators from finding anything out, usually by murdering them. It’s
dangerous to go alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theme is open to eladrin PCs of any class. Not all inhabitants of modern
Iliyanbruen are eladrin, but all of the features and powers here are aimed at
powering up their Fey Step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 1, PC can take one adjacent ally with them when they use Fey Step. The
ally also appears adjacent to the PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 5, they gain a +2 power bonus to History and Nature checks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 10, they can use Fey Step as a minor action instead of a move
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-powers&quot;&gt;Optional Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these are yet more teleport-related power-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blink Away&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 2 encounter power that lets the PC teleport 2 squares
as a reaction to an enemy ending their turn adjacent to the PC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evasive Step&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 6 daily power that lets then use Fey Step as an
interrupt if an enemy attacks them while Fey Step is unexpended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feywild Will&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 10 daily power that gives the PC a +2 power bonus to
Will and to saving throws until the end of the encounter. Whenever the PC
succeeds at a save while this is active, they gain 5 + WIS Modifier temporary
HP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peeking ahead a bit I see Forgotten Realms’ Moon and Sun elves are eladrin
variants in 4e. I remember they were both huge assholes, so it’s not a surprise
the eladrin of Iliyanbruen are just as unpleasant even if they’re only their
distant relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most other PCs would be very interested in preventing an invasion from
Iliyanbruen from adding to their troubles, so they’re natural allies of the
moderate Guardian. And this is another one of those themes that easily supports
multiple PCs, or even a whole mono-theme party (it’s a &lt;em&gt;team&lt;/em&gt; of
investigators). Such a party would be mostly uninterested in Neverwinter’s
political woes, except where they intersect with their quest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to optimize for the ability to do Teleport Shenanigans, this is the
theme for you. Little could stop a whole party of them from getting to where
they want to go. For other campaigns, it would also be relatively easy to strip
the standard Iliyanbruen backstory and just say a PC with this theme is a native
of the Feywild who moved to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/09/neverwinter-eladrin-guardian.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/09/neverwinter-eladrin-guardian.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Dead Rat Deserter</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-neverwinter-dead-rat-deserter.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luskan is a coastal city a ways north of Neverwinter. In the games, it was a
pirate and thief-infested cesspool secretly ruled by a cabal of evil
wizards. The evil wizards were defeated in a novel before the start of the
events in this book, so now it’s just exactly what it always appeared to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dead Rats are currently the most successful thieves’ guild in Luskan. They
have this name because their senior members are wererats, and their initiation
ceremony involves a ritual that imparts some wererat powers to the
initiate. Their leader is a halfling bard named Toytere, also known as “King
Toy”, who seems to have the power to see the future and uses it to foil the many
assassination attempts made on him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PC with this background used to be an average member of the Rats until they
were brought in before King Toy, who proclaimed the PC was destined to lead a
mutiny against him and ordered their execution. This was news to the PC, who
barely made it out of the room alive and managed to abscond to Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their original goal here was to build enough wealth and power to return to
Luskan and take revenge on those who wronged them, but this might have changed
by the time the campaign starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dead Rat Deserter PCs are usually shifty and shady types, though they’re loyal
to their friends (who include the other PCs). While rogues are the first to come
to mind, there aren’t any class restrictions. Characters should be either
humans, half-elves, or halflings, since those are the majority ancestries in
Luskan and make up all of the Dead Rat membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The background skills for this theme are Intimidate, Stealth, and Thievery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t need a theme just to make a shifty character with a shady criminal
past, so why choose this one? Because it also lets you be a &lt;em&gt;wererat&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level 1 feature is &lt;strong&gt;Body of the Rat&lt;/strong&gt;, an 1/round minor-action at-will
power that lets the PC assume the form of a Tiny rat. The same power also lets
them change back, and whenever they change shape they can also shift 1
square. In rat form, the PC can’t attack but gains a climb speed equal to half
their ground speed and a +4 to Stealth checks. The PC’s equipment melds into the
rat form, and continues to provide all of its passive benefits. There are a few
exceptions: they don’t get AC bonuses from shields, can’t use active item
powers, and can’t access any containers (like bags or potion vials). On the
other hand, their equipment can’t be removed in any way while it’s part of the
rat form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 5, the PC gains a +2 power bonus to Stealth and Bluff. This is useful
for a rogue-type, but would be much better if it was untyped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Level 10, &lt;strong&gt;Hybrid Bite&lt;/strong&gt; lets the PC assume the classic hybrid wererat
form. Changing back and forth is an at-will minor action, like above, and the
character retains all their equipment and can use it normally. The hybrid form
has the same size as the character. The character also gains a bite attack. The
attack bonus for this is (STR or DEX modifier)+4, and the damage is 1d8+(same
modifier) plus 5 ongoing damage (save ends). The bonus increases to +6 and the
damage to 2d8 at level 21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This attack is a little underwhelming, I think. If Strength or Dexterity is your
main attack stat, it’s going to be about on par with a +2 weapon with a +2
proficiency bonus, which means it’s less accurate than the characters’s actual
main weapon if any of those stats are better on it. Ongoing damage on an at-will
is good, but also maybe not as good as the bonuses of a level 10’s character
main weapon and class powers. If you use anything other than STR or DEX to
attack, this power is useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optional powers here are all about tapping into your inner rat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Savage Hiss&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 2 encounter power that helps intimidate enemies in a
fight. When the PC scores a critical hit, they can use this power to inflict
every enemy within 5 squares with a -4 penalty to attack the PC for a turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dead Rat Stealth&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 6 daily power that takes a minor action and
gives the PC a +2 power bonus to Stealth and Thievery for the rest of the
encounter. If the PC dislikes a roll for one of these skills, they can end the
effect and reroll it with a +5 power bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuitive Leap&lt;/strong&gt; is a Level 10 daily power that represents the PC inheriting
some of King Toy’s prophetic abilities. The PC can use it when it’s time to roll
initiative, gaining a +4 power bonus to the roll and being able to stand up or
move their speed for free at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, this theme suits high-Dex characters the best, since it boosts
Stealth and Thievery and might let a character who lacks both to get access to
one of them. Being able to turn into a normal-looking rat can enable &lt;em&gt;all sorts&lt;/em&gt;
of shenanigans, especially out of combat, but the hybrid form and bite attack
are of dubious utility at best. This is not a theme that will do a lot to boost
your damage output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Story-wise, I haven’t gotten far enough into the book to see whether Luskan and
the Rats influence Neverwinter in any significant way. It’s possible a Rat would
just be along for the ride if they’re the only one in the party. An &lt;em&gt;all-Rat&lt;/em&gt;
party would result in a significantly different path than those implied by the
other paths we saw so far. They all got set up together and would still retain
their goal of getting rich and powerful enough to return and get some revenge,
likely causing a lot of chaos in Neverwinter in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/06/neverwinter-dead-rat-deserter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/06/neverwinter-dead-rat-deserter.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Harper Agent</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-neverwinter-harper.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I remember, the Harpers used to be a “good conspiracy” back the “old
days” of the Forgotten Realms. A secret society dedicated to doing good,
fighting for freedom, and keeping the many evil factions of the setting in
check. Elminster was a big fan, and several of the setting’s iconic NPCs were
members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those Harpers got destroyed during the Spellplague, but sixty years before our
narrative present a new group took up the name. This incarnation of the group is
mostly focused on stopping the machinations of those Netheril survivors who came
out of the Shadowfell, though they also have their fingers in other pies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PC with this background has a very specific and rather tense backstory. They
always dreamed of joining the Harpers, and traveled to Everlund to apply. They
were given a trial mission - to go to Neverwinter and link up with a woman named
Cymril. Cymril was not only a fully-fledged Harper Agent but also the leader of
the Sons of Alagondar. The Sons are a group of rebels who opposes Dagult
Neverember, and who fight for an independent Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC gets included in night-time recon mission led by Cymril herself, and
their group gets ambushed by a force of Neverember’s mercs. In panic, the PC
hides, and then gets to witness as the rebels are massacred. The thing is,
Cymril herself turned coat as soon as the fight started, and began killing her
own underlings! In the end, the hidden PC is the only survivor on the rebel
side: Cymril gets taken out by one of her lieutenants, who in turn dies to the
mercenaries. They leave the rebels’ bodies on the street as a warning. Our PC as
the foresight to steal Cymril’s Harper pin before absconding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the title of “Harper Agent” is kind of misleading. The PC is actually a
&lt;em&gt;rogue&lt;/em&gt; agent, sympathetic to the organization’s ideals but operating without
their official support. The PC can’t let it become known that they’re not a real
Harper, and even without that secret coming out they’re already facing suspicion
from the very rebel group they were supposed to help, for being the only
survivor of the ambush that killed Cymril.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PC with this background wishes to discover the truth behind that massacre,
prove their innocence, and fulfill their original mission of preventing
Neverember from becoming the cutthroat merchant-king he wishes to be. This theme
brings even more intrigue and spy games into the game than the Neverwinter
Noble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no class or race prerequisites, though the book recommends Harper
characters be good at subterfuge and say many of them multiclass into bard,
rogue, ranger or wizard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This class gains only a single feature: that Harper Pin pried from Cymril’s
corpse. It marks the bearer as a member of the Harpers, brings with it a
blessing from one of their patron goddesses, and can be used as a key to secret
Harper hideouts and caches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, it’s a Rare Level 3 Wondrous Item, which means it doesn’t take up
any slots and can’t be bought in stores. The PC chooses one of three possible
blessings at character creation, and this becomes the pin’s item encounter
power. &lt;strong&gt;Llira’s Grace&lt;/strong&gt; lets them roll 1d6 and add it to an attack roll they
just missed, potentially turning it into a hit. &lt;strong&gt;Mielikki’s Endurance&lt;/strong&gt; lets
them reduce incoming damage from an attack by 5 + half level. And &lt;strong&gt;Tymora’s
Luck&lt;/strong&gt; lets them re-roll a save with a +2 bonus to the new roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This class’s optional utility powers continue to follow the themes of the divine
blessings above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harper’s Healing Boon&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 2 daily power that can be used as an
interrupt when the PC is hit by an attack. They take only half damage from the
attack and can immediately roll a save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unexpected Ally&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 6 power that represents the PC use fast-talk to
trick an enemy into believing the PC is a secret ally of theirs. This means the
enemy can’t make opportunity attacks against the PC and grants combat advantage
to them. The effect ends when the PC attacks the fooled enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resourceful Dastard&lt;/strong&gt; (yes, with a D) is a level 10 daily power. It’s a stance
that gives +4 to all defenses when the PC has cover or concealment, and lets
them ignore all difficult terrain when shifting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theme is very strongly oriented towards rogue, bard, or even ranger PCs, I
feel. Its blessing and utility power can help make these characters less fragile
and more mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A criticism I’d make is that this one is a lot less generic than the other
themes we saw so far. With a background like that, it’s a bit hard to make the
PC anything other than a rogue Harper in the Neverwinter region of the Forgotten
Realms. It’s also almost impossible to have more than one Harper Agent in a
party unless you change that very detailed background and come up with another
reason why they can’t contact out-of-town Harpers for support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Harper Agent in a party has reasons to cozy up to and aid the Neverwinter
Noble, and provides a good hook for the GM to introduce the group to the Sons of
Alagondar (or what’s left of them). Cooperation would not be automatic, since
the Sons distrust the Harper, but it would be a start. The Agent would also try
to convince any other neutral PCs to oppose Neverember.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/05/neverwinter-harper.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/05/neverwinter-harper.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Oghma's Faithful</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-neverwinter-oghmas-faithful.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oghma is the Forgotten Realms god of knowledge and thought, occupying the
roughly the same position as Ioun does in the default 4e setting. This
particular PC is one of his worshipers, and for a while now they’ve been
receiving dreams and visions from the god. These start as nightmares, but soon
the threats are burned away by divine fire and the dreamer finds themselves in a
grand hall where the sound of a water clock can be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meaning of these visions is clear: the faithful must go to Neverwinter and
restore the House of Knowledge, a big temple to Oghma that was destroyed in the
eruption. Neverwinter used to produce famously accurate water clocks, you
see. This, and many of the city’s other lost craft secrets, could be restored
from the temple’s archive, if it still survives. This would help the city’s
reconstruction immensely, and of course bring the worship of Oghma back to the
region in a big way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about as lofty a goal as that of the Noble, though it’s much less
concerned with secular politics. The Faithful is still going to need allies, and
so has a ready-made reason to work together with any other PCs interested in
restoring the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oghma’s Faithful can belong to any race or class. Though the book says the theme
fits divine characters better, the actual powers printed here surprisingly good
for skill-monkeys from all power sources. Essentials Clerics can also pick up an
Oghma domain, shown later. The theme’s background skills are History, Religion,
and Streetwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 1, the Faithful gains the &lt;strong&gt;Understand Language&lt;/strong&gt; power, an encounter
power that lets the PC choose a language they’ve heard or seen in the last 24
hours and become able to understand it until the end of the encounter. Outside
of combat, that would be about 5 minutes, but as this is an encounter power you
might as well consider the PC constantly able to understand that language during
extended exploration sequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 5 the PC gains another power, &lt;strong&gt;Sudden Insight&lt;/strong&gt;, which once per
encounter lets them re-roll a skill check and take the second result. This is
any skill, not just knowledge ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 10, they gain a +4 bonus to Perception checks made “to search”, which I
guess means to actively search for something (such as traps, treasure, or the
right book in the temple’s archive).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, these become additional options when it’s time for the PC to choose
utility powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learned Response&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 2 daily power that lets the PC use the result of
an Insight check as their initiative for that combat. Even to me this feels a
little too narrow in scope, but it does mean the low-Dex cleric will act much
earlier once per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad Idea&lt;/strong&gt; is a Level 6 encounter power which can be used as an interrupt when
an adjacent creature attacks the PC. The PC slides the attacker 2 squares to
another adjacent space, and inflicts a -2 penalty to its attacks and saves for a
turn. Good for melee skirmisher-types like rogues or avengers. Clerics probably
have something better to choose here from their class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tactical Inspiration&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 10 encounter power that lets the PC shift 3
squares to be adjacent to an enemy as a move action, and also allow an ally
within 5 squares to shift 3 squares for free. I could see a warlord or rogue
taking this too, to help gain combat advantage earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feels less spectacular to me than the Neverwinter Noble theme, as I’m not
very enthusiastic about the FR pantheon. Mechanics-wise, it’s mostly about
improving your skill checks, which can be awesome in the sort of campaign
suggested by this book where you can have plenty of non-combat investigative and
intrigue scenarios. It’s probably not going to do much for your combat
effectiveness, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple PCs with this background are very easy to accommodate in the same
party, as they would all share a common cause and would have every reason to
work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-neverwinter-blues-brothers.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    See? It's quite easy.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/02/oghmas-faithful.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/05/02/oghmas-faithful.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Neverwinter Noble</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-neverwinter-noble.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that Neverwinter is on the way to being restored, Lord Dagult Neverember of
Waterdeep has arrived to take control. He claims to be a distant relation of the
old rulers of Neverwinter, and has declared himself Lord Protector of the city
until “order is fully restored”. He’s backed by an army of mercenaries, and
everyone expects him to crown himself king once he stamps out resistance to his
rule and controls the whole city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people suspect his claim to the throne is a lie. You are completely
sure it’s bunk, because &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; are the true heir to the throne of
Neverwinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are the child of a noblewoman who escaped the city as it was being
destroyed, shortly before you were born. She would succumb to her wounds and her
grief shortly after having you, and you would be adopted by the Thann noble
house in Waterdeep. You were given a proper noble education and consumed a
steady diet of heroic poems and epics. They told you about your true heritage
shortly after Dagult took over Neverwinter, and by the time the campaign starts
you have decided to seek your birthright there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a lofty goal, and a difficult one: you need strong allies, and the sort
of conclusive evidence for your claim that can only be found in the ruins of the
city. It’s up to you whether the other PCs know of your heritage or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverwinter Nobles must be at least &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; human, because the historical lords
of the city were human. The powers suit melee defenders and give them a leaderly
bent, but there are no hard class prerequisites. The background skills are
Diplomacy and History.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level 1 feature is an extra encounter power named &lt;strong&gt;Take Heart, Friend!&lt;/strong&gt;,
which lets you use your lordly charisma to rally a comrade. It’s a minor-action
encounter power that gives an ally within 5 squares a +2 power bonus to all
defenses and 5/tier temporary HP. The “5/tier” bit means it would remain useful
even after the projected level range for this campaign, which is a nice touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level 5 and 10 features are less flashy, which follows the usual design
formula for themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 5, when you flank an enemy your allies gain a +1 power bonus to attack
that enemy. This does stack with the usual +2 bonus from combat advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At level 10, you are probably close to claiming the throne and your regal mien
is obvious for any to see. You gain a +4 bonus to Diplomacy when interacting
with citizens of Neverwinter, and a +4 bonus to Intimidate against anyone who
opposes your rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utility-powers&quot;&gt;Utility Powers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not mandatory, as I’ve said earlier. Rather, they become additional
choices alongside class powers whenever the PC would gain an utility power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honorable Challenge&lt;/strong&gt; is a Level 2 encounter power that requires a minor
action. It gives you an aura 2 that lasts a turn. Enemies inside take a -2
penalty to attack anyone other than you. In other words, it’s a wider Defender’s
Aura that lasts for a single round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover Your Ally&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 6 encounter power. When an ally within 3 squares
of you is attacked, and you are not a target of the attack, you can swap places
with your ally as an interrupt, and become the new target of the
attack. Castling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pillar of Lordly Might&lt;/strong&gt; is a level 10 daily power. It’s a move action that
gives you a +2 to all defenses and a +5 to Diplomacy, but also immobilizes
you. This lasts for a turn but can be sustained with minor actions. Great for
all those Thou Shall Not Pass moments, and it might even allow you to negotiate
peace in the middle of a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly don’t have a lot of skill at gauging the effectiveness of PC powers
in 4e. These seem cool to me. They do work much better for melee defenders, and
here they work equally well for Essentials and PHB classes. I like it that none
of the powers involves attack rolls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the theme’s mechanical effectiveness, it gains major points for me
because you get to become the ruler of Neverwinter if you follow the built-in
story and succeed at it! Very few of the GMs I’ve known would just let a PC be
the True Heir to the Throne if they asked it. Here, it’s just a character option
anyone can take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, multiple characters in the party could take this theme. Perhaps the
mother had twins, or perhaps you had multiple nobles who fled to Waterdeep with
small or unborn children. This being 4e, I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; recommend using this as
an excuse for deadly intra-party conflict. After all, Dagult Neverember is
already there to provide proper opposition to the PCs. Rather, players of
multiple nobles should probably agree on who has the actual claim to the throne
and who “merely” stands to inherit an estate and become a trusted advisor to the
monarch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/30/neverwinter-noble.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/30/neverwinter-noble.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter: Character Themes Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2 - Character Options is the one players will be most interested in, and
the reason the book strongly recommends creating new characters to play a
Neverwinter campaign. It’s divided into four major sections: Character Themes,
Racial Backgrounds, New Domains, and the Bladesinger class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we’ll introduce the concept of character themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-theme&quot;&gt;What is a Theme?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Character Themes are described here as the “third pillar” that defines your
character alongside race and class. I also describe them as the “thing” you have
in your Heroic Tier, just like Paragon Paths are the “thing” in Paragon and Epic
Destinies are the “thing” in Epic. They were first introduced in Dark Sun, and I
think we also got a few generic ones in Dragon before this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, themes are meant to give each character special knowledge and social ties
that firmly ground them in the Neverwinter campaign. Unlike a character class, a
theme is a thing that always exists and is acknowledged in the setting. People
will never really call you “a fighter”, but they will definitely notice if you
happen to be the lost heir to the throne of Neverwinter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from these narrative hooks, a theme also has several mechanical
widgets. At levels 1, 5 and 10, you gain a &lt;strong&gt;Feature&lt;/strong&gt; specified by your theme,
which gets added on top of everything you already gain from your class. It gives
you access to a few optional &lt;strong&gt;utility powers&lt;/strong&gt; which you can take instead of a
class power at levels 2, 6 and 10. And it also works like the &lt;strong&gt;backgrounds&lt;/strong&gt;
from the Dungeon Master’s Guide 2: each theme lists a handful of skills, and you
pick one. If it’s already a class skill you get a +2 bonus to it. If it’s not
you can make it into a class skill, and become able to choose it during
character creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These features and powers can act to reinforce a character’s mechanical roles,
or to broaden it in ways that weren’t possible before. The narrative bits can
provide excellent reasons for the party to work together beyond the usual “you
all meet in a tavern”. They’re not exclusive either. Several PCs can pick the
same theme, and you could theoretically have a party where everyone does
that. Some of the themes are better for this than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, themes are entirely optional. A heroic-tier character without a
theme would be just as viable. In practice, I’ve never seen anyone refuse to
choose a theme once they became widely available. A hypothethical edition that
refined the concepts of 4e would probably include them right in the PHB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few posts will be dedicated to looking at the Neverwinter Campaign
Setting themes in detail, and we’ll start with the most spectacular one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/28/character-options.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/28/character-options.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Neverwinter! Chapter 01: Jewel of the North</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/neverwinter-map.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another introductory chapter that goes into a little more detail about
the setting, but not too much more. It starts with a summary of the relevant
places in the region, then moves on to the obligatory super-long historical
timeline, and ends by offering campaign advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;neverwinter&quot;&gt;Neverwinter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite assuring the reader that no knowledge of the wider Forgotten Realms,
this section kind of assumes you’re familiar with the region already, probably
from reading the Forgotten Realms Campaign Setting. Having played the
Neverwinter Nights games was enough for me, but as they’re very much In the Past
at this point I would have preferred if they assumed no prior knowledge and had
a more basic summary of the region. In the following paragraphs I try to
summarize it for people who wouldn’t necessarily have prior FR kwowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neverwinter is a coastal city-state located in a region referred to as “The
North”, with seems to be a typical Frozen North type of deal but with less
vikings. It’s built on the mouth of the Neverwinter River, which is warmed by
underground heat sources and thus never freezes. This makes the city’s port
viable year-round, and brings it great wealth from trade. A series of canny
lords invested this wealth to make a solid industrial base for the city and
strengthen its defenses. It became a beacon of prosperity and stability in a
dangerous region full of monsters and slumbering ancient threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computer games end up being mostly about keeping it that way, but in this
book all of this is in the distant past. The Neverwinter in our book is a
destroyed city struggling to get back on its feet and threatened by foreign
interests and evil conspiracies alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Forgotten Realms setting has a tradition of marking edition transitions with
world-shaking metaplot events, which usually try to give in-setting explanations
for why the rules changed. They tend to make lasting changes to the world’s
geography and pantheon, usually involving the death of the current goddess of
magic. The big change that heralded 4e was The Spellplague, which caused a bunch
of horrible mutations and a planar conjunction that brought in a whole continent
from a parallel dimension. That was a hundred years ago, and it actually didn’t
affect Neverwinter all that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What destroyed the city was the eruption of the nearby Mount Hotenow, about
thirty years ago. The eruption caused a river of pyroclastic magma to flow
through the city, killing half its population outright and leveling whole
districts. Over the next decades, the people who fled the city began to return,
along with new waves of opportunists who came to loot and decided to stay, and
together they’ve managed to start rebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still plenty of scars from the eruption, including a huge chasm torn
into the earth, but Neverwinter managed to rebuild enough that it drew the
attention of one Dagult Neverember. This guy is one of the Lords of Waterdeep, a
big metropolis to the south, and he has an expansionist streak a mile wide. He
arrived with a dubious lineage claim and a mercenary army, and then declared
himself the Lord Protector of Neverwinter, clearly intent on adding the city to
his personal domain. The people who live here are divided over whether that’s a
good or a bad thing, and it’s one of the main plots of the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-nearby-locations&quot;&gt;Other Nearby Locations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several other places in the region should be familiar to Neverwinter Nights
players, though the combined damage from the Spellplague and the eruption means
they’re generally in a worse situation than they were back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of smaller towns and cities have simply been emptied or abandoned.  Port
Llast became a ghost town after its port was ruined by the appearance of the
nearby continent of Abeir. The mages that ran Luskan were killed off by Drizzt
in some novel, and now the city is just the pirate-riddled cesspool it always
appeared to be. Other towns and locations that were important because they
facilitated regional trade were abandoned after the destruction of Neverwinter
halted that trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mysterious Neverwinter Wood now contains both an eladrin city returned from
the Feywild (Sharandar), an ancient sky island crawling with remnants of its
original owners returned from the Shadowfell (Xinlenal), &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; an incomplete
necromantic fortress of unspeakable evil inhabited by people trying to complete
it (the Dread Ring). The Mere of Dead Men has grown bigger and more dangerous,
making it harder for supplies or help to arrive by land from the south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are legends of some ancient dwarven city named Gauntlgrym, but no one has
managed to find it yet. And then you have your standard stretches of hills and
mountains infested with ogres and dragons. The general thrust of this section is
that the Frozen North has gotten even more “frontier-ish” and dangerous than it
already was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;regional-history&quot;&gt;Regional History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Neverwinter is extremely focused on the region’s current situation, it
wouldn’t be a FR setting book if it didn’t include a historical timeline
stretching back tens of thousands of years. I’ll try to summarize this whole
thing and focus on the bits that are relevant to today’s adventurers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In very ancient times this region was dominated by an &lt;strong&gt;elven empire&lt;/strong&gt;
(Iliyanbruen), which after thousands of years of hegemony fell after fighting
back an enormous orcish invasion. Most of its inhabitants called it quits and
“traveled West” much like Tolkien’s elves do, but some of them fled into the
Feywild instead. These refugees built a city over there, and this is relevant
because that city has returned to the world and is the region’s main source of
eladrin characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the time of the elven empire, you also had a &lt;strong&gt;dwarven empire&lt;/strong&gt;
(Delzoun), which had several big underground cities in here. Its fabled capital
was Gauntlgrym, which started out as a big mine and got converted into a city
later. The empire collapsed after the big orcish invasion and the underground
mind flayer invasion that followed. This is relevant because it leaves a whole
bunch of lost dwarven ruins underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also had a &lt;strong&gt;human empire&lt;/strong&gt; (Netheril) that was ruled by archmages who loved
to show their power by building flying islands. This one fell quite suddenly due
to Metaplot Shenanigans elsewhere in the world, and one of their flying islands
crashed into the Neverwinter Wood. It’s still there! The survivors from this
empire are the ancestors of most of the present-day humans native to the
region. This includes the Uthgardt barbarians, but also other groups. Some of
these survivors settled the city of Illusk, which would become present-day
Luskan after being sacked and rebuilt a few dozen times. Neverwinter would be
founded much later by other descendants of Netheril who first settled islands to
the west and then sailed here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Modern-day developments” section includes quite a few spoilers, so players
beware! I do find it cute that it made a point to mention the plot of the first
Neverwinter Nights as a significant historical event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, after the Spellplague pulled the Realms into Fourth Edition, the
descendants of Netheril survivors who had fled to the Plane of Shadow came back
and started conspiring to take over the region by infiltrating Neverwinter’s
power structure. They got sidetracked when another conspiracy crashed into
theirs, but are still hanging around the ruins of that flying city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That crashing conspiracy is a doozy, by the way: a bunch of evil wizards (the
Red Wizards of Thay) tried to build a necromantic fortress of ultimate evil in
the Neverwinter Wood and &lt;em&gt;caused the volcanic eruption&lt;/em&gt; to destroy Neverwinter
and use the deaths to power the fortress. Their plan was foiled (probably in a
novel), so the fortress was never completed. It’s still there,
half-finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gauntlgrym is lost but still inhabited, and over the last few centuries it
changed hands several times. The current owners are duergar. Its big secret is
that it houses a slumbering primordial (Maegera the Inferno), who in ancient
times was used as a geothermal power source by the dwarves and the mages of old
Illusk, who cooperated on the operation of the power plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;running-a-neverwinter-campaign&quot;&gt;Running a Neverwinter Campaign&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section describes how the book works as a tool for running a campaign. It
restates much of what was said in the introduction, and it does so in a way that
makes it clear it’s taking a different tack from your traditional FR supplement
or adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we already know, it focuses on the Neverwinter region; it also only includes
details that are useful sources of inspiration rather than trying to list the
names of every innkeeper in the city. The characters presented in the book are
active and won’t sit around waiting to respond to the PCs. The PCs, in turn,
will have access to character themes that will get them involved in the campaign
right away. The campaign is also open-ended - it doesn’t assume an end state
that the characters must work towards. PCs are free to set their own goals,
confident that their actions will have an actual impact on events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a text box here that should make critics of previous versions of the
setting quite happy: it’s titled “Killable Villains”. It says that while it
might make sense to stat up the main villains of the campaign as epic threats
due to the scope and reach of their machinations, this often results in the
players feeling like they can never truly defeat those villains until they are
themselves epic. Until then, they remain trapped in conflict with an endless
series of underlings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason, every opponent here, even the main villains was given stats
that are “within reach” of heroic tier adventurers. While some of those major
villains might make for tough boss fights for 10th-level characters, those
characters still have a chance of defeating them. Of course, GMs who want to
stretch their campaigns beyond the heroic tier are free to level those villains
up or use other appropriate stat blocks for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GM advice for running the campaign centers mostly around being flexible. There
are a lot of plot threads flying around, so it’s okay to remind players of where
things stand (from their PC’s point of view) if they get lost. It’s also okay to
&lt;em&gt;change the facts&lt;/em&gt; of the campaign if your players end up coming to a “wrong”
conclusion during their investigations - particularly if their theories are more
fun than what’s written on the book! And finally, it’s okay to do what feels
right even if it contradicts what’s been written. Don’t sweat it if you forget
some detail and end up changing it in play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the book really recommends that players make new characters for this
campaign, so that they can take advantage of the several themes available to
them. It does have some advice for bringing existing characters into the
campaign, but my feeling is that this is a very sub-optimal approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impressions&quot;&gt;Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not the biggest knower or enjoyer of the broader Forgotten Realms setting,
but I do have good memories from the games, so a lot of the places mentioned
here were familiar to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the emphasis the book put, both in its introduction and here, on the
fact that your PCs will get the chance to do important and world-shaking things
on their own, and that even the top villains of the piece have no plot armor and
are defeatable. There’s a reason why I often refer to an excess of invincible
official NPCs as “The Elminster problem”, and I’m happy to know they’ll be
trying to avoid it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The material here does a lot to bring this region closer to the “points of
light” model prevalent in 4e, as a lot of what used to be safe places are just
&lt;em&gt;gone&lt;/em&gt;, and there are a lot more dangerous ones. There’s quite a lot going on in
the Neverwinter Wood, and inside Neverwinter proper as well. I could have done
without that timeline section and its attempts at summarizing novels, but I
suspect we’ll see more details about the region’s present situation soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/24/neverwinter-chapter-01.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/24/neverwinter-chapter-01.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read the Neverwinter Campaign Setting!</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/wir-neverwinter-cover.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Copyright 2011 Wizards of the Coast.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I started writing this post, I was convinced the &lt;strong&gt;Neverwinter Campaign
Setting&lt;/strong&gt; was the last setting book for D&amp;amp;D 4th Edition. Turns out there were
two more published in the following year, one for Undermountain and another for
Menzonberranzan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t even remember these books existed, which I guess makes sense since they
seem to have a much narrower potential audience. Neverwinter, in contrast, is
probably the most famous place in the Forgotten Realms, and at the time of this
book’s release in 2011 it was even known to a lot of people who were outside of
the FR fan community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s because by that point in time the city had already been the setting for
two successful computer games! Neverwinter Nights came out in 2002. It’s the
game that put Bioware on the map, and it didn’t take long for it to develop a
huge trove of fan-created modules and expansions, in addition to the official
ones it got in the years following its release. The sequel was developed by
Obsidian and came out in 2006, and though it was less open to fan additions it
kept getting expansions up to 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there was also the &lt;em&gt;third&lt;/em&gt; big game featuring Neverwinter, the MMORPG of the
same name. It was developed concurrently with the book, something the book
itself makes a point of advertising in a side box in its introduction. I think
the book came out a little earlier than the game, because delays are a fact of
life in video game development, but they’re much more integrated than I thought
at first. The MMO is still active as of this writing, over a decade after its
launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the Neverwinter Campaign Setting is also perfectly capable of
standing on its own merits. It places a much greater emphasis on the “campaign”
part of “campaign setting”, which was a novel approach when it came out and
influenced the presentation of most 5e campaign books too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-books-introduction&quot;&gt;The Book’s Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very first thing we see after the table of contents is an Introduction
chapter that explains its approach in a very concise manner. The book cover the
city of Neverwinter and its immediate surroundings, focusing on a small area of
a larger, already-published setting (Forgotten Realms). It’s not a static atlas
or travelogue - it’s a tool for running a campaign. It’s meant to be easy for a
GM to customize, and its player options help build PCs that are deeply involved
with several big plots that can make permanent changes to the setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is geared towards the Heroic tier (levels 1-10), so all threats and
challenges in the area are appropriate for characters of those levels. This
includes the main villains of the piece. Your PCs will not be stuck fighting the
grunts and flunkies of some epic-level villain. They will get to face legendary
threats on their own, without any overpowered NPCs around to bail them out or to
steal the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m paraphrasing the book here, and I like that these assurances are right on
the first page. It’s an important thing to include when dealing with the
Forgotten Realms, which has been traditionally full of untouchable epic villains
and scene-stealing epic NPCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The also emphasizes that the situation presented in its pages is a starting
point - it’s a situation that will quickly begin changing as soon as the actual
game starts. The PCs are not only expected but &lt;em&gt;encouraged&lt;/em&gt; to get in there and
meddle with things. There is plenty of intrigue going on and adventure hooks are
everywhere, but the story itself is not on rails. Just as the PCs are encouraged
to change things, the GM is encouraged to adapt to their actions and not try to
force a pre-determined outcome. This is a very nice sentiment! Let’s see if they
manage to uphold it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rules-wise, the book is going to make heavy use of character themes. Themes were
introduced in the Dark Sun Campaign Setting book as a new “thing” to complement
your class in the Heroic tier, just like paragon paths and epic destinies do
later. Dark Sun had several Athas-specific themes, and I think Dragon Magazine
introduced a few other more generic ones later. Neverwinter presents its own set
of themes, which are even more specific than Dark Sun’s - each of them ties into
one of the major plot threads they describe here, and some of them even make the
PC in question the “main character” of that thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for required book, the core set is a given - that can either be the PHB+DMG
duo or the equivalent Essentials set of Rules Compendium and “Heroes of…”
books, though it’s going to place a bit more emphasis on the latter. In both
cases the Monster Vault is recommended over the Monster Manual, and the
Forgotten Realms books (Player’s Guide and Campaign Setting) are nice-to-haves
in order to flesh out the wider setting and give players a few more options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few posts, we’ll be looking a the book chapter by chapter. Some
chapters my take up more than one post. This should take a lot less time than
the monster books did, but I hope you enjoy it just the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/23/neverwinter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/23/neverwinter.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>neverwinter</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fuzzy turns in GURPS Combat</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As you might know from reading here before, I hang out on the RPG.net forums a
lot. Whenever a discussion about GURPS starts there, some people often complain
they feel intimidated or annoyed by the 1-second combat turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other games tend to have a less granular concept of turn duration and of what
exactly constitutes an action, so players used to them usually expect to be able
to do one “complete thing” in each turn without bothering with detailed setup
steps. For example, a ranged attack with a bow in D&amp;amp;D takes a single action that
includes aiming, shooting, drawing a new arrow, and nocking it, all of which are
distinct steps in GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually like 1-second turns and will be keeping them in my games, but I
present here a possible way to make them fuzzier for those groups who don’t
enjoy them as much. This is a fairly fundamental change to the base GURPS
system, probably lends itself better to games that used simplified combat rules
instead of things like detailed hex maps and range measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also helps combat feel a bit more like what you might see in action movies
or similar media, which tend to slow down things to make them easier to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fuzzy-combat-in-gurps&quot;&gt;Fuzzy Combat in GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this rule, a combat round is no longer exactly 1 second long. Now it takes
an unspecified amount of time between 5 and 10 seconds long - enough for
everyone to act once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-maneuver actions that can be resolved in a 1-second turn under the
original rules still take 1 turn to resolve here. This includes most melee and
ranged attacks, movement, and the Aim and Evaluate maneuvers. Advantages such as
Extra Attack and techniques like Rapid Strike work exactly as written, with the
same limitations, but read “seconds” as “turns”. The RoF stat retains its value
for all weapons that have it, but read it as “shots per turn” instead of “shots
per second”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actions that would take multiple consecutive maneuvers over several turns to
perform now take 1 turn per 10 seconds or fraction thereof they would originally
take. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Swapping magazines on a modern gun took 3 seconds, so now it takes 1 turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reloading a musket took 40 seconds, so it takes 4 turns now.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Any spell that would require less than 10 seconds to cast can be cast in a
single turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Searching through your pack for an item took 2d seconds. As the average of
that roll is less than 10, it only requires a turn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Picking a lock takes a minute, which means 6 turns. Accepting a -5 penalty to
do it in 30 seconds means it takes 3 turns. This makes it possible to do
during a fight.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fast-Draw skill now encompasses a series of actions taken to speed up a
given process. It can reduce the time an appropriate action takes by 1 turn, to
a minimum of 0. So you can still use it to draw a weapon and attack on the same
turn, or to reload a pistol and keep firing on the same turn. That musket is
still going to take 3 turns before it can fire again. You might want to make it
Average instead of Easy since a single roll covers a larger set of actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes make characters such as archers and wizards more powerful in
combat, since the number of things they can do over a given amount of turns has
increased, while melee-focused character can still take more or less the same
number of actions. Note that I have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; tested how these changes interact
with the magic system, so I can’t measure how much of an impact it’s going to
have on spellcasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-we-avoided&quot;&gt;Things we Avoided&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that we didn’t attempt to increase the effective number of actions by the
same multiplier as the turn duration. If a character could attack every second
under the standard rules, they don’t get to make 5-10 attacks in a single turn
here. Aiming or Evaluating for multiple seconds gave you extra bonuses, but you
don’t get them automatically here - you must perform those maneuvers for the
same number of turns. Our goal is to remove multi-step complex procedures, not
to keep counting seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is more abstract and perhaps less realistic, and that is the point. If
you want to keep tracking events second-by-second, stick with the standard
rules.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/19/gurps-fuzzy-turns.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/19/gurps-fuzzy-turns.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I'm done with Threats to the Nentir Vale! Now what?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Wolf Runners were the last monster entry in the book, and after that there’s
only a glossary index. So we’re done with this book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only that, we’re also done with my big project of reading all of the
main D&amp;amp;D 4th monster books. I remember I started it January 1st 2019, with the
first posts going into an RPG.net thread and appearing here shortly
afterwards. So it took us a little over 4 years, 4 months, and 15 days to get it
all done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing all of this was an interesting experience. The idea for the project came
at a time when I was having a bit of a hard time coming up with subjects for
posts to this blog, mainly because I was getting anxious about writing good
articles. I’d think of something, then I’d begin writing, and then I’d get
blocked or mired in an endless round of revisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writting commentary on D&amp;amp;D monsters, in contrast, felt extremely easy. I could
sit down, cover a bunch of entries, and have them ready for a regular release
schedule. Granted, I had a hard time sticking to any sort of schedule for most
of the project’s runtime, but I think I did a pretty good job of it in Threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people who read these entries here in the blog were probably 4e fans
instead of the usual GURPS crowd, unless they happened to follow my RSS feed
directly or something like that. None of those posts had a GURPS tag, so they
didn’t appear in the aggregator I’m a member of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still want to have a ready source of posts for Octopus Carnival, and I also
really like the conversations I had in the RPG.net threads for the project, so
I’m going to begin a new Let’s Read. There’s voting going on in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.rpg.net/index.php?threads/lets-read-threats-to-the-nentir-vale.904788/&quot;&gt;RPG.net
thread&lt;/a&gt; for Threats, with the following candidates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neverwinter Campaign Setting&lt;/strong&gt; for 4e. I have it, and I have opinions about
it, so it’s a good subject.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hell’s Rebels&lt;/strong&gt; for Pathfinder, with commentary about converting it to other
systems. Extremely convenient because I’ve already written a lot about it in
this blog. Might also give me more incentive to actually finish the adventure
path too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dungeon Fantasy Roleplaying Game&lt;/strong&gt;: A large enough effort that I’d need to
give it serious thought. It would probably not be a page-by-page affair, but
it &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; merit the GURPS tag.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check the thread linked above if you want to vote or comment on any of the
entries. Otherwise sit back and enjoy the knowledge that there will soon be a
new thing to occupy your usual Let’s Read slots.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/17/tnv-done.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2023/04/17/tnv-done.html</guid>
        
        <category>dnd4</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>meta</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
