<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Octopus Carnival</title>
    <description>A repository of my English language RPG-related writings. Mostly GURPS with a smattering of other systems.
</description>
    <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 16:26:59 -0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 16:26:59 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>GURPS X-COM: Second Research Phase</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/xcom__extraction_by_antimingebag-d9abdgp.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=http://antimingebag.deviantart.com/art/XCOM-Extraction-561522409&gt;
      Illustration by AntiMingebag on DeviantArt
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The intrepid soldiers of my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/gurps-xcom-reports/&quot;&gt;X-COM campaign&lt;/a&gt; have just completed their second
field op and returned alive but not unharmed. They discovered and explored a
huge Forest of Woe in southeastern Brazil, met a new and more dangerous type of
enemy, and brought back what seems to be an alien defector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I once again invited the players to step out of character for a
while, and we entered the game’s second strategic/research phase. The bonus
event they got this time was a debriefing of the alien refugee, because Sokolov
was their head scientist. Had it been one of the others, this would have been a
normal research choice and would cost points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-event-the-refugee&quot;&gt;Bonus Event: The Refugee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alien is around 1.5m tall, and quite skinny. Its body is covered in a dark
purple, chitinous carapace, over which it wears clothes. It has four arms and
two legs, and moves in a somewhat discomforting and “twitchy” fashion. Its seems
to wear a mask, as there is a clear seam between its face and the rest of its
head, but this “mask” is soft and warm and almost human-like, and moves like it
was a natural face. It’s a strong royal blue in color. The alien’s eyes are
yellow with black pupils, and it has a very pronounced nose. This being does not
have a gender as humans conceive of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a genderless alien who wants to come and meet us, it was inevitable that the
refugee would receive the code-name of Ziggy (from David Bowie’s Ziggy
Stardust). Despite Dr. Vahlen’s strenuous protests, Dr. Sokolov elected to
debrief X-COM’s new guest by personally interviewing Ziggy, since it was capable
of communicating in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ziggy’s use of grammar was quite peculiar, and it refused to use the pronoun
“I”. Sokolov soon found out the movements of its mouth didn’t match what it
seemed to be saying, and recordings of the interview only showed it speaking the
same alien language the PCs had heard over their comms multiple times. As a
result, the interviews were all transcribed the old-fashioned way, using the
services of a stenographer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ziggy gave X-COM some basic organizational information on their opposition: they
were made up of multiple alien species, some from previously conquered worlds
and some engineered for war. The leaders of this force called themselves the
Ebon Masters, and arrived on Earth through “gates”. The trees were part of a
weaponized, artificial ecosystem it called “The Moon Flower”. Ziggy had been
only a civilian clerk in the employ of the Masters, so he wasn’t able to provide
much in the way of specific strategic detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ziggy also referred to something called “The One Power” several times, and said
none of the species previously conquered by the Masters had such an advanced
mastery of it. Figuring that misunderstanding out quickly revealed that the
advanced alien technology on display so far was, in fact, magic, and that humans
were totally ignorant of it. Ziggy became as fascinated by this revelation as
Sokolov was about the existence of magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the rest of the alien Masters, Ziggy’s look and culture are a mashup of the
original Ethereals from X-COM and the devils from the
excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://killsixbilliondemons.com/&quot;&gt;Kill Six Billion Demons&lt;/a&gt; comic. It’s the equivalent of a Blue
Devil, so low-ranked but quite intelligent. Ziggy also has a &lt;em&gt;conscience&lt;/em&gt;, which
makes it nearly unique among its species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/cio.png&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  A blue devil from the Kill Six Billion Demons comic.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole “friendly alien helps X-COM” idea sprung from a My Little Pony fanfic,
of all places. That story is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fimfiction.net/story/100455/stardust&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you’re curious, and though it becomes
a bit muddled later on its premise was interesting enough that I decided to
recycle it with a more campaign-appropriate alien.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/ddv4-1432482453-100455-full.jpeg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
  Also I didn't have the heart to replicate this scene.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-options&quot;&gt;Research Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, the players had 2 research points to allocate. Their options were the
following, with the ones in italics being new:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cutting-Edge Research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advanced Medkit (this was Vahlen’s “free” project”) 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal-scale combat drones (this was Shen’s “free” project) 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project Stardust&lt;/em&gt; (Employ Ziggy as part of the research staff and harness the
One Power) 0/2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alien Artifacts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pinnochio (Puppet of Ruin) corpse 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rosie (Bakegumo) corpse 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alien guns 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alien swords 0/1
 -Alien Explosives (from grenades/RPG rounds) 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Black Trees&lt;/em&gt; (Study those substantial Black Tree pieces) 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Red Dust&lt;/em&gt; (It’s sprinkled over every alien body and artifact, as you’ve
discovered earlier) 0/1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group discussed this for a while. Two new players had joined the group at
this time, and they provided their input as well. In the end, Project Stardust
won out. It was the equivalent of researching psionics in the computer games,
and it was even more vital here than in the original material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-one-power-setting-information&quot;&gt;The One Power: Setting Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Ziggy called “The One Power” is the ability to cause direct changes to
physical reality by visualizing them in extreme detail and willing them into
existence. It’s called that by the Ebon Masters because they never before had
encountered a civilization that managed to achieve more than a medieval level of
technology without resorting to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ziggy’s description of the theoretical underpinnings of the One Power match a
lot of human occult lore, sharing several similarities with Kabbalah and
Pythagorean numerology among other sources. Manifesting a given effect requires
modeling it through an equation in the alien numerological system, and then
repeatedly solving it in one’s mind. Using it in practice requires more than an
active imagination and skill at mathematics, however!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical scans show Ziggy’s body is permeated by an extensive network of
circuit-like metallic filaments, made from the same materials detected in the
tree fragments. These are naturally occurring in every species capable of using
the One Power, according to the alien. These “circuits” act as a conduit for it,
and take on some of the work of processing those mental equations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once X-COM’s scientists and engineers figured out the basics of how all of that
works, they realized it wasn’t much different from modeling a physical process
in software. With this knowledge in hand, they were able to separate the steps
of building the necessary model (“compilation”) and running its simulation
enough times to manifest the effect (“execution”). Sokolov didn’t like calling
these things “spells”, so he named them “metatronic loops” to make the whole
thing sound more scientific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-one-power-game-mechanics&quot;&gt;The One Power: Game Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind the scenes, the One Power as used by the aliens is basically Ritual Path
Magic from &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Monster Hunters 1: Champions&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Thaumathology:
Ritual Path Magic&lt;/strong&gt;. The main break from those supplements is that the aliens
are able to use it to create permanent items and constructs, which is where all
the “TL 4+n” stuff comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bit about naturally occurring “magic circuits” is swiped from the &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;
franchise; their game effect here is to allow a character to buy Magery (Ritual
Path) and Ritual Adept. Humans in this game lack these circuits and so can’t use
“classic” RPM at all. However, this discovery allows them to build similar
circuits into &lt;em&gt;computers&lt;/em&gt;, giving them access to the Technomagic variant from
&lt;strong&gt;GURPS Monster Hunters 5: Applied Xenology&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immediate game effect of this discovery was to add a new item to the group’s
master equipment list: the Metatronic Device, a hardened, custom-made PDA that
could store one metatronic loop in its memory and run it at the tap of an
icon. The thing’s processor would burn out after the effect ended, but it would
be possible to carry several of them into the field. The first loop available
was one that completely protected everyone in a given radius from the Hostage
Effect (AKA psychic numbness) for up to 6 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players can also elect to learn ritual magic paths from now on - once they do,
they’ll be able to develop their own loops using the top-of-the-line setup at
X-COM HQ and take them into the field using the PDAs. For now they’re limited to
what the NPC scientists can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, less visible effect of the discovery was to give X-COM access to the
magical side of every other discovery they made through research! This is why
researching the One Power was so vital - every possible countermeasure for the
Dreams of Ruin involves a healthy dose of magic, particularly the higher-end
ones. They couldn’t arrive at any of those solutions without this knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the choice was made and the effects explained, I took a little time to come
up with their next mission. In the next update to this series, we’ll begin
covering Operation SNAKE OIL.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/06/05/x-com-strategy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/06/05/x-com-strategy.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>x-com</category>
        
        <category>actual-play</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Hell's Rebels: In Hell's Bright Shadow, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to another installment of “Let’s Read Hell’s Rebels!” You can find links
to the whole series in its &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/hells-rebels/&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt;. This time we’ll go through Part 2
of its first adventure. It’s titled “Rebuilding the Ravens”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, we’ll be taking a look at how our hypotethical party consisting
of &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/11/27/pathfinder-df-knight.html&quot;&gt;Valeros&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/10/08/pathfinder-df-bard.html&quot;&gt;Lem&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/12/30/pathfinder-df-rogue.html&quot;&gt;Merisiel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/10/15/pathfinder-df-cleric.html&quot;&gt;Kyra&lt;/a&gt; would fare here as GURPS
Dungeon Fantasy delvers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Adventure Path” style modules have a reputation for being extremely
railroady. &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/10/hells-rebels-adventure-1.html&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; certainly lives up to that, since it consists of a series
of tightly scripted scenes and two back-to-back dungeons where the PCs have no
real alternative other than delve right in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Part 2, however, we leave the rails behind for a bit! It starts by stating
that the PCs plus Rexus and Laria are the group best-positioned to offer
organized opposition to Barzilai Thrune in the whole of Kintargo. It goes to
show how thorough the guy was in killing everyone else, I guess, since right now
our heroes have a snowball’s chance in Hell of taking him down. Before they can
have a shot at The Barzilai, they need to expand the newborn Silver Ravens into
a proper rebel army and consolidate support for their position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCs are expected to engage with the custom rebellion rules at this point,
which means this part of the adventure will play out over multiple weeks of game
time and will largely consist of PC-initiated actions and their consequences as
they focus on recruiting agents and gaining supporters. The book lists several
special events and missions that will happen or become available while the PCs
do this. By the end of the first adventure, the Silver Ravens should become a
substantial movement with broad support among the oppressed of Kintargo, and
should be ready to move out of Laria’s basement and into a more permanent base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-spy-among-us&quot;&gt;A Spy Among Us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The events mostly concern Blosodriette, the imp the party has unwittingly
brought from the Fair Fortune Livery along with the documents they recovered
there. She will hang around the hideout either invisible or transformed into a
rat or spider. Her goal is to be set free without being banished back to Hell,
and she begins sabotaging the rebels in an attempt to either convince the PCs to
let her go or to attract attention from outside allies who can free her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GM is free to come up with clues and setbacks caused by the imp. Events in
the book go from structural sabotage to mind-controlling an otherwise innocent
NPC into betraying the group to the dottari. The PCs can thwart her in several
ways: finding the contract and ripping it up will send the imp back to Hell, as
will spotting the invisible devil and defeating her in combat. If a PC happens
to belong to the Sarini noble lineage, they can actually &lt;em&gt;command&lt;/em&gt; Blosodriette
and turn her to their service, since the contract binds her to that lineage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably best if these events are interspersed with the special missions
the book describes later, and/or with the normal turns of the rebellion
management mini-game. Solving each one gives the party a XP award, as does
defeating the imp. Of course, the party might end up finding the imp quite soon,
and all of this will be moot if they already dealt with her back at the
Livery. Defeating the devil early awards the party XP for any events that hadn’t
occurred yet; the party &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; successful in preventing them, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another unrelated event here that provides a bit of foreshadowing about
the Rose of Kintargo, an NPC who appears in the second adventure. Foreshadowing
is all this is, but I suppose it’s possible for a frustrated party to link
this to the imp’s sabotage instead. It’s something to watch out for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conversion-notes&quot;&gt;Conversion Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blosodriette should be built as a Wizard with the Shapeshifting, Suggestion and
False Memory spells, plus any pre-requisites and other spells the GM deems
suitably annoying (like summoning swarms of rats). In her natural form, she’s SM
-3. Her advantages include Flight (Winged) and switchable Invisibility as an
advantage rather than as a spell, since she can keep it up for a very long
time. Her disadvantages include Sadism and an Obsession with being freed from
her contract, as well as any vulnerabilities common to demons and devils in your
game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;missions&quot;&gt;Missions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are “special missions” which occur outside the rebellion management
rules. They’re numbered, but can happen in any order as decided by the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-1-decode-the-documents&quot;&gt;Mission 1: Decode the Documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decoding the documents requires skills with Linguistics and fluency in
Celestial, Elven and Strix. Rexus has all of this and will take 7 weeks to do
the job by himself, but PCs who also meet the prerequisites can try to help
shorten this time. Finishing the job in 4 weeks or less is worth bonus XP, and
regardless of the time it takes the party will get a permanent bonus to all
Silver Raven organization stats from the tactical information contained in
there. They’ll also learn a lot about the history of the original group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is a long-running thing, the PCs can obviously engage in other
activities or missions while it goes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-2-investigate-the-fires&quot;&gt;Mission 2: Investigate the Fires&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of places connected to dissident characters and organizations burned down
in the Night of Ashes, and the PCs can look into those fires if they are so
inclined. The only site that will yield something of value are the ruins of the
Silver Star, Shensen’s shop, which has a hidden stash of potions and scrolls
which wasn’t damaged by the fire. More substantial clues as to what happened at
these locations will be found elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-3-prisoners-of-salt&quot;&gt;Mission 3: Prisoners of Salt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freeing the high-profile prisoners from Kintargo Castle might be more than what
the group can handle at this point, but that’s not the only place where
prisoners are being held. A group of rogues and mercenaries friendly to Laria is
being held prisoner at the Salix Salt Works, and they would make a good addition
to the Silver Ravens. They’re guarded by a group of thugs hired by Thrune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book provides a keyed map of the area, but this will be mostly just a big
brawl. There’s a total of eight CCG Thugs led by a dwarf fighter named Kessrin,
but only half of the group is on guard duty at any one time, with the other half
asleep in an outbuilding. Our hypothetical party should have no trouble at all
moping the floor with these doofuses, particularly if they strike at
night. Rescuing the prisoners allows the PCs to recruit them to the Ravens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conversion-notes-1&quot;&gt;Conversion Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already discussed the CCG Thugs in Part 1. Kessrin should be built as a
well-armored dwarf Squire with a few extra points of ST, Overconfidence, and the
Throwing skill. He wields a mace and shield, and has a couple of alchemical
grenades. The original uses Tanglefoot Bags, but the GM might want to employ
something more devious like poisons or sleep potions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-4-murders-in-the-nursery&quot;&gt;Mission 4: Murders In the Nursery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I talked about Golarion having more horror elements than your
typical D&amp;amp;D setting? We’ll get to see some of them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, tieflings face a lot of racial prejudice in Cheliax, even in
Kintargo. I find this a bit surprising in a nation that generally considers
everything devil-related to be just swell. Perhaps the justification for this is
in a setting book I don’t have. Most of Kintargo’s tieflings live in a decrepit
slum nicknamed “The Devil’s Nursery”, and the harassment they face when they try
to move out makes it very difficult for them to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thrune made their lives even worse by not only imprisoning the most effective
advocate for their civil rights during the Night of Ashes, but having a witch in
his employ conduct an horrific ritual in the Nursery that summoned a pack of
eight tooth fairies (the &lt;em&gt;Hellboy&lt;/em&gt; kind, not the children’s story kind). The fey
roam around the slums every few days, killing people and taking their
teeth. It’s causing a panic that may erupt into a riot if nothing is done about
it. If the PCs help here, they’ll earn many supporters from among Kintargo’s
downtrodden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mission is a meaty investigative scenario - all the PCs know at the start
is that people are getting killed in the slums. This might require interviewing
reluctant witnesses, examining a body before the locals can cremate it, or even
having one of the PCs act as bait for the killers by wandering the streets alone
at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fairies fight to the death once they’re cornered in their lair, which is
also where the PCs can find the remains of the ritual that summoned the fairies
here, which include the body of a child. Treating it with respect and solving
the case earns them extra supporters in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conversion-notes-2&quot;&gt;Conversion Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A GM who wants to really focus on the investigation here might break out the
rules from &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Monster Hunters&lt;/strong&gt;, which cover the “identify the monster and
find it” part pretty well. Social skills would be useful for interviewing
witnesses, &lt;strong&gt;Diagnosis&lt;/strong&gt; for examining the bodies, and &lt;strong&gt;Hidden Lore (Faeries)&lt;/strong&gt;
to idenfity the culprits and their weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathfinder Tooth Fairies are pixy-sized fey (SM -6) who wield magical pliers
that attack like SM 0 magical knives and give them the ability to pull out
someone’s teeth mid-fight. They also have a paralytic bite, and explode into
nauseating glitter when they die. The eight fairies in this encounter can give a
party who relies exclusively on physical attacks some unexpected trouble!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for our party, this would mostly be Lem’s and Meririel’s show until they
managed to confront the fairies, in my estimation. Fighting them might be tricky
unless Lem can get off a Mass Daze or Mass Sleep spell, or Kyra can set them on
fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-5-crackdown-at-clenchjaws&quot;&gt;Mission 5: Crackdown at Clenchjaw’s&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clenchjaw’s was a fairly unremarkable bar until recently. Now it’s becoming a
hotbed of anti-government sentment as well as the stage for huge, nightly
brawls. Its owner used to keep a lid on this stuff, but he’s been passing out
early each night for some weird reason. PCs can get involved here while looking
for recruits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs who look hang around the bar long enough will eventually find out the cause
of the increased chaos is Vendalfek, a fairy dragon! He moved here after the
other bar he lived in was burned in the Night of Ashes, and has been using his
illusion powers to make Clenchjaw’s rowdier to stave off his boredom. This in
turn attracted more dissidents to the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vendalfek can be convinced to stop his shenanigans peacefully, and some skilled
diplomacy might convince him to join the rebellion as a special ally. Outright
invinting him to live on their base will have the same result. Failing to
resolve the situation will eventually cause the bar to be raided, which will
cost the Ravens some supporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conversion-notes-3&quot;&gt;Conversion Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vendalfek should be based on the Shoulder Dragon template on p. 27 of &lt;strong&gt;GURPS
Dungeon Fantasy 5: Allies&lt;/strong&gt;, with the addition of some spellcasting ability
focused on illusion. He makes a good spy, being basically a less powerful but
also less ethically questionable version of Blosodriette the imp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-6-an-unsanctioned-excruciation&quot;&gt;Mission 6: An Unsanctioned Excruciation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section goes on a bit about “excruciations”, which are public torture and
humilation sessions the Chelish government likes to punish its dissidents and
criminals with. Barzilai’s preferred method is “doghousing”, in which the victim
is forced to share a space with two large angry dogs for days and choose between
fighting them for food or starving. No official excruciations are scheduled
during this adventure, but the ever punchable members of the Chelish Citizen’s
Group have decided to perform a few of their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an event that should happen once the Silver Ravens have gained a fair
bit of notoriety. The CCG captures a friendly NPC who isn’t a member of the
Ravens, perhaps someone who helped the PCs during Mission 4 or 5, and stages a
doghousing in Aria Park. The PCs should get wind of this fairly quickly once it
happens, since it’s not exactly a discreet event. It’s up to them whether and
when to stage a rescue, but waiting too long will obviously prove lethal for the
victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fighting the four CCG thugs and their two big angry dogs would be a literal walk
in the part for our brave delvers. Doing so in a public fashion increases the
Ravens’ notoriety, but I personally think it’s worth it. The dottari show up a
few minutes after a fight breaks out, but by them the party will be long gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-7-threat-of-the-red-jills&quot;&gt;Mission 7: Threat of the Red Jills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Red Jills are a small but violent gang of thieves who are taking advantage
of the current chaos to prey on the citizens of Kintargo. They leave the dottari
and the CCG alone, so Thrune lets them keep operating to keep the population
afraid. As such, making them stop will benefit the Ravens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recruiting the Jills as allies isn’t possible: they’re led by Scarplume, a strix
with a particularly fierce hatred of humans. Tracking the Jills down to their
abandoned orphanage hideout will lead to a big fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conversion-notes-4&quot;&gt;Conversion Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again the investigation rules from &lt;strong&gt;Action&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Monster Hunters&lt;/strong&gt; would
do a good job here! &lt;strong&gt;Streetwise&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Area Knowledge (Kintargo)&lt;/strong&gt; would be
particularly important for finding the hideout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strix are winged humanoids, and their stats should be basically like a human’s
aside from the Flight (Winged) advantage. Scarplume is a sorcerer whose spell
list can be summed up as “All The Fire”, which means she can be statted up as
either a Fire Elementalist or a DF Sorcerer with lots of burning Innate
Attacks. She has Intolerance (Humans) and a host of other sociopathic
disadvantages. The rest of the Jills should be built using the Cutpurse or
Skirmisher templates from &lt;strong&gt;DF 15&lt;/strong&gt;, and should all be non-human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for part 2 of the book! Part 3 contains a substantial dungeon delve,
but doesn’t necessarily happen after all of the events here: the timing for that
is entirely up to the PCs, so they might end up having to deal with the stuff
here even into the second adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/27/hells-rebels-adventure-1-part-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/27/hells-rebels-adventure-1-part-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Alternatives to GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It seems my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/21/to-gurps-or-not-to-gurps.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; on this subject caught more attention than usual! I
got a significant number of comments on Google Plus and Facebook. I honestly
wouldn’t have thought people would be this interested in my opinions. So let’s
elaborate on this a bit more, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that post I mentioned that the first system I tend to think of when
I visualize a game in my head is GURPS about 90% of the time. In the other 10%,
something else comes to mind. And in some part of the first 90%, there may come
a time where I decide GURPS is not the best fit either. Why do I end up thinking
that, and what systems I prefer at these times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-why&quot;&gt;The Why&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of my reasoning has been explained in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/21/to-gurps-or-not-to-gurps.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; on this
subject: sometimes the setting assumptions just don’t mesh well with GURPS in
terms of their preferred level of exactness, internal consistency, or sheer
scale. The rest of the time I come to this conclusion is because I know of a
system that can handle what I see as that particular setting’s “essence” better
than GURPS. Usually it’s a mix of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With enough work I could probably modify GURPS into something that can handle
these cases. However, I feel that there’s a point where it’s simpler and easier
to use another system whose design and default assumptions already match what
I’m going for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this doesn’t have anything to do with the level of “crunch” in a
system! It’s more about the specific feelings I want to evoke in actual play
than about the complexity of the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some examples from fiction and other media that I feel fit the criteria
above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By the end of &lt;em&gt;Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann&lt;/em&gt;, you have the protagonists piloting
a universe-sized robot who uses galaxies as throwing weapons. How to even
begin modeling that?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The joke at the core of Andrew Hussie’s &lt;em&gt;Problem Sleuth&lt;/em&gt; is that the exact
game mechanics of the stuff you do don’t matter one bit and trying to properly
understand them leads only to madness. This remains an ever-present theme in
his subsequent story, &lt;em&gt;Homestuck&lt;/em&gt;, as well. Despite the jokes some people like
to make, GURPS works in precisely the opposite way.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An &lt;em&gt;Overwatch&lt;/em&gt; campaign that sought to capture the feel of the original’s
&lt;em&gt;gameplay&lt;/em&gt; would need a fight between a non-superhuman shirtless dude with an
improvised shotgun and someone wearing the best powered armor German
engineering can build to be an even match. GURPS can’t easily handle that
level of gameplay and setting segregation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Everything in the entirely non-violent and pastoral &lt;em&gt;Flying Witch&lt;/em&gt; happens at
a scale where you could sit down and figure everyone’s DX scores and
encumbrance levels, but that would feel like it’s missing the point of what
the show is really about.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-what&quot;&gt;The What&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do I usually go for, when I decide GURPS wouldn’t be a good fit? Let’s
look at my usual alternatives in rough alphabetical order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dungeons--dragons-4th-edition&quot;&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons 4th Edition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my favorite edition of Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons; Quite possibly the only
edition I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt;. People like to denigrate it as being too
“video-gamey”, but I find its combat system and the power system that supports
it to be immensely fun in a very specific way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, D&amp;amp;D 4 combat &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; feel like a video-game to me, but not like the MMOs
its detractors usually compare it to. No, to me it feels like a grid- and turn-
based tactical RPG in the vein of Final Fantasy Tactics, Fire Emblem or
Disgaea. I love that sort of game to bits, and my fond memories of playing them
stretch back into my pre-teen years. Having an ruleset that allows me to run
something like that on the tabletop is basically a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its encounter and monster design system is easy to use and produces remarkably
consistent results. Monster stats in D&amp;amp;D 4 are mostly independent from the
in-setting description for those monsters. Everything is based on level - the
equipment a monster of a certain level wears and even its basic attributes are
mostly there for color, and can even be safely omitted from the stat block
itself. This makes reskinning monsters to fit your specific scenario a simple
matter of changing your description and maybe switching out a minor power in the
stat block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use D&amp;amp;D 4th Edition when I want to experience the feel of its grid-based
combat, and when I want a high level of separation between a character’s game
stats and their in-setting description. That last reason is why I would use this
system for a “gameplay first” adaptation of &lt;em&gt;Overwatch&lt;/em&gt;. In a “setting first”
adaptation I would still go with GURPS (and Roadhog vs. Reinhardt wouldn’t be an
even match).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;exalted-3rd-edition&quot;&gt;Exalted 3rd Edition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love Exalted’s setting! I didn’t love the second edition all that much, but
the third won me back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I could take this game’s excellent setting and run it as a high-powered
“fantasy supers” GURPS game, I find the original rules have a certain, well,
charm to them. So unless I have a very strong reason not to, when I run Exalted
I use the Exalted 3rd edition rules. I would probably go for a system conversion
before I used the second edition, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;chuubos-marvelous-wish-granting-engine&quot;&gt;Chuubo’s Marvelous Wish Granting Engine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chuubo’s is a system as rigorously designed as GURPS, but with a diametrically
opposite focus. While GURPS is all about the mechanical actions and physical
results of character actions, Chuubo’s is all about the intention and the
emotions behind these actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes it well-suited for pastoral, non-violent games inspired by material
such as &lt;em&gt;Flying Witch&lt;/em&gt;. Games where &lt;em&gt;how an action makes you feel&lt;/em&gt; is more
important than whether it is successful, and where the climax of the story
consists of &lt;em&gt;witnessing something wonderful&lt;/em&gt; rather than overcoming a conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system also has support for other genres as well, and a large selection of
miraculous powers that truly feel miraculous. It generally excels at running
games where the &lt;em&gt;metaphysics&lt;/em&gt; of the setting matter far more than its physics
(such as one based on &lt;em&gt;Homestuck&lt;/em&gt;). Its narrative-based XP mechanics are also
quite interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another system that has very good support for non-violent pastoral games is
&lt;em&gt;Golden Sky Stories&lt;/em&gt;. Unlike Chuubo’s, it works at a more prosaic level and
doesn’t try to support other genres, but it’s pretty good at what it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wushu&quot;&gt;Wushu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FATE seems to be all the rage these days when it comes to
relatively-rules-light, narrative-driven games, but Wushu is the game that
captured my heart in that area. Its first iterations were dedicated to emulating
kung-fu movies, but it eventually became a generic, action-oriented system that
reaches that status by &lt;em&gt;not caring&lt;/em&gt; about the physical details of character
actions. Its very light rules mostly concern themselves with ensuring the group
maintains a coherent narrative, and use that narrative as a means to gather the
dice players roll for actual tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes it perfect for games where the exact “physics” of the world take a
backseat to the spectacle of the story. &lt;em&gt;Gurren Lagann&lt;/em&gt; is the perfect example
of such a setting, and it would also work wonderfully for &lt;em&gt;Problem Sleuth’s&lt;/em&gt;
“nonsensical adventure game” paradigm since players would be able to make up
stupid mechanics on the spot as part of their narration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-you&quot;&gt;What About You?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much the list of all of my go-to systems. What are yours? What
specific things draw you to these games?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/24/alternatives-to-gurps.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/24/alternatives-to-gurps.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>exalted</category>
        
        <category>wushu</category>
        
        <category>dnd</category>
        
        <category>chuubo</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dragon's Dogma Bestiary: Golems</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/DDENEMIES.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Copyright 2012 Capcom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an entry in the Dragon’s Dogma bestiary. The remaining entries along
with the full adaptation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dragons-dogma/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in other fantasy settings, golems are animated statues created by magicians
to fulfill a certain mission, usually to guard some important place. In Gransys,
the secret of their creation has been lost to the ages, but there are still a
fair number of dormant golems still extant. Sages speculate their creators
belonged to the same culture that worshipped the elemental deities whose shrines
still survive underground. This speculation comes mostly from observing the
designs of both the ruins and the golems and concluding their builders liked to
think &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, none of the golems found so far were even near the elemental shrine
ruins. They slumber out in the wild, looking like boulders until an unwary
intruder crosses some unseen boundary. Perhaps the truth is that the golems are
even older than the shrines, and the places they have been set to guard have
long since crumbled to dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advanced-stone-golem&quot;&gt;Advanced Stone Golem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GURPS Dungeon Fantasy 2: Dungeons&lt;/strong&gt; contains stats for a stone golem on
p. 26. As that book says, those stats represent a &lt;em&gt;basic&lt;/em&gt; model. At SM+1, this
type of golem can comfortably fit in most dungeons and might indeed be guarding
some deep chamber in an elemental shrine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “advanced” stone golems found on the wild are quite a bit larger and more
dangerous, and have the ability to shoot coruscating energy beams from their
foreheads at foes they can’t reach with their powerful fists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ST&lt;/strong&gt; 50; &lt;strong&gt;DX&lt;/strong&gt; 11; &lt;strong&gt;IQ&lt;/strong&gt; 8; &lt;strong&gt;HT&lt;/strong&gt; 14;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SM&lt;/strong&gt; +3; &lt;strong&gt;Dodge&lt;/strong&gt; 8; &lt;strong&gt;DR&lt;/strong&gt; 15;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HP&lt;/strong&gt; 90; &lt;strong&gt;Will&lt;/strong&gt; 8; &lt;strong&gt;Per&lt;/strong&gt; 8; &lt;strong&gt;FP&lt;/strong&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic Speed&lt;/strong&gt; 5.50; &lt;strong&gt;Move&lt;/strong&gt; 6;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Punch (16)&lt;/strong&gt;: 5d+1 cr. Reach C-2.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grab (16)&lt;/strong&gt;: Grapples at ST 51.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brilliant Lance (14)&lt;/strong&gt;: 3d burning; Acc 3; Range 10/100; RoF 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traits&lt;/strong&gt;: Automaton; Cannot Learn; Doesn’t Breathe; Doesn’t Eat or Drink;
Doesn’t Sleep; Fragile (Unnatural); High Pain Threshold; Immunity to Metabolic
Hazards; Indomitable; Injury Tolerance (Homogenous, No Blood); Pressure Support
3; Reprogrammable; Unfazeable; Unhealing (Total); Vacuum Support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class&lt;/strong&gt;: Construct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;: See below for additional weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fighting-the-golem&quot;&gt;Fighting the Golem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a six meter tall, six-ton stone statue the advanced golem has the sort of HP
and DR that puts it well outside the range of most personal weapons. Despite its
relatively low IQ and Will, it’s not very succeptible to mind-affecting magic
either. Fighting it directly would require siege engines or apocalyptic
magic. Fortunately, there’s a better way!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it requires much more magical energy than the basic golem described in
&lt;strong&gt;DF 2&lt;/strong&gt;, this advanced model is powered by 1d+1 Powerstones encrusted in its
surface (roll a random hit location for each one). Each can be targeted at a
penalty equal to that of the hit location it’s in plus an additional -1, and
despite being as Homogenous as the golem has a “mere” HP 10 and DR 0. Reducing
the stone to 0 HP cracks it and makes it worthless as a power source. Destroying
all of them deactivates the golem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, parties who stumble upon a golem can also just run away and leave the
zone it’s guarding. They will never pursue anyone or fire their beams past that
boundary. Even if the golem is on the way to something you need, you can retreat
and come back prepared to face it later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golems are always alone - they kill anything else that enters their protected
area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;golem-variants&quot;&gt;Golem Variants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iron Golem&lt;/strong&gt;: Some places were apparently deemed too important to be guarded
by mere &lt;em&gt;stone&lt;/em&gt; golems. They have faded away to nothing just the same, leaving
their immortal guardians watching over empty stretches of bog or meadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do iron golems have double the HP and DR, their 2d+2 power sources are
located outside their bodies, placed along the boundary of their guarded
area. These special talismans are as resistant to time as the golem itself, but
have a mere DR 0 and HP 5 each. The problem is &lt;em&gt;finding&lt;/em&gt; them while the golem
attacks - destroying an iron golem is the ultimate exercise in Extreme
Archaeology.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/23/golems.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/23/golems.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dragons-dogma</category>
        
        <category>monster</category>
        
        <category>bestiary</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>To GURPS or Not To GURPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m sure many people have posted their takes on this over the years. In a
continuing attempt to procrastrinate on finishing the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dragons-dogma&quot;&gt;Dragon’s Dogma&lt;/a&gt;
bestiary, I decided to post mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-history-with-gurps&quot;&gt;My History with GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS has always been one of my favorite systems ever since I first heard of it
somewhere during the early Nineties. Back then, GURPS 3rd Edition was one of the
Big Three systems in Brazil, mostly because it was one of the three systems that
had been translated by this one publisher who had a strategy of buying All The
Licenses from US companies. The other two were AD&amp;amp;D 2nd Edition and Vampire: The
Masquerade, at the time also in its second edition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of those three, I went with GURPS, mostly by a process of elimination. Buying
only one core book was way cheaper than buying three, and I wasn’t a fan of
vampires as player characters. I read and enjoyed the book, but didn’t actually
use it in play very much. I mostly played Tagmar, which is a fantasy system that
should be pretty much unknown to anyone outside of Brazil, and later on a bit of
Shadowrun 2nd edition (and my relationship with &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; one deserves an article
of its own).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After ‘96 or so, when my English skills had improved considerably and I had
moved to a bigger city with a proper FLGS, I began to discover the joy of GURPS
supplements. Some of them had been translated to Portuguese, but the ones I
found myself drawn to only had English versions. I still have and cherish my
physical copies of Russia, Callahan’s Crosstime Saloon, the first Discworld, and
consider my relative recent finding of a used GURPS Goblins to be a major stroke
of luck. Even though I still didn’t play much GURPS, the books were a joy to
read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought the GURPS 4th Edition corebooks when they came out in
2005, in English. By then the Brazilian edition of the game had been languishing
for a while, publishing-wise: aside from those first few translated sourcebooks,
all we had were some locally-produced historical games based on GURPS Lite,
and even those were fading out of print by the time Fourth Edition rolled
around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the new core rules quite a lot, and kept buying print books as they came
out until I switched to PDF for good. These days, GURPS is pretty much my
absolute favorite system, though ironically that doesn’t seem to be an opinion
shared with any of my fellow face-to-face players. But they’ve all moved into
board games anyway, so they don’t count here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, every time I watch or read some particularly interesting piece of media I
try to think what it would look like adapted to some RPG system. And pretty much
the first system I always try to fit in there is GURPS. 90% of the times the
result looks pretty good, at least for a 15-minute purely mental effort, but
sometimes I find it’s not the best system for the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-to-gurps&quot;&gt;When To GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS excells at representing settings and stories where the specific details of
the actions you take are &lt;em&gt;important&lt;/em&gt; and have &lt;em&gt;mechanical weight&lt;/em&gt;. This usually
means relatively grounded and internally consistent settings, though not
necessarily &lt;em&gt;realistic&lt;/em&gt; ones. Most action movies fit here, as does a whole lot
of science fiction and quite a few martial arts stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fantasy does, too, as long it has the traits above. IMHO, GURPS does
low-to-mid-level D&amp;amp;D a lot better than most actual editions of D&amp;amp;D. If you want
“I wait until the armored ogre lifts his arm to attack and stab his armpit with
my spear” to actually &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; something mechanically, GURPS is your system!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would use GURPS for a game inspired in say, the &lt;em&gt;Killjoys&lt;/em&gt; science fiction
series, the &lt;em&gt;Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon&lt;/em&gt; movie, the &lt;em&gt;My Hero Academia&lt;/em&gt;
comic, or the &lt;em&gt;Valkyria Chronicles&lt;/em&gt; video-game. I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; used GURPS for games
inspired on &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/gurps-xcom-reports/&quot;&gt;X-COM&lt;/a&gt; and plain old Dungeon Fantasy, and wrote a fairly
complete &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dragons-dogma&quot;&gt;Dragon’s Dogma&lt;/a&gt; adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a more general note, GURPS also thrives when your group has a little time to
prepare for the game - choose which subset of the rules to use, create
characters, that sort of thing. The more of that the GM does themselves the less
experience with the system their players will need to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-not-to-gurps&quot;&gt;When Not to GURPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; 10% of times, I find GURPS wouldn’t be the best fit for the
show/book/video-game in question. These works usually have the opposite traits
from the ones I listed above: action details are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; less important than
their effects, and their settings tend to lack one of “grounded” or
“consistent”. Often they lack both! This doesn’t imply they’re &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; works, just
that they have a different focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GURPS bases all of its numbers in real-world measurements. Powers have ranges in
yards or meters, an attack’s damage is based on the force behind it, and so
on. Therefore, stories where characters have fuzzily-defined skills and powers
are hard to pin down. If your character’s specific capabilities are defined more
by the needs of the story rather than by anything measurable in-world, it would
be best to use a system that supports this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sort of science fiction that has characters switch bodies a lot is also hard
to model in GURPS, whose rules assume its characters will usually not undergo
this sort of drastic change so often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have much time to prepare for a game, the best system for it
will inevitably be whatever your players are more familiar with! At least where
I live, that’s unlikely to be GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-you&quot;&gt;What about you?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What have you used GURPS successfully for? If that game fit into my “When Not to
GURPS” description, what did you do to make it work well? Please leave a comment!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/21/to-gurps-or-not-to-gurps.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/21/to-gurps-or-not-to-gurps.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Hell's Rebels: Meet the NPCs of Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to another installment of “Let’s Read Hell’s Rebels!” You can find links
to the whole series in its &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/hells-rebels/&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt;. This time we’ll take a more
detailed look into the friendly NPCs the group has met by the end of
Part 1. Let’s look at them in order of appearance and discuss how we should
convert them to GURPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rexus-victocora&quot;&gt;Rexus Victocora&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/PZO9097-Rexus.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Rexus. Copyright 2016 Paizo.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heir and sole survivor of what was possibly Kintargo’s nicest noble
family. His parents belonged to the Sacred Order of Archivists ever since before
he was born, and after a youth spent looking for a cause Rexus had finally
decided to join them upon returning home from his studies abroad. Instead he
found his home in flames with everyone who was inside dead, and regretfully fled
into the night. He’s having some trouble adjusting to life as a destitute
outcast, not just because he misses the luxury of a noble lifestyle but because
his he has what sounds like a chronic respiratory disease that demands regular
treatment with expensive alchemical drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the death of his parents, Rexus is more determined than ever to see
Kintargo free, both from Thrune’s government and from Chelish rule in
general. However, he will not compromise his principles to do it, and will leave
a rebellion that turns too bloody or exclusionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting bit: Rexus is transgender! This will probably never come up in
play or be noticeable to the PCs (this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a world with well-developed
polymorph magic), but it’s nice to see it on the page nevertheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conversion-notes&quot;&gt;Conversion Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rexus’ original stats have him as a Neutral Good Human Aristocrat
2/Sorcerer 1. Despite being higher-level than the PCs to start, he’s more of a
support character whose main function is to translate some important documents
the party finds in Part 1 of the adventure. His low Constitution score and
mostly noncombat spell selection make him unsuitable for adventuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to stat Rexus up in &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/strong&gt; would be to make him
a Scholar (from &lt;strong&gt;DF 4&lt;/strong&gt;) with the necessary linguistic and research skills to
fulfill his dramatic role, and perhaps a few Knowledge spells to round him
out. His poor health might be represented by lower than average HT and/or
disadvantages such as Very Unfit and Chronic Pain, perhaps with a Mitigator to
represent those alchemical treatments. He would still provide valuable skills,
but wouldn’t be someone you would want to take with you to the front lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Rexus has fulfilled his function in Adventure 1, the GM is entirely free
to run him as they see fit. His permanence in the rebellion depends entirely on
how well the PCs treat him and how well their own morals match his. Our
hypotethical party shouldn’t have a problem in this area, which means he would
continue to lend them his vital scholarly skills. I mean, who else would you
task with translating those encrypted Celestial writings? Merisiel?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCs who get along specially well with Rexus could purchase him as an Ally, in
which case the GM might want to stat him up so he’s a bit more survivable in the
field. Buying him as a Contact would be sort of redundant, however, since as a
member of the resistance he’s already always around and has a defined skillset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;laria-longroad&quot;&gt;Laria Longroad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/octopus-carnival/assets/353px-Laria_Longroad.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Laria. Copyright 2016 Paizo.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laria is a halfling, and was born a slave in Cheliax. Her owners were unusually
cruel even by Chelish slave-holder standards, and when one of them killed her
parents and brother she beat the guy to death with her bare hands and escaped to
join the Bellflower Network. A few years later she ended up as a coordinator for
them in Kintargo while running a very well-regarded coffee-house as a front. She
worked not just with Bellflower agents but with smugglers, criminals, and rebels
of all sorts - anyone working to undermine Chelish rule in Kintargo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, Barzilai’s rise to power has left her without an much of a
network to coordinate. She’s been keeping her head down but by the time the PCs
meet her has grown conviced something must be done to improve the
situation. Where Rexus is idealistic, Laria is cynical: she wants a free
Kintargo as much as he does, but is less picky about which methods are
acceptable to reach that outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laria provides the PCs with a temporary hideout in Adventure 1, and if they
treat her well can continue to give them logistical support and access to a
network of smugglers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conversion-notes-1&quot;&gt;Conversion Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laria’s original stats have her as a Chaotic Good Halfling Brawler
2/Rogue 1. Brawlers are kinda like monks, only they replace the philosophy and
chi powers with the fighter’s large amount of bonus feats and with the ability
to switch them around mid-fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this, Laria’s main contribution to the cause are her social skills and
her useful position in both polite society and the underworld. Therefore, it
makes sense to stat her up in &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Dungeon Fantasy&lt;/strong&gt; using the Agent template
from &lt;strong&gt;DF 15&lt;/strong&gt;, with plenty of Savoir-Faire, Current Affairs (Kintargo),
Streetwise and Contacts. The lower-point template would prevent her from
overshadowing Lem from our hypothetical party, and those points would go into
areas where an active DF PC might be reluctant to invest in. For &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt;
parties who lack a bard or other specialist “social” character the GM can bump
her up to a full 250 points of halfling crime boss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with Rexus, Laria could make an interesting Ally for a PC who gets along with
her especially well, particularly if that PC’s party lacks strong social
skills. As she is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a formal member of the Silver Ravens and has her own
operation going on, it could also make sense to acquire her as a Contact. Laria
can also be the “face” of a larger Contact Group representing her own network of
smugglers.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/18/hells-rebels-npcs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/18/hells-rebels-npcs.html</guid>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GURPS X-COM: The Arsenal of Ruin, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/xcom__extraction_by_antimingebag-d9abdgp.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=http://antimingebag.deviantart.com/art/XCOM-Extraction-561522409&gt;
      Illustration by AntiMingebag on DeviantArt
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their second field-op, our brave &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/gurps-xcom-reports/&quot;&gt;X-COM squad&lt;/a&gt; saw new enemies with new
equipment, so it’s time to update the Arsenal of Ruin! This post will focus on
the gear carried by the Elite Puppets, also known as White Masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;white-mask-gear&quot;&gt;White Mask Gear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White Masks are elite Puppets of Ruin in service to the Ebon Masters. Like their
“lesser” brethren, they are borne as fruit from the Trees of Ruin, but they only
appear in the heart of the woods where the Trees of Woe are older. At the stage
where our campaign stopped, there were still no trees old enough to drop elite
puppets, so the ones the party met are all “imported” from off-world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original Dreams of Ruin material, elite puppets carried TL 8 military
equipment equivalent to that of a first-world military soldier: automatic
assault rifles and more modern rocket launchers. For this campaign, they had to
step up their game, as that sort of gear is starting equipment for my PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2017/03/30/x-com-arsenal-of-ruin.html&quot;&gt;equipment carried by normal puppets&lt;/a&gt;, all of this gear is produced
by the trees themselves along with the puppet that wears it. The only “custom”
addition by the Ebon Masters here is painting the masks on their armors white to
denote rank within their organization. This equipment is meant to be more
advanced than anything carried by modern Earth infantry, but it’s still
considered somewhat cheap and low-end by the aliens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;puppet-assault-rifle&quot;&gt;Puppet Assault Rifle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the standard-issue puppet rifle seen in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2017/03/30/x-com-arsenal-of-ruin.html&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, this bullpup
design fires a lighter 7mm round at a much higher rate of fire. It has an
electrothermal-chemical (ETC) action and uses the High-Cyclic Controlled Bursts
rule from &lt;strong&gt;High-Tech&lt;/strong&gt;, p. 83.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weapon also has an integral underbarrel grenade launcher that fires 25mm
rounds with greater force and accuracy than its TL 8 counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Puppet Assault Rifle lacks any targetting electronics, as the puppet’s
supernatural senses fill the same role. It is otherwise extremely reliable and
easy to operate, being able to work for years in adverse conditions without
regular maintenance. It is operated with Guns (Longarm), or with Guns (Rifle)
and Guns (Grenade Launcher) under the standard rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weapon&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Damage&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Acc&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Range&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;RoF&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shots&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;ST&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bulk&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Rcl&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Puppet Assault Rifle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7d pi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1100/4500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.5/0.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9#&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50+1(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grenade Launcher&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4d pi++ or as grenade&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;360/2200&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;–&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3(3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;–&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;–&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The weapon is usually loaded with standard ammunition (in table), but it’s
perfectly capable of firing APDS (9d(2) pi-) or APEP (7d(3) pi-) rounds. Both
are would ruin the day of those players who think their vests-with-plates make
them immune to puppet weaponry. Even without armor-piercing ammo, they’re still
smart enough to aim for the arms and legs if they notice center-of-mass shots
don’t result in an immediate kill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grenade launcher is usually loaded with TL9 HE or thermobaric warheads
(&lt;strong&gt;Ultra-Tech&lt;/strong&gt; p. 153 and 155), though the Ebon Masters can certainly issue
crueler and/or higher-TL loads to their servants if the mission calls for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;white-mask-armor&quot;&gt;White Mask Armor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Mask Armor suit covers the torso and head in rigid plates of the same
composite material used to make puppet swords. The neck and limbs are covered in
a mesh of ultra-tech ballistic fibers equivalent to Reflex armor (from
&lt;strong&gt;Ultra-Tech&lt;/strong&gt;). All of this material is colored a dull gray, except for the
helmet plates, which are white.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suit is sealed, chemically-coated and contamination-proof, but does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
feature ports for air tanks or even a visor, as its intended wearers have no
need for such things. In fact, it can’t even be removed from the puppet wearing
it without being cut open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White Mask Armor provides DR 30 to the torso, groin and head. It provides DR
20 against cutting and piercing damage and DR 10 against all other damage types
to the limbs and neck. While DR 30 is a little less than the DR 35 provided by a
TL 8 assault vest with trauma plates, this DR is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; semi-ablative like that
of the plates, and is more than enough to stop rounds from an X-COM issue
assault rifle. The full suit is also about a bit lighter than the starting
“heavy armor” package for PCs and provides more DR to all non-torso locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;TL&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;DR&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Weight&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;White Mask Armor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;torso, groin, head&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15kg&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;arms, legs, neck&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-white-mask-gear&quot;&gt;Using White Mask Gear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each Elite Puppet wears a White Mask Armor suit, and carries a Puppet Assault
Rifle with 4 reloads for the rifle and 2 for the grenade launcher. They also
each carry a sword and a couple of hand grenades, and may carry a Puppet RPG or
extra rounds for one carried by a squadmate. These items are described
in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2017/03/30/x-com-arsenal-of-ruin.html&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These weapons also fall within the “second tier” of my tech tree. Researching
these weapons would have allowed X-COM to make similar versions for themselves,
which would have the advantage of not being tainted by spores. They never did
get a “researchable” White Mask corpse, but if they had they could have obtained
a version of their armor that’s actually fit for human use. Having access to at
least this much would enable the PCs to better stand up to the sort of alien
that would show up later on, as their successes mounted.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/15/arsenal-of-ruin-part-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/15/arsenal-of-ruin-part-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>x-com</category>
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>GURPS X-COM: DARK JUDAS Analysis</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/xcom__extraction_by_antimingebag-d9abdgp.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;a href=http://antimingebag.deviantart.com/art/XCOM-Extraction-561522409&gt;
      Illustration by AntiMingebag on DeviantArt
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As promised in the &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/04/dark-judas.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, this one will contain the spoilers and fight
analysis for Operation DARK JUDAS. For the rest of the Actual Play, take a look
at its &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/gurps-xcom-reports/&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first encounter on &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/04/19/dark-judas.html&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; didn’t show any new enemies, but did
introduce players to the fact that the trees drop puppets when threatened. This
time they were quite a bit better at staying out of melee range, and the puppets
were undone by their own overconfidence despite being able to do some damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no shocking revelations in the “Puppet Theater” fight in &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/04/29/dark-judas.html&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;
either, aside from the fact that puppet theater is a thing. As I said in that
part, I messed up by not having additional battle-ready puppets show up when the
PCs grenaded the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things get a lot more interesting when we get into the firefight
on &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/04/dark-judas.html&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;. There was a lot of new stuff packed into it! The players didn’t
manage to figure out much before they left, but I’m laying it all out here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downed alien craft was a small &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vimana&quot;&gt;vimana&lt;/a&gt;, which is why it looked like a
house. It was originally piloted by the alien the PCs rescued, who had defected
from the Ebon Masters (the alien faction using the forest as a weapon). Despite
their exotic looks, these magic-powered vimanas have more or less the same
capabilities as the UFOs in the original games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two factions having a firefight over the vimana and its pilot had found the
crash site just like X-COM did and were converging on it with the goal of taking
everything they could. The people occupying the vimana itself were indeed
humans, something the PCs would have noticed if they had managed to approach
them a bit more. That doesn’t mean they were friendly! This was the first
on-screen appearance of X-ALT. They likely wouldn’t have fired at the PCs right
away, but would take their help and backstab them later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group firing at them from the ruined building were Elite Puppets in direct
service to the Ebon Masters. This explains the white masks. Elite Puppets in the
original rules have somewhere between 5 and 7 hit dice as opposed to the 3 of
the rank-and-file, and these were similarly improved over their GURPS
counterparts, making them better in a fight than all but the most badass human
action heroes. On top of that, they had some pretty beefy TL 9 gear, including
armor that made them basically immune to assault rifle fire from the PCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC’s biggest mistake here was sticking too close to that black tree by the
container, since its emissions allowed the puppets to spot them. Puppets can
&lt;em&gt;see through cover&lt;/em&gt;, particularly when they have the trees spotting for them, so
once they noticed the players they only took distance penalties to
attack. Retreating was a wise decision!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would have been nice to play out the extended fight/chase scene as the PCs
retreated through the woods back to where they had stashed the puppet RPG, but I
didn’t think there would be a fun way to do it over a forum, so I abstracted it
out with a contest of Tactics and simply narrated the outcome. The PCs won by a
small margin, so they managed to get the puppets in place for Choi’s shot (which
I did roll as an attack). That was the only real way to harm the enemies they
had left, as they had already spent all their frag grenades on earlier
encounters and those wouldn’t guarantee a kill either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the PCs did about as well here as could be expected. I really wish
we could have played out the White Mask encounter in more detail, but such is
the way of play-by-forum games.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/12/dark-judas-analysis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/12/dark-judas-analysis.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>x-com</category>
        
        <category>actual-play</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's Read Hell's Rebels: In Hell's Bright Shadow, Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;figure class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/350px-Hell's_Rebels_Logo.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/2017/05/01/hells-rebels-player-guide.html&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I went over the Player’s Guide and provided some GURPS
conversion notes. Today we’ll look at the actual scenes of the first adventure
in the Path, &lt;strong&gt;In Hell’s Bright Shadow&lt;/strong&gt;. Seriously, what does that name even
mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;part-1-fledglings-of-silver&quot;&gt;Part 1: Fledglings of Silver&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this part is to get the PCs on track to restoring the Silver
Ravens. It begins with a protest!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-aria-park-protest&quot;&gt;The Aria Park Protest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the story begins, the PCs find themselves in Aria Park, so named because it’s
right next to the Kintargo Opera House. Paracount Thrune is catching a show
inside the Opera House while a huge crowd protests outside, watched by his
guards. Thrune has been in power for a couple of weeks, and in that time he’s
issued seven odd proclamations that generally make city life inconvenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The player’s guide to Hell’s Rebels describes many possible reasons for why the
PCs would be here. Two of the most interesting ones are looking for a famous
performer who recently disappeared and looking for a contact who has information
about the Silver Ravens secret society, which was rumored to defend Kintargo
from outside threats in the past. They could also simply be here to participate
in the protest, people-watch, or simply tag along a friend with a stronger
reason to be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of our four Iconic PCs, I imagine &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/10/08/pathfinder-df-bard.html&quot;&gt;Lem&lt;/a&gt; would be the one most interested in
getting in contact with a resistance movement and looking for info on the
legendary Silver Ravens. &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/10/15/pathfinder-df-cleric.html&quot;&gt;Kyra&lt;/a&gt; might be concerned about the fate of Shensen,
a half-elf singer who was very outspoken both about her faith in Sarenrae and
against the evil of House Thrune. She is currently missing. &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/12/30/pathfinder-df-rogue.html&quot;&gt;Merisiel&lt;/a&gt; would
definitely be here to riot and pickpocket people, and aimless &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/11/27/pathfinder-df-knight.html&quot;&gt;Valeros&lt;/a&gt; would
just tag along, likely to keep Merisiel out of trouble. The rules in the
Player’s Guide actually give out skill bonuses for each different motive and
further bonuses depending on different background traits chosen by the PCs. In
GURPS, I feel none of that is necessary, since the system already has a good
skill system. The GM should instead guide the players to buy some social and
subterfuge-related skills with their points, as they would be important
throughout the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a big, chaotic gathering: you have quite a few people protesting
&lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; Thrune for several different reasons, some loyalists protesting &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;
him, and a handful of yahoos who just want the riot to start already. There’s
several actions the PCs can take here, which include looking for that mysterious
contact, suppressing one or more factions, organizing the protest, or simply
picking people’s pockets. Suppressing the loyalists or yahoos will bring
benefits later on. The PCs also get XP for performing successful actions - this
seems to be a common thing here, as the adventure path is very particular about
getting them to the appropriate levels for each scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-eighth-proclamation&quot;&gt;The Eighth Proclamation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few hours of this, The Barzilai makes an appearance, and makes his
eighth proclamation. The previous seven were things like banning mint and
embroidered clothing, or bounties for live dogs. This one forbids all ship
captains from leaving their ships and setting foot on Kintargo under pain of
torture. The stated reason for it is that Barzilai has the best brain and
noticed his subjects have been angry about out-of-towners nosing in on their
business. So he’s going to solve the problem, bigly, with a ban.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This absurd proclamation starts a riot, which is what Thrune actually
wants. Why? He simply feels like watching his guards and loyalists beat up some
protesters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the riot starts, someone throws a handful of manure at Barzilai, and
while that missile misses its mark it causes him to spill some wine on his fancy
robes. This sends him into a rage, and he orders his main bodyguard Nox and the
dottari under her command to move in and start killing people. At the same time,
the off-brand Brown Shirts of the Chelish Citizen’s Group that were infiltrated
in the crowd draw their clubs and begin attacking the protesters as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The players must fight a gang of four CCG thugs to start with, and they get to
witness Nox’s powers of regeneration as she shrugs off a dagger to the throat in
a “cutscene”. I guess the idea here is that the party should get away as soon as
possible. The thugs are basically shclubs with clubs who shouldn’t pose too much
of a problem, but sticking around for too long attracts a pair of the stronger
and better-armed dottari. Finally Nox comes in with a pet hellhound and a squad
of 12 dottari guards. That last bit would be a clear sign that the four
1st-level characters must run away - the crowd certainly does! If they still
stick around, the hellhound focuses on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gurps-conversion-notes&quot;&gt;GURPS Conversion Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s two ways to go about this here. GMs who want to be true to the fiction
could give the Chelish Citizen’s Group thugs average stats, clubs, and a couple
of points in Shortsword, while using the 62-point Guard template from &lt;strong&gt;GURPS
Dungeon Fantasy 15&lt;/strong&gt; with decent gear for the dottari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who want to make things more challenging for their delvers should go with
the Guard template for the thugs, perhaps upgrading them to light armor and
small maces. The guards would be built using the 125-point Squire or Brute
templates. This is also closer to what the Pathfinder version does with the
stats for these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nox should be built &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; on a 250-point Knight template with special
powers added on, and the Hell Hound can be built using the guidelines
on &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/12/17/wolves.html&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; from the Dragon’s Dogma bestiary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In either case, a party of four 250-point delvers would have far less trouble
dealing with the riff-raff than the 1st-level Pathfinder PCs. If they’re smart
and lucky they could even beat the final pack of 12 guards plus Nox and her
hellhound right here! Kyra does know Resist Fire…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GM might want to increase the number of dottari to a realistic level, since
12-14 of them wouldn’t be able to contain a riot of thousands anyway. Or they
could keep the numbers as they are and deal with the changes an complete victory
here would bring to the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-new-friend-in-need&quot;&gt;A New Friend In Need&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, after the party leaves the site of the riot, they hear sounds of
fighting from a nearby alley. There, five CCG thugs are in the process of
beating a man to death. Since this man happens to be the contact one of the PCs
is looking for, it’s in their interest to crush the thugs and save the
man. Unlike the thugs in the riot, these ones fight to the death, but they
should still be manageable. There’s an extra XP reward for succeeding in helping
Rexus, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their victim is Rexus Victocora, the young scion of the nicest noble family in
Kintargo, who of course was disappeared and had their house burned down in the
Night of Ashes. He survived because he was out of the house at the time. Rexus
has either taken an interest in the PCs during the protest or was the one who
called them here in the first place with promises of information on the Silver
Ravens. After going somewhere private, he tells them the story above, and how he
plans to fight back against Thrune’s takeover but needs help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hypotethical party would readily accept the request, and yours should too. I
mean, they’ve been telling you to make that sort of character since the Player’s
Guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, once the PCs are on board, Rexus reveals his parents left him a letter
in which they confessed to be members of the Sacred Order of Archivists, a
secret society dedicating to uncovering and preserving the &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; history of
Kintargo, as opposed to the heavily redacted official version. The letter also
tells of how they feel the Silver Ravens must fly again if the city is to stand
any chance against this new oppression, and says that the Fair Fortune Livery is
rumored to be one of their ancient safehouses. Rexus needs help investigating
the place because he’s not exactly adventurer material. By way of compensation,
he offers most of the rest of the stuff his parents left him, which include some
money and valuables, a silver dagger, and a set of &lt;em&gt;bracers of armor +1&lt;/em&gt;. He
keeps the letter and a mythril key, which will be important later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fair-fortune-livery&quot;&gt;The Fair Fortune Livery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus begins the first official “dungeon delve” of this adventure! This place
used to be a slaughterhouse-turned-stable and conceal a minor Silver Raven
safehouse, but has been abandoned for quite a while. Rexus wants to come along
and help investigate despite not being a combatant, but will accept it if the
PCs tell him to sit this one out instead. Bringing him along turns this into
something of an escort quest, and is worth a little bit of extra XP at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delve begins in the livery’s the ground level. It’s mostly empty and in
ruins. Some locked doors and a small pack of feral dogs are the main obstacles
here. Once the dogs are dealth with the grimples (small, annoying, evil fey
beings) from the basement come up and begin to play poltergeist. In any case, it
shouldn’t be hard for the PCs to find the trapdoor going down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next comes the basement, which was mostly used when the livery was a
slaughterhouse. What 1st-level adventure is complete without a basement full of
rats? Also here is the grimple nest, where the PCs finally have a chance to get
rid of the pests and pillage their treasure (which includes a &lt;em&gt;cloak of
resistance +1&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hideout proper is situated in some old city ruins accessible from the
basement. The main problem with them is that the ancient Silver Ravens
unwittingly brought a devil’s contract here when they plundered a cache of
government documents, and the imp bound to it has been trying to find a way to
leave the place for 80 years. One of those attempts summoned two lemure devils
who now spend their time mindlessly wallowing in a polluted cistern. It’s a good
thing the PCs have that silver dagger with them, because lemures are resistant
to everything else. They are otherwise not terribly dangerous, but serve as a
warning that things down here are Not Right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s three boxes in here full of loot: the first has some interesting armor
and weapons including a silver morningstar, which means this delve is an example
of that annoying trope where the weapon to kill a monster is in a box behind the
monster. The second box is locked and contains a bunch of spell scrolls and the
hundreds of pages of documents that are the actual goal of the quest. And the
third has six &lt;em&gt;figurines of wondrous power&lt;/em&gt; in the shape of silver
ravens. They’re useful for secure communication and are in fact the origin of
the group’s name. The party could also sell them off for a fat load of cash,
something the adventure begs the GM to prevent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The afore-mentioned imp, named Blosodriette, is also here - her contract is
somewhere inside the second box. She limits herself to watching invisibly and
hoping someone takes the box away so she can go along. It’s possible a canny
party might spot and confront her here - if they don’t she’ll cause trouble
later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gurps-conversion-notes-1&quot;&gt;GURPS Conversion Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats and dogs already have stats for GURPS! Grimples are SM -3 or -4 fairies
with minor telekinetic abilities and the ability to cast the Grease spell, which
should make a fight against them look more like a bad comedy movie than actual
combat. Lemures aren’t exactly fearsome combatants, but they should have plenty
of DR against non-silver weapons. Even so, this will be a walk in the park for
250-point delvers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-long-roads-coffee-house&quot;&gt;The Long Roads Coffee House&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the party retrieves the documents, Rexus takes then to the Long Roads
Coffee House to meet Laria Longroad, the proprietor. This halfling is a member
of the Bellflower Network, which is Kintargo’s equivalent of the Underground
Railroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laria is quite happy to support the PCs in their rebellious efforts, not the
least because her extensive network of contacts and informants is mostly gone
now (Thrune hates abolitionists). In fact while she would be glad to let them
crash in the secret hideout underneath the coffee house, she doesn’t even have
control of &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;. A smuggler buddy of hers went in there to stash a cargo of
contraband silks and never came out. It’s been days. If the PCs want a temporary
home base, they’ll need to do some cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hideout occupies the coffee house’s basement and those of the two abandoned
houses to either side of it. It has bunk rooms, a large storeroom, and a dock
leading into an underground river. There’s an albino alligator chilling in the
river, but it’s not the main source of trouble here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, Mr. Smuggler Buddy didn’t just bring a shipment of cloth here, he also
brought a group of tengu sisters on the run from the law back in Varisia. The
plan was to hand them off to another smuggler who would take them the rest of
the way to their destination, but the Night of Ashes put an end to that. When
the guy told the sisters they were on their own, they beat him unconscious, and
then one of them got a little too enthusiastic and killed him. Now they’re holed
up down here, in the dark, despairing about what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathfinder tengu are basically raven-people. The sisters aren’t automatically
hostile, but getting in their good graces will take some doing. There’s four of
them, plus Chough, the “enthusiastic” sister, who is actually an adopted dire
corby and basically responsible for all the trouble the rest have gone
through. Dire corbies look kinda like tengu, but are a lot stronger and less
psychologically stable. The lead sister, Korva, has recently decided Chough
needs to be put down. It’s actually quite possible the party will run into a
murderous Chough before they meet Korva, so that’s one thing taken care of, I
guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly diplomatic parties can convince the sisters to stick around and
join the Silver Ravens, becoming a “special unit” under the rebellion management
rules in the Player’s Guide. If they can’t manage that, they can still let them
leave without a fight as long as they don’t try to pin Mr. Smuggler’s death on
them. PCs get XP for dealing with them whether there’s combat or not, and a
little bonus for telling Laria about her buddy’s fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the sisters are dealt with one way or the other, the party gains the use of
this hideout as a temporary base while they set out to rebuild the Silver
Ravens. We’ll take a look at how that goes in the next installment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gurps-conversion-notes-2&quot;&gt;GURPS Conversion Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Korva should be a 250-point stabby Thief not too different
from &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/gurps/2016/12/30/pathfinder-df-rogue.html&quot;&gt;Merisiel&lt;/a&gt;. Her sisters are 125-point Cutpurses, with Chough probably
being a monstrous Barbarian who fights with Talons and a Sharp Beak and has
serious Berserk and Bloodlust issues. Give her some natural DR, extra HP and
perhaps one or two levels of Extra Attack if you want her to stand up to the
whole party by herself.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/10/hells-rebels-adventure-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/10/hells-rebels-adventure-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>pathfinder</category>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>lets-read</category>
        
        <category>hells-rebels</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dragon's Dogma Bestiary: Gryphons and Cockatrices</title>
        <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/assets/DDENEMIES.jpg&quot;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Copyright 2012 Capcom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an entry in the Dragon’s Dogma bestiary. The remaining entries along
with the full adaptation can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/octopus-carnival/projects/dragons-dogma/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gryphons are considered a symbol of strength and victory in Gransys, much like
in the real world. These creatures used to be considered mythical, but the
coming of the Dragon has proved otherwise. One such beast has taken roost in the
ancient ruins of Bluemoon Tower, and ranges as far as Gran Soren in its search
for prey, devastating herds of cattle and attacking unwary caravans. There might
be others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Basic Set actually has stats for a gryphon in page B461, but those would
only suit a smaller than average individual in this setting. The gryphon of
Bluemoon Tower is much larger, and able to carry a grown person away with
ease. It’s also clever enough to fly away if it thinks itself overmatched, so
hunting it has proven particularly difficult. Ending its threat would mean
undertaking an expedition to Bluemoon Tower and facing the many dangers therein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ST&lt;/strong&gt; 25; &lt;strong&gt;DX&lt;/strong&gt; 14; &lt;strong&gt;IQ&lt;/strong&gt; 5; &lt;strong&gt;HT&lt;/strong&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dodge&lt;/strong&gt; 11; &lt;strong&gt;DR&lt;/strong&gt; 3 (Tough Skin); &lt;strong&gt;SM&lt;/strong&gt; +3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will&lt;/strong&gt; 14; &lt;strong&gt;Per&lt;/strong&gt; 14; &lt;strong&gt;HP&lt;/strong&gt; 24; &lt;strong&gt;FP&lt;/strong&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speed&lt;/strong&gt; 7.5; &lt;strong&gt;Move&lt;/strong&gt; 7 (ground); 14 (air).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beak (15)&lt;/strong&gt;: 2d+2 pi+. Reach C, 1. Parried as a weapon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talons x2 (15)&lt;/strong&gt;: 2d+1 cutting. Reach C-2. May grapple at skill-15. Parried
as a weapon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flyby Attack (-)&lt;/strong&gt;: The Gryphon can perform a Move and Attack maneuver to
swoop down, strike with its talons, and fly back up, covering a distance equal
to its Air Move in total. The attacks are made at no penalty. The talon attack
can be a &lt;em&gt;grapple&lt;/em&gt; instead, which if successful means the gryphon carries the
victim with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traits&lt;/strong&gt;: Acute Vision 5; Combat Reflexes; Extra Attack 2 (claw/claw/beak);
Flight (Winged); Penetrating Voice; Quadruped; Restricted Diet (Fresh Meat);&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skills&lt;/strong&gt;: Brawling-15; Stealth-15; Wrestling-15;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class&lt;/strong&gt;: Hybrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;: Can retreat &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; in combat for a +4 to Dodge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gryphon-variants&quot;&gt;Gryphon Variants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cockatrice&quot;&gt;Cockatrice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the small variant presented in &lt;strong&gt;GURPS Dungeon Fantasy Monsters 3&lt;/strong&gt;, the
Gransys cockatrice is a huge creature that looks like a gryphon from far
away. Upon closer inspection, one can see its avian half resembles more a turkey
or buzzard than an eagle, with black feathers and fur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to possessing the same natural weapons as a gryphon, the cockatrice
can spew a cloud of noxious gas that turns any who breathe it to stone! And
unlike the gryphon, it will never run from a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the same stats as for a gryphon, but add the following attack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Petrifying Breath (16 vs. HT)&lt;/strong&gt;: Covers an area 5m in diameter in front of
the cockatrice. Any who fail the listed resistance roll are turned to stone as
per the Flesh to Stone spell. Can be used once every 10 seconds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/08/gryphon-and-cockatrice.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://Bira.github.io/octopus-carnival/2017/05/08/gryphon-and-cockatrice.html</guid>
        
        <category>gurps</category>
        
        <category>dragons-dogma</category>
        
        <category>monster</category>
        
        <category>bestiary</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
